<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="review-article" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PRB</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spprb</journal-id><journal-title>Probation Journal</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0264-5505</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1741-3079</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/026455051205900202</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_026455051205900202</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research &amp; reports</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mental health disordered probationers and access to health services</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>Kathryn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-026455051205900202"/></contrib><aff id="aff1-026455051205900202"><italic>Greater Manchester Probation Trust</italic></aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>6</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>59</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="society">The Trade Union and Professional Association for Family Court and Probation Staff</copyright-holder></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p>The University of Lincoln published a recent study on <italic>An Investigation into the Prevalence of Mental Disorder and Patterns of Health Service Access in a Probation Population </italic>where they piloted an assessment process to identify how prevalent mental disorder and substance misuse is for those on probation in Lincolnshire. This was achieved through a screening tool used on a random sample of offenders of varying risk levels (p. 3) and qualitative data (p. 6).</p><p>The study found that 27.2 per cent of offenders had a current mental illness and 39.9 per cent had a historic mental illness (p. 4). The sample findings strongly indicated that substance misuse and alcohol misuse were at a hazardous level (p. 4).</p><p>The second stage of the research aimed to identify whether or not probation staff were aware of the offender's mental disorder and how well this was being documented. The study highlighted that probation staff were more likely to record the offender's substance misuse, than his or her mental disorder (p. 6). It identified the barriers to accessing treatment faced by the offender including dual diagnosis, low motivation and the referral criteria not being met.</p><p>The study aimed to identify what works well in terms of the offender accessing the treatment provider and what the barriers are that he or she faces (p. 7). Those who were interviewed recognized the importance of the relationship between the offender and probation officer particularly as a supportive role in accessing treatment services. The staff viewed the referral systems, lack of flexibility from the treatment service and their own limited training in mental disorder as a barrier to treatment for offenders (p. 8). The offenders also found long waiting lists, travel distances and stigma as a barrier to services. The findings indicated that the most valuable services to the offender were those easily accessed and those which offered a level of flexibility in treatment methods (p. 9). The potential improvements that were proposed by the study are: to co-work cases between the probation service and treatment provider; to improve communication between the services; and reduce waiting lists by expanding upon the service provisions (p. 9). It concluded that based upon this study that mental disorder is prevalent of those on probation and that these complex health needs are not being met (p.10).</p><p><italic>An Investigation into the Prevalence of Mental Disorders and Patterns of Health Service Access in a Probation Population</italic> is published by Criminal Justice and Health Research Group, University of Lincoln (2011) and can be downloaded at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.lincoln.ac.uk/cjmh/RfPB%20Executive%20Summary.pdf" xlink:type="simple">http://www.lincoln.ac.uk/cjmh/RfPB%20Executive%20Summary.pdf</ext-link></p><sig-block><sig><bold>Kathryn Thomson</bold><break/><italic>Greater Manchester Probation Trust</italic></sig></sig-block></body></article>