<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JHS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjhs</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Hand Surg Eur Vol</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Hand Surgery (European Volume)</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1753-1934</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2043-6289</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1753193412449804</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1753193412449804</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Full length articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Test–retest reliability of grip strength measurement in full elbow extension to evaluate maximum grip strength</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Savva</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Karagiannis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-1753193412449804">Department of Health Science, Diogenous 6, Engomi, European University, Nicosia, Cyprus</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Rushton</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-1753193412449804">School of Health and Population Sciences, College of Medical and Dental Sciences, University of Birmingham, Edgbaston, Birmingham, UK</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1753193412449804">Christos Savva, Argolidos 25 Panthea, Limassol, Cyprus Email: <email>savva.christos@hotmail.com</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jhs.sagepub.com/site/Podcast/podcast_dir.xhtml">http://jhs.sagepub.com/site/Podcast/podcast_dir.xhtml</ext-link></p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>38</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>183</fpage>
<lpage>186</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>18</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>6</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>7</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">The British Society for Surgery of the Hand</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The objective of this study was to investigate the test–retest reliability of measurement of grip strength in full elbow extension. The grip strengths of 19 healthy participants were measured using the Jamar dynamometer by the same rater on two occasions with an interval of 7 days between measures. Test–retest reliability of grip strength measurement was excellent in full elbow extension and associated with low values of standard error of measurement and small variations in the differences between the two measurements in both testing sessions.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Test–retest reliability</kwd>
<kwd>grip strength measurement</kwd>
<kwd>hand strength</kwd>
<kwd>Jamar dynamometer</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1753193412449804" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Grip strength (GS) measurement using a dynamometer is commonly used by hand surgeons and physiotherapists to assess the functional integrity of the hand and upper limb. It is advocated as an outcome measure in conditions affecting the hand, elbow, and neck, because it can identify and quantitatively determine any limitation of GS.</p>
<p>Outcome measures that are widely used in clinical practice should provide similar and stable results when applied by the same rater on repeated trials (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1753193412449804">Sim and Wright, 2000</xref>). Acknowledging the importance of an outcome measure to provide stable measurements, the American Society of Hand Therapists (ASHT) developed a standardized protocol to enhance the test–retest reliability of grip strength measurement (GSM) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1753193412449804">Fess and Moran, 1981</xref>). According to this protocol, measurement of GS is highly reliable in a standardized upper limb position with the individual sitting with the shoulders in 0° of flexion, abduction, and neutral rotation, elbow flexed to 90°, and forearm resting in a neutral position, with the wrist in an extended and ulnar deviated position of 0°–30° and 0°–15°, respectively.</p>
<p>Although the excellent test–retest reliability of GSM has been recognized in some studies, their methodological quality has been questioned due to inappropriate data analysis, lack of male participants, and potential learning and fatigue effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1753193412449804">Ng and Fan, 2001</xref>).</p>
<p>Despite the ASHT protocol, which recommends use of the standardized arm position during GSM, research suggests that the position of 90° elbow flexion does not facilitate measurement of maximum GS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1753193412449804">Oxford, 2000</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1753193412449804">Su et al. (1994)</xref> compared GS in various elbow positions. All the healthy participants in their study were measured in accordance with the ASHT protocol in other respects, and maximum GS measurements were obtained when the elbow joint rested in full elbow extension (FEE). A similar conclusion was reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1753193412449804">Oxford (2000)</xref> who measured GS in 90° elbow flexion and FEE. Participants were measured using the Greenleaf electrodynamometer and exhibited maximum GS in FEE. However, the Greenleaf electrodynamometer is not recommended by the ASHT for GSM because it cannot provide the most reliable measures. The Jamar dynamometer is recommended by the ASHT because it produces similar measures across repeated trials (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1753193412449804">Mitsionis et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Reports of test–retest reliability of GSM in FEE raise methodological questions. Two studies have investigated the effectiveness of a treatment in 10 patients with tennis elbow using the GSM as an outcome measure and have shown excellent test–retest reliability with an obtained intraclass correlation coefficient (ICC<sub>2,1</sub>) of 0.94 and 0.98 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753193412449804">Fernandez-Carnero et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1753193412449804">Vicenzino et al., 2001</xref>). Nevertheless, the findings of these studies cannot be generalized due to their small sample sizes and lack of estimation of measurement error.</p>
<p>Despite the limited research evidence to support the test–retest reliability of GSM in FEE, this position is often used in practice because of the potential maximal GS performance that can be obtained (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1753193412449804">Ng and Fan, 2001</xref>). To date, no study has explored the test–retest reliability of GSM in a healthy population. The objective of this study was to investigate the test–retest reliability of GSM using the Jamar dynamometer in FEE in healthy participants.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1753193412449804" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="section3-1753193412449804">
<title>Study design</title>
<p>Measurements of GS in FEE were taken for each participant by the same rater on two separate occasions. A time interval of 7 days between test and retest was sufficient to avoid factors that could distort the validity of the findings, such as learning or fatigue effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1753193412449804">Sim and Wright, 2000</xref>). A blinded rater measured and recorded participants’ measurements of GS, and participants were blinded to their measurement scores to avoid potential expectation bias.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1753193412449804">
<title>Study participants</title>
<p>The rater was a qualified physiotherapist with 3 years of post-qualification experience in the field of musculoskeletal physiotherapy, who was randomly selected (names were drawn from a hat) from all clinical trainers working at the European University of Cyprus. A sample size of 19 participants were recruited from healthy students of the university, to detect a difference in reliability of 0.9 and 0.7 at 80% power and a 5% level of significance using two ratings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1753193412449804">Walter et al., 1998</xref>). Ten male (age range 21–26, SD 2.5 years) and nine female (age range 21–23, SD 1 year) student volunteers were recruited. Participants had no current or past history (in the previous 6 months) of neck or upper limb pain or reported neurological symptoms in the upper limbs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1753193412449804">
<title>Ethical considerations</title>
<p>On meeting the requirements for inclusion, participants gave informed consent before participation. The study was approved by the ethics committee of the University of Birmingham, UK.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1753193412449804">
<title>Instrument</title>
<p>GS data were collected using the Jamar dynamometer (Saehan Corporation, Masan, South Korea). According to the ASHT protocol, it provides the most reliable measure of GS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1753193412449804">Mathiowetz et al., 1984</xref>). Its test–retest reliability has been examined in healthy participants in a range of studies. Using the standardized elbow position (90° elbow flexion), results have shown excellent test–retest reliability with ICC<sub>2,1</sub> ranging from 0.81 to 0.98 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1753193412449804">Innes, 1999</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1753193412449804">
<title>Procedure</title>
<p>The time of day has been shown to affect test–retest reliability of GSM, with previous studies finding GS stronger in the afternoon compared with the morning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1753193412449804">Innes, 1999</xref>). Timing of testing was therefore standardized and participants were asked to attend in the morning between 8:00 <sc>am</sc> to 12:00 midday.</p>
<p>GS was tested in each participant’s dominant hand. The procedure for data collection was divided into two phases: familiarization and measurement.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1753193412449804">
<title>Familiarization phase:</title>
<list id="list1-1753193412449804" list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>The Jamar dynamometer was set at the second handle space, as recommended by the ASHT protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1753193412449804">Fess and Moran, 1981</xref>).</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>The standardized arm position was demonstrated by the researcher.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Participants were positioned in accordance with the ASHT protocol. Specifically, they sat in a straight-backed chair with their back supported and their feet flat on the floor. The shoulder and wrist were positioned as recommended by the ASHT protocol, but the elbow joint was placed in FEE instead of 90° of flexion. Participants were allowed one gripping movement using the Jamar dynamometer to enable familiarization with the task.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Participants were encouraged to follow verbal instructions from the rater that were based on the standardized ASHT protocol: “Please hold the handle like this and squeeze as hard as you can. Are you ready? Squeeze as hard as you can. Harder. . . Harder. . . Harder. . . Relax.”</p></list-item></list>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1753193412449804">
<title>Measurement phase:</title>
<list id="list2-1753193412449804" list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>The ASHT standardized testing procedure was used for data collection.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Participants were encouraged to make three maximum gripping efforts (5 seconds isometric contraction in each trial).</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>To avoid potential fatigue effects, there was a 15 second rest period in between each effort.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>During the rest period, the same rater recorded the maximum GS of each effort.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Three maximum GSs were recorded for each participant (measured in kilogram force) and their mean value was used in the analysis.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1753193412449804">
<title>Data analysis</title>
<p>The ICC<sub>2,1</sub>, standard error of measurement (SEM) and Bland–Altman plot were used. The ICC<sub>2,1</sub> evaluates the degree of agreement of participant’s scores on both occasions. It has been used in similar research and therefore is widely recommended for test–retest reliability research using one rater (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1753193412449804">Sim and Wright, 2000</xref>). The 95% confidence interval of the ICC<sub>2,1</sub> enabled probabilistic statements about the precise score of ICC<sub>2,1</sub>. Shrout’s classification was used to interpret the ICC<sub>2,1</sub> value, and reliability was considered good for an ICC of 0.61 to 0.80 and excellent for 0.81 to 1.00 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1753193412449804">Shrout, 1998</xref>). The SEM and Bland–Altman plot were used to evaluate the measurement precision and convey information about the magnitude of measurement error (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1753193412449804">Bland and Altman, 1986</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1753193412449804" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>GSM results are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1753193412449804">Table 1</xref> and show that 11 participants had a higher GS on the second test occasion.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1753193412449804" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>GSMs of participants on the two testing occasions</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1753193412449804" xlink:href="10.1177_1753193412449804-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Participant no.</th>
<th align="left">First measurement, kgf</th>
<th align="left">Second measurement, kgf</th>
<th align="left">Difference</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>−1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>−1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>28.5</td>
<td>−0.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>25.5</td>
<td>−0.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>59</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>−2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>9</td>
<td>55</td>
<td>62</td>
<td>−7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>−6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>13</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>−5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>42</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15</td>
<td>18.5</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>0.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>16</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>−3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>17</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>18</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>−1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>19</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>−4</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>GSM in FEE demonstrated an ICC<sub>2,1</sub> of 0.96. Lower and upper bounds of the 95% confidence interval were 0.91 and 0.98, respectively. The calculation of measurement error showed that the magnitude of test–retest reliability of GSM in FEE was not significantly influenced by measurement error, as reflected by the low SEM values. During the first testing session, SEM was slightly lower (2.79) than during the second session (2.94).</p>
<p>In the Bland–Altman analysis, the mean difference of the two measurements was −0.17 kgf and the SD of the differences was 3.1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1753193412449804">Figure 1</xref>). The width of the 95% limits of agreements (mean difference ± 2SD) was −6.8 to 5.5 kgf. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1753193412449804">Figure 1</xref>, the cluster of the GS data points lies within the 95% limits of agreement, indicating a normal distribution of the differences.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1753193412449804" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Bland-Altman plot.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1753193412449804-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1753193412449804" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Our results demonstrated that the test–retest reliability of GSM in healthy participants in FEE can provide stable and similar measurements. With a time interval of 7 days between the two testing occasions, the ICC<sub>2,1</sub> was 0.96 which, based on Shrout’s classification, is interpreted as excellent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1753193412449804">Shrout, 1998</xref>). The high value of the ICC<sub>2,1</sub> indicated the reliable measurement of GS in this elbow position (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1753193412449804">Sim and Wright, 2000</xref>). The low SEMs and small width of the 95% limits of agreement in the Bland–Altman plot reflect the good measurement precision of GS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1753193412449804">Bland and Altman, 1986</xref>). One possible explanation for the slightly higher SEM on the second measurement is that participants may have learnt to squeeze the Jamar dynamometer harder over the two trials and, thus, produced their maximum grip strength on the second occasion. Such learning effects may contribute to error in measurements of GS. The grip performance of 11 participants did increase over the two sessions. In the Bland–Altman plot analysis, the 95% limits of agreement demonstrated narrow ranges of participants’ scores in most of the repeated measurements. The width of the 95% limits of agreement represents the precision of the two measurements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1753193412449804">Sim and Wright, 2000</xref>). The small width reflects the narrow variation of the differences and high precision of measurement of GS.</p>
<p>Our results are similar to two pilot studies on test–retest reliability of GSM in FEE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753193412449804">Fernandez-Carnero et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1753193412449804">Vicenzino et al., 2001</xref>). However, ours is the first adequately powered study in this area.</p>
<p>Our study does have some limitations. During the tests the elbow position was maintained by observation of the rater. An adjustable elbow splint might have been better (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1753193412449804">Ng and Fan, 2001</xref>), although this would not represent GSM in clinical practice. Participants were young healthy students and, undoubtedly, they were not representative of the population that would be measured in clinical practice.</p>
<p>Our results show the excellent test–retest reliability of GSM in FEE in healthy participants, demonstrating its potential for use in clinical practice. Further investigation in symptomatic patients and those of a broader age range is now required to assess its usefulness as an outcome measure in clinical practice.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack><p>Chris Wright, Research Methodologist and Programme Director — Research Degrees, Nursing and Physiotherapy, School of Health and Population Sciences, College of Medical and Dental Sciences, University of Birmingham, UK. Technical support (Jamar dynamometer, laboratory) was provided by the European University of Cyprus.</p></ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Conflict of interests</label>
<p>None declared.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1753193412449804">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bland</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Statistical methods for assessing agreement between two methods of clinical measurement</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>1986</year>, <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1753193412449804">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fernandez-Carnero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fernandez-de-las-Penas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cleland</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Immediate hypoalgesic and motor effects after a single cervical spine manipulation in subjects with lateral epicondylalgia</article-title>. <source>J Manipulative Physiol Ther</source>. <year>2008</year>, <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>675</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1753193412449804">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fess</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clinical assessment recommendations</article-title>. <source>Raleigh, American Society of Hand Therapists</source>, <year>1981</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1753193412449804">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Innes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Handgrip strength testing: A review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Aust Occup Ther J</source>. <year>1999</year>, <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>120</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1753193412449804">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mathiowetz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Volland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kashman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Reliability and validity of grip and pinch strength evaluations</article-title>. <source>J Hand Surg Am</source>. <year>1984</year>, <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>222</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1753193412449804">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mitsionis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pakos</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stafilas</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paschos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Papakostas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beris</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Normative data on hand grip strength in a Greek adult population</article-title>. <source>Int Orthopaedics</source>. <year>2009</year>, <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>713</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1753193412449804">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>GYF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>ACC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Does elbow position affect strength and reproducibility of power grip measurements?</article-title> <source>Physiotherapy</source>. <year>2001</year>, <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>68</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1753193412449804">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Oxford</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Elbow positioning for maximum grip performance</article-title>. <source>J Hand Ther</source>. <year>2000</year>, <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1753193412449804">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shrout</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Measurement reliability and agreement in psychiatry</article-title>. <source>Stat Methods Med Res</source>. <year>1998</year>, <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>301</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1753193412449804">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Research in health care: Concepts, design and methods</article-title>. <source>Nelson Thornes, Chippenham and Eastbourne</source>, <year>2000</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1753193412449804">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chien</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Grip strength in different positions of elbow and shoulder</article-title>. <source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil</source>. <year>1994</year>, <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>812</fpage>–<lpage>5</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1753193412449804">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vicenzino</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paungmali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buratowski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Specific manipulative therapy treatment for chronic lateral epicondylalgia produces uniquely characteristic hypoalgesia</article-title>. <source>Manual Ther</source>. <year>2001</year>, <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1753193412449804">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eliasziw</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Donner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Sample size and optimal designs for reliability studies</article-title>. <source>Stat Med</source>. <year>1998</year>, <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>101</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>