<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CNC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcnc</journal-id>
<journal-title>Capital &amp; Class</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0309-8168</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2041-0980</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0309816813489943d</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0309816813489943d</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book review: <italic>The Politics of Equality: An Introduction</italic>, by Jason C. Myers</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Risak</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0309816813489943">University of Vienna, Austria</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>37</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>315</fpage>
<lpage>317</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>Jason C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <source>The Politics of Equality: An Introduction</source>, <publisher-name>Zed Books</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>, <year>2010</year>; <page-count count="159"/> pp: <isbn>978184813843</isbn>, <price>£14.99</price> (pbk)</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Conference of Socialist Economists</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In this handy and very readable book, Jason C. Myers, professor at the Department for Politics and Public Administration at California State University, Stanislaus, sets out to clarify and rearticulate in contemporary terms the core values of ‘socialist, communist and social democratic political philosophy’ in terms of the establishment of social rights and the promotion of social equality. It is not a university textbook full of theories, their founders and the history of the field, but more an introductory text geared to a wider audience interested in progressive political thinking. The book is structured in five parts around the topics of historical materialism, equal freedom, economy and society, democracy and internationalism. These chapters, especially the first four, evolve naturally one from the other, and Myers thereby develops a strong and in many respects also convincing narrative of how progressive politics should look in his opinion.</p>
<p>The first chapter introduces the concept of historical materialism – the idea that the development of a society is very much determined by the productive forces reigning within. It emphasises the role of class and class struggles, a notion that Myers traces back to the ancient Greek philosophers, but that, of course, was sharpened by Marx and Engels. The author concludes that the materialist theory of history tells us that because we have choices to make about the nature of productive relations and that those choices will affect distribution of wealth and leisure time, we should anticipate conflict between those who stand to gain or lose. Social egalitarians have consistently argued and fought for those excluded from the means of production, and promoted the creation of meaningful social equality. The second chapter thus deals with the notion of equality understood as equal freedom. It stresses the importance of material resources as preconditions of meaningful choice. A good society should endeavour to provide its members with real possibilities for the free development of their capacities to the greatest extent possible. In a logical progression, Chapter 3 deals with the question of how material resources should be distributed and how a society’s economy should be organised. It lays out the concept of exploitation in a capitalist economy, where the profitability of a firm depends upon the availability of workers whose wage demands do not exceed the profit margin. This is achieved on the basis of the unequal distribution of productive capital, and the employer’s advantage that the worker’s entry into the labour market is only in the very limited sense a voluntary one, being in fact a choice between life and death. One alternative for eliminating the causes of such exploitation – public ownership and central economic planning – is discussed, but seen as having limited possibilities of success, especially because public managers would become de facto owners and exploiters. For Myers, the preferred option – very much like the European social-democratic approach – lies in the development of a hybrid economy that respects private property but levels income distribution, provides public goods (especially education and health services), and also free time as the basis for the provision and the expansion of freedom for all. Within this framework of ownership, formal institutions of government are considered necessary, as they are vitally important for counterbalancing the potential exploitative power of private property that is not to be abolished, and for providing the material foundations for equal freedom in the form of public goods. Though mostly of historical interest, the anarchist notion of a society without a state is discussed in length and, not surprisingly, rejected. Promoted in Chapter 4 is the idea of parliamentary democracy, but the question also put forth is whether more direct mechanisms of participation should not be introduced. This approach is rejected for arguments of inefficiency and the risk of being hijacked by wealthy individuals or corporations, but in the same breath, Myers stresses the role of labour unions and parties outside of government. Social egalitarianism must be fought for continually through mechanisms of formal democracy.</p>
<p>The last two chapters on internationalism and on the privation of the state do not fit easily with the others, which follow a natural line of argument. The fifth is chronological in its conception, and deals with the historical development of international communism, with the final subchapter on internationalism as ideology taking up the flow of the rest of the book. The sixth chapter on the privation state is very US-centred, and applies the theory developed in the preceding chapters on the austerity measures that have become even more prominent since the publication of the book. It will be of interest to readers outside the USA mostly from a comparative perspective.</p>
<p>In summary, this is a very good and compact introduction to the main notions of social egalitarian thinking, putting it into a wider historical and philosophical context. It is obviously written from a US perspective – unfortunately, you will search in vain for the treatise of influential European authors like Foucault, Gramsci or Adorno. This may limit its potential use for courses at European universities, but does not lessen its undeniable value as an introductory, very inspired and at times also inspirational text, written for a wider audience in easily understandable language, without becoming superficial.</p>
</body>
<back>
<bio>
<title>Author biography</title>
<p><bold>Martin Risak</bold> is an associate professor in the Department of Labour Law and Law of Social Security at the University of Vienna. His main areas of research interest include Austrian, European and comparative labour law and industrial relations, as well as alternative dispute resolution.</p>
</bio>
</back>
</article>