<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TAK</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptak</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ther Adv Cardiovasc Dis</journal-id>
<journal-title>Therapeutic Advances in Cardiovascular Disease</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1753-9447</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1753-9455</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1753944712468627</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1753944712468627</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Editorial</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Comparing the safety of ticagrelor <italic>versus</italic> clopidogrel: insights from the FDA reports</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>DiNicolantonio</surname><given-names>James J.</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-1753944712468627">Wegmans Pharmacy, 500 South Meadow Street, Ithaca, NY 14850, USA</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Serebruany</surname><given-names>Victor L.</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-1753944712468627">HeartDrug Research Laboratories, Johns Hopkins University, Towson, MD, USA</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1753944712468627"><email>jjdinicol@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>7</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>5</fpage>
<lpage>9</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s), 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Ticagrelor is a new antiplatelet agent chemically known as a cyclopentyltriazolopyrimidine, with distinguishing properties from that of theinopyridines. Theoretically in acute coronary syndrome (ACS) a rapid acting antiplatelet agent such as ticagrelor, with a greater inhibition of platelet activation, should improve outcomes. Thus, ticagrelor was tested against clopidogrel in the Platelet Inhibition and Patient Outcomes (PLATO) trial, which was a phase III, randomized, double-blind, parallel-group, multinational, clinical study of 18,624 patients with moderate- to high-risk ACS undergoing coronary intervention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1753944712468627">Wallentin <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>]. Patients were randomized to ticagrelor 180 mg loading dose followed by 90 mg twice daily thereafter, or clopidogrel 300–600 mg loading dose followed by 75 mg once daily for 6–12 months [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1753944712468627">Wallentin <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>]. The primary endpoint was the time of the first event of death from vascular causes, myocardial infarction or stroke, and occurred in 11.7% of patients treated with clopidogrel <italic>versus</italic> 9.8% of patients randomized to ticagrelor, representing a highly significant benefit for ticagrelor [hazard ratio (HR) 0.84; 95% confidence interval (CI) 0.77–0.92; <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1753944712468627">Wallentin <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>]. Importantly, the benefit of ticagrelor was driven equally by the reduction of vascular death (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and myocardial infarction (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.005) with 89 events favoring ticagrelor each, but not stroke (<italic>p</italic> = 0.22) with 19 less events in the clopidogrel arm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1753944712468627">Wallentin <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>]. However, such an overoptimistic interpretation of the ticagrelor efficacy has been somewhat clouded by the repeated US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) reviews [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1753944712468627">2012</xref>], suggesting multiple safety issues with ticagrelor. We will be focusing on some major safety issues outlined in the FDA publications.</p>
<sec id="section1-1753944712468627">
<title>Race and gender</title>
<p>The PLATO trial enrolled over a thousand (1081) patients of Chinese or Japanese descent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1753944712468627">2012</xref>]. Importantly, Japanese patients experienced a 40% greater exposure to ticagrelor <italic>versus</italic> Caucasians, which was shown in an 8-day phase I study [both for maximum concentration (Cmax) and for under the curve (AUC)] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1753944712468627">FDA, 2012</xref>]. While there are insufficient safety data in this subgroup, Japanese patients may have an increased risk for overdosing on ticagrelor compared with their white counterparts. However, data are lacking to confirm that higher exposure to ticagrelor in Japanese patients leads to an increased risk of hemorrhagic events. Moreover, women on ticagrelor tended to have more adverse events (AEs), including serious AEs (SAEs), increased discontinuation because of AEs and an increased risk of death compared with men, also suggesting potential overdosing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1753944712468627">FDA, 2012</xref>]. Whether these differences were statistically significant was not mentioned in the FDA complete response review (CRR) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1753944712468627">
<title>Bleeding</title>
<p>The primary safety concern with ticagrelor in the PLATO trial is bleeding. The FDA CRR indicates that nonprocedural bleeding events were significantly increased after ticagrelor <italic>versus</italic> clopidogrel [major + minor + minimal: 24.3% <italic>versus</italic> 15.9%, HR 1.62, 95% CI 1.51–1.74); major + minor: 5.9% <italic>versus</italic> 4.3%, HR 1.39, 95% CI 1.21–1.60; major: 3.1% <italic>versus</italic> 2.3%, HR 1.31, 95% CI 1.08–1.60) with a nonsignificant 9% increase in major life-threatening or fatal bleeds (1.3% <italic>versus</italic> 1.2%, HR 1.09, 95% CI 0.82–1.44) and fatal bleeds (0.2% <italic>versus</italic> 0.2%, HR 1.09, 95% CI 0.50–2.38) respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>]. Thus, ticagrelor significantly increases major, minor and minimal nonprocedural bleeds compared with clopidogrel. Furthermore, major bleeds were predominately coronary artery bypass graft (CABG)-related bleeding complications (~67%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>]. However, in PLATO, the reporting of (CABG) bleeds and procedural hemorrhages was set up in ticagrelor’s favor. Indeed, the reporting of procedural bleeds was set up to be related to the procedure rather than the study drug. The protocol stated that procedural bleeding should not be reported as an AE if it is expected during the procedure, yet there was no guidance on the form about what is ‘expected’ during the procedure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>]. Furthermore, on the AE form, the checkbox for ‘Bleed is related to a procedure and does not represent an adverse event’ did not allow the severity of the bleed (minimal, minor or major) to be recorded and the remainder of the AE form was not to be completed. However, the reporting of CABG-related bleeds was set up to document as much as possible (i.e. the electronic case report form system automatically created a bleed event form for all CABG forms) as the ‘CABG-related’ checkbox also had minimal, minor and major bleeding severity checkboxes (unlike the reporting for procedural bleeds) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>]. Moreover, the investigator was to complete the rest of the AE form for CABG-related bleeds, which was not required for procedural-related bleeds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>]. As ticagrelor has a faster offset, one would expect fewer CABG bleeds but more procedural-related bleeds due to ticagrelor’s higher inhibition of platelet activity compared with clopidogrel. Thus, it seems that the PLATO investigators stacked the deck of cards in ticagrelor’s favor (i.e. reporting more CABG bleeds but fewer procedural bleeds). Despite this ploy, the risk of CABG bleeding was increased in patients receiving ticagrelor compared with clopidogrel-treated patients in those who did not wait until day 5 after stopping treatment, which is recommended in ACS guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1753944712468627">Levine <italic>et al</italic>. 2011</xref>]. Thus, the antiplatelet effects of ticagrelor last significantly longer than predicted by its pharmacokinetics/pharmacodynamics. In addition, the purported ‘faster’ offset of ticagrelor (compared with clopidogrel) is not clinically relevant as it does not translate into fewer bleeding events. There were statistically more overall bleeds (PLATO-defined major, life-threatening or fatal, minor and minimal) in the ticagrelor arm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>]. In summary, in patients treated with ticagrelor, clinicians should consider delaying CABG and other major surgeries until 5 days after cessation of therapy.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1753944712468627">
<title>Strokes and embolic events</title>
<p>There were more intracranial bleeds on ticagrelor compared with clopidogrel [27 (0.3%) <italic>versus</italic> 14 (0.2%), relative risk (RR) 1.90, <italic>p</italic> value not stated; one extra intracranial bleed for every 1000 patients treated] and more hemorrhagic strokes (26 <italic>versus</italic> 16, RR 1.63, <italic>p</italic> value not given) with 11 (0.12%) fatal hemorrhagic strokes on ticagrelor <italic>versus</italic> only 1 (0.0%) on clopidogrel (i.e. there was a 10-fold increase in fatal hemorrhagic strokes with ticagrelor <italic>versus</italic> clopidogrel; <italic>p</italic> = 0.02) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>]. Furthermore, for every 10 all-cause deaths avoided with ticagrelor, there was one extra hemorrhagic stroke death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>]. A higher degree of platelet inhibition with ticagrelor may precipitate a clinical hemorrhagic event in someone with a subclinical stroke compared with someone on clopidogrel. Supporting this theory was the significant increase in intracranial hemorrhages (ICHs) on ticagrelor compared with clopidogrel (27 <italic>versus</italic> 14) as well as fatal ICH [11 (0.1%) <italic>versus</italic> 2 (0.0%), RR 5.47; 1 extra fatal ICH for every 1000 patients treated with ticagrelor]. Moreover, peripheral vascular disease was increased by 17% (RR 1.17, 155 <italic>versus</italic> 132), thromboembolic disease (arterial and venous) was increased by 24% (RR 1.24, 84 <italic>versus</italic> 68), any venous thrombotic event was increased by 11% (RR 1.11, 72 <italic>versus</italic> 65), deep vein thrombosis was increased by 11% (RR 1.11, 72 <italic>versus</italic> 65) and pulmonary embolism was increased by 46% (35 <italic>versus</italic> 24) with ticagrelor compared with clopidogrel (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1753944712468627">Table 1</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>]. A higher platelet inhibition may lead to clots that are more brittle and thus more likely to embolize on ticagrelor. Another explanation purported by the FDA document was that ticagrelor may increase the risk for plaque rupture and subsequent embolization further downstream in the vasculature. In summary, a higher antiplatelet potency and ‘faster’ antiplatelet offset with ticagrelor does not seem to give it a clinical advantage with regard to reduced embolic events or reduced hemorrhagic events.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1753944712468627" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Embolic/vascular events: ticagrelor compared with clopidogrel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>].</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1753944712468627" xlink:href="10.1177_1753944712468627-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Event</th>
<th align="left">Ticagrelor</th>
<th align="left">Clopidogrel</th>
<th align="left">RR</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Amaurosis fugax</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>2.33</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Stroke</td>
<td>138</td>
<td>111</td>
<td>1.24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Intracranial hemorrhage</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>1.65</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Stroke/TIA</td>
<td>178</td>
<td>152</td>
<td>1.17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cerebrovascular and carotid disease</td>
<td>214</td>
<td>190</td>
<td>1.13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Thromboembolic disease (arterial and venous)</td>
<td>84</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>1.24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Peripheral vascular disease</td>
<td>155</td>
<td>132</td>
<td>1.17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Necrotic limb/amputation</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Venous event</td>
<td>72</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>1.11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>DVT</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>1.14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PE</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>1.46</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1753944712468627">
<p>DVT, deep vein thrombosis; PE, pulmonary embolism; RR, relative risk; TIA, transient ischemic attack.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1753944712468627">
<title>Dyspnea</title>
<p>Shortness of breath or dyspnea was reported more frequently with ticagrelor compared with clopidogrel (14.49% <italic>versus</italic> 8.78%, RR 1.6, <italic>p</italic> value not stated), with one-third of patients experiencing dyspnea throughout study termination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>]. Thus, one out of three patients experiencing dyspnea on ticagrelor will continue to have this serious adverse event for a prolonged period of time. Moreover, dyspnea leading to discontinuation was nine times higher with ticagrelor <italic>versus</italic> clopidogrel (0.9% <italic>versus</italic> 0.1%, RR and <italic>p</italic> value not given). Discontinuation for dyspnea (from sponsor) indicated an almost eightfold increase with ticagrelor <italic>versus</italic> clopidogrel [77 (0.8%) <italic>versus</italic> 10 (0.1%), RR 7.66] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>]. Thus, the reported side effect of ‘dyspnea’ with ticagrelor seems to be more clinically relevant than originally stated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1753944712468627">Wallentin <italic>et al</italic>. 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>]. While a pulmonary function substudy was performed, flaws in its design, conduct and analysis prevented any ascertainment of conclusions. High baseline smoking status as well as lack of the preferential inclusion of individuals who experienced dyspnea on ticagrelor may have suppressed a difference, even if one had existed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1753944712468627">
<title>Gynecomastia</title>
<p>While the absolute rate of gynecomastia was low (approximately 3 per 1000 men at 1 year), ticagrelor significantly increased gynecomastia 5.3 fold compared with clopidogrel [15 (0.16%) <italic>versus</italic> 3 (0.03%), RR &gt; 5.0]. Thus, in patients experiencing or having a history of gynecomastia, clopidogrel may be preferred.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1753944712468627">
<title>Arrhythmias and bradycardia</title>
<p>The DISPERSE 2 trial, a phase II trial comparing two doses of ticagrelor <italic>versus</italic> clopidogrel in 990 patients, indicated a higher frequency of arrhythmias with ticagrelor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>]. In PLATO, while there were more atrial arrhythmias and ventricular pauses with ticagrelor <italic>versus</italic> clopidogrel, a somewhat favorable effect was seen for sudden death and ventricular arrhythmias [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>]. However, PLATO excluded patients at increased risk of bradycardic events as ticagrelor was shown to significantly increase this side effect compared with clopidogrel in the DISPERSE 2 trial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>]. Thus, patients at risk of a bradycardia should not be placed on ticagrelor.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1753944712468627">
<title>History of hepatic disorder</title>
<p>Approximately 400 patients with a ‘history of baseline hepatic disorder’ were enrolled in the PLATO trial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>]. In these individuals, compared with clopidogrel, ticagrelor significantly increased death by over threefold (3.1% <italic>versus</italic> 0.9%), and frequency of SAEs (20.4% <italic>versus</italic> 16.6%) and AEs (84.2% <italic>versus</italic> 81.1%). Moreover, ticagrelor increased major bleeds compared with clopidogrel in these individuals (11.2% <italic>versus</italic> 8.7%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>]. In summary, clinicians should use caution when prescribing ticagrelor in patients with a history of hepatic disorder.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1753944712468627">
<title>Renal insufficiency</title>
<p>Compared with clopidogrel, patients receiving ticagrelor with a baseline estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) of less than 30 ml/min had an increased risk of major bleeding complications [23 (19%) <italic>versus</italic> 16 (11.3%)], death [31 (26.5%) <italic>versus</italic> 34 (23.4%)] and renal failure [12 (13.6%) <italic>versus</italic> 5 (5.4%)] respectively. This contrasts with a recent publication by James and colleagues, indicating that a cohort of 214 patients with calculated creatinine clearance less than 30 ml/min showed similar results for the primary composite endpoint, 28.9% per 12 months (27 patients) for ticagrelor <italic>versus</italic> 39.0% (39 patients) for clopidogrel (HR 0.77; 95% CI 0.49–1.30), and for mortality, 23.4% (21 patients) <italic>versus</italic> 29.6% (29 patients) (HR 0.77; 95% CI 0.47–1.44) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1753944712468627">James <italic>et al</italic>. 2010</xref>]. Thus, in patients with a baseline eGFR less than 30 ml/min, ticagrelor may have a net clinical harm compared with clopidogrel.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1753944712468627">
<title>Drug interactions</title>
<p>Ticagrelor is a cytochrome P450 (CYP)-3A4 substrate and a relatively weak CYP3A4 inhibitor, increasing the exposure of simvastatin (50%, up to two- to threefold in some individuals), atorvastatin (36%), lovastatin (similar to simvastatin) and estradiol (30% in Cmax and 20% in AUC) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>]. CYP3A inducers such as rifampin, dexamethasone, phenytoin, carbamazepine and phenobarbital increase ticagrelor’s clearance by 110%. Thus, patients on CYP3A inducers may have less benefit on ticagrelor. In summary, CYP3A4 inhibitors, inducers and substrates need to be given with caution with concomitant ticagrelor administration. Moreover, ticagrelor inhibits the <italic>p</italic>-glycoprotein (PgP) efflux pump and can significantly increase digoxin levels (75% increase in Cmax, 28% increase in AUC; mean digoxin trough levels increased by 30%, with some individual maximum increases of up to twofold). Thus, in patients on ticagrelor, digoxin concentrations should be monitored closely. Furthermore, concomitant use of ticagrelor and other PgP inhibitors such as verapamil, quinidine and cyclosporine should be used with caution.</p>
<p>Despite the favorable efficacy of ticagrelor <italic>versus</italic> clopidogrel, there are a plethora of subgroups and clinical scenarios in which the safety of ticagrelor may outweigh its benefit (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1753944712468627">Table 2</xref>). When prescribing ticagrelor, clinicians should be fully aware of these potential harmful scenarios, and have an action plan in case adverse events emerge. While ticagrelor has very limited (if any) ‘real-world’ experience, the progressive years of its inclusion in the ACS preventive cocktail should allow us to better gleam its overall efficacy and safety profile.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1753944712468627" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Scenarios in which ticagrelor safety may outweigh benefit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1753944712468627">FDA, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1753944712468627">EMA, 2010</xref>].</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1753944712468627" xlink:href="10.1177_1753944712468627-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>CYP3A4 substrates, inhibitors and inducers</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PgP substrates/inhibitors – digoxin, cyclosporine and verapamil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Women and Japanese</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Baseline GFR &lt; 30 ml/min</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>History of cerebrovascular disease</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>History of a thromboembolic event</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>History of ICH</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>History of Hepatic disease</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Patients at risk of bradycardia</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1753944712468627">
<p>CYP3A4, cytochrome P450 3A4; GFR, glomerular filtration rate; ICH, intracranial hemorrhage; PgP, P glycoprotein.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Conflict of interest statement</label>
<p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest in preparing this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1753944712468627">
<citation citation-type="web"><collab>EMA</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Ticagrelor (Brilique) Summary of product characteristics. European Medicines Agency</article-title>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ema.europa.eu/docs/en_GB/document_library/EPAR_-_Product_Information/human/001241/WC500100494.pdf">http://www.ema.europa.eu/docs/en_GB/document_library/EPAR_-_Product_Information/human/001241/WC500100494.pdf</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 10 May 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1753944712468627">
<citation citation-type="gov"><collab>FDA</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Complete response review. Drug approval package</article-title>. <source>US Food and Drug Administration</source>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/nda/2011/022433Orig1s000TOC.cfm">http://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/nda/2011/022433Orig1s000TOC.cfm</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 5 November 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1753944712468627">
<citation citation-type="gov"><collab>FDA</collab> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Ticagrelor Advisory Committee Briefing Document. US Food and Drug Administration</article-title>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fda.gov/downloads/AdvisoryCommitteesMeetingMaterials/Drugs/CardiovascularandRenalDrugsAdvisoryCommittee/UCM220197.pdf">http://www.fda.gov/downloads/AdvisoryCommitteesMeetingMaterials/Drugs/CardiovascularandRenalDrugsAdvisoryCommittee/UCM220197.pdf</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 10 May 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1753944712468627">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>James</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Budaj</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aylward</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cornel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Ticagrelor versus clopidogrel in acute coronary syndromes in relation to renal function: results from the Platelet Inhibition and Patient Outcomes (PLATO) trial</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <volume>122</volume>: <fpage>1056</fpage>–<lpage>1067</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1753944712468627">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blankenship</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>ACCF/AHA/SCAI guidelines for percutaneous coronary intervention: a report of the American College of Cardiology Foundation/American Heart Association task force on practice guidelines and the Society for Cardiovascular Angiography and Interventions</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> <volume>124</volume>: <fpage>e574</fpage>–<lpage>e651</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1753944712468627">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wallentin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Budaj</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Emanuelsson</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Held</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>.; <collab>the PLATO Investigators</collab> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Ticagrelor versus clopidogrel in patients with acute coronary syndromes</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source> <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>1045</fpage>–<lpage>1057</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>