<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">UEX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spuex</journal-id>
<journal-title>Urban Education</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0042-0859</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-8340</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0042085912446165</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0042085912446165</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Influence of Process Drama on Elementary Students’ Written Language</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>Alida</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0042085912446165">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0042085912446165"><label>1</label>American University, Washington, DC, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0042085912446165">Alida Anderson, American University, School of Education, Teaching, and Health, 4400 Massachusetts Avenue, NW, Washington, DC 20016, USA Email: <email>aanderso@american.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>47</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>959</fpage>
<lpage>982</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article describes the influence of process drama on fourth grade students’ written language productivity and specificity. Participants included 16 students with learning and/or behavioral challenges at an urban public charter school. The influence of process drama on students’ written language was compared across contextualized and decontextualized activities to identify associations between activities and language outcomes. Significant increases in students’ written language productivity and specificity were observed in contextualized dramatic arts activities, as compared to decontextualized language arts activities. Implications and directions for future research in arts integration within content area instruction for students in inclusive settings are discussed.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>written language</kwd>
<kwd>elementary</kwd>
<kwd>disabilities</kwd>
<kwd>drama</kwd>
<kwd>productivity</kwd>
<kwd>specificity</kwd>
<kwd>inclusion</kwd>
<kwd>contextualized</kwd>
<kwd>decontextualized</kwd>
<kwd>literate language</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0042085912446165" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>This study contributes to the development of a literacy approach for students with language-based learning disabilities (LD) and developmental disabilities (DD), as well as those with literacy failure due to limited economic resources or socioeconomic status (SES) and emotional-behavioral disabilities (EBD) in an inclusive urban classroom setting. An unquestionable hallmark of recent educational initiatives is the concern for literacy achievement in students identified as “at-risk” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0042085912446165">Novosel, Deshler, Pollitt, Mark, &amp; Mitchell, 2011</xref>) for school failure due to a variety of learning challenges (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr82-0042085912446165">Williams, Ari, &amp; Dortch, 2011</xref>). One avenue for informing literacy initiatives in these populations involves the development of an instructional practice aimed at increasing students’ linguistic productivity and specificity through literate language feature (LLF) use.</p>
<p>Students who struggle in their use of precise and specific language (i.e., literate language) in academic contexts are among those at-risk for school failure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0042085912446165">Scott, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0042085912446165">Ukrainetz, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-0042085912446165">Wallach, Chariton, &amp; Christie, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-0042085912446165">Westby, 2006</xref>). In contrast, students who use literate language are characterized as those who “talk like books” and are reported to perform better on academic tasks than students who do not (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0042085912446165">Wallach &amp; Butler, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-0042085912446165">Westby &amp; Torres-Velasquez, 2000</xref>). However, studies examining the development of students’ language specificity and productivity in inclusive classrooms are few, and have not been conducted with diverse populations of students at-risk for literacy failure (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0042085912446165">Ukrainetz, 2006</xref> for a discussion). The current study examines the influence of process drama as a contextualized language activity on literacy outcomes (i.e., written productivity and specificity) in a classroom of fourth grade students at an urban charter school.</p>
<p>This line of inquiry is relevant to current education policy, research, and practice. At present, there is an emphasis on arts-based learning as a way to reach and teach all children (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-0042085912446165">U.S. Department of Education, 2010</xref>), and drama-based interventions are being adopted by education practitioners in an effort to improve students’ literacy outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0042085912446165">Hoyt, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0042085912446165">Rose, Parks, Androes, &amp; McMahon, 2010</xref>). However, to date, the relation between drama-based intervention and language-learning outcomes is underspecified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0042085912446165">Podlozny, 2000</xref>). The current study contributes to the literature by framing drama-based intervention as a contextualized language environment, allowing for a greater specification of the relation between drama and literacy outcomes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0042085912446165">
<title>Conceptual Framework</title>
<p>Literature related to development of linguistic specificity and productivity, contextualized–decontextualized language, and drama in education frames the current study. Cognitive and social learning theories explain children’s language development in terms of linguistic specificity and productivity. As children engage in symbolic representation, assimilation and accommodation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0042085912446165">Piaget, 1926</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0042085912446165">1963</xref>), and social interaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-0042085912446165">Vygotsky, 1978</xref>), they use increasingly complex and specific language features such as adverbs, conjunctions (causal, temporal, and sequential), noun phrases, and mental/linguistic verbs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0042085912446165">Anderson, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0042085912446165">Curenton &amp; Justice, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0042085912446165">Paul, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0042085912446165">Pellegrini, 1985</xref>). Social interaction theory has been used to interpret children’s increased understanding and use of specific language features such as noun phrases, conjunctive clauses, adverbs, and mental and linguistic verbs in dramatic-symbolic play contexts with peers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0042085912446165">Kempe, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0042085912446165">Pellegrini, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0042085912446165">Peter, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>Oral and written language mutually influence students’ development of linguistic specificity and productivity, since the structure and function of the language features is shared in expressing relationships among ideas (e.g., coordinating and subordinating conjunctions), open class-content words, noun phrases with attributive adjectives, relative clauses, and prepositional phrases (i.e., LLFs; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0042085912446165">Paul, 2002</xref>). Thus, students with problems in linguistic specificity in oral language evident first in early childhood, also have difficulties with LLF use in oral and written language (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0042085912446165">Scott, 2004</xref>). In particular, students with language-based exceptionalities (e.g., LD, DD) have documented struggles with linguistic specificity and productivity stemming from early deficits in semantic diversity and syntactic knowledge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0042085912446165">Scott, 1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0042085912446165">1995</xref>). Likewise, students from low SES backgrounds enter school with less semantic diversity and syntactic knowledge than their age-matched peers from middle-to-high SES backgrounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0042085912446165">Hart &amp; Risley, 1995</xref>). Similarly, students with EBD struggle with linguistic productivity and specificity in academic settings due to emotional and/or behavioral issues affecting motivation and engagement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0042085912446165">Brown, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0042085912446165">Foley, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0042085912446165">Nelson, Benner, Neill, &amp; Stage, 2006</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section3-0042085912446165">
<title>Contextualized–Decontextualized Language Use</title>
<p>A number of language researchers distinguish between two types of language use: contextualized and decontextualized (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0042085912446165">Figure 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0042085912446165">Paul, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0042085912446165">Scott, 1994</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-0042085912446165" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption><p>Differences Between Contextualized and Decontextualized Language</p>
<p>Source: Adapted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0042085912446165">Paul, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0042085912446165">Scott, 1994</xref>.</p></caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0042085912446165-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Contextualized language is related to “everyday” language activities like face-to-face conversations, in which shared knowledge and vocabulary, gestures, interactive negation of meaning, and listener feedback facilitate the apprehension of meaning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0042085912446165">Snow, 1991b</xref>). Contextualized language is associated with oral language, simple syntax, and repetition of high frequency vocabulary. As well, contextualized language often refers to the here-and-now, referencing of objects, people, and actions in the immediate environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0042085912446165">Westby, 1994</xref>).</p>
<p>In contrast, decontextualized language is associated with classroom language tasks, particularly reading and writing text, in which the speaker is removed from the context. Thus, decontextualized language is “comprehensible to an unknown audience without support from others” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0042085912446165">Westby, 1994</xref>, p. 56). Thus, decontextualized language tasks such as text reading are grounded in time and space, do not assume shared knowledge and vocabulary, and are often linguistically complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0042085912446165">De Temple, Wu, &amp; Snow, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Notably, both contextualized and decontextualized languages involve LLF use. Children are exposed to LLFs in events such as story sharing and symbolic play contexts with increasing shift to less familiar contexts such as school-based tasks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0042085912446165">Pellegrini &amp; Galda, 1998</xref>). Thus, children’s language production in literacy contexts such as storybook sharing and narration is typically characterized as their first experience with explicit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0042085912446165">Snow, 1991b</xref>) and decontextualized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0042085912446165">Snow, 1991a</xref>) language. Literacy researchers identify LLF use as the bridge between oral and written discourse, since LLF use develops across contextualized, oral language activities such as conversations, and also is required in decontextualized, written language activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0042085912446165">Dickinson &amp; McCabe, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0042085912446165">Kavanaugh, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0042085912446165">Paul, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>The contextualized–decontextualized language continuum has been used to explain children’s attainment of school-based literacy skills, particularly in relation to LLF use. For instance, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0042085912446165">Westby (1994)</xref>, in her work with school age populations, used this continuum to describe students’ attainment of school-based literacy skills across a variety of academic contexts (e.g., language arts, science, and mathematics). She found increased LLF use to differentiate high-performing from low-performing students (also see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0042085912446165">Pellegrini &amp; Galda, 1998</xref>, pp. 120-155 for a review). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0042085912446165">Wallach and Butler (1994)</xref> also indicated associations between elementary age students’ academic performance and linguistic specificity, in that students who effectively used LLFs early on in their academic careers were more likely to meet teachers’ expectations and to be rewarded, encouraged, and motivated in school than students who did not.</p>
<p>The contextualized–decontextualized continuum has also been used to characterize development of specific language registers in African American English, in which children use language features such as noun phrases, conjunctions, and adverbs (i.e., LLFs) in less familiar or unknown contexts (i.e., school), as compared to familiar (i.e., home) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0042085912446165">Charity, Scarborough, &amp; Griffin, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0042085912446165">Curenton &amp; Justice, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0042085912446165">Heath, 1983</xref>). In this application, researchers have described how children transition from familiar or contextualized oral language communication of events, to unfamiliar or decontextualized forms of classroom-based oral and written discourse.</p>
<p>Only a few studies, however, have investigated the influence of context on written language (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0042085912446165">Craig, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0042085912446165">Jones &amp; Pellegrini, 1996</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0042085912446165">Jones and Pellegrini (1996)</xref> found that contextualized writing, as defined by interaction between first grade students and their friends as well as their teachers, had a facilitating effect on the quality of students’ written narratives, in comparison to solitary writing activities. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0042085912446165">Craig (2006)</xref> also examined the effect of a contextualized interactive approach on kindergarten age children’s early literacy skills. Features of this contextualized instruction included teachers’ use of supportive, interactive discourse to mediate children’s participation and maximize children’s involvement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0042085912446165">Mariage, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0042085912446165">Pinnell &amp; McCarrier, 1994</xref>). Children participating in contextualized activities made greater gains in word reading and comprehension achievement than children participating in solitary reading activities. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0042085912446165">Ukrainetz et al. (2005)</xref> found that an interactive oral narrative storytelling activity using picture sequences influenced early elementary age students’ academic (i.e., decontextualized language such as LLFs) and artistic (e.g., quality of ideas, content, interest, individuality, and engagement) oral expression.</p>
<sec id="section4-0042085912446165">
<title>Contextualized–decontextualized language use in students with exceptionalities</title>
<p>Students with language-based LD have been reported to use fewer LLFs across contextualized and decontextualized activities, particularly in oral narrative storytelling, despite similar exposure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0042085912446165">Gillam &amp; Johnston, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0042085912446165">Kaderavek &amp; Sulzby, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0042085912446165">Ukrainetz &amp; Gillam, 2009</xref>). However, only a few studies have compared children with and without language-based exceptionalities across contextualized and decontextualized activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0042085912446165">Anderson, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0042085912446165">McKeough, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0042085912446165">Ukrainetz &amp; Gillam, 2009</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0042085912446165">McKeough (1984)</xref> showed a strong relationship between LLF use and dramatic play in oral narrative retellings of 8-to-12-year-old students with and without LD. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0042085912446165">Ukrainetz and Gillam (2009)</xref> found both elementary age children with and without LD to show increased oral language productivity and specificity using contextualized support (pictures and interactive practice) in narrative storytelling. More recently, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0042085912446165">Anderson (2011)</xref> found that preschool age children with and without language impairment had significantly greater linguistic specificity and productivity (as measured through LLF use) in contextualized play, as compared to storybook reading, children’s presumed earliest decontextualized language experience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0042085912446165">Snow, 1991b</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0042085912446165">
<title>Dramatic Arts in Education</title>
<p>Dramatic arts integration is generally defined as the linking of drama with a content area for the purposes of reaching a deeper level of engagement, learning, and reflection than would be possible without inclusion of the art form. In a drama-integrated classroom, students are working “with” and “through” drama to reach academic, social, and personal goals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0042085912446165">Cornett, 2007</xref>, p. 13). Throughout parts of the world such as Canada, England, Ireland, Turkey, and Australia, drama in education has been recognized as a dynamic methodology for teaching (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0042085912446165">Okvuran, 2010</xref>). Dramatic arts integration is most commonly identified as a process-oriented approach, which activates “learners’ imaginations by using dramatic structures associated with a larger theatrical field to explore content area curriculum, texts, relationships readers have with texts, issues connected to texts, and other aspects of literacy learning in diverse educational settings” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0042085912446165">Schneider, Crumpler, &amp; Rogers, 2006</xref>, p. XIV).</p>
<p>Generally, practitioners who implement dramatic arts integration support students in committing to a fictional world in which they identify with and assume multiple roles. In this context, students operate in two frames: the “meaning frame,” where understanding is shaped and manifested, and the “expressive frame,” where understanding is communicated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0042085912446165">Morgan &amp; Saxton, 1989</xref>, p. 21). Teachers facilitate learning experiences using structures within the dramatic context; teachers also may position themselves within the dramatic context as a character (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0042085912446165">Baldwin, 2008</xref>, p. 23). The organization of dramatic structures to support student learning is generally known as process drama (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0042085912446165">Cornett, 2007</xref>).</p>
<p>Dramatic arts approaches have been reported to influence students’ learning in a variety of content areas such as mathematics (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0042085912446165">Sengün &amp; Iskenderogulu, 2010</xref>, for a review), science (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0042085912446165">Kamen, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0042085912446165">Kase-Polisini, &amp; Spector, 1992</xref>) and vocabulary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0042085912446165">Demircioglu, 2010</xref>). Research on the integration of drama and literacy activities has focused on the idea that the arts influence academic and social/emotional outcomes, leading to students’ improved reading proficiency and academic self-concept in comparison to uninvolved students (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0042085912446165">Catterall, Chapleau, &amp; Iwanaga, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0042085912446165">Eisner, 1998</xref>). In addition, the relationship between dramatic arts activities and student achievement has been shown to be powerful for students from diverse socioeconomic, linguistic, and cultural backgrounds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0042085912446165">Ingram &amp; Seashore, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0042085912446165">Kempe, 2003</xref>). In particular, researchers have reported reliable causal relationships between elementary and secondary students’ increased verbal skills and participation in dramatic arts activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0042085912446165">Hetland &amp; Winner, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0042085912446165">Podlozny, 2000</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0042085912446165">Kempe (2003)</xref> explained the contribution of dramatic arts to language learning as increasing students’ social capital through their identification, analysis, and use of aural, visual and verbal grammar of spoken English to understand and express discourse appropriate for a range of situations.</p>
<sec id="section6-0042085912446165">
<title>Dramatic arts integration and students with exceptionalities</title>
<p>Research on the relationship between dramatic arts activities and literacy skills for students with exceptionalities (LD, EBD, and DD) has identified positive influences on reading comprehension, oral, and written language production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0042085912446165">Mason &amp; Steedly, 2006</xref>). A similar result of drama integration was reported from gains made by elementary age students with LD participating in a creative drama program, which led to their increased social and oral expressive language skills (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0042085912446165">de la Cruz, 1995</xref>). The impact of integrated arts activities on students’ social, cognitive, and language skills has also been documented from teachers’ and parents’ evaluations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0042085912446165">Mason, Steedly, &amp; Thormann, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>The social validity of dramatic arts-based approaches has been established in some studies. Students with primary difficulties in social and language skills (those identified with autism spectrum disorder, ASD) made robust gains in their social communication understanding and concept development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0042085912446165">Peter, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0042085912446165">Schieman &amp; Nichols, 2010</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0042085912446165">Peter’s (2003)</xref> dramatic play-based intervention for elementary age students with ASD supported their development of symbolic representations, social interactions, and emotional responses with peers. These findings indicated that the contextualized learning environment of dramatic play influenced students’ language, social, and emotional skills.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0042085912446165">
<title>Rationale</title>
<p>There is promising research to indicate that dramatic arts activities enhance verbal learning and academic engagement for involved students (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0042085912446165">Deasy, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0042085912446165">Podlozny, 2000</xref>), including evidence that the use of dramatic arts within academic settings potentially mediates linguistic specificity in students’ written language (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-0042085912446165">Wagner, 1998</xref>). However, to date, there have been insufficient explanations of how and why arts activities, including drama-based interventions, are related to academic outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr83-0042085912446165">Winner &amp; Cooper, 2000</xref>). The current study provides one potential explanation for the relation between dramatic arts and linguistic productivity and specificity in written language; namely by framing process drama as a case of contextualized language learning, and assessing linguistic productivity and specificity through LLF use. It is expected that process drama activities will operate as a facilitating mechanism of linguistic specificity and productivity for students who struggle with decontextualized language use, since the dramatic context supports them to understand and use specific and precise discourse across both oral and written activities.</p>
<p>Evidence to support this expectation includes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0042085912446165">Pellegrini’s (1985)</xref> assessment of linguistic specificity and productivity in preschoolers’ oral discourse, in which he reported highest correlations between contextualized dramatic play and LLF use over constructive and solitary play. Children’s increased LLF use in dramatic-play was interpreted as evidence of their mental representation of events and objects. As children acquired and integrated information to form increasingly sophisticated mental representations, they relied on increasingly specific and complex language features (i.e., LLFs) to express their ideas.</p>
<p>Other researchers have found children to use more LLFs in ideational, symbolic play, as compared to constructive or solitary object play (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0042085912446165">Culatta, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0042085912446165">Pellegrini, Galda, Bartini, &amp; Charak, 1998</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-0042085912446165">Van Oers (1998)</xref> suggested that children’s LLF use was linked to their development of meaningful abstract thinking or the ability to recontextualize previously experienced events, since they described temporal and sequential information through specific features such as conjunctive phrases. As well, children have been shown to understand and use specific features such as noun phrases, conjunctive clauses, adverbs, and mental/linguistic verbs most reliably in dramatic-play contexts with peers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0042085912446165">Pellegrini, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0042085912446165">Peter, 2003</xref>). Thus, the context of dramatic-play has been linked to children’s linguistic specificity since it supports their symbolic interactions and is linked to concrete objects in the environment, as well as to more abstract and socially mediated symbols (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0042085912446165">Kempe, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>The contextualized–decontextualized continuum of language use offers another possible explanation of “how” dramatic arts activities facilitate linguistic productivity and specificity across oral and written language use. Linguistic specificity and productivity develops through “facilitating mechanisms” of interaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0042085912446165">Luciarello &amp; Nelson, 1987</xref>) and setting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0042085912446165">Dickinson &amp; McCabe, 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0042085912446165">2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0042085912446165">Snow, 1991a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0042085912446165">1991b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-0042085912446165">Wells, 1985</xref>), both of which are critical aspects of dramatic arts integration.</p>
<p>While these studies have examined the relation between dramatic play and LLF use in early childhood and elementary age children, they have focused on oral, rather than written language, and have not explicitly framed dramatic arts integration as a contextualized language environment. The current study extends this line of inquiry by explicating this relation. The study poses two guiding research questions to examine the influence of process drama on students’ written language:</p>
<list id="list1-0042085912446165" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>What is the influence of process drama on students’ written language productivity?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>What is the influence of process drama on students’ written language specificity?</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0042085912446165" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<p>The next section provides information on the participating students and teachers and the school setting. This information is followed by a description of the intervention, data collection, and analysis procedures of the study.</p>
<sec id="section9-0042085912446165">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>In the present study, 16 fourth grade students (12 male, 4 female) participated in drama and language arts activities as part of their academic school day. All of the students had scored significantly below grade level (more than 2 years) on standardized reading and/or writing measures (<italic>Dynamic Indicators of Basic Early Literacy Skills</italic> (<italic>DIBELS</italic>), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0042085912446165">Good &amp; Kaminski, 2002</xref>). The majority (approximately 80%) of the classroom population was eligible for special education services based on diagnoses of LD, DD, and EBD.</p>
<p>The classroom teacher played an active role in the project as a participant-observer and as a drama character in-role. This teacher had a master’s degree in special education and 15 years of experience as a special education classroom teacher. At the time of the study, the teacher was enrolled in his 6 month of a year-long professional development program to integrate arts-based activities within content area instruction. The researcher and graduate assistants volunteered their time at the school to support the implementation of the arts-integration program through coaching activities. One graduate student trained in discourse analysis assisted with transcription and coding of students’ written language samples.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0042085912446165">
<title>Setting</title>
<p>The study took place in an urban charter school whose mission was to integrate the arts within classroom content area instruction across kindergarten through eighth grade. The school used an inclusive classroom model to serve a diverse array of students with and without disabilities. Sixty percent of the students attending the charter school had identified disabilities (e.g., DD, EBD, LD, and physical/motor disabilities). Across kindergarten through eighth grade, the majority of students without disabilities (approximately 40% of the school population) functioned at least 2 years below grade level in reading and written language skills. Each classroom had between 12 and 16 students and a master’s level certified special educator as well as a general education teacher. Over 95% of the school’s student population qualified for free and reduced lunch on the basis of their family’s economic status.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0042085912446165">
<title>Procedures</title>
<p>The process drama intervention occurred over an 8-week period in hour-long sessions averaging twice weekly. Initial activities began with students during their third month of the school year and concluded at the end of the 6 month. The initial 2 weeks of the intervention included decontextualized written language activities. These activities served as students’ introduction to the research team, activities and procedures. During this 2-week baseline period, students participated in an orientation to the dramatic arts medium.</p>
<p>The next 4 weeks involved students’ selection of, and acting in drama roles with the research team and classroom teacher in the fictional world created by a contemporary adaptation of <italic>Little Red Riding Hood</italic>. During this time, students participated in dramatic events with the researchers and completed contextualized written language tasks. For example, students were grouped for activities involving observation, interpretation, and discussion of the story events and character motives. Students participated in tableaux activities in which they illustrated ideas or concepts using nonverbal gesture and body positions. Assuming the role of protagonist, students completed independent in-role writing activities. The final 2 weeks involved decontextualized data collection through follow-up writing prompts.</p>
<sec id="section12-0042085912446165">
<title>Dependent variables</title>
<p>Students’ written language productivity was measured through the number of total words (NTW), number of different words (NDW) and number of utterances (UTT) they used in each of the written language samples collected over the course of the intervention period. These productivity measures have been shown to accurately and reliably assess students’ written language production in both contextualized as well as decontextualized activities (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0042085912446165">Greenhalgh &amp; Strong, 2001</xref>). Students’ written language specificity was measured through semantic diversity and expressed as the proportion of NDW/NTW. In addition to this semantic diversity measure, students’ use of LLFs was assessed, since LLF use has been shown to enable speakers to be specific and precise in both contextualized and decontextualized oral and written communication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0042085912446165">Anderson, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0042085912446165">Curenton &amp; Justice, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0042085912446165">Greenhalgh &amp; Strong, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0042085912446165">Jones, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0042085912446165">Ukrainetz, 1998</xref>). Literate language features included simple elaborated noun phrases (SENP; e.g., <italic>a dog, the girl</italic>), complex elaborated noun phrases (CENP; e.g., <italic>the red apple, our little dog</italic>), adverbs (ADV), conjunctions (CONJ), and mental and linguistic verbs (MLV; e.g., <italic>talk, think, feel</italic>). Number and frequency of LLFs, calculated as a proportion of students’ NTW, were used to describe changes in linguistic specificity of written discourse across activities.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0042085912446165">
<title>Independent variable</title>
<p>Students participated in written language sampling activities individually with the research team at three points in the project: (a) genre writing before the intervention period (WL1); (b) decontextualized genre writing at the end of the intervention period (WL2); and (c) contextualized in-role writing during the intervention period (WL3).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0042085912446165">
<title>Fidelity measures</title>
<p>Macro-level qualitative analysis of students’ written discourse was conducted to obtain information about their attitudes towards literacy learning activities as well as their topic focus and maintenance during written language activities. Preliminary data collection during the pre-intervention interviews indicated students had a limited understanding of the activities and skills comprising language arts as an instructional area. Students reported a range of ideas from science- to history-focused. Only one of the 16 students responded to the question of <italic>what is your favorite language arts activity</italic> with a statement that reflected his accurate understanding of language arts. Most students reported consistently high attitudes towards literacy activities (listening, reading, speaking, and writing); however, their self-reported, high literacy ratings contradicted their interview responses to probes such as, <italic>what do you like the most/least about language arts</italic>. In response to these probes, students stated that they did not like activities involving writing, reading, or speaking; and, in particular, that writing made their “hand hurt”.</p>
<p>Due to the inconsistency of baseline attitudinal data and students’ limited knowledge base and awareness of language arts components, we included an instructional focus within the process drama activities as an orientation to language arts and process drama. The intensity of the eight-session intervention period with the fourth grade class focused solely on the relationship between students’ contextualized process drama experience and its impact on decontextualized written language use.</p>
<p>In the current study, methods of inquiry included quantitative and qualitative analysis of students’ language samples across baseline, intervention and follow-up periods. Micro analysis of students’ written language was conducted via coding for productivity and specificity of language use. Two graduate students trained in language analysis discourse methods participated with the researcher in coding of students’ writing samples. In order to ensure fidelity, inter-rater agreement reached 95% accuracy level between coders, with disagreements resolved via conference.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0042085912446165" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Paired sample <italic>t</italic> tests were used to compare differences among variables of interest across written language contexts for the group of students. Data cleaning measures were taken to remove outliers and to check normality assumptions of the sample (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0042085912446165">Duncan, 1975</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section16-0042085912446165">
<title>Written Language Productivity</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0042085912446165">Table 1</xref> shows means, standard deviations, and significance levels for students’ written language productivity across baseline decontextualized written language (WL1), follow-up decontextualized written language (WL2), and contextualized written language (WL3) activities.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0042085912446165" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Means (and Standard Deviations) of Written Language Productivity Measures for Students (<italic>n</italic> = 16)</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0042085912446165" xlink:href="10.1177_0042085912446165-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Baseline Writing (WL1)<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Follow-Up Writing (WL2)<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Significance<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Follow-Up Writing (WL2)<hr/></th>
<th align="center">In-role Writing (WL3)<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Significance<hr/></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td/>
<td><italic>M</italic> (<italic>SD</italic>)</td>
<td><italic>M</italic> (<italic>SD</italic>)</td>
<td/>
<td><italic>M</italic> (<italic>SD</italic>)</td>
<td><italic>M</italic> (<italic>SD</italic>)</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NTW</td>
<td>22 (13)</td>
<td>36 (20)</td>
<td>.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0042085912446165">*</xref></td>
<td>36 (20)</td>
<td>71 (45)</td>
<td>.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0042085912446165">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NDW</td>
<td>18 (9)</td>
<td>25 (8)</td>
<td>.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0042085912446165">*</xref></td>
<td>25 (8)</td>
<td>44 (22)</td>
<td>.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0042085912446165">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>UTT</td>
<td>5 (2)</td>
<td>8 (3)</td>
<td>.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0042085912446165">**</xref></td>
<td>8 (3)</td>
<td>13 (7)</td>
<td>.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0042085912446165">*</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0042085912446165">
<p>Note: NTW = number of total words; NDW = number of different words; UTT = number of utterances.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0042085912446165">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt;.01.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>In the decontextualized written language activities, students were asked to write about a character and setting from their language arts assignment. In the contextualized writing activity, students were asked to select a setting and character from their language arts-drama integrated assignment and write from the character’s perspective (e.g., in-role). This activity was considered contextualized since students’ writing occurred in the context of the drama activity.</p>
<p>The dependent variable measures of written language productivity were NTW, NDW, and UTT used in each writing sample. Paired independent sample <italic>t</italic> tests revealed significant increases in students’ decontextualized written productivity as measured by differences in their production of NTW (<italic>p</italic> = .04), NDW (<italic>p</italic> = .03), and UTT (<italic>p</italic> = .00) from baseline to follow-up writing. The most significant increases in students’ written productivity were observed between decontextualized genre writing (WL2) and contextualized in-role writing (WL3). Data show students produced significantly more NTW and NDW in contextualized in-role (WL3) than in decontextualized (WL2) writing (<italic>p</italic>s = .01 and .00, respectively). Students’ most significant increases in written language productivity occurred between decontextualized baseline (WL1) and follow-up (WL2) writing in UTT (<italic>p</italic> = .00). As expected, students also showed increased UTT production between decontextualized (WL2) and contextualized in-role (WL3) writing (<italic>p</italic> = .03). No comparison was made between decontextualized baseline genre (WL1) and contextualized in-role writing (WL3) since students’ WL1 baseline was likely to be impacted by the external validity factor of familiarity with the researchers and procedures of the task.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0042085912446165">
<title>Written Language Specificity</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0042085912446165">Table 2</xref> shows means, standard deviations, and significance levels for written language specificity across the baseline decontextualized written language (WL1), follow-up decontextualized written language (WL2), and contextualized in-role written language (WL3) activities. Dependent measures of written language specificity included semantic diversity (NDW/NTW), frequency of LLF use (LLF/NTW), total number of LLFs, number of simple elaborated noun phrases (SENP), number of complex elaborated noun phrases (CENP), number of adverbs (ADV), number of conjunctions (CONJ), and number of mental/linguistic verbs (MLV). Similar to written language productivity, students showed significant differences between decontextualized writing and contextualized in-role writing in their increased use of LLF (<italic>p</italic> = .05), CENP (<italic>p</italic> = .05), CONJ (<italic>p</italic> = .04) and MLV (<italic>p</italic> = .05) in contextualized writing samples.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0042085912446165" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption><p>Means (and Standard Deviations) of Written Language Specificity Measures for Students (<italic>n</italic> = 16)</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0042085912446165" xlink:href="10.1177_0042085912446165-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Baseline Writing (WL1)<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Follow-Up Writing (WL2)<hr/></th>
<th/>
<th align="center">Follow-Up Writing (WL2)<hr/></th>
<th align="center">In-role Writing (WL3)<hr/></th>
<th/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic> (<italic>SD</italic>)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic> (<italic>SD</italic>)</th>
<th align="center">Significance</th>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic> (<italic>SD</italic>)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic> (<italic>SD</italic>)</th>
<th align="center">Significance</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Semantic diversity</td>
<td>0.84 (0.13)</td>
<td>0.74 (0.15)</td>
<td>.12</td>
<td>0.74 (0.15)</td>
<td>0.71 (0.15)</td>
<td>.44</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LLF frequency</td>
<td>0.33 (0.06)</td>
<td>0.35 (0.07)</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>0.35 (0.07)</td>
<td>0.31 (0.11)</td>
<td>.12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LLF</td>
<td>7.4 (5.21)</td>
<td>10.31 (8.5)</td>
<td>.14</td>
<td>10.31 (8.5)</td>
<td>20.31 (12.8)</td>
<td>.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0042085912446165">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SENP</td>
<td>3.33 (2.35)</td>
<td>4.33 (3.67)</td>
<td>.24</td>
<td>4.33 (3.67)</td>
<td>6.31 (4.32)</td>
<td>.20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CENP</td>
<td>0.53 (0.83)</td>
<td>0.80 (0.77)</td>
<td>.26</td>
<td>0.80 (0.77)</td>
<td>1.85 (1.57)</td>
<td>.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0042085912446165">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ADV</td>
<td>0.6 (0.73)</td>
<td>1.27 (1.38)</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>1.27 (1.38)</td>
<td>1.08 (0.95)</td>
<td>.77</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CONJ</td>
<td>1.93 (1.83)</td>
<td>2.47 (2.97)</td>
<td>.54</td>
<td>2.47 (2.97)</td>
<td>5.46 (4.09)</td>
<td>.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0042085912446165">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MLV</td>
<td>1.46 (1.18)</td>
<td>2.13 (1.55)</td>
<td>.20</td>
<td>2.13 (1.55)</td>
<td>5.62 (4.8)</td>
<td>.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0042085912446165">*</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0042085912446165">
<p>Note: Semantic Diversity = NDW/NTW; LLF Frequency = Number of literate language features (LLF)/NTW; LLF = Total number of LLF; SENP = Simple elaborated noun phrases; CENP = Complex elaborated noun phrases; ADV = Adverbs; CONJ = Conjunctions; MLV = Mental/linguistic verbs.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-0042085912446165">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> ≤ .05.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0042085912446165" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>This section summarizes the influences of the dramatic arts intervention on students’ written language. Implications for practice and future research are discussed, as well as conclusions.</p>
<sec id="section19-0042085912446165">
<title>Influences on Written Language</title>
<p>The dramatic arts intervention was positively associated with gains in students’ decontextualized and contextualized written language, both in terms of productivity and specificity. Significant differences in students’ contextualized and decontextualized written language indicated that the contextualized in-role writing experience had a mediating effect on students’ written linguistic specificity as it did for their productivity. Students produced twice as many LLFs in contextualized as compared to decontextualized written language activities. There were significant increases in students’ use of CENPs in their detailed descriptions and elaborations. Students used significantly more CONJs to convey temporal, causal, and sequential ideas in contextualized written language. Also, students used significantly more MLVs to communicate feelings, moods, and expressions in contextualized written language activities as compared with decontextualized written language activities.</p>
<p>The relation between the drama intervention and students’ written language can be explained by students’ contextualized in-role writing, in that the drama context provided scaffolding for students to mentally represent concepts and ideas, and then to use oral and written language in the service of expression (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0042085912446165">Durham, 2010</xref>). In other words, since the students were situated within the text (drama), their writing in-role was contextualized and was likely to reflect increased specificity and productivity “as it rose naturally in response to the situations encountered” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0042085912446165">Cremin, Goouch, Blakemore, Goff, &amp; Macdonald, 2006</xref>, p. 276).</p>
<p>One of the most interesting aspects of the dramatic arts intervention was in the apparent transfer from students’ gains in contextualized writing to decontextualized genre writing. Arguably, this increase in students’ decontextualized written language productivity resulted from their exposure, experience, and success with contextualized in-role writing. In other words, the observed gains in decontextualized written language productivity were likely influenced by students’ direct experience with the learning context as well as their emotional engagement with the subject matter, supporting social-interactionist framework (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0042085912446165">Ukrainetz, 2006</xref>). Anecdotally, teachers shared that students who received individualized occupational therapy service for written language, and who had been previously classified as “non-writers,” were attempting to write independently during their therapy sessions in the period following the drama intervention. While this finding was not systematically examined in the present study, teachers’ spontaneous reports do offer an interesting extension of the reported findings.</p>
<p>This evidence is encouraging, and indicates that with more time and experience in using linguistically specific discourse in contextualized activities, students could demonstrate more substantial increases to their decontextualized written language productivity and specificity. It is likely that some students would continue to need concrete and representational aspects of the context to produce linguistically specific discourse. This interpretation is consistent with findings on the ways in which students with language-based learning challenges benefit from concrete and/or representational forms to support concept development and expression of ideas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0042085912446165">Anderson, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0042085912446165">Durham, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0042085912446165">Ukrainetz, 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0042085912446165">2001</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0042085912446165">
<title>Implications</title>
<p>The findings of this study have important implications for the development of interventions to support students’ literacy skill acquisition through meaningful and authentic experiences that foster practice and capacity building in decontextualized language use through contextualized language activities. Other researchers contend that students’ engagement enables them to create, express, and extend their ideas through a meaningful context that empowers them “to make connections between the thinking involved in different parts of the drama with their thinking in real life contexts” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0042085912446165">McGuiness, 1999</xref>, p. 55). The current study provides empirical support for this contention.</p>
<p>As well, the information about the use of dramatic arts activities and students’ written language outcomes has implications for practitioners and caregivers working with students with diverse literacy learning needs, as it may challenge conventional learning expectations held for them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0042085912446165">Flowers &amp; Flowers, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0042085912446165">Shepherd, 2011</xref>). These results demonstrate the ways in which context supports students’ increasing exposure to, and success with literacy learning.</p>
<p>This work also implies a shift in the way that teachers position themselves in the classroom (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-0042085912446165">Ye, Varelas, &amp; Guajardo, 2011</xref>). Conventional approaches to remediation and literacy instruction tend to focus exclusively on teacher-directed examinations of text (i.e., decontextualized). Dramatic arts integration provides an alternative context in which students and teachers coexist and engage in activities that “support and give opportunities for inference and the understanding of subtext and the meaning and emotions lying behind spoken and written words” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0042085912446165">Baldwin, 2008</xref>, p. 52).</p>
<p>A final implication of this work is the effectiveness of shifting the focus of student experience from that of passive observer to active explorer of the meaning of text by actualizing it or performing its meaning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0042085912446165">Iser, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0042085912446165">Schneider et al., 2006</xref>). Furthermore, the fictional environment of process drama encouraged individual students to take risks and develop ideas rather than to simply receive information (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-0042085912446165">Wagner, 1998</xref>, p. 10).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-0042085912446165">
<title>Future Research</title>
<p>One of the untapped areas of this study is the relationship between students’ participation in the dramatic arts activities and their engagement with literacy learning. Anecdotal evidence from the classroom’s special educator, occupational therapist, and speech therapist indicated that the majority of the students showed increased willingness to participate in and positive attitudes towards written language activities. This is a clear area for future research to address insofar as student engagement and motivation played a key role in written language production over the course of the intervention period.</p>
<p>Additional research in this area could aim to involve teachers in generating performance-based rubrics (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0042085912446165">Mason &amp; Steedly, 2006</xref>) to assess students’ language, social, and arts skills in dramatic activities, which could then be triangulated with students’ written language data. Another direction for research could include behavioral observations and parent/caregiver evaluations of students’ literacy learning before, during, and after dramatic arts integrated activities. Informal analysis of practitioner data revealed that students made significant gains in their engagement, motivation, and willingness to participate in both contextualized and decontextualized written language activities. The relationship between student engagement and learning through the arts has been demonstrated in arts integrated settings with students having LD (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0042085912446165">Durham, 2010</xref>), and clearly fits within the social-interactionist framework used in contextualized language intervention (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0042085912446165">Ukrainetz, 2006</xref> for a review).</p>
<p>Further research regarding the influence of dramatic arts integration on literacy learning could focus on the social and emotional transfer of ideas and thoughts. For instance, most art forms merge the emotion of one’s inner world with the representational systems of external environment, or outer world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0042085912446165">Kempe, 2003</xref>). Therefore, a learning context comprising inner emotions and outer world conventions may foster students’ increased command and voice in written language, as evident in students’ increased use of LLFs such as mental, linguistic, and descriptive language.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-0042085912446165" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>This study extends previous research by incorporating analysis of elementary age students’ expressive written language across contextualized and decontextualized activities to identify associations between skills and context of use. The evidence generated by this study supports process drama as a contextualized literacy activity to address linguistic specificity, motivation, and engagement among students with diverse learning needs.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack><p>Appreciation is extended to the teachers, students and administrators at the charter school in which the intervention project occurred. Special thanks extended to Linda Krakaur for leadership of the drama intervention activities. Appreciation is extended to Patrick Shaw for his classroom collaboration, and to Sarah Baracks for research assistance with data analysis. Thanks to Sandra Loughlin and Nicole Scifo for sharing feedback and expertise.</p></ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<title>Bio</title>
<p><bold>Alida Anderson</bold> is an Assistant Professor of Special Education in the School of Education, Teaching and Health at American University, Washington, DC. Alida’s research interests are in language acquisition, literacy development, and learning-related challenges to literacy. Her research focuses on the contextualization of language to support students with a range of literacy-related challenges.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Linguistic specificity through literate language use in preschool age children with specific language impairment and typical language</article-title>. <source>Child Language Teaching and Therapy</source>, <volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>The practical primary drama handbook</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Lost and turned out: Academic, social, and emotional experiences of students excluded from school</article-title>. <source>Urban Education</source>, <volume>42</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>432</fpage>-<lpage>455</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Catterall</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chapleau</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iwanaga</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Involvement in the arts and human development: General involvement and intensive involvement in music and theater arts</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Fiske</surname><given-names>E. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Champions of change: The impact of the arts on learning</source> (pp. <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>18</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Arts Education Partnership</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Charity</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scarborough</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Familiarity with school English in African-American children and its relation to early reading achievement</article-title>. <source>Child Development</source>, <volume>75</volume>, <fpage>1340</fpage>-<lpage>1356</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cornett</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Creating meaning through literature and the arts</source>. <publisher-loc>Saddle River, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pearson</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The effects of an adapted interactive writing intervention on kindergarten children’s phonological awareness, spelling, and early reading development: A contextualized approach to instruction</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>98</volume>, <fpage>714</fpage>-<lpage>731</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cremin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goouch</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blakemore</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goff</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Macdonald</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Connecting drama and writing: Seizing the moment to write</article-title>. <source>Research in Drama in Education</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>273</fpage>-<lpage>291</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Culatta</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Representational play and story enactments: Formats for language intervention</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Duchan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sonnenmeier</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Pragmatics: From theory to practice</source> (pp. <fpage>105</fpage>-<lpage>119</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice-Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Curenton</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Justice</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Low-income preschoolers’ use of decontextualized discourse: Literate language features in oral narratives</article-title>. <source>Language, Speech, and Hearing Services in Schools</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>240</fpage>-<lpage>253</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deasy</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Critical links: Learning in the arts and student academic and social development</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Arts Education Partnership</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="thesis">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>de la Cruz</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source>The effects of creative drama on the social and oral language skills of children with learning disabilities</source> (<comment>Doctoral dissertation</comment>). <publisher-name>Illinois State University</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Bloomington</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Demircioglu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Teaching English vocabulary to young learners via drama</article-title>. <source>Procedia Social and Behavioral Sciences</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>439</fpage>-<lpage>443</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>De Temple</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Papa pig just left for pigtown: Children’s oral and written picture descriptions under varying instructions</article-title>. <source>Discourse Processes</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>469</fpage>-<lpage>495</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>The acquisition and development of language: A social-interactionist account of language and literacy development</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Kavanaugh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.). <source>The language continuum: From infancy to literacy</source> (pp. <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>40</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Parkton, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>York Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Bringing it all together: The multiple origins, skills, and environmental supports of early literacy</article-title>. <source>Learning Disabilities Research &amp; Practice</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>186</fpage>-<lpage>202</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1975</year>). <article-title>T-tests and intervals for comparisons suggested by the data</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>339</fpage>-<lpage>360</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Durham</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Sally Smith’s arts-based and integrated curricular approach to educating students with learning disabilities</article-title>. <source>Learning Disabilities: A Multidisciplinary Journal</source>, <volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>45</fpage>-<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eisner</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Does experience in the arts boost academic achievement?</article-title> <source>Art Education</source>, <volume>51</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>7</fpage>-<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Flowers</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Flowers</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Factors affecting urban African American high school students’ achievement in reading</article-title>. <source>Urban Education</source>, <volume>43</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>154</fpage>-<lpage>171</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Academic characteristics of incarcerated youth and correctional educational programs: A literature review</article-title>. <source>Journal of Emotional and Behavioral Disorders</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>248</fpage>-<lpage>259</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gillam</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Spoken and written language relationships in language/learning-impaired and normally achieving school-age children</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech and Hearing Research</source>,<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>1303</fpage>-<lpage>1315</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Good</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaminski</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Dynamic indicators of basic early literacy skills</source> (<edition>6th ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Eugene, OR</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Institute for the Development of Educational Achievement</publisher-name>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dibels.uoregon.edu">http://dibels.uoregon.edu</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Greenhalgh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strong</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Literate language features in spoken narratives of children with typical language and children with language impairments</article-title>. <source>Language, Speech, and Hearing Services in Schools</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>114</fpage>-<lpage>125</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Risley</surname><given-names>R. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source>Meaningful differences in the everyday experience of young American children</source>. <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Paul H. Brookes</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <source>Ways with words: Language, life and work in communities and classrooms</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hetland</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Winner</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>The arts and academic achievement: What the evidence shows</article-title>. <source>Arts Education Policy Review</source>, <volume>102</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hoyt</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Many ways of knowing: Using drama, oral interactions, and the visual arts to enhance reading comprehension</article-title>. <source>The Reading Teacher</source>, <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>580</fpage>-<lpage>584</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ingram</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seashore</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>Arts for academic achievement: Summative evaluation report</source>. <publisher-loc>Minneapolis, MN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Center for Applied Research and Educational Improvement</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Iser</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <source>Prospecting: From reader response to literary anthropology</source>. <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Collaborative writing and children’s use of literate language: A sequential analysis of social interaction</article-title>. <source>Journal of Early Childhood Literacy</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>165</fpage>-<lpage>178</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>The effects of social relationships, writing media, and microgenetic development on first-grade students’ written narratives</article-title>. <source>American Educational Research Journal</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>691</fpage>-<lpage>718</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaderavek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sulzby</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Narrative production by children with and without specific language impairment: Oral narratives and emergent readings</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech, Language, and Hearing Research</source>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>34</fpage>-<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kamen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Creative drama and the enhancement of elementary school students’ understanding of science concepts</article-title>. <source>Dissertation Abstracts International</source>, <volume>52</volume>(<issue>07</issue>), <fpage>2489</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kase-Polisini</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spector</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Improvised drama: A tool for teaching science</article-title>. <source>Youth Theatre Journal</source>, <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>15</fpage>-<lpage>19</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Kavanaugh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). (Ed.). <source>The language continuum: From infancy to literacy</source>. <publisher-loc>Parkton, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>York Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kempe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The role of drama in the teaching of speaking and listening as the basis for social capital</article-title>. <source>Research in Drama Education: The Journal of Applied Theatre and Performance</source>, <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>65</fpage>-<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Luciarello</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <article-title>Remembering and planning: Talk between mothers and children (EJ360623)</article-title>. <source>Discourse Processes</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>219</fpage>-<lpage>235</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mariage</surname><given-names>T. V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Features of an interactive writing discourse: Conversational involvement, conventional knowledge, and internalization in morning message</article-title>. <source>Journal of Learning Disabilities</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>172</fpage>-<lpage>206</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>C. Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steedly</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Rubrics and an arts integration community of practice</article-title>. <source>Teaching Exceptional Children PLUS</source>, <volume>39</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>36</fpage>-<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steedly</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thormann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>The impact of arts integration: Voice, choice and access</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>VSA Arts</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McGuiness</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>From thinking skills to thinking classrooms</source>. <publisher-loc>Nottingham, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department for Education and Employment Publications</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McKeough</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <source>Developmental stages in children’s narrative composition</source> (<comment>ED249461</comment>). <conf-name>Paper presented at the 68th Annual Meeting of the American Educational Research Association</conf-name>, <conf-loc>New Orleans, LA</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saxton</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <source>Teaching drama: A mind of many wonders</source>. <publisher-loc>Cheltenham, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nelson Thornes</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Benner</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neill</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stage</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Interrelationships among language skills, externalizing behavior, and academic fluency and their impact on the academic skills of students with EBD</article-title>. <source>Journal of Emotional and Behavioral Disorders</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>209</fpage>-<lpage>216</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Novosel</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deshler</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pollitt</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>At-risk learners (characteristics)</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Seel</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Encyclopedia of the Science of Learning</source> (pp. <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>5</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Verlag, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Okvuran</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The relationship between arts education, museum education and drama education in elementary education</article-title>. <source>Procedia Social and Behavioral Sciences</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>5389</fpage>-<lpage>5392</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Language disorders from infancy through adolescence: Assessment and intervention</source>. <publisher-loc>St. Louis, MO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Mosby</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Relations between preschool children’s symbolic play and literate behaviors</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Galda</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Play, language and stories: The development of children’s literate behavior</source> (pp. <fpage>79</fpage>-<lpage>97</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Norwood, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Albex</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Galda</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Peer interaction, play, and literate language: Naturalistic and experimental evidence from preschool and primary classrooms</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Galda</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The development of school-based literacy: A social-ecological perspective</source> (pp. <fpage>60</fpage>-<lpage>88</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Galda</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bartini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Charak</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Oral language and literacy learning in context: The role of social relationships</article-title>. <source>Merrill-Palmer Quarterly</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>38</fpage>-<lpage>54</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Drama, narrative and early learning</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Special Education</source>, <volume>30</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>21</fpage>-<lpage>28</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Piaget</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1926</year>). <source>The language and thought of the child</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harcourt Brace</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Piaget</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1963</year>). <source>The origins of intelligence in children</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Norton</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pinnell</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCarrier</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Interactive writing: A transition tool for assisting children in learning to read and write</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hiebert</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Getting reading right from the start: Effective early literacy interventions</source> (pp. <fpage>149</fpage>-<lpage>170</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Needham, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Allyn &amp; Bacon</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Podlozny</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Strengthening verbal skills through the use of classroom drama: A clear link</article-title>. <source>Journal of Aesthetic Education</source>, <volume>34</volume>(<issue>3/4</issue>), <fpage>239</fpage>-<lpage>275</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Parks</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Androes</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Imagery-based learning: Improving elementary students’ reading comprehension with drama techniques</article-title>. <source>Journal of Educational Research</source>, <volume>94</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>55</fpage>-<lpage>63</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schieman</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>, <month>April</month>). <source>How a drama program improves the social understanding of adolescents with Autism</source>. <conf-name>Presentation at the Council for Exceptional Children 2010 Convention and Expo</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Nashville, TN</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Crumpler</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Process drama and multiple literacies: Addressing social, cultural, and ethical issues</source>. <publisher-loc>Portsmouth, NH</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Heinemann</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>A discourse continuum for school-age students</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Wallach</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Language learning disabilities in school-age children and adolescents: Some principles and applications</source> (pp. <fpage>219</fpage>-<lpage>252</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Syntax for school age children: A discourse perspective</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Fey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Windsor</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Language intervention: Preschool through the elementary years</source> (pp. <fpage>107</fpage>-<lpage>143</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brookes</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Syntactic contributions to literacy learning</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Silliman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ehren</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Apel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Handbook of language and literacy: Development and disorders</source> (pp. <fpage>340</fpage>-<lpage>362</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sengün</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Iskenderogulu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>A review of creative drama studies in math education: Aim, data collection, data analyses, sample and conclusions of studies</article-title>. <source>Procedia Social and Behavioral Sciences</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1214</fpage>-<lpage>1219</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Effects of ethnicity and gender on teachers’ evaluation of students’ spoken responses</article-title>. <source>Urban Education</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>1011</fpage>-<lpage>1028</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991a</year>). <article-title>Diverse conversational contexts for the acquisition of various language skills</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Research on child language disorders: A decade of progress</source> (pp. <fpage>105</fpage>-<lpage>124</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Austin, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pro-Ed</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991b</year>). <article-title>The theoretical basis for relationships between language and literacy development</article-title>. <source>Journal of Research in Childhood Education</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ukrainetz</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Stickwriting stories: A quick and easy narrative notation strategy</article-title>. <source>Language, Speech, and Hearing Services in the Schools</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>197</fpage>-<lpage>207</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ukrainetz</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Narrative assessment: Coherence, cohesion, and captivation</article-title>. <source>Perspectives on Language Learning and Education</source>, <volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>11</fpage>-<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ukrainetz</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Contextualized language intervention</source>. <publisher-loc>Eau Claire, WI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Thinking Publications</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ukrainetz</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gillam</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The expressive elaboration of imaginative narratives by children with specific language impairment</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech, Language, and Hearing Research</source>, <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>883</fpage>-<lpage>898</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ukrainetz</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Justice</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaderavek</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gillam</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harm</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The development of expressive elaboration in fictional narratives</article-title>. <source>Journal of Speech, Language, and Hearing Research</source>, <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>1363</fpage>-<lpage>1377</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>U.S. Department of Education</collab>. (<year>2010</year>). <source>Issue brief: Arts education through the U.S. Department of Education</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.artsusa.org/get_involved/advocacy/aad/issue_briefs/2007/advocacy_issuebrief_004.asp#">http://www.artsusa.org/get_involved/advocacy/aad/issue_briefs/2007/advocacy_issuebrief_004.asp#</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Van Oers</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Mathematics learning in sociocultural contexts (EJ582925)</article-title>. <source>Learning and Instruction</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>469</fpage>-<lpage>572</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vygotsky</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <source>Mind in society: The development of higher psychological processes</source> (<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>John-Steiner</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scribner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Souberman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, Eds.). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Educational drama and language arts: What research shows</source>. <publisher-loc>Portsmouth, NH</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Heinemann</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wallach</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Creating communication, literacy, and academic success</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Wallach</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Language learning disabilities in school-age children and adolescents</source> (pp. <fpage>2</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr77-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wallach</surname><given-names>G. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chariton</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Christie</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Making a broader case for the narrow view: Where to begin?</article-title> <source>Language, Speech, and Hearing Services in Schools</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>201</fpage>-<lpage>211</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr78-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>Preschool literacy-related activities and success in school</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Torrance</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hildyard</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Literacy, language, and learning: The nature and consequences of reading and writing</source> (pp. <fpage>229</fpage>-<lpage>253</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr79-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Westby</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>The effects of culture on genre, structure, and style of oral and written texts</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Wallach</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Language learning disabilities in school-age children and adolescents</source> (pp. <fpage>180</fpage>-<lpage>218</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr80-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Westby</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>There’s more to passing than knowing the answers: Learning to do school</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Ukrainetz</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Contextualized language intervention</source> (pp. <fpage>319</fpage>-<lpage>387</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Eau Claire, WI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Thinking Publications</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr81-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Westby</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Torres-Velasquez</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Developing scientific literacy: A socio-cultural approach</article-title>. <source>Remedial and Special Education</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>101</fpage>-<lpage>110</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr82-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ari</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dortch</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The relationships between human capital, implicit views of intelligence, and literacy performance: Implications for the Obama education era</article-title>. <source>Urban Education</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>563</fpage>-<lpage>587</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr83-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Winner</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Mute those claims: No evidence (yet) for a causal link between arts study and academic achievement</article-title>. <source>Journal of Aesthetic Education</source>, <volume>34</volume>(<issue>3/4</issue>), <fpage>11</fpage>-<lpage>75</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr84-0042085912446165">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Varelas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guajardo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Subject-matter experts in urban schools: Journeys of enacted identities in science and mathematics classrooms</article-title>. <source>Urban Education</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>845</fpage>-<lpage>879</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>