<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JIC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjic</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Intensive Care Med</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Intensive Care Medicine</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0885-0666</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1525-1489</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0885066611411410</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0885066611411410</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Review of a Large Clinical Series</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Mortality of Patients With Respiratory Insufficiency and Adult Respiratory Distress Syndrome After Surgery</article-title>
<subtitle>The Obesity Paradox</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Memtsoudis</surname>
<given-names>Stavros G.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, PhD, FCCP</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0885066611411410">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0885066611411410"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bombardieri</surname>
<given-names>Anna Maria</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0885066611411410">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>Yan</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD, FCCP</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0885066611411410">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Walz</surname>
<given-names>J. Matthias</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD, FCCP</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0885066611411410">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chiu</surname>
<given-names>Ya Lin</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MS</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0885066611411410">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mazumdar</surname>
<given-names>Madhu</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0885066611411410">4</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0885066611411410">
<label>1</label>Department of Anesthesiology, Hospital for Special Surgery, New York, NY, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0885066611411410">
<label>2</label>Division of Biostatistics, Hospital for Special Surgery, New York, NY, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0885066611411410">
<label>3</label>Department of Anesthesiology, Division of Critical Care Medicine, University of Massachusetts Medical School, Worcester, MA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0885066611411410">
<label>4</label>Department of Public Health, Division of Biostatistics and Epidemiology, Weill Medical College of Cornell University, New York, NY, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0885066611411410">Stavros G. Memtsoudis, Department of Anesthesiology. Hospital for Special Surgery, 535 East 70th Street, New York, 10021, NY, USA. Email: <email>MemtsoudisS@hss.edu</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>27</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>306</fpage>
<lpage>311</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>8</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2010</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>12</day>
<month>1</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>8</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec>
<title>Introduction:</title><p>Obesity has long been considered a risk factor for the development of various pathologies, yet evidence supporting increased risk of perioperative mortality in obese individuals developing postoperative complications is limited. Therefore, we sought to characterize the demographics of obese and nonobese individuals developing postoperative respiratory insufficiency (RI)/adult respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) and to quantify the impact of obesity on in-hospital mortality among this patient population utilizing data collected for the Nationwide Inpatient Sample (NIS).</p></sec>
<sec>
<title>Methods:</title><p>Nationwide Inpatient Sample data for each year between 1998 and 2007 were accessed. Entries were included if they underwent a surgical procedure and had a diagnosis of RI/ARDS following surgery. Patients fulfilling entry criteria were divided into those with and without obesity. In-hospital mortality was the primary outcome. A logistic regression model was fitted to elucidate if obesity was associated with increased odds for the outcome while controlling for age, gender, admission and procedure type, and comorbidity burden.</p></sec>
<sec>
<title>Results:</title><p>We identified 9 149 030 admissions that underwent the included surgical procedures between 1998 and 2007. Of those, 5.48% had a diagnosis of obesity. The incidence of RI/ARDS was 1.82% among obese and 2.01% among nonobese patients. Obese patients whose postoperative course was complicated by RI/ARDS had a significantly lower incidence of the need for mechanical ventilation (50% vs 55%). In-hospital mortality was significantly lower compared to nonobese patients (5.45% vs 18.72%). For those patients with RI/ARDS requiring intubation, the in-hospital mortality rate was 11% for obese and 25% for nonobese patients. In the multivariate regression analysis, obesity was associated with a 69% reduction in the odds of in-hospital mortality in postoperative patients with RI/ARDS.</p></sec>
<sec>
<title>Conclusion:</title><p>In our analysis, obesity was associated with a decreased incidence and adjusted odds for in-hospital mortality after surgery. Our results support the emerging concept of the “obesity paradox.”</p></sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>obesity</kwd>
<kwd>respiratory insufficiency/adult respiratory distress syndrome</kwd>
<kwd>in-hospital mortality</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<custom-meta-wrap>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
<meta-value>September/October 2012</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-wrap>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0885066611411410">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Obesity has long been considered a risk factor for the development of a wide spectrum of pathologies, including hypertension, heart failure, cardiovascular diseases, and death from all causes.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0885066611411410">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0885066611411410">2</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Although the increased incidence of a variety of comorbidities associated with excess body weight has been well documented, the literature assessing perioperative risk of adverse outcomes in obese patients is sparse. While an increase in complications such as surgical site infections and perioperative hypoxemia has been reported, the risk of further morbidity and mortality in this patient population is not well studied.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0885066611411410">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0885066611411410">4</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Recent publications have described a phenomenon known as the “obesity paradox” or “reverse epidemiology,” suggesting that morbidity and mortality decrease with increasing body mass index (BMI) in settings such as acute heart failure and after cardiac catheterization.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0885066611411410">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0885066611411410"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0885066611411410">7</xref>
</sup> Thus, it has been suggested that obesity may offer protection from fatal outcomes in patients with well-known cardiovascular pathologies. Available studies are limited by their single institutional nature and relatively small sample sizes diminishing their ability to appropriately address low-incidence outcomes.</p>
<p>Furthermore, little is known about the role of obesity on the outcome of mortality in patients developing complications after surgical procedures.</p>
<p>In this context, we aimed to evaluate the impact of obesity on in-hospital death in patients with postoperative respiratory insufficiency (RI)/adult respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), a condition associated with a high risk of mortality.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0885066611411410">8</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Utilizing a large nationally representative database, our goals were to (1) characterize the demographics of obese and nonobese patients developing postoperative RI/ARDS after some of the most common surgical procedures and (2) quantify the impact of obesity on in-hospital mortality among this patient population.</p>
<p>We hypothesized that obese patients who developed RI/ARDS after major surgery had a reduced postoperative rate and risk of in-hospital mortality compared to their nonobese counterparts.</p>
<sec id="section2-0885066611411410" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<p>Nationwide Inpatient Sample (NIS) data files sponsored by the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ) were commercially obtained from the Hospital Cost and Utilization Project (HCUP) and analyzed for this study. The NIS represents the largest all-payer inpatient discharge database in the United States. Detailed information on the NIS design can be accessed electronically.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0885066611411410">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0885066611411410">10</xref>
</sup> Recognizing its utility to answer valuable clinical questions, a large number of studies addressing various aspects across the spectrum of medical specialties have been published.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0885066611411410">11</xref>
</sup> As the data used in this study are sufficiently de-identified, this project was exempt from review by the institutional review board.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0885066611411410">
<title>Selection of Study Sample and Statistical Analysis</title>
<p>Our study sample consists of all data in NIS for each year between 1998 and 2007. Entries included in our analysis had to fulfill 2 criteria: (1) indication of the performance of a surgical procedure (as defined below) and (2) contain a diagnosis of RI/ARDS following a surgical procedure. Procedure types included were open abdominal, laparoscopic abdominal, hip and knee arthroplasty, spine, cardiac, thoracic, major vascular, and surgeries of the head and neck. Procedures were selected using the Clinical Classifications Software for Services and Procedures (CCSSP)<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0885066611411410">12</xref>
</sup> provided by the AHRQ. Discharges with <italic>International Classification of Diseases, Ninth Revision, Clinical Modification</italic> (<italic>ICD-9-CM</italic>) diagnosis code 518.5 were used to define RI/ARDS following a surgical procedure in this study. In the third step, patients with this diagnosis code were divided into groups with and without the diagnosis of obesity as defined by the Clinical Classification Software (CCS). In-hospital mortality was chosen as the primary outcome as it is a robust outcome and unlikely affected by coding bias. Patient and health-care system-related characteristics were analyzed by obesity status. Approximately 40% of entries in the race category were not available and were imputed as “white.” This step was based on an approach previously described and the fact that facilities with high rates of missing data for race served populations with higher than average white/black patient ratios.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0885066611411410">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0885066611411410">14</xref>
</sup> Additionally, in order to account for overall comorbidity burden, the average Deyo comorbidity index was calculated.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0885066611411410">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0885066611411410">16</xref>
</sup> Weighted means and percentages were estimated for continuous and categorical variables, respectively. A logistic regression model was fitted to elucidate whether obesity was associated with independently increased odds ratio (OR) for in-hospital mortality in postoperative patients with RI/ARDS while controlling for age (&lt;45, 45-65, 65-75, and &gt;75), gender, race (black, Hispanic, other, and white), admission (elective, emergent, and urgent/other) and procedure type (cardiac, head and neck, laparoscopic abdominal, open abdominal, joint arthroplasty, and spine thoracic), hospital location (rural and urban), hospital teaching status (teaching and nonteaching), hospital size (small, medium, and large), and comorbidity index. We used the data-splitting approach for model development and validation. The study data set was split into a training data set (66.7%) to build a predictive model, and a test data set (33.3%) to evaluate model performance.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0885066611411410">17</xref>
</sup> The Area Under the Receiver Operating Characteristic (ROC) Curve (AUC), also referred to as the c statistic (or concordance index), was utilized for assessing the model’s discriminatory power. Odds ratio, 95% confidence intervals (CIs), and <italic>P</italic> value were also estimated. The conventional threshold of statistical significance (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .05) was used to determine the significance of variables and 95% CIs were reported to allow readers interpret the significance of the findings in light of the potential undue effect a very large sample size might have on the <italic>P</italic> values. All statistical analyses were performed using SAS version 9.2 (SAS Institute, Cary, North Carolina). To facilitate the analysis of data collected in a complex survey design and to obtain consistent estimates of mean and variance parameters taking into account the complex survey data setting, SAS procedures SURVEYMEANS, SURVEYFREQ, and SURVEYLOGISTIC were utilized for descriptive analyses and modeling efforts.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0885066611411410">
<title>Results</title>
<p>We identified 9 149 030 admissions which underwent the defined surgical procedures between 1998 and 2007, representing a national estimate of 44 793 273 patient admissions. Of those, 5.48% had a diagnosis of obesity. The incidence of RI/ARDS was 1.82% among patients with obesity and 2.01% (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .0001) among those without the diagnosis. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0885066611411410">Table 1</xref>
details patient and health-care system-related demographics of patients with the diagnosis of RI/ARDS by obesity status. Among other differences, obese patients tended to be younger and more likely female compared to their nonobese counterparts. Hospital admissions for obese patients were more likely of an urgent but less likely of an emergent nature compared to nonobese patients. The average comorbidity burden was higher among patients with obesity (Deyo index 1.38 [1.35; 1.40] vs 0.89 [0.89; 0.90], <italic>P</italic> &lt; .0001), which was reflected in the higher rates of comorbidities such as previous myocardial infarction, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, and diabetes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0885066611411410">Figure 1</xref>
). Patients with obesity whose postoperative course was complicated by RI/ARDS had a significantly lower incidence of the need for mechanical ventilation (50% vs 55%, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .0001). In-hospital mortality was significantly lower compared to nonobese patients (5.45% vs 18.72%, <italic>P</italic> &lt; .0001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0885066611411410">Figure 2</xref>
). For those patients with RI/ARDS requiring intubation, the in-hospital mortality rate was 11% for obese and 25% for nonobese patients, respectively (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .0001). In comparison, in-hospital mortality among all patients in our data set was 2.42%, and 2.10% among all those who did not developed RI/ARDS.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0885066611411410" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Characteristics of Patients With and Without Obesity</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0885066611411410" xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611411410-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Demographics</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Group</th>
<th align="center">Obesity</th>
<th align="center">Nonobesity</th>
<th align="center">
<italic>P</italic> Value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Weighted N</td>
<td align="center">44 566</td>
<td align="center">866 045</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Average age (years)</td>
<td>59.77</td>
<td>63.15</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Average comorbidity index</td>
<td>1.38</td>
<td>0.89</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Age groups (%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 0-44</td>
<td>12.47</td>
<td>15.23</td>
<td rowspan="4">&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 45-64</td>
<td>47.53</td>
<td>26.90</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 65-74</td>
<td>27.05</td>
<td>24.78</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> &gt;75</td>
<td>12.95</td>
<td>33.09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Gender(%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Male</td>
<td>47.84</td>
<td>55.96</td>
<td rowspan="2">&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Female</td>
<td>52.16</td>
<td>44.04</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Race(%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> White</td>
<td>77.08</td>
<td>78.76</td>
<td rowspan="4">&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Black</td>
<td>10.34</td>
<td>9.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hispanic</td>
<td>9.29</td>
<td>7.83</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>3.28</td>
<td>4.40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Admission type (%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Emergent</td>
<td>33.25</td>
<td>44.08</td>
<td rowspan="3">&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Elective</td>
<td>19.01</td>
<td>19.53</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Urgent + other</td>
<td>47.74</td>
<td>36.39</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Hospital location (%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Rural</td>
<td>4.52</td>
<td>4.66</td>
<td rowspan="2">.5389</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Urban</td>
<td>95.48</td>
<td>95.34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Hospital teaching status (%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Nonteaching</td>
<td>51.14</td>
<td>42.90</td>
<td>&lt;.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Teaching</td>
<td>48.86</td>
<td>57.10</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Hospital size (%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Small</td>
<td>6.45</td>
<td>7.36</td>
<td rowspan="3">.0003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Medium</td>
<td>21.75</td>
<td>20.53</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Large</td>
<td>71.80</td>
<td>72.11</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig1-0885066611411410" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Comorbidities; comorbidity profiles of patients with and without obesity.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611411410-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig2-0885066611411410" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>In-hospital mortality; in-hospital mortality in patients with and without obesity.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611411410-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>When employing multivariate regression analysis and controlling for age, gender, race, admission status, hospital characteristics, type of surgery, and comorbidity burden, obesity was associated with a 69% reduction in the odds of in-hospital mortality in postoperative patients with RI/ARDS (OR = 0.31; CI = 0.28-0.36). Factors associated with increased risk were increasing age, male gender, black race compared to white, and nonelective hospital admission. Patients with RI/ARDS after major vascular and thoracic surgeries were at highest risk of death compared to other interventions (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0885066611411410">Table 2</xref>
).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0885066611411410" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Multivariate Regression Analysis Controlling for Age, Gender, Race, Admission Status, Hospital Characteristics, Type of Surgery and Comorbidity Burden Based on the Training Data Set</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0885066611411410" xlink:href="10.1177_0885066611411410-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th colspan="4">Multivariate Analysis-Risk factors for Mortality <italic>c</italic>-Statistics = 0.70</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Factor</th>
<th align="center">Odds Ratio</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">95% Confidence Limits</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Obesity Status (referent: nonobese) (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .0001)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Obesity</td>
<td>0.314</td>
<td>0.275</td>
<td>0.359</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Intubation and mechanical ventilation (referent: no requirement)</td>
<td>1.705</td>
<td>1.644</td>
<td>1.769</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Type of surgery (referent: major vascular; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .0001)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Cardiac</td>
<td>0.604</td>
<td>0.565</td>
<td>0.646</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Head and neck</td>
<td>0.365</td>
<td>0.296</td>
<td>0.449</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Laparoscopic abdominal</td>
<td>0.643</td>
<td>0.467</td>
<td>0.884</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Open abdominal</td>
<td>0.852</td>
<td>0.799</td>
<td>0.907</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Joint arthroplasty</td>
<td>0.609</td>
<td>0.56</td>
<td>0.663</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Spine</td>
<td>0.397</td>
<td>0.351</td>
<td>0.449</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Thoracic</td>
<td>0.986</td>
<td>0.904</td>
<td>1.075</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Age group (referent: 45-65 years) <italic>P</italic> &lt; .0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> &lt;45</td>
<td>0.536</td>
<td>0.498</td>
<td>0.578</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 65-75</td>
<td>1.602</td>
<td>1.523</td>
<td>1.685</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> &gt;75</td>
<td>2.499</td>
<td>2.387</td>
<td>2.616</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Gender (referent: female) (<italic>P</italic> = .013)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Male</td>
<td>0.957</td>
<td>0.924</td>
<td>0.991</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Race (referent: white) add <italic>P</italic> value here (<italic>P</italic> = .002)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Black</td>
<td>1.074</td>
<td>1.003</td>
<td>1.15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hispanic</td>
<td>0.873</td>
<td>0.801</td>
<td>0.95</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>1.028</td>
<td>0.921</td>
<td>1.147</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Hospital location (reference: urban; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .0001)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Rural</td>
<td>1.207</td>
<td>1.123</td>
<td>1.297</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Teaching status (reference: teaching; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .0001)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Nonteaching</td>
<td>0.879</td>
<td>0.848</td>
<td>0.91</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Hospital size (reference: small; <italic>P</italic> = .004)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Medium</td>
<td>1.119</td>
<td>1.041</td>
<td>1.201</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Large</td>
<td>1.113</td>
<td>1.042</td>
<td>1.188</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Admission type (reference: elective) <italic>P</italic> &lt; .0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Emergent</td>
<td>1.571</td>
<td>1.506</td>
<td>1.64</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Urgent/other</td>
<td>1.444</td>
<td>1.375</td>
<td>1.517</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Comordibidy burden (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .0001)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Deyo (increase 1 unit)</td>
<td>0.918</td>
<td>0.901</td>
<td>0.935</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0885066611411410">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In our analysis of a large nationally representative sample of admissions for surgical procedures, we found that patients with a diagnosis of postoperative RI/ARDS and obesity have a 69% reduction of in-hospital mortality (OR = 0.31; CI = 0.28-0.36) compared to their nonobese counterparts.</p>
<p>While epidemiologic data are consistent with an increased risk of death from all causes and higher in-hospital mortality in obese individuals,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0885066611411410">18</xref>
</sup> data on the relationship between BMI and mortality in patients with critical illness are less clear. In a recent cohort study of critically ill patients at risk of ARDS, Gong et al<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0885066611411410">19</xref>
</sup> were able to show that although obesity was associated with increased risk of the development of ARDS, no link to higher mortality could be established. They also reported a higher requirement for intubation in overweight and obese patients, a finding that we could not reproduce in our analysis. Another prospective cohort study in patients with acute lung injury (ALI) from the King County Lung Injury Project revealed that BMI is not associated with mortality in this setting.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0885066611411410">20</xref>
</sup> In contrast, O’Brien et al<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0885066611411410">21</xref>
</sup> examining patients with ALI/ARDS in the Project Impact database were able to demonstrate that overweight and obese BMIs were associated with a decreased odds of mortality from ALI/ARDS, which is consistent with the findings of our analysis. While the observed effect of obesity on mortality in patients with RI/ARDS in our study appears large, this “paradoxical” protective effect has been previously described in a number of acute medical settings.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0885066611411410">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0885066611411410"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0885066611411410">7</xref>
</sup> Fonarow et al observed a protective effect of obesity in acute heart failure and during a short period of hospitalization.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0885066611411410">5</xref>
</sup> The authors studied the impact of BMI on in-hospital mortality in patients admitted with acute decompensated heart failure and found that patients with obesity had significantly lower in-hospital mortality rates than their lean counterparts even after adjusting for confounding factors. Interestingly, and similar to our observations, obese patients were younger and had a higher incidence of comorbidities, including diabetes and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. Furthermore, there is mounting experimental evidence that the proinflammatory response observed in ALI/ARDS might be attenuated in patients with high BMIs, which could partly explain the mortality benefit in our analysis. Stapleton and coworkers analyzed plasma biomarker levels in 1409 participants in prior National Heart Lung and Blood Institute (NHLBI) Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome Network trials.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0885066611411410">22</xref>
</sup> They found that obese patients with ALI have lower levels of several proinflammatory cytokines, particularly interleukin (IL) 6 and IL-8, as compared to nonobese patients with ALI. In addition, obese patients may be better equipped to get through the initial catabolic phase of acute illness because of additional energy stores in the form of adipose tissue, and lipids and lipoproteins such as cholesterol can bind endotoxin and neutralize its inflammatory effects. These and other proposed mechanisms remain speculative at this time and require further systematic studies on the subject. The incidence of mortality in postsurgical patients with ARDS in our study was 18.1%, which is lower than the range reported in the general ARDS population. A recent systematic review found ARDS mortality rates to be 40% to 45% in observational studies and 35% to 40% in randomized controlled clinical trials.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0885066611411410">8</xref>
</sup> This discrepancy may be explained by the fact that the cohort in our study included patients with potentially less severe respiratory compromise (ie, RI) and focused exclusively on postsurgical patients. As opposed to the trauma population, very little data are currently available examining the incidence, causes, and outcomes of ARDS in the nontrauma surgical population. In a recent, prospective observational study spanning over 5 years, the authors were able to identify ARDS as an independent predictor of mortality in nontrauma surgical patients; however, no data on the mortality rate attributable to ARDS are provided.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0885066611411410">23</xref>
</sup> It has been demonstrated, however, that mortality attributable to ALI/ARDS varies depending on the patient population studied. In a recent prospective cohort study including 2768 patients comparing the clinical characteristics and outcomes of sepsis-related versus nonsepsis-related ARDS, the authors report a mortality rate of 22.6% in the latter group.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0885066611411410">24</xref>
</sup> In light of the fact that our patient sample includes patients with ARDS as well as those who were coded as RI and therefore less acutely ill, our findings appear to be consistent with the published literature in the nontrauma surgical patient population.</p>
<p>Increasing age in our analysis was associated with increased risk of mortality in the RI/ARDS population. In the multivariate analysis, odds of mortality were 2.49 in patients &gt;75 years compared to those aged 45 to 64 years. Similarly, Phua et al<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0885066611411410">8</xref>
</sup> reported a significant increase in mortality with increasing patient age (OR, 1.27 for every 10-year increase; 95% CI, 1.07-1.50; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .006). The link between advanced age and mortality may be explained with a decrease in end-organ reserve, limiting the ability of older patients to recover from major insults such as ARDS.</p>
<p>We found a slightly increased risk of mortality among black patients (OR = 1.074, CI = 1.003-1.15) as compared to white patients. In an epidemiologic study specifically designed to look at race and gender differences in the annual ARDS mortality rate in the United States, Moss and Mannino<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0885066611411410">25</xref>
</sup> observed that African American men had the highest fatality rate when compared to both white men and men of other racial backgrounds. Although speculative, reasons for this finding may be secondary to genetic factors affecting susceptibility or response to therapy. The same authors found that males had a higher mortality rate when compared to woman. This is in contrast to our findings where male gender did not increase the risk of mortality (OR = 0.96, CI = 0.92-0.99; <italic>P</italic> = .013). Mortality was also associated with an emergent or urgent admission nature as compared to elective surgery. This could be due to higher rates of trauma requiring surgery and overall worse patient status; however, no causal relationship could be established due to the design of our study.</p>
<p>In the multivariate regression analysis, cardiac, head and neck, abdominal, and joint and spine surgery were associated with decreased odds of mortality as compared to vascular and thoracic surgery patients developing postoperative RI/ARDS. Vascular and thoracic patients may be at a distinct disadvantage if affected by RI/ARDS as they often represent a population with decreased reserve because of advanced end-organ dysfunction in the former, and preexisting impaired lung function in the latter group. We also found a steady increase in the odds of mortality with increasing hospital size and in teaching hospitals. It is quite feasible that there is a bias toward performing more complex cases at teaching and larger hospitals with presumably better access to ancillary services. Nevertheless, the relationship between outcomes and hospital size remains unstudied in this setting and requires further evaluation.</p>
<p>Our study is limited by a number of factors inherent to secondary analysis of large administrative databases. As such, clinical information (ie, specific intraoperative and postoperative events, etc) available in the NIS is limited, and our analysis must be interpreted in this context. Because of the nature of the NIS, only inpatient data are available and thus complications and events after discharge are not captured. Furthermore, readmissions cannot be discerned from this database. Thus, conclusions should be limited to the acute perioperative setting with the notion that complications are likely underestimated. While it cannot be excluded that data entry may be subjected to some form of coding or reporting bias, there is no reason to believe that reporting should differ between patients within the database. Thus both obese and nonobese discharges are exposed to the same bias within the same data collection construct. Comparative analysis should therefore be less likely affected by such bias.</p>
<p>A further limitation is the lack of information about the extent of obesity with the use of <italic>ICD-9</italic> codes as no actual BMI is available. Further, the average prevalence of obesity seems rather low in our study compared to that reported in the general population. However, a trend toward increase in prevalence over time was documented in our data set, with rates increasing from 3.4% in 1998 to 8.6% in 2007.</p>
<p>Likely causes for lower overall rates in this study may include underreporting and possibly preselection of nonobese patients for surgery. If this assumption is correct, the preselection of nonobese patients may represent a significant disparity in health care worth further investigation. Additionally, if “healthier” obese patients were indeed selected for surgery as may be the case in our study, this may represent a bias that would favor better outcomes in this patient group and explain some of our findings. It is noteworthy, however, that obese patients had an overall higher comorbidity burden in this study than nonobese patients, theoretically putting them at a disadvantage.</p>
<p>An additional limitation is posed by the inability to distinguish the severity of RI/ARDS in this study. It is feasible that more severe cases of RI/ARDS are associated with increased risk of adverse outcomes. Indeed, in our study, patients with RI/ARDS requiring intubation had a higher mortality rate (11% vs 25% in obese and nonobese patients, respectively; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .0001). However, the discrepancy between obese and nonobese patients was maintained in this subpopulation, suggesting that more severe cases are associated with worse outcome but less so in patients with obesity.</p>
<p>Recognizing that patients developing RI/ARDS represent a widely diverse group, we attempted to restrict our data set to those patients who developed this complication in the context of a surgical procedure, thus eliminating the more heterogeneous medical population.</p>
<p>Further, it must be mentioned that predisposition to mortality of patients with ARDS on the other side of the spectrum, that is those who are underweight, may also differ significantly from that of patients with normal body weight. However, this analysis was beyond the scope of this study.</p>
<p>In conclusion, utilizing a large nationally representative database, we found that obesity was associated with a decreased incidence and adjusted odds for in-hospital mortality in patients with RI/ARDS after surgery. These findings support the emerging concept of the “obesity paradox.” While no causal relationships can be drawn from our data, they provide a basis for future studies to explore possible mechanisms.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="presented-at" id="fn1-0885066611411410">
<p>The paper was presented as a Poster Discussion at the American Society of Critical Care Anesthesiology (ASCCA) Annual Meeting, October 14, 2010, San Diego, CA, USA.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn2-0885066611411410">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn3-0885066611411410">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: Supported with funds by the Department of Anesthesiology at the Hospital for Special Surgery (to Dr. Memtsoudis), Center for Education and Research in Therapeutics (CERTs) (AHRQ RFA-HS-05-14) (to Dr. Mazumdar) and Clinical Translational Science Center (CTSC) (NIH UL1-RR024996) (to Dr. Mazumdar).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0885066611411410">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hubert</surname>
<given-names>HB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Feinleib</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McNamara</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Castelli</surname>
<given-names>WP</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Obesity as an independent risk factor for cardiovascular disease: a 26-year follow-up of participants in the Framingham Heart Study</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>968</fpage>–<lpage>977</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0885066611411410">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Calle</surname>
<given-names>EE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thun</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Petrelli</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rodriguez</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Heath</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Body mass index and mortality in a prospective cohort of US adults</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>341</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>1097</fpage>–<lpage>1105</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0885066611411410">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Waisbren</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rosen</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bader</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lipsitz</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rogers</surname>
<given-names>SO</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eriksson</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Percent body fat and prediction of surgical site infection</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Surg</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>210</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>389</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0885066611411410">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ahmad</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nagle</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McCarthy</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fitzgerald</surname>
<given-names>PC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sullivan</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Prystowsky</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Postoperative hypoxemia in morbidly obese patients with and without obstructive sleep apnea undergoing laparoscopic bariatric surgery</article-title>. <source>Anesth Analg</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>107</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>138</fpage>–<lpage>143</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0885066611411410">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fonarow</surname>
<given-names>GC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Srikanthan</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Costanzo</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cintron</surname>
<given-names>GB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lopatin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<collab collab-type="author">ADHERE Scientific Advisory Committee and Investigators</collab>.. <article-title>An obesity paradox in acute heart failure: analysis of body mass index and inhospital mortality for 108927 patients in the Acute Decompensated Heart Failure National Registry</article-title>. <source>Am Heart J</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>153</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>74</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0885066611411410">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gruberg</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Weissman</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Waksman</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The impact of obesity on the short-term and long-term outcomes after percutaneous coronary intervention: the obesity paradox?</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>578</fpage>–<lpage>584</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0885066611411410">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Uretsky</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Messerli</surname>
<given-names>FH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bangalore</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Obesity paradox in patients with hypertension and coronary artery disease</article-title>. <source>Am J Med</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>120</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>863</fpage>–<lpage>870</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0885066611411410">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Phua</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Badia</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Adhikari</surname>
<given-names>NKJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Has mortality from acute respiratory distress syndrome decreased over time? A systematic review</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>179</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>220</fpage>–<lpage>227</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0885066611411410">
<label>9</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Healthcare Cost and Utilization Project Databases</collab>. [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hcupus.ahrq.gov/nisoverview.jsp]">http://www.hcupus.ahrq.gov/nisoverview.jsp</ext-link>]
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0885066611411410">
<label>10</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Introduction to the HCUP National Inpatient Sample (NIS)</collab> <year>2006</year>. <article-title>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality, Healthcare Cost and Utilization Project (HCUP)</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Rockville, MD</publisher-loc>, <year>2008</year>. [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hcupus.ahrq.gov/db/nation/nis/2006NIS_INTRODUCTION.pdf">http://www.hcupus.ahrq.gov/db/nation/nis/2006NIS_INTRODUCTION.pdf</ext-link>]</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0885066611411410">
<label>11</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<article-title>Publications from the HCUP Databases. Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality, Healthcare Cost and Utilization Project (HCUP)</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Rockville, MD</publisher-loc>, <year>2008</year>. [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ahrq.gov/data/hcup/hcupref.htm]">http://www.ahrq.gov/data/hcup/hcupref.htm]</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0885066611411410">
<label>12</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">HCUP CCS-Services and Procedures. Healthcare Cost and Utilization Project (HCUP)</collab>. <month>June</month> <year>2009</year>. <article-title>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality</article-title>, <publisher-loc>Rockville, MD</publisher-loc>. [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.hcup-us.ahrq.gov/toolssoftware/ccs_svcsproc/ccssvcproc.jsp]">www.hcup-us.ahrq.gov/toolssoftware/ccs_svcsproc/ccssvcproc.jsp]</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0885066611411410">
<label>13</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Memtsoudis</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>González Della Valle</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Perioperative outcomes after unilateral and bilateral total knee arthroplasty</article-title>. <source>Anesthesiology</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1206</fpage>–<lpage>1216</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0885066611411410">
<label>14</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kozak</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Underreporting of race in the National Hospital Discharge Survey</article-title>. <source>Adv Data</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>265</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0885066611411410">
<label>15</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Charlson</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pompei</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ales</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>MacKenzie</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A new method of classifying prognostic comorbidity in longitudinal studies: development and validation</article-title>. <source>J Chronic Dis</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>373</fpage>–<lpage>383</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0885066611411410">
<label>16</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Deyo</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cherkin</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ciol</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Adapting a clinical comorbidity index for use with ICD-9-CM administrative databases</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>613</fpage>–<lpage>619</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0885066611411410">
<label>17</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Steyerberg</surname>
<given-names>EW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Harrell</surname>
<given-names>FE</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Borsboom</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eijkemans</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vergouwe</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Habbema</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Internal validation of predictive models: efficiency of some procedures for logistic regression analysis</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>774</fpage>–<lpage>781</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0885066611411410">
<label>18</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Calle</surname>
<given-names>EE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thun</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Petrelli</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rodriguez</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Heath</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Body-mass index and mortality in a prospective cohort of US adults</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>341</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>1097</fpage>–<lpage>1105</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0885066611411410">
<label>19</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gong</surname>
<given-names>MN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bajwa</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>BT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Christiani</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Body mass index is associated with the development of acute respiratory distress syndrome</article-title>. <source>Thorax</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0885066611411410">
<label>20</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Morris</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stapleton</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rubenfeld</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hudson</surname>
<given-names>LD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Caldwell</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Steinberg</surname>
<given-names>KP</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The association between body mass index and clinical outcomes in acute lung injury</article-title>. <source>Chest</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>131</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>342</fpage>–<lpage>348</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0885066611411410">
<label>21</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>O’Brien</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Phillips</surname>
<given-names>GS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ali</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lucarelli</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Marsh</surname>
<given-names>CB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lemeshow</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Body mass index is independently associated with hospital mortality in mechanically ventilated adults with acute lung injury</article-title>. <source>Crit Care Med</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>738</fpage>–<lpage>744</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0885066611411410">
<label>22</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stapleton</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dixon</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Parsons</surname>
<given-names>PE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ware</surname>
<given-names>LB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Suratt</surname>
<given-names>BT</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<collab collab-type="author">the NHLBI Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome Network</collab>. <article-title>The association between body mass index and plasma cytokine levels in patients with acute lung injury</article-title>. <source>Chest</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>138</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>568</fpage>–<lpage>577</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0885066611411410">
<label>23</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Towfigh</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Peralta</surname>
<given-names>MV</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Martin</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Acute respiratory distress syndrome in nontrauma surgical patients: a 6-year study</article-title>. <source>J Trauma</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1239</fpage>–<lpage>1243</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0885066611411410">
<label>24</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sheu</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gong</surname>
<given-names>MN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhai</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clinical characteristics and outcomes of sepsis-related vs. non-sepsis-related acute respiratory distress syndrome</article-title>. <source>Chest</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>138</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>559</fpage>–<lpage>567</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0885066611411410">
<label>25</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Moss</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mannino</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Race and gender differences in acute respiratory distress syndrome deaths in the United States: an analysis of multiple-cause mortality data (1979-1996)</article-title>. <source>Crit Care Med</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1679</fpage>–<lpage>1685</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>