<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SLS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsls</journal-id>
<journal-title>Social &amp; Legal Studies</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0964-6639</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7390</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0964663912458113</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0964663912458113</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Satire and the Politics of Corruption in Kenya</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Harrington</surname>
<given-names>John</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff1-0964663912458113">University of Liverpool, UK; British Institute in Eastern Africa, Kenya</aff>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0964663912458113"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Manji</surname>
<given-names>Ambreena</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff2-0964663912458113">Keele University, UK; British Institute in Eastern Africa, Kenya</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0964663912458113">John Harrington, British Institute in Eastern Africa, PO Box 30710, Nairobi 00100, Kenya. Email: <email>john.harrington@liv.ac.uk</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>22</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>3</fpage>
<lpage>23</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Corruption in Kenya has been a matter of intense concern for foreign donors and the international financial institutions. External efforts to change the ‘governance culture’ in this regard are not simply instrumental, composed of material restrictions and incentives. They are also inherently rhetorical, seeking to establish the plausibility of a set of values rooted in political economy. This paper examines two widely reported speeches of a former British High Commissioner that can be read together as a highly figurative satire on political standards in Kenya. Having developed a reading of anti-corruption governance as satire, we extend it to the role of the legal profession in the illegal and irregular allocation of public land. We argue that, as well as demonstrating an application of the rhetorical analysis of neo-liberal governance, the case of land grabbing in Kenya also highlights the instability of many of the key binary oppositions underpinning dominant anti-corruption strategies. This instability can be understood in rhetorical terms by drawing on the work of post-colonial writers and critics on the category of excremental satire. Rather than a clear binary opposition, these suggest the interrelation, or more precisely the mutual contamination, of corruption and normal capitalist accumulation.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Governance</kwd>
<kwd>rhetoric</kwd>
<kwd>excremental satire</kwd>
<kwd>primitive accumulation</kwd>
<kwd>Constitution of Kenya 2010</kwd>
<kwd>legal profession</kwd>
<kwd>land grabbing</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0964663912458113">
<title>Introduction</title>
<sec id="section2-0964663912458113">
<title>Corruption in Kenya</title>
<p>The last two decades in Kenya have been marked by an often bitter and sometimes faltering struggle against authoritarianism and toward democratic government (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0964663912458113">Murunga and Nasong’o, 2007</xref>). This campaign has been lead by diverse civil society groups and fitfully supported by foreign donors, notably the United States and the European countries, including the UK. Among its fruits have been a return to multiparty electoral politics and the passing by referendum of a new constitution in 2010. This moment has been widely represented as a second liberation, an opportunity to make good the failed promise of the first liberation after the departure of the colonial power in 1963 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0964663912458113">Branch, 2011</xref>: 282). The struggle has been impelled in part by a popular desire to challenge corruption and the deep economic inequalities that it perpetuates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0964663912458113">Mwangi, 2008</xref>: 268).</p>
<p>Graft is a feature of life in Kenya at all levels, from the daily interaction of citizens with policemen and public servants to the elaborate networks of patronage and influence linking state and commercial sectors. In 2010, for example, the UK suspended its financial support for free primary education in Kenya. Audits had revealed that £880,000 out of a total initial budget of £20 million had been diverted from its intended purpose (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0964663912458113">Burgis, 2010</xref>). This was merely the latest in a long list of corruption scandals in Kenya, some of which cost the state hundreds of millions of dollars and the scope and ingenuity of which often bordered on the fantastical (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0964663912458113">Mwangi, 2008</xref>: 273–275). Corruption is estimated to account for 8% of gross domestic product (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0964663912458113">Mwangi, 2008</xref>: 281). Current Kenyan Treasury estimates show that at least 20–30 percent of budgeted monies are lost each year through rigged bidding, fraudulent procurement and so on (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0964663912458113">Kariuki, 2011</xref>: 60). The immense opportunity costs in terms of human welfare and national development of this gap in effective expenditure cannot be doubted. To borrow a phrase from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0964663912458113">Adebanwi and Obadare (2011</xref>: 190), corruption in Kenya often appears to be ‘a directive principle of social policy’. It is, in addition, politically destabilizing as elite factions strive to secure access to state resources by all means necessary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0964663912458113">Ogude, 2009</xref>: 15). The organized post-election violence of 2007–2008, which is currently the subject of prosecutions at the International Criminal Court, saw over 1000 violent deaths and the expulsion of almost half a million citizens from their homes, farms and small businesses on the basis of their ethnic background (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0964663912458113">Branch, 2011</xref>: 269–277). Commentators have characterized these crimes and Kenya’s near disintegration as a grim consequence of an ongoing intra-elite struggle over the fruits of state power (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0964663912458113">Mueller, 2008</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0964663912458113">
<title>Governance and Corruption</title>
<p>Public sector reforms aimed at tackling corruption form an important strand of the governance measures recommended to or imposed on developing countries seeking loans from the International Financial Institutions (IFIs), that is, the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund, or accepting bilateral aid from Western countries (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0964663912458113">Department for International Development, 2006</xref>: 30). Moreover, donors have increasingly provided moral and material support for national anti-corruption initiatives. The UK spent over three times as much on governance projects in Kenya in 2005 (£5,830,898) as it had in 2000, and this was greater than the amount spent on supporting education (£5,729,126;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0964663912458113"> Department for International Development, 2007</xref>: 15). Between them, the United States and Germany allocated US$9 million to meet the costs of establishing the Kenya Anti-Corruption Commission, although this was later reduced in light of problems with the running of the Commission (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0964663912458113">Lawson, 2009</xref>: 93). Thus, as well as being a matter of pressing importance in national politics, anti-corruption strategy is also a vehicle by which the IFIs and the Western powers have sought to globalize specific forms of economic governance.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0964663912458113">
<title>Overview</title>
<p>This paper considers an important, although neglected, aspect of these governance strategies: their moral and rhetorical nature. It develops this analysis with reference to two widely reported speeches made by Sir Edward Clay, British High Commissioner to Kenya in 2004 and 2005. These interventions came as the anti-corruption drive initiated by the donors and the World Bank in the late 1990s began to stall across Africa. Initially reforming governments drew back from their commitments to donors and the electorate as elite factions, old and new, sought to defend their political and economic positions. Anti-corruption ‘czars’ favoured by donors and NGOs were driven from office in Nigeria and Kenya (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0964663912458113">Adebanwi and Obadare, 2011</xref>: 204; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0964663912458113">Lawson, 2009</xref>: 79). This focus allows us to make some tentative remarks in relation to the mode of governance under the ‘Post-Washington Consensus’. We read the latter as a moral regime, one that works rhetorically through moral criticism and that can thus be understood using methods of literary analysis – in this particular case, satire.</p>
<p>Having developed this reading of anti-corruption governance as satire, we extend it to the case of land grabbing in Kenya, focussing in particular on the role of the legal profession as facilitators and active participants in the illegal and irregular acquisition of land. As well as demonstrating an application of the rhetorical analysis of neo-liberal governance, the case of land grabbing in Kenya also highlights the instability of a key distinction underpinning dominant anti-graft strategies: that between corruption and ordinary commerce. This instability can be explained in rhetorical terms by drawing on the work of post-colonial writers and critics on the genre of ‘excremental satire’. Rather than a clear binary opposition, these suggest the interrelation or, more precisely, the mutual contamination of corruption, understood as a form of accumulation, and the normal workings of the market. While it may be true that, as Wole Soyinka says, ‘the tree of democracy cannot thrive on the compost of corruption’,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0964663912458113">1</xref></sup> this is not true of the capitalist economy.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0964663912458113">
<title>Governance, Corruption and Anti-corruption</title>
<sec id="section6-0964663912458113">
<title>Corruption and the Post-Washington Consensus</title>
<p>Although Kenya was subject to the structural adjustment programmes favoured by the ‘Washington Consensus’ from the early 1980s, these were focussed on economic reforms such as privatization and the relaxation of capital controls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0964663912458113">Brown, 2007</xref>: 305). It was not until the end of the Cold War that the country lost its privileged status as a dependable ally of the Western powers and became the target of political and governance conditionalities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0964663912458113">Brown, 2007</xref>: 308, 324). This deepening of foreign and international involvement in the running of the Kenyan state was intensified by the shift to what is called the Post-Washington Consensus on the part of the IFIs later in the 1990s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-0964663912458113">Tan, 2011</xref>: 63ff). The new consensus was concerned not only with core economic measures, but also with the development of the non-market institutions that were required for an ideally functioning capitalist economy. Goals such as the rule of law and administrative efficiency, it was realized, would not be delivered by the market alone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0964663912458113">Harrison, 2001</xref>: 532). Anti-corruption strategies formed an important part of this initiative, with the World Bank issuing its first substantive policy document on the theme in 1997.</p>
<p>The World Bank’s early definition of corruption was ‘the abuse of public office for private gain’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-0964663912458113">World Bank, 1997</xref>: 8). This definition and the governance interventions that it has sustained are structured around a pair of related binary oppositions: politics vs economics; fraud and theft vs normal commercial activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0964663912458113">Murphy, 2011</xref>: 130; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0964663912458113">Polzer, 2001</xref>: 7). On this view, corruption is essentially a state imposition upon the market. Graft is something that happens to businesses, not something in which they are actively involved. This basic theme is articulated with a further distinction between developed and developing countries. Politics and administration in the former is held to be broadly legal–rational in form, that is, ‘based on principles of legality’ and operating ‘according to principles of impartiality and equity rather than personal favours and prejudices’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0964663912458113">Szeftel, 2000</xref>: 298). By contrast, in the latter resources are allocated according to a neo-patrimonial pattern, which manipulates modern bureaucratic structures to enable allocation according to kinship or shared membership of an ethnic group (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0964663912458113">Erdmann and Engel, 2007</xref>). Neo-patrimonialism drives corruption, which is thus understood as being a largely endogenous phenomenon, rooted in the pre-modern, or insufficiently modern, nature of affected societies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0964663912458113">Brown and Cloke, 2004</xref>: 280–281). Graft is then a cause, not a symptom, of the failure of African countries to develop (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0964663912458113">Szeftel, 2000</xref>: 304).</p>
<p>The authority of these interventions is to be secured by their presentation in the ‘scientific’ idiom of neo-classical economics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0964663912458113">Hay, 2004</xref>: 507). For example, the World Bank in its early work on the problem took as its guide the equation formulated by the economist Robert Klitgaard:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0964663912458113">
<mml:math id="mml-disp1-0964663912458113">
<mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Discretion</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Monopoly</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">−</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Accountability</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Corruption</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>World Bank</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext> </mml:mtext><mml:mn>1997</mml:mn><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mn>12</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-0964663912458113" xlink:href="10.1177_0964663912458113-eq1.tif"/>
</disp-formula>
This format simulates mathematical formulae and suggests simplicity in defining both the nature of the problem and the likely solutions. Indeed each term implies a specific remedy for corruption in accordance with the World Bank’s broader adjustment aims: stronger managerial control, particularly through privatization to eliminate the discretion of public sector workers; political and economic competition to allow the users of public services to outflank monopolies; and the development of mechanisms of transparency and consumerism to ensure accountability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0964663912458113">Lawson, 2009</xref>: 74).</p>
<p>The World Bank’s approach to corruption has been closely informed by that of Transparency International (TI), the leading non-governmental organization in the field. Founded in 1993 by Peter Eigen, a former East African Director for the World Bank, TI has been supported in its work by the IFIs and donors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0964663912458113">Murphy, 2011</xref>: 129). They, in turn, have relied on TI’s Corruption Perception Indices in their engagement with specific countries and regions of the world. Although actually based on the subjective views of business leaders and others, Corruption Perception Indices are cast in the form of ostensibly hard empirical data arranged in league table format (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0964663912458113">Murphy, 2011</xref>: 136). Moreover in drawing on the views of elites, they tend to focus on bribe takers in developing countries, rather than bribe payers both local and foreign, as the main cause of corruption (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0964663912458113">Szeftel, 2000</xref>: 293).</p>
<p>Critics have argued that the anti-corruption strategies of the TI and the World Bank tend to promote the interests of foreign investors in developing countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0964663912458113">Szeftel, 2000</xref>: 301). The ability to trade across borders, investing and disinvesting without significant obstruction, is a key objective of this group. Corruption constitutes a considerable limitation on this, given that it tends to privilege well-connected local elites at the expense of outside companies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0964663912458113">Murphy, 2011</xref>: 128). By attributing corruption to the pathologies of local states and societies, governance and transparency initiatives seek to remove this obstacle. At the same time they tend to suppress the fact that developed country businesses, in the arms industry, for example, have systematically used bribery to win orders in Africa and elsewhere (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-0964663912458113">The Corner House, 2011</xref>). The costs of such strategies are largely borne by citizens of the target countries.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0964663912458113">
<title>The Moral Rhetoric of Anti-corruption Strategies</title>
<p>The Post-Washington Consensus, thus, involves a broadening of the areas of concern for donors and the IFIs to include issues such as corruption. However, it has also seen a qualitative deepening of their engagement with developing country states (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0964663912458113">Hearn, 2007</xref>: 1098). In particular, it involves a move away from the externally imposed economic discipline, towards a form of self-discipline or ‘consensual conditionality’. Under the new dispensation the state takes ‘ownership’ of the reform process and local citizens ‘participate’ in setting its terms, most notably through the drafting of Poverty Reduction Strategy Papers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-0964663912458113">Tan, 2011</xref>: 122). In return for this freedom, however, donors demand a direct voice in economic decision-making. Foreign consultants funded by and answerable to donors are present and active in policy-making fora (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-0964663912458113">Tan, 2011</xref>: 158). World Bank representatives and donor country diplomats intervene via speeches and newspaper articles with a steady flow of advice. Indeed it has been argued that, under the Post-Washington Consensus, donors and the IFIs can no longer be seen as wholly separate from developing country states. They have become part of the state itself (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0964663912458113">Hearn, 2007</xref>: 1099). This influence is underwritten by the growing cadre of local administrators and experts trained in neo-liberal orthodoxy in the economics departments and business schools of Western universities. Taken together, these actors constitute a ‘highly integrated milieu’ within states and as between them and the IFIs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0964663912458113">Harrison, 2010</xref>: 52–53).</p>
<p>The work of this milieu can be understood in Gramscian terms as giving intellectual and moral form to the interests of the ‘transnational capitalist class’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0964663912458113">Chimni, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0964663912458113">Gill, 1995</xref>). This is done at the level of ‘know-how’: for example, in the form of ‘integrity toolkits’ promoted by TI and the World Bank (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-0964663912458113">Szeftel, 1998</xref>: 229). However, it is also achieved at the level of high politics and diplomacy, through mechanisms for inter-state peer review, indices of ‘economic freedom’ and ease of doing business, as well as treaty negotiations and ad hoc speeches. This is an ongoing process of inculcating aspirations, beliefs and orientations for conduct among elected officials, administrators and citizens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-0964663912458113">Tan, 2011</xref>: 13; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0964663912458113">Harrison, 2010</xref>: 73–74). As well as seeking a material extension of the private sector, such interventions also tend to promote markets as the chief vehicle of individual self-realization and national development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0964663912458113">Ayers, 2006</xref>: 332). Any specific intervention, regarding governance in general or corruption in particular, thus falls to be analysed as a strategic exercise in creating a shared community of typically neo-liberal values. Equally it will often involve moral criticism of third parties and institutions that violate prevailing norms of economic rectitude and good governance.</p>
<p>The moral import and strategic effectiveness of anti-corruption discourse can be clarified using rhetorical analysis, as well as insights from cultural and literary studies (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0964663912458113">Harrington, 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0964663912458113">2012</xref>). As regards substance, such arguments commonly reproduce and build on a set of assumptions shared with the audience. This rhetorical common sense may be expressed positively in terms of significant distinctions and binary oppositions, such as those that were seen to structure international anti-corruption strategies. However, it is also constituted negatively in terms of what it conceals and allows to go unexpressed, in this case the enduring connections between corruption and regular business. The stylistic and generic dimensions of speech are also an important, although often neglected, means by which an audience may be moved to identify with the moral purposes of the speaker (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0964663912458113">Frow, 2006</xref>: 14). As has been seen, World Bank and TI documents seek to reproduce the ‘scientific’ genres as a token of their truth and objectivity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0964663912458113">Bukovansky, 2006</xref>: 194). In the following section we consider the deployment of a different stylistic repertoire in the cause of anti-corruption governance: satire.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0964663912458113">
<title>Satire as Anti-corruption Strategy</title>
<sec id="section9-0964663912458113">
<title>Vomit and the High Commissioner</title>
<p>In 2004 Sir Edward Clay, then British High Commissioner to Kenya, delivered a widely reported speech to an audience of British businesspeople in Nairobi. The speech focussed on the problem of corruption in Kenya. Clay was scathing in his criticism of the Kenyan government for failing to live up to its commitment to tackle the problem and to investigate previous, notorious cases of graft and fraud (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0964663912458113">Clay, 2004</xref>: 1). He carefully spelled out the opportunity costs of massive corruption to ordinary Kenyans in terms of national shortfalls in basic social services and the infrastructure needed for development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0964663912458113">Clay, 2004</xref>: 2). That speech was followed by another in early 2005, made at an award ceremony for Kenyan journalists, which showed the High Commissioner to be unrepentant as regards the controversy which his earlier remarks had stirred up (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr86-0964663912458113">Wrong, 2009</xref>: 202–204). Indeed he added further detail to his charges against the Kenyan political class (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0964663912458113">Clay, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>In this section we explore the rhetorical form of Clay’s interventions. Although not conceived as sustained literary productions in the manner of Orwell’s <italic>Animal Farm</italic> or Swift’s <italic>Modest Proposal</italic>, the speeches are nonetheless marked by many features traditionally identified with satire. These include the manner in which the speaker presents himself, the ideal roles that he attributes to his audience, the values that he suggests they have in common and the mode of expression adopted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0964663912458113">Burke, 1969</xref>: 55ff). We argue that these formal qualities are closely related to Clay’s substantive purpose in creating a community of shared values as regards corruption in Kenya within the broader context of neo-liberal governance.</p>
<p>Orthodox approaches to satire see it as having two essential components: moral and stylistic. Without a moral focus, satire is merely comedy; without a playful or entertaining style, it is merely sermonizing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0964663912458113">Greenberg, 2011</xref>: 4). As to morals, the satirist is usually conceived of as a stern social critic. He performs the essentially conservative function of calling particular individuals or groups, or a whole society, back to propriety and rectitude (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0964663912458113">Bloom and Bloom, 1969</xref>: 119). Thus, within the satirical work certain vices are identified and condemned. At the same time, the corresponding virtues are urged on both the target and the audience, although this is more often done by implication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0964663912458113">Aden, 1981</xref>: 443–444). Given these strategic purposes, satire is inherently rhetorical, a matter of persuasion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0964663912458113">Bloom and Bloom, 1969</xref>: 128–130). Its success requires that speaker and audience have in common certain moral values. The latter are present not merely as bare precepts or rules. They are embedded in what Raymond Williams called a shared ‘structure of feeling’, that is, a widespread set of intuitions and assumptions regarding matters of justice, right conduct and admirable characteristics or virtues, an instinct for what is ugly and obscene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr82-0964663912458113">Williams, 1965</xref>: 78–79). The structure of feeling changes over time and place (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr83-0964663912458113">Williams, 1977</xref>: 132–135). This suggests that such texts need to be read with reference to their specific contexts and that they are themselves a rich source of understanding as regards these contexts, including the one presently under discussion. Moreover it should be added that part of an innovative satirist’s intent is to re-shape the structure of feeling, to extend it to include the specific conduct or characteristic of which she disapproves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0964663912458113">Bloom and Bloom, 1969</xref>: 136).</p>
<p>In the context of corruption the obvious vices are avarice and gluttony: boundless greed and unrestrained consumption (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0964663912458113">Miller, 1997</xref>). The rival virtues would be moderation and thrift. The moral tenor of Clay’s speeches in this regard is clear. Kenya’s rulers had made commitments to their own people and to donors regarding graft.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0964663912458113">2</xref></sup> Instead of keeping these promises they had indulged in ‘grand corruption’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0964663912458113">Clay, 2004</xref>: 2), a form of ‘gluttony’, he says explicitly, for which they cannot expect to be forgiven (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0964663912458113">Clay, 2004</xref>: 2). He takes care to note, not only the precise amounts being stolen, US$180 million in the first two years of the Kibaki government, but also what is foregone as a result of graft: 15,000 classrooms or a new road from Mombasa to Malaba (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0964663912458113">Clay, 2004</xref>: 3).</p>
<p>Information on corruption is, of course, widely available to Kenyans and donors alike, through the reports of the World Bank and TI discussed above.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0964663912458113">3</xref></sup> As has been noted, however alarming in content, such reports usually adopt a fairly colourless mode of expression, emphasizing the factual nature of the information presented. In contrast, Clay’s speeches are notable for their rhetorical self-awareness. He recalls with heavy irony the suggestion of one minister that Kenyans avoid the threat of famine by eating rats, ‘quite a delicacy, particularly when you are starving’. Both speeches conclude with elaborate re-workings of children’s verse: <italic>The King’s Breakfast</italic> by AA Milne and <italic>Macavity the Mystery Cat </italic>by TS Eliot. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0964663912458113">Clay, 2004</xref>: 6, 2005: 11).</p>
<p>The language and imagery used often betrays an ‘indifference to decorum’ typical of satirical writing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0964663912458113">Aden, 1981</xref>: 442). Clay describes the problem in terms borrowed from the register of ordinary speech. It is a ‘gigantic looting spree’, promoted by shady characters who ‘find receptive palms in every political party’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0964663912458113">Clay, 2004</xref>: 2, 2005: 8). Anyone who shakes their hands should ‘count his fingers’ afterwards. Those who seek to hold them to account are likely to be ‘nobbled’, ‘sabotaged’ or ‘kneecapped’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0964663912458113">Clay, 2004</xref>: 6). The verbal extravagance reaches a highpoint, if we can call it that, in Clay’s representation of corruption itself, which draws on the idea of politics as eating, well established in African literature and in the Kenyan vernacular (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0964663912458113">Ogude, 2009</xref>). Although Kenya’s leaders enjoy ‘Oxfam lunches’, their access to foreign aid may be in jeopardy, since ‘their gluttony has caused them to vomit all over our shoes’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0964663912458113">Clay, 2004</xref>: 3–4). This juxtaposition of the demotic and the visceral with sober statistics and high moral condemnation, all uttered by a senior diplomat, gives the speeches much of their satirical power. The text, in its fierce indignation reproduces the vulgarity that has long been associated with gluttony and avarice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0964663912458113">Miller, 1997</xref>: 102). In itself it parodies the grotesque and obscene practices of the Kenyan elite (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0964663912458113">Mbembe, 2001</xref>: 115).</p>
<p>Owing to its sharp moral criticism and excessive style, satire represents a violation of what Charles Knight calls ‘the conditions of politeness’: norms regarding what may and may not be said in specific contexts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0964663912458113">Knight, 1992</xref>: 29). These generic difficulties are exacerbated in Clay’s case by his position as senior representative of the former colonial power in Kenya, verbally attacking the host authorities. He admits the problem at the outset – ‘What business is it of ours?’ and adopts diverse rhetorical strategies to deal with it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0964663912458113">Clay, 2004</xref>: 1). He anticipates local hostility, condemning it as motivated by a patriotism ‘behind which an army of scoundrels could find refuge’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0964663912458113">Clay, 2004</xref>: 1). More positively he takes on a number of personae through which he can re-route his undiplomatic criticism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0964663912458113">Booth, 1983</xref>: 74–75). These include: the traditional satirist proclaiming his ‘outrage’; the disappointed partner ‘feeling let down’ when promises made in respect of good governance ‘are broken’; the nineteenth-century radical challenging ‘old corruption’; the innocent abroad made to feel ‘foolish and misled’ by obfuscating officials and expressing his perplexity in verses that even children can understand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0964663912458113">Clay, 2004</xref>: 1-4). As well as justifying himself, the successful critic also needs to win the ‘conspiratorial co-operation’ of his audience in attacking the target (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0964663912458113">Knight, 1992</xref>: 32). Literary satirists often achieve this by representing both the audience and its relationship to the speaker within the text itself (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0964663912458113">Knight, 1992</xref>: 32). In this regard Clay, for example, identifies strongly with the journalists he is addressing in the second speech. He borrows their jargon – ‘man bites dog’ and ‘sharpening your pencils’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0964663912458113">Clay, 2005</xref>: 2). He expresses a shared concern with ‘balanced reporting’ in listing such progress as has been made on corruption (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0964663912458113">Clay, 2005</xref>). Recent scandals are ‘secrets to all but a few – which now includes you and me’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0964663912458113">Clay, 2005</xref>: 9). Of course, the relevant audiences extend beyond those immediately present. Most significant among them are the ordinary citizens who are ‘the government’s paymasters’, who ‘lose their shirts’ to corruption and whose shoes are covered in vomit, where they can afford shoes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0964663912458113">Clay, 2005</xref>: 8–9). This emphasis on the watchdog role of the media and the civil society is consistent with World Bank thinking on effective anti-corruption strategies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0964663912458113">Adebanwi and Obadare, 2011</xref>: 197). It is also an example of the imperative to call forth and reinforce personae deemed typical of market societies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0964663912458113">Harrison, 2010</xref>: 34). Furthermore the evidently populist construction of the relationship between satirist and audience ensures that Clay is perceived, not only or even chiefly as a spokesman for Britain or the other donors, but as a tribune of the Kenyan people themselves.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0964663912458113">
<title>Hypocrisy, Satire and Governance</title>
<p>Beyond the specific vices targeted, hypocrisy is a central focus of satire (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0964663912458113">Harris, 2004</xref>: 3). Indeed, as many have noted, satire is only possible where vice pays lip-service to virtue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0964663912458113">Greenberg, 2011</xref>: 7). Absent this, the bad man is inured against mockery: he is shameless and unshameable. The persuasiveness of satire, thus, depends on the acknowledgement of a fairly stable set of values by speaker, audience and target alike. The lack of sincerity involved means that anti-graft campaigning properly takes the form of ‘immanent critique’ whereby the corrupt ‘are called to account by their own standards’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-0964663912458113">Warren, 2006</xref>: 803). It is obvious that the target of Clay’s satire is the Kenyan political elite, or at least that significant portion of it that engages in corrupt activities. However, the nature (or structure) of their hypocrisy bears further investigation. In doing so we can refer to a distinction drawn by Dennis Thompson (1999: 191) between personal and institutional hypocrisy. The former can be understood in the simple terms just set out, that is, where an individual says one thing and does another. The latter is present in cases of ‘disparity between the publicly avowed purposes of an institution and its actual performance or function’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0964663912458113">Thompson, 1999</xref>: 191). This institutional focus is useful for understanding the reach of Clay’s satire. As much as the personal venality and hypocrisy of individual politicians and administrators, the ‘eating’ as it were, he is also targeting the gap between the declared values and objectives of many Kenyan institutions and the purposes to which these institutions are in fact put. Indeed this distinction identifies a target for satirical criticism even in cases where corrupt individuals are wholly shameless about their behaviour.</p>
<p>The list of such institutions begins with the Kenyan state itself.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0964663912458113">4</xref></sup> Its institutional values can be said to come from two sources, internal and external. Chief among the internal sources is the new Constitution adopted by the people of Kenya in a referendum of 2010. Article 10(2)(b) states that the national values and principles of governance include ‘integrity’ and ‘transparency’. Article 201 states that ‘all aspects of public finance’ should be guided by ‘accountability’ and the promotion of ‘an equitable society’. In the light of Clay’s concern with the link between corruption and poverty, it is also worth mentioning Article 43(1)(c), which provides that ‘every person has the right to be free from hunger’. The betrayal of these values by the Kenyan state would (and does) represent a form of institutional hypocrisy, quite apart from such legal responsibility as may be generated. Of course these provisions were not in force at the time of Clay’s speeches. The independence constitution of 1963 committed the state to rather less in both moral and legal terms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0964663912458113">Ghai and McAuslan, 1970</xref>), hence the importance of also considering external sources of institutional values.</p>
<p>Given the deep intervention of donors and the IFIs in the workings of developing country states, the governance regime associated with the Post-Washington Consensus is the obvious source for such external values. As discussed above, this regime involves the reconstruction of developing country institutions the better to facilitate the spread of markets: for example, the legal system, the public service and even the national parliament (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0964663912458113">Department for International Development, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0964663912458113">Ayers, 2006</xref>: 329). These are to be animated by the official values of accountability, the rule of law and citizen participation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0964663912458113">Harrison, 2010</xref>:81-82; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0964663912458113">Manji, 2010</xref>). Moreover, the reform process itself is to be marked by local ownership. In the earlier phase of adjustment, hypocrisy on the part of developing countries was simply not possible, since open coercion precludes moral commitment. By contrast, under the current dispensation, the institutions of the African state appear to bind themselves willingly to an extensive and detailed catalogue of principles and values. In the somewhat cynical view of <italic>The Economist</italic>, whereas the Washington Consensus saw IFIs and donors telling African states what to do, the Post-Washington Consensus involves governments telling the IFIs what they want to hear (quoted in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0964663912458113">Harrison, 2010</xref>: 57). Adapting a phrase of Jean-François Bayart, we can call this an ‘extraverted hypocrisy’ aimed at mobilizing external resources for the sustenance of domestic elites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0964663912458113">Bayart, 1993</xref>: 27). The appointment of anti-corruption ‘czars’, for example, is seen as ‘sending the right messages to local and international audiences’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0964663912458113">Lawson, 2009</xref>: 78). We also noted that donors increasingly demand a direct voice in internal policy formation. Put in terms of satire, the audience and, indeed, the class of authorized critic are widened considerably under the Post-Washington Consensus. It is this moral and institutional reconfiguration that makes Clay’s interventions possible.</p>
<p>At a formal level both satire and governance can be said to be structured by a metaphorics of visibility (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0964663912458113">Lakoff and Johnson, 1980</xref>: 48). As noted above, hypocrisy is a matter of pretence, the wearing of a mask. Quite apart from identifying the specific wrong, the job of the satirist then is to expose the very fact of dissimulation, to call attention to the mask itself. Similarly the Post-Washington Consensus gives pre-eminence to the value of transparency. ‘Corruption’, says the World Bank, ‘thrives in the dark’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-0964663912458113">World Bank, 1997</xref>: 45). In generalizing this value it mandates an ‘unending game of mutual unmasking’ in developing countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-0964663912458113">Runciman, 2005</xref>: 3). Much of the imagery in Clay’s speeches exhibits this dialectic of concealment and revelation. There is a need to ‘unearth what is buried’, to ‘surface scandalous stories’ and to ‘uncover the skeletons of corruption’, for example (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0964663912458113">Clay, 2005</xref>: 4). The vomit image mentioned above also partakes of this idiom. The proceeds of corruption had been concealed within the guts of the elite, but they were spewed forth on the shoes of donors and Kenyans alike, for all to see.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0964663912458113">5</xref></sup> By the time of the second speech the shoes had been ‘whitewashed’ again (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0964663912458113">Clay, 2005</xref>: 4). The dialectic is even more finely wrought in a Rumsfeldian reflection on Clay’s meeting with the head of the Kenyan civil service. The latter was probably ‘aware that we know a lot, but perhaps uneasily aware that he does not know just how much we know; equally, he will be aware that we know how much he knows’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0964663912458113">Clay, 2004</xref>: 3). The invisible hand of Adam Smith’s ideal market is complemented here by a regime of reciprocal observation suggestive of his <italic>Theory of Moral Sentiments </italic>(see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0964663912458113">Marshall, 1984</xref>: 605). In line with World Bank anti-corruption policies, Clay urges participation in this ‘watchdog’ regime on a range of actors and institutions. Journalists and their readers ‘will be watching’ the register of politicians’ interests, parliament is ‘properly curious’, British businesspeople in Kenya should ‘keep their eyes open’ for evidence of graft, ‘the newsvendor and the shoe-shiner’ will provide a highly informed list of who the corrupt officials are (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0964663912458113">Clay, 2005</xref>: 10). In Kenya the most famous combination of these roles is to be found in the work of ‘Gado’, a celebrated cartoonist in the <italic>Daily Nation </italic>and name-checked by Clay in his second speech.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0964663912458113">6</xref></sup> Like Clay, Gado deploys a grotesque imagery of over-eating and physical deformity to ridicule and shame Kenya’s corrupt elite (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0964663912458113">Musila, 2007</xref>). For both the diplomat and the artist ‘doing’ satire is ‘doing’ governance.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0964663912458113">
<title>Land Grabbing and the Legal Profession</title>
<p>In his second speech Clay highlighted the problem of ‘land-grabbing’ – the misallocation of public land to well-connected private citizens – as a notable instance of corruption in Kenya. Those seeking hard data concerning corruption, he suggested, should examine the <italic>Report of Commission of Inquiry into the Illegal/Irregular Allocation of Public Land</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>), more widely known as the Ndung’u Report after its chairperson (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0964663912458113">Clay, 2005</xref>: 4).The Report highlights the role of the legal profession in land grabbing. It presents an image of lawyers wholly at odds with that which the profession presents to the Kenyan public and, indeed, with the role envisaged for it in the governance agenda of donors and the IFIs. In this section we read the findings of the Ndung’u Report using Clay’s satirical method, interpreting lawyers’ involvement in land-grabbing as an instance of institutional hypocrisy.</p>
<sec id="section12-0964663912458113">
<title>The Ndung’u Report on Illegal and Irregular Allocation of Public Land</title>
<p>Land grabbing, which was inaugurated by colonialism in Kenya, has continued in diverse forms since independence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0964663912458113">Harbeson, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0964663912458113">Boone, 2012</xref>). While corruption in land matters is both widespread and widely recognized to exist in Kenya, it has received less international attention than examples of graft involving export credit and procurement scams (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-0964663912458113">Southall, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0964663912458113">Manji, 2012</xref>). The latter has involved secret looting on a grand scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr86-0964663912458113">Wrong, 2009</xref>: 61–65). By contrast the form of corruption recorded by the Ndung’u Commission is distinctive for the prominent – and, as we show below, indispensible – involvement of mid-level professionals and bureaucrats.</p>
<p>The Ndung’u Commission was appointed by President Kibaki on taking office in 2002 in pursuance of the new government’s generalized commitment to deal with widespread corruption (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0964663912458113">Kibaki, 2004</xref>). Its report, made public in 2005, provides a detailed account of the illegal land awards made over the years to the families of President Kenyatta and President Moi, to numerous former ministers, members of parliament and civil servants, as well as to individuals in the military and the judiciary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>: 182–183). It is admitted that it only provides a snapshot of the illegal and irregular land allocations that have actually taken place (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>). The Commission found that ‘illegal allocation of public land is one of the most pronounced manifestations of corruption and political patronage’ in Kenya (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0964663912458113">Africog, 2009</xref>: 10-11; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>: 192) The public land affected has included forests, national parks and game reserves, civil service houses, government offices, roads and road reserves, wetlands, research farms and the lands of state corporations. The Report confirms that illegal allocations took place either on the direct orders of the President of the day or at the instigation of prominent, senior public officials and well-connected business people and politicians (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>: 14). Those who benefited included ministers, senior civil servants, politicians and business people, as well as religious groups of all denominations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>: 182). The Report also provides an invaluable source of information about the specific legal mechanisms used to defeat ‘the public interest’ in the administration of land and the role of practising lawyers in this (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>: 8–9; Southall, 2005: 146). Of the wide variety of ways in which lawyers used their technical knowledge and professional skills to facilitate the illegal and irregular acquisition of land we focus on just four in the following discussion.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0964663912458113">7</xref></sup></p>
<sec id="section13-0964663912458113">
<title>Setting up Bogus Companies</title>
<p>According to the Report, the Ndung’u Commission
<disp-quote>
<p>discovered quite early in its work that many illegal allocations of public land were made not to individuals but [to] companies. These companies were ostensibly registered at the Registry of Companies in conformity with the requirements of the Companies Act. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>: 40)</p>
</disp-quote>However, when the Commission tried to trace the names of those who had acquired land through the structures of companies, it encountered serious problems in identifying the those behind companies that had been allocated land. Sometimes the companies did not exist in law (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>: 40). In these cases, individuals had acquired blank Certificate of Incorporation forms that they submitted to acquire public land, but which were not filed or reflected in the records of the Companies Register. In other cases, companies that had not been fully incorporated acquired land (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>: 40). The Ndung’u Report shows that most high profile allocations of public land were made to companies incorporated specifically for that purpose, largely to shield the directors and shareholders of such entities from easy public view (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>: 40). It was apparent to the Commission that the skills of lawyers familiar with Kenyan company law had been engaged to allow those involved in land corruption to hide their true identities.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0964663912458113">
<title>Misconstrual of Letters of Allotment</title>
<p>Land grabbing was also facilitated by the existence of a thriving market in letters of allotment. These are, in effect, formal offers of public lands made to the named individual by the relevant land officer and which expire after 30 days (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>: 13, 48). Given this, it is clear that, unlike formal land titles, letters of allotment confer no transferable interest or rights over land in favour of the person to whom they are addressed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>: 48). The Ndung’u Commission found, however, that letters of allotment were treated as if they were titles in just this way (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>: 13, 48). As such they enabled misallocated public property to be traded, allowing the profits of land grabbing to be safely realized. Legal skills were again essential to this documentary alchemy. Lawyers actively did the work of transforming letters of offer into land instruments to be transacted: by failing persistently to advise their clients of the legal impediments to the transferability of such letters, they transformed their meaning and use over time.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0964663912458113">
<title>Obtaining Changes of Use</title>
<p>Land grabbing was also made possible by a perversion of the planning process according to which different areas are zoned for specific uses, public and private. Normally the Development Plan for a given region will reserve land for, say, schools, medical clinics or roads, as well as dwellings or factories. So-called changes of use are available, but these must be applied for in accordance with the proper procedure and properly gazetted. This allows interested parties, including civil society groups, to raise objections and queries where appropriate. The Ndung’u Commission found, however, that land reserved for public purposes had been systematically reallocated via the change of use mechanism and then either developed for residential and commercial purposes or sold on at a large profit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>: 77). Again lawyers played a central role either by not advising their clients of the prior zoning of the land or by actively dealing with the authorities to obtain the changes themselves. Planning officials colluded with lawyers so that changes were made without publicity or consultation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>: 78). Since, as Ndung’u notes, approvals obtained in this way could not result in valid changes of use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>: 54), lawyers’ involvement here went close to and often crossed the line separating legal from illegal conduct. Either way, professional expertise was mobilized to defeat the profound public interest in controlling the use to which particular pieces of land are put and in ensuring that decisions on the development of the physical environment are made rationally and transparently.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0964663912458113">
<title>Benefitting from the Chaos of the Land Ministry</title>
<p>Their detailed knowledge of, and extensive networks within, the infamously chaotic Ministry of Lands and Settlement enabled lawyers to identify suitable plots of public land to be targeted for illegal allocation. The Ministry of Lands and Settlement is widely known to be one of Kenya’s most inefficiently run public services. Ndung’u found that one of the main reasons for the illegal allocation of public land was the ‘chaotic record keeping system’ in the Ministry and in the district registries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>: 188). In addition, records were falsified or hidden in order to conceal the illegal allocation of land (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>: 188). In such an environment, the skills of lawyers accustomed to navigating their way through disorganized land records were invaluable. In particular they commonly collaborated with surveyors at the Ministry to ensure that two titles to the same piece of land were issued under Kenya’s system of dual land registration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>: 80). This facilitated illegal allocation and subsequent trading in the grabbed land.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0964663912458113">
<title>Institutional Hypocrisy and the Legal Profession</title>
<p>At its most general the Ndung’u Report found that ‘public land had been allocated contrary to the substantive and procedural provisions of the relevant laws’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>: 53). By way of remedy, it recommended that illegally acquired land titles should be revoked and the remainder rectified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>: 83–85). As regards the responsibility of professionals, including lawyers, it recommended that those involved be investigated and where appropriate subject to criminal prosecution and disciplinary sanction, and that all money and other assets acquired through professional malpractice be recovered (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0964663912458113">Republic of Kenya, 2004</xref>: 83–85). To date none of these measures have been initiated, much less completed. Lawyers in effect benefit from full criminal, civil and disciplinary impunity in relation to land grabbing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0964663912458113">Africog, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>In the absence of legal responsibility and formal sanctions, it is appropriate to consider the terms in which moral criticism can be made of the actions of individual lawyers and of the profession as a whole. The satirical strategies deployed as a mode of governance in Sir Edward Clay’s speeches offer a useful guide in this regard. At a personal level it is clear that a significant proportion of lawyers – those in private practice and some holding public office, such as that of Land Registrar – were complicit in the misallocation of public land. Many reaped rich personal rewards and sometimes gained political office as a result. For several leading law firms it was the mainstay of their work. However, as Ndung’u shows, corruption is not merely a matter of eating (and sometimes vomiting). Viewed from the perspective of lawyers and surveyors, for example, it has a productive, as well as an acquisitive, dimension. As has been seen, professional skills and knowledge creatively used were indispensible to land grabbing in Kenya. It is in light of this widespread perversion of legal practice that the profession as a whole can be accused of institutional hypocrisy in the terms set out above.</p>
<p>As in the case of the Kenyan state, the institutional hypocrisy of the legal profession needs to be judged against the values to which it binds itself publicly. These are similarly derived from both internal and external sources. As regards the first, all lawyers are, of course, sworn to uphold the national Constitution, including the provisions regarding transparency and accountability, as well as fundamental rights, previously discussed.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-0964663912458113">8</xref></sup> Members of the Law Society of Kenya are bound to maintain and promote the rule of law by ensuring that an independent and efficient legal profession serves the people (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0964663912458113">Law Society of Kenya, 2011</xref>). The profession also draws legitimacy from the high reputation of those lawyers who struggled and suffered in the campaign for democracy during the 1980s and 1990s. Indeed during this period the Law Society became known as the ‘conscience of the people’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0964663912458113">Murungi, 2008</xref>: 40). In particular, its leaders have been prominent in campaigns against corruption, including land grabbing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0964663912458113">Oywa, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>The external values by which Kenyan lawyers may be judged are to be found chiefly within the governance agenda associated with the Post-Washington Consensus that we have been considering in this paper. Most important of these is the rule of law (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0964663912458113">Faundez, 2009</xref>). This is understood in the first instance as a vital pre-requisite to economic growth, but it also resonates with the work of broader human rights and pro-democracy movements in Africa. Rule of law assistance, training lawyers, judges and magistrates, for example, is now a major component of development aid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0964663912458113">Manji, 2010</xref>). Such programmes place the values of legal professionalism at their centre (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0964663912458113">Department for International Development, 2006</xref>). Law is taken to be synonymous with transparency and accountability and a well-trained, ethically oriented cadre of lawyers is seen as a bulwark against tyranny and corruption. These programmes aim, not simply to impose a set of abstract norms, but to effect a moral re-orientation, a change in the structure of feeling within the legal profession.</p>
<p>The hypocrisy of the legal profession is not just evident in its collective betrayal of general rule of law values or transparency in the abstract. It is also manifest in the perversion of specific legal instruments and procedures documented by Ndung’u. In each case we find a particular instance of the dialectic of appearance and reality intrinsic to hypocrisy. Thus, the form of the company, the corporate veil as it were, was used to hide the identity of land grabbers (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0964663912458113">Ndigwa, 2012</xref>). The letter of allocation was misrepresented to the world as something it was not. The ‘face of the document’ could not be trusted. The planning process was subverted by backroom deals out of sight of affected communities. Lawyers exploited their unique ability to manoeuvre around the dark world of the Lands Ministry. In each case we see a hollowing out of legal forms and their use as masks to conceal the nefarious intent of certain lawyers and their clients. As Dennis Thompson puts it, ‘they exploited the official purpose of the institution while using it for illegitimate purposes’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0964663912458113">Thompson, 1999</xref>: 191). Law was mobilized to defeat the law. Instead of light, the profession thrived on opacity. In the words of Dickens' <italic>Bleak House</italic>, itself a satire on old corruption and law gone astray, there was ‘fog everywhere’ (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-0964663912458113">Rubinstein, 1983</xref>: 84).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0964663912458113">
<title>Excremental Satire and the Nature of Corruption</title>
<p>Having read Ndung’u in the light of Clay, in this penultimate section we reverse the procedure. We argue here that the image of corruption presented in the High Commissioner’s speeches needs to be qualified by the findings of the Report as regards the role of lawyers in the misallocation of land. Whereas Clay’s imagery represents graft as sterile and ideally separate from the regular working of the economy, Ndung’u suggests that there are in fact close and pervasive links between the two.</p>
<p>We return to Clay’s striking metaphor of Kenya’s elite vomiting their ill-gotten gains back on to the shoes of donors. The connotation here is of graft as unproductive waste, economically sterile. Consistent with donor and IFI thinking, it implies that corruption is an ‘aberrant and deviant’ phenomenon that can be sharply distinguished from normal business practice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0964663912458113">Rocha et al., 2011</xref>: 159). It preserves the purity of the market, as ‘realm of peaceful competition and pure commodity exchange’, separating it strictly from the realm of capitalism’s blustering violence which is regarded as more or less incidental (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0964663912458113">Luxemburg, 1913/2003</xref>: 432–433). Thrift, self-denial and innovation are the true motors of capitalist growth. However, as the Ndung’u Report showed, corruption cannot be neatly separated off from normal commercial activity in this way. On the one hand, routine professional work was essential to the practice of corruption. On the other hand, the assets thus grabbed have been widely used as capital in legitimate businesses (e.g. as land for commercial horticulture and tourist facilities, including conservancies and ecotourism projects) or sold on to foreign investors (Southall, 2005: 150). It appears that the proceeds of corruption do not simply disappear into the belly of the thief or back out on to the shoes of donors in the form of vomit.</p>
<p>These findings echo the views of critical writers on political economy who have identified a structural connection between corruption and the development of capitalism. Viewed as the appropriation of common property by theft or deception, corruption can be understood as an example of what Marx termed ‘primitive accumulation’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0964663912458113">Marx, 1867/1976</xref>: 874). On Marx’s account this provided a vital initial impetus to the development of modern economies by concentrating capital in the hands of a few and creating a class of propertyless wage labourers (Marx, 1867/1976: 873ff). However, later writers have shown that primitive accumulation has played a more enduring role, functioning to the present day as a source of cheap inputs allowing for profitable investment and, thus, helping to alleviate the crisis tendencies inherent in capitalism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0964663912458113">Harvey, 2003</xref>: 138, 149). Colonialism was identified by Rosa Luxemburg (1913/2003: 328ff) as one such form. More recently, David <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0964663912458113">Harvey (2003</xref>: 137ff) contends that neo-liberal strategies of privatization, credit booms and bank rescues are equivalent strategies of what he labels ‘accumulation by dispossession’. Most importantly in the present context, Festus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0964663912458113">Iyayi (1986</xref>: 33) has argued that grand corruption represents an accumulation strategy vital to the constitution of post-colonial elites as a capitalist class.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-0964663912458113">9</xref></sup> We can say, somewhat schematically, that both aspects of primitive accumulation are evident in the type of land grabbing discussed in this paper. On the one hand, unlawful and irregular appropriation transfers capital to a privileged few in Kenya. On the other hand, the unavailability of land for subsistence farming or petty commodity production creates an expanding class of wage labourers who have no option but to work for the owners of agri-businesses or tourist facilities (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0964663912458113">Bush et al., 2011</xref>: 191).</p>
<p>In each case it is important to stress, as Luxemburg did, the ‘organic’ connection between primitive and market-based accumulation (Luxemburg, 1913/2003: 433). This implies an element of functional necessity already alluded to: without ongoing primitive accumulation capitalism would collapse. At the level of form and image, it also suggests that there is a continuity of substance between what is taken by fraud or force and what is acquired legitimately through the market. Corruption is dirt ‘dripping from every pore’ of capital (Marx, 1867/1976: 926). This continuity is anticipated in the work of post-colonial novelists, filmmakers and critics in Kenya and elsewhere who have pioneered what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0964663912458113">Esty (1999</xref>) calls a form of ‘excremental satire’. As Sarah <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0964663912458113">Lincoln (2008</xref>: 32) has remarked, excrement in African literature is an over determined figure, a ‘powerful semiotic node capable of signifying many disparate, even contradictory ideas’. Where vomit is unambivalently sterile, excrement has a dual aspect, being both wasteful and productive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0964663912458113">Esty, 1999</xref>: 28). Used as fertilizer, the expelled returns to contribute to a cycle of growth. As the Ghanaian novelist Ayei <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0964663912458113">Kwei Armah (1968</xref>: 85) put it, ‘out of the decay and the dung there is always a new flowering’. The connotation of this image is that corruption and normal business are in fact closely linked. They feed off each other.</p>
<p>The sharp separation of state and market, of corruption and commerce, partakes of the kind of sanitary utopia pursued by both colonial administrators and some nationalist elites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0964663912458113">Anderson, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0964663912458113">Chakrabarty, 1992</xref>). In contrast, excremental satire suggests a hardly resistable process of contamination, a blurring of boundaries. This mutual contamination is evident in the widely noted phenomenon that market-oriented reforms, such as privatization, have in fact led to increased corruption as state assets are sold for next to nothing to cronies of the regime in power (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0964663912458113">Murunga, 2007</xref>: 284). Notwithstanding 30 years of neo-liberal adjustment, as Harrison observes, most African political economies continue to be ‘characterized by a strong unity of private and state power’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0964663912458113">Harrison, 2001</xref>: 540). An excremental reading of corruption also challenges the sharp distinction between developed and developing countries upon which anti-corruption policies are premised. On the input side, donor funding and loans from the IFIs have provided further resources to be looted, securing the material position of corrupt elites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0964663912458113">Glennie, 2008</xref>: 70–77). On the output side, it can be fairly argued that a great portion of the proceeds of corruption leaves Africa for the developed world, including tax havens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0964663912458113">Ndikumana and Boyce, 2011</xref>). These monies do not, in the words of the Elizabethan sermonist ‘lie stinking … as in a loathsome sink or channel’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0964663912458113">Miller, 1997</xref>: 101). Rather they rejoin the circuits of normal accumulation, being reinvested around the world in order to generate a return for their owners and a commission for their financial agents.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0964663912458113">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>This paper has explored a matter of intense concern for foreign donors and the international financial institutions in Kenya and elsewhere, corruption, and shown how external efforts to intervene in governance in this regard have been more than simply instrumental. It has argued that it is important to understand interventions in Kenyan governance as inherently rhetorical: they seek to establish the plausibility of a set of values rooted in political economy. We develop in this paper a reading of anti-corruption governance as satire and, taking the complicity of the Kenyan legal profession in the illegal and irregular allocation of public land as our starting point, argue that the long-standing experience of land grabbing in Kenya also highlights the instability of many of the key binary oppositions underpinning dominant anti-corruption strategies. We have argued that this instability can be understood in rhetorical terms by drawing on the work of post-colonial writers and critics on the category of excremental satire. Rather than a clear binary opposition, these writings, we have suggested, alert us to the interrelation or more precisely the mutual contamination of corruption, understood as a form of accumulation.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>Earlier versions of this paper were presented as the British Institute in Eastern Africa Annual Lecture at the British Academy, London (24 November 2011), at a Research Seminar of Warwick Law School (25 April 2012) and at a workshop on Culture and Politics in East Africa at the British Institute in Eastern Africa, Nairobi (14 June 2012). We are grateful to the participants for discussing our paper. We would also like to thank Donald Cole and Kenneth Veitch for their helpful comments on earlier drafts and to acknowledge the invaluable research assistance provided by Chris Day, Misha Mintz-Roth and David Thompson. All responsibility for errors and infelicities is ours alone.</p>
</ack>
<notes>
<title>Notes</title>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0964663912458113">
<label>1.</label>
<p>Quoted in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0964663912458113">Adebanwi and Obadare (2011</xref>: 209).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0964663912458113">
<label>2.</label>
<p>As President Kibaki put it to an international conference on the topic held in Nairobi: ‘Rampant corruption has undermined our development efforts and caused widespread poverty in our society. We therefore promise Kenyans, and our well-wishers abroad, that we are determined to root out this evil from our midst’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0964663912458113">Kibaki, 2004</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0964663912458113">
<label>3.</label>
<p>See, for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr85-0964663912458113">World Bank (2010</xref>); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-0964663912458113">Transparency International (2011</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0964663912458113">
<label>4.</label>
<p>Indeed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0964663912458113">Chabal and Daloz (1999</xref>: 16) suggest that the African state in general is no more than a ‘pseudo-western façade’, masking an effectively patrimonial system of government that is materially sustained through corruption.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0964663912458113">
<label>5.</label>
<p>As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0964663912458113">Miller (1997</xref>: 100) remarks, the ‘culminating vileness of gluttony is the vileness of vomit’.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0964663912458113">
<label>6.</label>
<p>Indeed, the outraged reaction of Kenyan leaders to Clay’s criticisms was itself satirized by Gado in subsequent cartoons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr86-0964663912458113">Wrong, 2009</xref>: 202).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-0964663912458113">
<label>7.</label>
<p>Land is <italic>illegally</italic> issued when the legal safeguards governing the allocation of land are ignored or subverted. For instance, where a title is issued for a piece of land that is not legally available for allocation the title acquired is illegal. Land is <italic>irregularly</italic> allocated when administrative procedures for dealing in land are not followed.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-0964663912458113">
<label>8.</label>
<p>See Article 3(1) Constitution of Kenya: ‘Every person has an obligation to respect, uphold and defend this Constitution’.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-0964663912458113">
<label>9.</label>
<p>While it is true that corruption is used ‘unproductively’ to fund electoral campaigns, in Kenya and elsewhere, these must be seen as part of a broader strategy to secure the economic, as well as the political position of dominant factions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0964663912458113">Mwangi, 2008</xref>: 273–276).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adebanwi</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Obadare</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>When corruption fights back: Democracy and elite interest in Nigeria’s anti-corruption war</article-title>. <source>Journal of Modern African Studies</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Aden</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Satire or sense: A truer mix</article-title>. <source>The Sewanee Review</source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>441</fpage>–<lpage>447</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Africog</collab> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Mission Impossible? Implementing the Ndung’u Report</source>. <publisher-loc>Nairobi</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>African Centre for Open Governance</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Anderson</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Excremental colonialism: Public health and the poetics of pollution</article-title>. <source>Critical Inquiry</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>640</fpage>–<lpage>669</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ayers</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Demystifying democratisation: The global constitution of (neo) liberal polities in Africa</article-title>. <source>Third World Quarterly</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>338</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bayart</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <source>The State in Africa. The Politics of the Belly</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Longman</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bloom</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bloom</surname>
<given-names>LD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1969</year>) <article-title>The satiric mode of feeling. A theory of intention</article-title>. <source>Criticism</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>139</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Boone</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Land conflict and distributive politics in Kenya</article-title>. <source>African Studies Review</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Booth</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <source>The Rhetoric of Fiction</source>, <edition>2nd edn</edition>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Chicago University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Branch</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Kenya. Between Hope and Despair, 1963–2011</source>. <publisher-loc>New Haven, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cloke</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Neo-liberal reform, governance and corruption in the south: Assessing the international anti-corruption crusade</article-title>. <source>Antipode</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>272</fpage>–<lpage>294</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>From demiurge to midwife: Changing donor roles in Kenya’s democratisation process</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Murunga</surname>
<given-names>GR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nasong’o</surname>
<given-names>SW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Kenya: The Struggle for Democracy</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Zed Books</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>301</fpage>–<lpage>329</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bukovansky</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The hollowness of anti-corruption discourse</article-title>. <source>Review of International Political Economy</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Burgis</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>UK cuts off Kenyan education aid</article-title>. <source>Financial Times</source>, <issue>16 March</issue>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Burke</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1969</year>) <source>A Rhetoric of Motives</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bush</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bujra</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Littlejohn</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Editorial: The accumulation of dispossession</article-title>. <source>Review of African Political Economy</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chabal</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Daloz</surname>
<given-names>J-P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>Africa Works. Disorder as Political Instrument</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>James Currey</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chakrabarty</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Garbage, modernity and the citizen’s gaze</article-title>. <source>Economic and Political Weekly</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>541</fpage>–<lpage>547</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chimni</surname>
<given-names>BS</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>International institutions today: An imperial global state in the making</article-title>. <source>European Journal of International Law</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Clay</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>UK envoy’s speech on Kenyan corruption [full text]</article-title> <source>BBC News</source> <comment>[online]. Available at</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/3893625.stm">http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/3893625.stm</ext-link> <comment>[accessed 9 July 2012]</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Clay</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>), <comment>Speech given by the British High Commissioner, Sir Edward Clay, at the Annual Journalists of the Year Awards Dinner, on 2 February 2005 [copy on file with authors.]</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Department for International Development</collab> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Eliminating World Poverty: Making Governance Work for the Poor. A White Paper on International Development</source>. <comment>Cm. 6876</comment>. <publisher-loc>Norwich</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>HMSO</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Department for International Development</collab> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Evaluation of DFID Country Programmes. Country Study: Kenya Final Report Ev 674</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>DFID</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Department for International Development</collab> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Eliminating World Poverty: Building Our Common Future. A White paper on International Development</source>. <comment>Cm. 7656</comment>. <publisher-name>Norwich</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>HMSO</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Erdmann</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Engel</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Neopatrimonialism reconsidered: Critical review and elaboration of an elusive concept</article-title>. <source>Commonwealth and Comparative Politics</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>119</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Esty</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Excremental postcolonialism</article-title>. <source>Contemporary Literature</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Faundez</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Rule of law or Washington Consensus: The evolution of the World Bank’s approach to legal and judicial reform</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Parry-Kessaris</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Law in the Pursuit of Development: Principles into Practice?</source> <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Frow</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Genre</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ghai</surname>
<given-names>YP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McAuslan</surname>
<given-names>JPWB</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1970</year>) <source>Public Law and Political Change in Kenya: A Study of the Legal Framework of Government from Colonial Times to the Present</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gill</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Globalisation, market civilisation and disciplinary neo-liberalism</article-title>. <source>Millennium – Journal of International Studies</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>399</fpage>–<lpage>423</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Glennie</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>The Trouble with Aid. Why Less Could Mean More for Africa</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Zed Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Greenberg</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Modernism, Satire and the Novel</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Harbeson</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Land and the quest for a democratic state in Kenya: Bringing citizens back in</article-title>. <source>African Studies Review</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Harrington</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Migration and access to health care in English law: A rhetorical critique</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Law in Context</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>315</fpage>–<lpage>335</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Harrington</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Time as a dimension of medical law</article-title>. <source>Medical Law Review</source> <volume>20</volume>, <comment>in press</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Harris</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The purpose and method of satire</article-title>. <source>Virtual Salt</source>, <issue>24 October</issue> <comment>(original 20 August 1990).Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.virtualsalt.com/satire.htm">http://www.virtualsalt.com/satire.htm</ext-link> <comment>[accessed 9 July 2012]</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Harrison</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Administering market friendly growth? Liberal populism and the World Bank’s involvement in administrative reform in Sub-Saharan Africa</article-title>. <source>Review of International Political Economy</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>528</fpage>–<lpage>547</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Harrison</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Neoliberal Africa. The Impact of Social Engineering</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Zed Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Harvey</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>The New Imperialism</source>. <publisher-name>Oxford</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Oxford University Press</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hay</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The normalizing role of rationalist assumptions in the institutional embedding of neo-liberalism</article-title>. <source>Economy and Society</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>500</fpage>–<lpage>527</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hearn</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>African NGOs: The new compradors?</article-title> <source>Development and Change</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>1095</fpage>–<lpage>1110</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Iyayi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>The primitive accumulation of capital in a neo-colony: The Nigerian case</article-title>. <source>Review of African Political Economy</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kariuki</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A faltering fight on graft withers investor optimism</article-title>. <source>The Nairobi Law Monthly</source> <volume>2</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>60</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kibaki</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Speech by HE Mwai Kibaki CGH, MP President and Commander-in-Chief of the Armed Forces of the Republic of Kenya on the Occasion of the International Experts Meeting on Anti-Corruption and Transparency International Annual Membership Meeting</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Safari Park</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Nairobi</publisher-name>, <issue>12 October</issue> [copy on file with authors].</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kwei</surname>
<given-names>Armah A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1968</year>) <source>The Beautyful Ones are Not Yet Born</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Heinemann</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Knight</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Satire, speech, and genre</article-title>. <source>Comparative Literature</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lakoff</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>) <source>Metaphors We Live By</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Law Society of Kenya</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>About LSK</article-title>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.lsk.or.ke/index.php/about-lsk">http://www.lsk.or.ke/index.php/about-lsk</ext-link> <comment>[accessed 9 July 2012]</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lawson</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The politics of anti-corruption reform in Africa</article-title>. <source>Journal of Modern African Studies</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>73</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="thesis">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lincoln</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Expensive shit: Aesthetic economies of waste in postcolonial Africa</article-title>. <publisher-name>Doctoral Thesis</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Duke University</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Luxemburg</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1913/2003</year>) <source>The Accumulation of Capital</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Manji</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Eliminating poverty: ‘Financial inclusion’, access to land and gender equality in international development</article-title>. <source>Modern Law Review</source> <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>985</fpage>–<lpage>1025</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Manji</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The grabbed state: Lawyers, politics and public land in Kenya</article-title>. <source>Journal of Modern African Studies</source> <volume>53</volume> (<issue>in press</issue>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Marshall</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Adam Smith and the theatricality of moral sentiments</article-title>. <source>Critical Inquiry</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>592</fpage>–<lpage>613</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Marx</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1867/1976</year>) <source>Capital. A Critique of Political Economy</source>, <volume>Vol. 1</volume>. <publisher-loc>Harmondsworth</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Penguin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mbembe</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>On the Postcolony</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>WI</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Gluttony</article-title>. <source>Representations</source> <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>92</fpage>–<lpage>112</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mueller</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The political economy of Kenya’s crisis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Eastern African Studies</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>185</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Murphy</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Capitalism and transparency</article-title>. <source>Critical Perspectives on International Business</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>125</fpage>–<lpage>141</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Murunga</surname>
<given-names>GR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Governance and the politics of structural adjustment in Kenya</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Murunga</surname>
<given-names>GR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nasong’o</surname>
<given-names>SW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Kenya: The Struggle for Democracy</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Zed Books</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>300</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Murunga</surname>
<given-names>GR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nasong’o</surname>
<given-names>SW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) (eds) <source>Kenya: The Struggle for Democracy</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Zed Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Murungi</surname>
<given-names>BK</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>For whom, for what and about what? The legitimacy of human rights NGOs in Kenya</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Mutua</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Human Rights NGOs in East Africa</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Pennsylvania Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>46</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Musila</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title><italic>Democrazy</italic>: Laughter in Gado’s editorial cartoons</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Ogude</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nyairo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Urban Legends and Colonial Myths. Popular Culture and Literature in East Africa</source>. <publisher-loc>Trenton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Africa World Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mwangi</surname>
<given-names>OG</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Political corruption, party financing and democracy in Kenya</article-title>. <source>Journal of Modern African Studies</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>285</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ndigwa</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Proposed company law will boost business</article-title>. <source>Nairobi Law Monthly</source> <volume>3</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>84</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ndikumana</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Boyce</surname>
<given-names>JK</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Africa’s Odious Debts. How Foreign Loans and Capital Flight Bled a Continent</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Zed</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ogude</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The state as a site of eating. Literary representation and the dialectics of ethnicity, class and the nation state in Kenya</article-title>. <source>Africa Insight</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Oywa</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Lawyers protest inefficiency at Lands Ministry</article-title>. <source>The Standard</source>, <issue>28 June</issue>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Polzer</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Corruption: Deconstructing the World Bank Discourse – Destin Working Papers Series No. 01-18</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>London School of Economics</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Republic of Kenya</collab> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Report of Commission of Inquiry into the Illegal/Irregular Allocation of Public Land (Ndung’u Report)</source>. <publisher-loc>Nairobi</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Government Printer</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rocha</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cloke</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Of legitimate and illegitimate corruption. Bankruptcies in Nicaragua</article-title>. <source>Critical Perspectives on International Business</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rubinstein</surname>
<given-names>WD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>The end of ‘old corruption’ in Britain 1780–1860</article-title>. <source>Past and Present</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Runciman</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Institutional hypocrisy</article-title>. <source>London Review of Books</source>, <volume>27</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Southal</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The Ndung’u Report: Land and graft in Kenya</article-title>. <source>Review of African Political Economy</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>142</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Szeftel</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Misunderstanding African politics: Corruption and the governance agenda</article-title>. <source>Review of African Political Economy</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>240</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Szeftel</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Between governance and under-development: Accumulation and Africa’s catastrophic corruption</article-title>. <source>Review of African Political Economy</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>287</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr77-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tan</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Governance through Development. Poverty Reduction Strategies, International Law and the Disciplining of Third World States</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr78-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">The Corner House</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Submission to the International Development Committee Inquiry into Financial Crime and Development</source>. <publisher-loc>Sturminster Newton</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Corner House</publisher-name> <comment>available at</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.thecornerhouse.org.uk/resource/international-development-committee-inquiry-financial-crime-and-development">http://www.thecornerhouse.org.uk/resource/international-development-committee-inquiry-financial-crime-and-development</ext-link> <comment>[accessed 9July 2012]</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr79-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Democratic secrecy</article-title>. <source>Political Science Quarterly</source> <volume>114</volume>: <fpage>181</fpage>–<lpage>193</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr80-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Transparency International</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <source>The East African Bribery Index 2011</source>. <publisher-loc>Nairobi</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transparency International</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr81-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Warren</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Political corruption and duplicitous exclusion</article-title>. <source>PS: Political Science and Politics</source> <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>803</fpage>–<lpage>807</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr82-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1965</year>) <source>The Long Revolution</source>. <publisher-loc>Harmondsworth</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pelican</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr83-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Williams</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>) <source>Marxism and Literature</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr84-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">World Bank</collab> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Helping Countries Combat Corruption: A Report of the Poverty Reduction and Economic Management Network</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Bank Institute</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr85-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">World Bank</collab> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Worldwide Governance Indicators: Country Data Report for Kenya, 1996–2010</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Bank Institute</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr86-0964663912458113">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wrong</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Our Turn to Eat: The Story of a Kenyan Whistle Blower</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harper Collins</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>