<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CJO</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcjo</journal-id>
<journal-title>Canadian Journal of Occupational Therapy</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0008-4174</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1911-9828</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0008417413481956</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0008417413481956</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles / Articles originaux</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Psychometric testing of a self-report measure of engagement in productive occupations</article-title>
<subtitle>Évaluation psychométrique d’un instrument d’autoévaluation de la participation à des occupations productives</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Tjörnstrand</surname>
<given-names>Carina</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0008417413481956"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bejerholm</surname>
<given-names>Ulrika</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eklund</surname>
<given-names>Mona</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<bio>
<title>Author Biographies</title>
<p>
<bold>Carina Tjörnstrand</bold>, PhD, OT Reg., is Lecturer, Department of Health Sciences/Occupational Therapy and Occupational Science, Lund University, Box 157, SE 221 00, Lund, Sweden. E-mail: <email>carina.tjornstrand@med.lu.se</email>. At the time of the study, Carina was a doctoral candidate in the Department of Health Sciences/Occupational Therapy and Occupational Science, Lund University, Lund, Sweden.</p>
<p>
<bold>Ulrika Bejerholm</bold>, PhD, OT Reg., is Associate Professor, Department of Health Sciences/Occupational Therapy and Occupational Science, Lund University, Box 157, SE 221 00, Lund, Sweden.</p>
<p>
<bold>Mona Eklund</bold>, PhD, OT Reg., is Professor, Department of Health Sciences/Occupational Therapy and Occupational Science, Lund University, Box 157, SE 221 00, Lund, Sweden.</p>
</bio>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0008417413481956">Carina Tjörnstrand, Department of Health Sciences/Occupational Therapy and Occupational Science, Lund University, Box 157, SE 221 00, Lund, Sweden. Telephone: +46 46-222 19 54. E-mail: <email>carina.tjornstrand@med.lu.se</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>80</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>101</fpage>
<lpage>110</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© CAOT 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="other">Canadian Association of Occupational Therapists (CAOT)</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec>
<title>Background</title>
<p>Occupational therapists working with clients in productive occupations explicitly or implicitly assess their clients’ occupational engagement.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Purpose</title>
<p>To investigate the psychometric properties of the Profiles of Occupational Engagement in People with Severe Mental Illness: Productive Occupations (POES-P) in terms of internal consistency, initial construct validation, and floor and ceiling effects.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Method</title>
<p>Participants (<italic>n</italic> = 93) from six day centres completed the data collection. Correlations between the POES-P and instruments measuring similar and dissimilar attributes, such as satisfaction, psychosocial functioning, and unmet needs, were studied.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Findings</title>
<p>A moderate relationship was found between the POES-P and occupational satisfaction (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = 0.43) and a weak one with psychosocial functioning (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = 0.22). The association with researcher-assessed participant engagement was slightly higher (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = 0.37), and the relationship with unmet needs was nonsignificant (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = –0.15). Internal consistency of the POES-P (alpha = 0.85) was good, but the distribution of responses indicated a ceiling effect.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Implications</title>
<p>The POES-P seems promising for assessing engagement in work-like occupations but would benefit from further development.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<abstract xml:lang="fr">
<sec>
<title>Description</title>
<p>Les ergothérapeutes intervenant auprès des clients à l’aide d’occupations productives évaluent la participation occupationnelle de leurs clients de manière explicite ou implicite.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>But</title>
<p>Examiner les propriétés psychométriques du Profiles of Occupational Engagement in People with Severe Mental Illness: Productive Occupations (POES-P) en fonction de la cohérence interne, la validité structurale initiale et les effets plancher et plafond.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Méthodologie</title>
<p>Des participants (<italic>n</italic> = 93) de six centres de jour ont participé à la cueillette de données. Les corrélations entre le POES-P et des instruments mesurant des attributs semblables et différents, comme la satisfaction, le fonctionnement psychosocial et les besoins non satisfaits ont été analysées.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Résultats</title>
<p>Une relation modérée a été observée entre le POES-P et la satisfaction occupationnelle (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = 0,43) et une relation faible a été constatée entre le POES-P et le fonctionnement psychosocial (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = 0,22). L’association entre le POES-P et la participation occupationnelle des participants évaluée par le chercheur était un peu plus élevée (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = 0,37) et la relation avec les besoins non-satisfaits n’était pas significative (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = –0,15). La cohérence interne du POES-P (alpha = 0,85) était bonne, mais la distribution des réponses indiquait un effet plafond.</p>
</sec>
<sec>
<title>Conséquences</title>
<p>Le POES-P semble prometteur pour évaluer la participation à des occupations s’apparentant au travail, mais il serait avantageux de développer davantage cet instrument de mesure.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Day centres</kwd>
<kwd>Mental health</kwd>
<kwd>Occupational engagement</kwd>
<kwd>Persistent mental illness</kwd>
<kwd>Psychometrics</kwd>
</kwd-group>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>centres de jour</kwd>
<kwd>maladie mentale persistante</kwd>
<kwd>participation occupationnelle</kwd>
<kwd>psychométrie</kwd>
<kwd>santé mentale</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Occupational engagement has long been seen as a human necessity for well-being and as an integral part of health. It has been defined as a lifestyle characteristic and the extent to which a person has a daily rhythm that includes both activity and rest and experiences a sense of meaning when performing occupations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0008417413481956">Bejerholm &amp; Eklund, 2006b</xref>). Occupational engagement as a phenomenon is said to capture clients’ connection to occupations and their investments in them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0008417413481956">Edgelow &amp; Krupa, 2011</xref>) and has been described as the ability to perform occupations within a certain context, the range and variety of meaningful occupations, and the routines that a person has (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0008417413481956">Bejerholm &amp; Eklund, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0008417413481956">Edgelow &amp; Krupa, 2011</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0008417413481956">Jonsson, Josephsson, and Kielhofner (2001</xref>) argued that the concept of occupational engagement can be vital when analyzing a client’s occupational pattern. More recently, the Canadian Model of Occupational Performance was amended to acknowledge the importance of engagement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0008417413481956">Polatajko et al., 2007</xref>). Furthermore, it has been suggested that occupational engagement may be the missing link to explaining how occupational performance can generate experiences of meaning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0008417413481956">Krupa, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>People with psychiatric disabilities stand a risk of having a low level of occupational engagement and of being passive and socially excluded from society. Many of them may rely on community mental health services, such as day centres, for their daily occupations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0008417413481956">Bejerholm &amp; Eklund, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0008417413481956">Catty &amp; Burns, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0008417413481956">Catty, Goddard, &amp; Burns, 2005</xref>). Some may find it too challenging to engage in competitive employment, and alternatives that offer engagement in other types of occupations are therefore important. In Sweden, people with a psychiatric disability not capable of engaging in competitive employment access daily occupations and alternatives to paid work through the community-based day centres (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0008417413481956">National Board of Health and Welfare, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0008417413481956">Tjörnstrand, Bejerholm, &amp; Eklund, 2011</xref>). The occupations performed within day centres have been categorized as social occupations, maintenance occupations, creative occupations, manufacturing occupations, and service and information-oriented occupations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0008417413481956">Tjörnstrand et al., 2011</xref>). The occupational levels of demand may vary among the day centres. A related study showed that performing an occupation with an individually adjusted level of demand, such as being part of a work group that entails challenges and responsibilities, could be perceived as work regardless of the occupational category (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0008417413481956">Tjörnstrand, Bejerholm, &amp; Eklund, 2013</xref>). A day centre can thus be seen as a productivity option available to persons diagnosed with severe mental illnesses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0008417413481956">Krupa, McLean, Eastabrook, Bonham, &amp; Baksh, 2003</xref>). Productive occupations were defined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0008417413481956">Pierce (2001</xref>) as occupations that include a goal-focused dimension and often provide personal satisfaction. This definition thus goes beyond that of the category of work and is particularly relevant in the case of people with psychiatric disabilities. Coming to a day centre has been shown to be a goal in itself for people with psychiatric disabilities, a reason to get up in the morning, breaking passivity and social seclusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0008417413481956">Bejerholm &amp; Eklund, 2004</xref>), and a way of spending productive hours seen as work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0008417413481956">Tjörnstrand et al., 2013</xref>).</p>
<p>When guiding clients to engage in occupations, for example, in a day centre, the occupational therapist gains from having an assessment tool that would help him or her to understand the clients’ needs and evaluate the intervention. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0008417413481956">Fuller (2011</xref>) identified a need for client-centred instruments in mental health and found a limited number of clinically based studies evidencing the validity and reliability of occupational performance outcome measures used by occupational therapists in mental health practice. She argued that to gain a client-centred perspective, an individualized outcome measure would be suitable, and a self-report could contribute with such a perspective. To our knowledge, however, there is no instrument available that measures self-reported occupational engagement with a focus on productive occupations in work-like settings, revealing a knowledge gap. To meet this requirement, the Profile of Occupational Engagement in People with Severe Mental Illness: Productive Occupations (POES-P) was developed on the basis of the Profiles of Occupational Engagement in People with Schizophrenia (POES; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0008417413481956">Bejerholm &amp; Eklund, 2006a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0008417413481956">Bejerholm, Hansson, &amp; Eklund, 2006</xref>). The original instrument consists of a 24-hr time-use diary (Part 1), where the client reports his or her occupational performance during that time span. On the basis of the diary content, the occupational therapist makes an assessment (Part 2) of the client’s occupational engagement.</p>
<p>The <italic>P</italic> in the POES-P, denoting “productive occupations,” indicates that the time-use diary focus is only on the 8 hours spent in productivity and on engagement in such occupations. It may therefore be suitable in work-like settings, such as a day centre. In addition, unlike the POES, the POES-P is a self-report questionnaire where both the diary report and the assessment of occupational engagement are made by the client. Self-reports generate the subjective experience of a construct (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0008417413481956">Grady, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0008417413481956">Streiner &amp; Norman, 2008</xref>) and are vital in occupational therapy practice to capture the self-perceived occupational barriers and direct best practice in mental health rehabilitation.</p>
<sec id="section1-0008417413481956">
<title>Considerations Regarding Psychometric Testing</title>
<p>When developing an instrument, it is vital to investigate its psychometric properties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0008417413481956">Streiner &amp; Norman, 2008</xref>). Internal consistency addresses whether a multiple-items questionnaire measures the single underlying concept (construct) it intends to measure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0008417413481956">Terwee et al., 2007</xref>). Investigating both ceiling and floor effects is important to indicate the constraints and utility of the instrument. A ceiling effect would give little opportunity to detect an increase on the measured phenomenon, and a floor effect makes it difficult to discern deterioration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0008417413481956">Cramer &amp; Howitt, 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>Discriminant validation is important in investigating the extent to which the instrument differs from another measure and is an aspect of construct validity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0008417413481956">Streiner &amp; Norman, 2008</xref>). For example, theory about occupational engagement does not explicitly refer to people’s needs as a component of the construct of occupational engagement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0008417413481956">Bejerholm &amp; Eklund, 2006b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0008417413481956">2007</xref>). Engagement is the person’s performance of a variety of meaningful and routine-based occupations in different social settings, whereas a person’s unmet needs are about something that is lacking in his or her life. One may be engaged in occupations at a day centre and still have unmet needs, for example, requiring help with hygiene or looking after one’s home. Accordingly, the POES-P should exhibit a low correlation with an instrument for needs assessment, which was therefore chosen to estimate the discriminant validity of the POES-P.</p>
<p>Convergent validation is another way to test construct validity and is assessed by investigating how closely a new scale is related to a measure of a construct to which it should be related according to theory. In the case of the POES-P, the level of engagement could hypothetically be related to satisfaction with daily occupations, which has been shown to be related to occupational engagement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0008417413481956">Bejerholm &amp; Eklund, 2006a</xref>). Research from the education field has indicated that there is an association between engagement and satisfaction in terms of the positive feeling about what one is doing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0008417413481956">Wefald &amp; Downey, 2009</xref>). Psychosocial functioning in everyday life may also be relevant for the assessment of convergent validity, because it has been shown to be related to different aspects of subjective perceptions of occupational performance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0008417413481956">Bejerholm &amp; Eklund, 2006a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0008417413481956">Eklund, Hansson, &amp; Bejerholm, 2001</xref>). Another aspect of convergent validation is to see how the new scale correlates with a measure of the same construct and to evaluate how the scales differ by the measuring process. An ideal way of evaluating this is correlating a self-report against one completed by an observer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0008417413481956">Streiner &amp; Norman, 2008</xref>). However, the validation process may be strengthened by stating hypotheses about the magnitude and nature of correlations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0008417413481956">Streiner &amp; Norman, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>The aim of the study was thus to examine the psychometric properties in terms of (a) internal consistency, (b) initial construct validation, and (c) floor and ceiling effects of the POES-P. Hypotheses were stated regarding the relationships between the POES-P and other instruments, tested to reveal construct validity as reflected in convergent and discriminant validity. The first hypothesis for this article was that there would be a moderate relationship between the POES-P ratings and satisfaction with daily occupations. The reason for expecting only a moderate relationship was that occupational engagement has been shown to be a construct in its own right, although partly overlapping with satisfaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0008417413481956">Bejerholm &amp; Eklund, 2006a</xref>). On the basis of research on the POES (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0008417413481956">Bejerholm &amp; Eklund, 2006a</xref>), we also expected a moderate relationship between the POES-P and psychosocial functioning. In addition, the research aimed to determine the relationship between the POES-P and another’s perspective of occupational engagement. We decided to create an opportunity for this; thus a tool to enable an alternative way of assessing occupational engagement was developed. The new assessment concerned the researcher’s rating of the diary content. This method also meant a variation in perspectives, especially personwise (researcher vs. self-rated). It is, thus, of course a problem if the instruments used in the validation process have not been psychometrically tested. We hypothesized a moderate relationship between the researcher’s rating and the participant’s self-rating. They were both based on the occupations reported in the diary and had a common time frame, but the person perspectives differed. Regarding the relationship between the POES-P and the assessment of unmet needs, a low correlation was hypothesized. The limits set for weak and moderate relationships build on the interpretation that a correlation of 0.5 or more is large, 0.3 to 0.5 is moderate, and 0.1 to 0.3 is small (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0008417413481956">Cohen, 1992</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0008417413481956" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<p>The development of the POES-P followed a three-step strategy as proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0008417413481956">Streiner and Norman (2008</xref>): (a) considering the theory on the phenomenon based on research, (b) reviewing relevant instruments, and (c) gathering expert opinions to serve as a source for both content validation and suggested changes. The theoretical reasoning was supported by reviewing research within the area of occupational engagement and mental health as presented in the introduction. The second step revealed that the POES was the only instrument found to focus on occupational engagement. In accordance with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0008417413481956">Streiner and Norman (2008</xref>), the content of the POES was used to develop the POES-P. For the last step, two types of experts’ opinions were collected. Both the researchers’ clinical observations when trying the POES-P and consumers’ opinions on the content of the POES-P were taken into account.</p>
<p>Ethical approval was obtained from the Regional Ethical Review Board, Lund University, Sweden (Dnr 303/2006). The ethical considerations included informed consent and the voluntary nature of participation, and the preservation of participants’ anonymity by using codes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0008417413481956">
<title>Study Context</title>
<p>This study was conducted in six day centres located in four municipalities in Sweden. The day centres studied were both meeting place oriented and work oriented. The former represent more open-access services with a focus on leisure occupations and the latter more scheduled work-like occupational opportunities. The day centres studied, however, mainly constituted a mix of both orientations; thus the meeting place–oriented centres generally presented opportunities for lower levels, and the work-oriented centres offered higher levels of occupational demands. As shown in earlier studies from the same sample, a distinct demarcation between the two orientations was impossible to make, as the participants used the day centres in accordance with their needs and their current capabilities for low or high demands in occupations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0008417413481956">Tjörnstrand et al., 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>The staff at the day centres had varying qualifications, ranging from craft specialists to persons with a health care degree at the college or undergraduate university level. They included profession vocational teachers, nurses, and social workers. Only a minority were occupational therapists, and those who were had in general a leading position as a manager of the day centre.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0008417413481956">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>To select participants, information was given to the staff at the selected units, who then informed eligible participants both orally and in writing about the study. Eligible participants were those individuals who had attended the day centre for at least 1 month, 4 hours or more per week, and were between 18 and 65 years of age. A key worker, a key contact person among the staff who had worked together with the prospective participant at the day centre, made the initial contact with each individual. This process was used to maintain confidentiality. The information was given out at a regular meeting at the day centre. After giving oral consent, the participants also provided their written consent, which was then given to one of three interviewers, all of whom were occupational therapists. The interviewers then contacted the participants to make appointments for the questionnaire sessions, which were conducted at the day centres. From a total of 196 eligible participants, 93 handed in their written consent. This sample was large enough to detect a correlation of 0.2, considered small and statistically significant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0008417413481956">Altman, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0008417413481956">Cohen, 1992</xref>). Sociodemographic and clinical characteristics of the sample are compiled in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0008417413481956">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0008417413481956" position="float">
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Description of Study Sample (<italic>n</italic> = 93)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0008417413481956" xlink:href="10.1177_0008417413481956-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th>
<italic>M</italic> (<italic>SD</italic>)</th>
<th>
<italic>n</italic>
</th>
<th>%</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Age</td>
<td>46 (10)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Attendance hours/week</td>
<td>13 (8)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Gender (male/female)</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Male</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>55</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Female</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>38</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Self-reported diagnosis</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Schizophrenia and other psychosis </td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>44</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mood disorders</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Anxiety, phobia, and stress disorders</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other disorders</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Civil status</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Living alone</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>81</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Cohabitant/married</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>19</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0008417413481956">
<title>Measures</title>
<p>To meet the aims of this study, the instruments listed below were used to analyze internal consistency (first aim), construct validation of the measurement process and the attribute in terms of convergent validity and discriminant validity (second aim), and floor and ceiling effects of the POES-P (third aim).</p>
<sec id="section6-0008417413481956">
<title>POES-P</title>
<p>The POES-P was based on the POES, which has demonstrated good internal consistency and content validity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0008417413481956">Bejerholm et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0008417413481956">Bejerholm &amp; Eklund, 2006a</xref>). The POES-P generates self-reported information about an individual’s productive, work-related engagement and was developed by the second author of the present study. The instrument is structured in two parts. Part 1 is a time-use diary with five columns (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0008417413481956">Figure 1</xref>). The first column is divided into 1-hr intervals. The second column captures what the individual does during those hours, and the third column captures with whom the occupations are done. The fourth captures where the occupation is done, and the fifth and last covers the way the occupation was perceived, that is, reflections and thoughts around the doing. As with the POES, the theoretical construct behind the POES-P time-use diary originates from the Person-Environment-Occupation model launched by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0008417413481956">Law et al. (1996</xref>). The contents of the four columns are intended to cover aspects of the occupational (second column), environmental (third and fourth columns), and personal domains (fifth column), which together create an understanding of an individual’s occupational performance. The POES-P also contains instructions on how to administer the instrument with the client. The relevant hours are printed in the far left column. The client is to independently complete the remaining columns. The interviewer is instructed to assist with supplementary questions as a cognitive aid for the participant to recall his or her occupations, for example, the chronological order of events listed in column 2. After completion of the time-use diary, the participant and the interviewer review it together to clarify that the data reported are correctly understood by the interviewer.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0008417413481956" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>The Profiles of Occupational Engagement in Severe Mental Illness: Productive Occupations (POES-P) is composed of two parts. Part 1 is a time diary used by a client to document his or her occupational performance. Part 2 is an eight-item questionnaire for investigating occupational engagement based on the occupational performance reported in POES-P Part 1. Each item in POES-P Part 2 is assessed by the client according to a response scale ranging from 1 (<italic>not at all</italic>) to 5 (<italic>always</italic>). The items in POES-P were adapted from the Profiles of Occupational Engagement in People with Schizophrenia (Bejerholm, Hansson, &amp; Eklund, 2006).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0008417413481956-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The second part of POES-P is an eight-item questionnaire for investigating occupational engagement based on the occupational performance reported in POES-P Part 1. Each item is assessed by the client according to a response scale ranging from 1 (<italic>not at all</italic>) to 5 (<italic>always</italic>). The items in POES-P were adapted from the original POES (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0008417413481956">Bejerholm et al., 2006</xref>), whose items were derived from theory on occupational engagement based on two qualitative studies (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0008417413481956">Bejerholm &amp; Eklund 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0008417413481956">2006b</xref>). To address the face validity of the instrument, the items were discussed with a panel of people living with psychiatric disabilities, some of whom were users and some potential users of day centres. A panel of researchers with knowledge of the theory behind occupational engagement was also consulted. Both panels agreed that the items seemed to measure occupational engagement, and the scale was appropriate for that purpose. The items are seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0008417413481956">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0008417413481956">
<title>Satisfaction with Daily Occupations (SDO)</title>
<p>The Swedish version of the SDO (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0008417413481956">Eklund, 2004</xref>) was used in this study to test the POES-P measures’ convergent validity (second aim). The SDO is a structured interview–based instrument measuring people’s activity level and how satisfied they are with their occupations. The SDO includes nine items covering four occupational areas. The participants rate whether or not they presently perform certain occupations within the areas of work, leisure, domestic tasks, and self-care and then rate their level of satisfaction on a 7-point Likert-type scale, ranging from 1 (lowest possible satisfaction) to 7 (highest possible satisfaction). The instrument generates a satisfaction score with a minimum of 9 points and a maximum of 63. The satisfaction scale has been shown to have good test-retest reliability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0008417413481956">Eklund &amp; Gunnarsson, 2007</xref>), good internal consistency when used with people with mental health issues and people with a rheumatologic disease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0008417413481956">Eklund &amp; Sandqvist, 2006</xref>), and satisfactory content validity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0008417413481956">Eklund &amp; Gunnarsson, 2008</xref>). The Cronbach’s alpha value for the sample in the present study was 0.77.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0008417413481956">
<title>Global Assessment of Functioning (GAF)</title>
<p>With the GAF, researchers or mental health care staff rate an individual’s psychosocial functioning on a scale from 0 to 100. The GAF was used to test the convergent validity of the POES-P (second aim). GAF is defined as a comprehensive scale of mental health and constitutes the fifth axis of the <italic>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</italic> (4th ed.; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0008417413481956">American Psychiatric Association, 1994</xref>) system. The GAF aims to measure the severity of mental illness by focusing on the patient’s social, psychological, and occupational functioning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0008417413481956">Tungström, Söderberg, &amp; Armelius, 2005</xref>). Psychometric research on the GAF has repeatedly demonstrated that the instrument is reliable after very little rater training (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0008417413481956">Startup, Jackson, &amp; Bendix, 2002</xref>). The GAF has been shown to give a valid assessment of psychiatric symptoms and psychosocial functioning in patients with schizophrenia, and the interrater reliability for the measure has been found to be good (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0008417413481956">Startup et al., 2002</xref>). Interrater reliability was also calculated for the present study, resulting in an intraclass correlation of 0.86.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0008417413481956">
<title>Researcher’s rating of occupational engagement</title>
<p>The researcher’s rating of occupational engagement was used to test the construct validity of the POES-P with regard to the measurement process (second aim). The participants’ occupational engagement was also assessed by a researcher, the first author of this study, using the same items and rating scale as in the POES-P. The researcher’s rating was based purely on the participant’s time-use diary (POES-P, Part 1), and no observation of the participants’ actual occupational performance was made. The Cronbach’s alpha value calculated for the researcher perspective was 0.91.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0008417413481956">
<title>Camberwell Assessment of Need (CAN)</title>
<p>From the original 22 items in the Swedish version of the CAN, four items (i.e., food, looking after the home, hygiene, and regular daily activities) were selected to assess unmet “activity needs.” Each need is rated according to three alternatives—0 (no problems), 1 (no problem because of ongoing treatment or moderate problem), and 2 (severe problems)—and the person’s problem level during the past month is in focus. A sum score, based on all four activity needs, was calculated. The instrument has been shown to have good interrater agreement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0008417413481956">Hansson, Björkman, &amp; Svensson, 1995</xref>) and to be generally reliable over time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0008417413481956">Arvidsson, 2003</xref>). A Cronbach’s alpha was calculated, showing a value of 0.73 in the present sample.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0008417413481956">
<title>Procedure</title>
<p>When possible, the participants filled in the self-administered instruments, such as the POES-P, independently; however, some found it difficult to understand or asked for help filling in the questionnaires. Those participants were provided with assistance from the interviewers as needed. The interviewers were in such cases careful to employ consistent routines in the data collection and with the help they provided. Directly after the questionnaire session, the interviewer rated the participant according to the GAF.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0008417413481956">
<title>Data Analysis</title>
<p>The data were analysed using the software SPSS Version 18.</p>
<sec id="section13-0008417413481956">
<title>Internal consistency</title>
<p>To investigate internal consistency, Cronbach’s alpha was computed for the POES-P Part 2. The corrected item-total correlations (CITCs) were calculated as well, and a lower limit of &gt; 0.20 was set as a satisfactory association between an item and the total scale, in line with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0008417413481956">Streiner and Norman (2008</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0008417413481956">
<title>Construct validation</title>
<p>The data were found not to be normally distributed; therefore nonparametric statistics were used to test relationships between instruments. Convergent and discriminant validity were investigated by using the Spearman correlation test to calculate the relationship between the total score of POES-P Part 2 and the other instruments, namely, the Satisfaction scale generated from the SDO, the GAF, the researcher’s diary-based rating, and the CAN.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0008417413481956">
<title>Ceiling and floor effects</title>
<p>Ceiling and floor effects of the POES-P Part 2 were investigated by employing descriptive statistics and exploring the frequency distribution at the item level.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0008417413481956">
<title>Findings</title>
<sec id="section17-0008417413481956">
<title>Internal Consistency</title>
<p>The Cronbach’s alpha value for the POES-P was 0.85, which indicates good internal consistency. The CITC values varied between 0.55 and 0.65, thus well above the lower limit of 0.20 set as acceptable. Deletion of single items did not in any case result in a better alpha value.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0008417413481956">
<title>Construct Validation</title>
<p>The correlations between the POES-P and the other instruments are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0008417413481956">Table 2</xref>, which also indicates the mean values on the instruments used. A moderate correlation was found in the convergent validation for the SDO scale, but the relationship to the GAF had a weak correlation. When assessing convergent validity based on differences in the measurement process, a moderate correlation was found between the POES-P and the interviewer rating of occupational engagement. The association between the POES-P and the CAN, indicating discriminant validity, was nonsignificant.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0008417413481956" position="float">
<label>Table 2</label>
<caption>
<p>Correlations Between Sum Score of POES-P and Instruments Used in Construct Validation</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0008417413481956" xlink:href="10.1177_0008417413481956-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Instrument</th>
<th>
<italic>M</italic>
</th>
<th>
<italic>SD</italic>
</th>
<th>
<italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub>
</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Convergent validity: Focus on the attribute</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Satisfaction With Daily Occupations</td>
<td>47.9</td>
<td>8.75</td>
<td>0.43*</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Global Assessment of Functioning</td>
<td>57.9</td>
<td>6.69</td>
<td>0.22**</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Convergent validity: Focus on the measurement process</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Researcher rating of occupational engagement</td>
<td>28.7</td>
<td>4.72</td>
<td>0.37**</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Discriminant validity</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Camberwell Assessment of Need</td>
<td>1.54</td>
<td>0.89</td>
<td>–0.15</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0008417413481956">
<p>
<italic>Note. </italic>POES-P = Profiles of Occupational Engagement in Severe Mental Illness–Productive Occupations (<italic>M</italic> = 32.5;<italic> SD</italic> = 5.49); <italic>r</italic>
<sub>s</sub> = Spearman’s rank order correlation; <italic>SD</italic> = standard deviation.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0008417413481956">
<p>*<italic>p</italic> = .01 (two tailed). **<italic>p</italic> = .05 (two tailed).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0008417413481956">
<title>Floor and Ceiling Effects</title>
<p>The frequency distribution showed a ceiling effect on all items (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0008417413481956">Table 3</xref>), with a majority of the responses allocated to the alternatives <italic>always</italic> or <italic>usually</italic>. These response categories represented together 62% to 81% of the answers. The percentages of respondents using the lowest rating were 1% to 3.3%. However, the ceiling effect was not so evident on the scale level, as indicated by a mean of 32.5 on a scale where the maximum score was 40 and 13% were scoring at the maximum level.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0008417413481956" position="float">
<label>Table 3</label>
<caption>
<p>Response Distribution of Respondents (<italic>n</italic> = 90)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0008417413481956" xlink:href="10.1177_0008417413481956-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th rowspan="2">Item no.</th>
<th colspan="5">Score</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>1</th>
<th>2</th>
<th>3</th>
<th>4</th>
<th>5</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>1 (1.1)</td>
<td>4 (4.4)</td>
<td>13 (14.4)</td>
<td>28 (31.1)</td>
<td>44 (48.9) </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>1 (1.1)</td>
<td>5 (5.6)</td>
<td>14 (15.6)</td>
<td>32 (35.6)</td>
<td>38 (42.2) </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>3 (3.3)</td>
<td>5 (5.6)</td>
<td>16 (17.8)</td>
<td>31 (34.4)</td>
<td>35 (38.9) </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>2 (2.2)</td>
<td>6 (6.7)</td>
<td>14 (15.6)</td>
<td>30 (33.3)</td>
<td>38 (42.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>0 (0.0)</td>
<td>5 (5.6)</td>
<td>13 (14.6)</td>
<td>34 (38.2) </td>
<td>37 (41.6) </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>1 (1.1)</td>
<td>7 (7.8)</td>
<td>26 (28.9)</td>
<td>26 (28.9)</td>
<td>30 (33.3) </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7</td>
<td>1 (1.1)</td>
<td>9 (10.0)</td>
<td>16 (17.8)</td>
<td>27 (30.0)</td>
<td>37 (41.1) </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>3 (3.3)</td>
<td>2 (2.2)</td>
<td>12 (13.3)</td>
<td>31 (34.4)</td>
<td>42 (46.7) </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-0008417413481956">
<p>
<italic>Note</italic>. Data are number of responses for each score with percentages in parentheses.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0008417413481956">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The aims of the study were to examine the psychometric properties in terms of internal consistency, initial construct validation, and floor and ceiling effects of the POES-P. The internal consistency was considered satisfactory. Cronbach’s alpha analysis indicated that each POES-P item correlated well with the entire scale, and the alpha value was satisfactorily above 0.80 and very close to 0.90. According to Steiner and Norman (2008), alpha up to 0.90 is considered to be good. A value exceeding 0.90 may indicate that the items overlap to a considerable extent, forming a scale that is too homogeneous, but the value obtained for the POES-P was seen as optimal. When addressing the second aim, regarding construct validity, we verified the first hypothesis. The relationship between the POES-P and the SDO showed to be moderate, indicating that the two constructs partly overlapped. The relationship between the POES-P and psychosocial functioning (GAF) was, however, lower than hypothesized. The hypothesis of a moderate relationship was based on prior research on the POES (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0008417413481956">Bejerholm &amp; Eklund, 2006a</xref>). The POES-P, in contrast to the POES, may have correlated only weakly with the GAF because the POES-P rating is concerned only with the productive hours, whereas the POES considers occupations during the entire day. Another reason for the stronger associations between the POES and the GAF (alpha = 0.73) shown in the study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0008417413481956">Bejerholm and Eklund (2006a</xref>) may be that those instruments are both assessed by professionals. The findings from estimating the convergent validity of the POES-P thus suggested that self-assessed engagement in productive, work-like occupations was largely a construct in its own right but overlapped as expected with SDO.</p>
<p>With respect to convergent validity, in terms of differences in the measurement process, the result indicated that the scale scores were determined not only by the attribute, occupational engagement, but also by the way it is measured. The moderate correlation between the POES-P and the researcher’s rating indicated, as hypothesized, that occupational engagement viewed from a different person’s perspective represented different aspects of the phenomenon under study. As proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0008417413481956">Wefald and Downey (2009</xref>), self-rated engagement includes an affective component, less reflected in the researcher’s rating, which may be an explanation of the merely moderate relationship. The moderate agreement may, however, suggest that the time-use diary enhances outsider knowledge of the clients’ actual perceived occupational performance by making some of the affective content of occupational engagement visible.</p>
<p>As hypothesized, a low correlation was found between unmet needs and occupational engagement, and the relationship was not statistically significant. The POES-P thus showed discriminant validity in relation to unmet activity need as measured in the CAN, which says something about the uniqueness of the POES-P.</p>
<p>Findings related to the third aim, addressing floor and ceiling effects, showed that the POES-P had a ceiling effect on the item level that leaves little room for improvements from one occasion to another, and the variation in the data becomes limited. Although the ceiling effect on the scale level was less pronounced, this effect reduces the utility of the instrument and further indicates a need to look into the instrument’s construct and design. The clients’ high ratings of engagement in productive occupations may reflect that these occupations were perceived as being meaningful and perhaps successfully matched their abilities and needs. It may also, however, indicate that the items used were too easy to endorse. Adding more difficult items may affect the ceiling effect. A recent study found that participants in different day centre orientations were capable of doing a variety and range of occupations and characterized these occupations as complex and combined (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0008417413481956">Tjörnstrand et al., 2011</xref>). Results from another study showed that engaging occupations in day centres inferred different degrees of responsibility (Tjörnstrand et al., 2013). If one were to add new items to the POES-P, both complexity and responsibility may be worthy of consideration. Moreover, Pierce’s (2001) definition of productivity, underscoring its goal-focused dimension, indicates that goal direction may be a further aspect to take into account.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-0008417413481956">
<title>Implications for Research and Practice</title>
<p>Data collected with the POES-P could be potentially useful in research in areas such as day centres for people living with mental health issues or other programs focused on productivity or occupations analogous to work. Moreover, when collecting data for research purposes, one could find that the sum score from the POES-P Part 2 may, if the ceiling effect can be reduced, be useful when estimating change. However, the instrument’s suitability for assessing change would need to be further explored by ensuring its test-retest reliability and its ability to detect change. Moreover, the POES-P Part 1, in its current form, has been shown useful for use in qualitative research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0008417413481956">Tjörnstrand et al., 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Day centres, workplaces, and occupational therapy services with a focus on productive occupations are possible arenas where the POES-P may be useful in clinical practice to monitor individuals’ occupational engagement within a program. Instruments such as the POES-P can bring forward the client’s perspective, which may then be used to visualize individually meaningful occupations and to match occupations to the individual’s needs. The POES-P may thereby be used to enhance the support of the clients’ engagement in productive occupations. Moreover, as the time-use diary within the instrument is recommended to be completed in collaboration with an occupational therapist, the assessment enables joint decision making in the rehabilitation and recovery process ahead, which is especially important since a client perspective is a highly relevant focus in the recovery process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0008417413481956">Merryman &amp; Riegel, 2007</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-0008417413481956">
<title>Study Limitations</title>
<p>Some methodological considerations need to be discussed. The use of only four items in the CAN may be seen as a limitation, as the psychometric qualities regarding the CAN refer to all 22 items. However, all CAN items do not form a homogenous scale, and it has been proposed that researchers may benefit from creating subscales of related items (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0008417413481956">Wennström, 2008</xref>). This proposition renders support to the procedure used in the present study, where the selected items were chosen on the basis of their reference to occupation, and a test of the four items’ reliability showed that they possessed satisfactory internal consistency.</p>
<p>Another consideration worthy of mentioning is that the researcher who rated the participants’ occupational engagement on the basis of the diaries had carried out one third of the interviews. Two types of analysis were therefore made to see whether the ratings based on the interviews differed compared to the ratings of the diaries from the group aided by another researcher. First, visual inspection of the ratings showed that the distribution across the response categories was very similar in both groups. Second, a Mann-Whitney U-test indicated that the POES-P ratings did not differ between the groups (<italic>p</italic> = 0.28). Furthermore, the researchers’ prior knowledge of engagement as a phenomenon may influence the ratings. In the present study, all three interviewers had similar backgrounds, which may have hidden such a potential methodological weakness. This limitation would require further consideration of the knowledge base needed for the POES-P assessors if the POES-P were to be developed into an assessment using both client and staff perspectives of engagement.</p>
<p>Another weakness of the study is that the new tool, the researcher’s rating of occupational engagement, had not been psychometrically tested. However, as discussed in the instrument description above, an initial test of its reliability indicated satisfactory internal consistency, which, when viewed together with the correlations that were obtained, supports the hypotheses, rendering trustworthiness to the findings.</p>
<p>Consideration was given to include the POES within the study design, but that was seen as too time-consuming for the present study. Considering the results from this study and that the POES-P and the POES reflect perspectives that differ regarding both time and person, the association between the two instruments could be expected to be in line with those found for the GAF. That, however, remains a speculation.</p>
<p>The ceiling effect may be further discussed in light of a possible social desirability bias, meaning the participants may have answered in a manner that would be considered favourable by others. Measures such as ensuring the participants’ confidentiality and using interviewers who were not connected to the day centre were employed to counteract social desirability, as this is a common problem with self-report instruments. This study offers initial psychometric testing of the POES-P, indicating that it reflects a construct in its own right when used in day centres in Sweden.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-0008417413481956">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The psychometric properties of the POES-P reported in this study suggest that the internal consistency was satisfactory, a logical pattern of relationships between the POES-P and other instruments was found, and the hypotheses were largely confirmed. More specifically, convergent validity was indicated, suggesting that occupational engagement is more closely related to the attribute of occupational satisfaction than to psychosocial functioning. The analysis of discriminant validity showed that the construct reflected in the POES-P was unrelated to unmet activity needs. Testing convergent validity with regard to the measuring process emphasized that occupational engagement is multifaceted in the sense that it can be viewed from different perspectives and that the different estimates of a client’s engagement vary accordingly. The pattern of associations with other instruments was thus logical and indicated that self-assessed occupational engagement as measured by the POES-P was mainly a construct in its own right. Although the indicated ceiling effect suggests that additional items, those items less likely to be endorsed, should be included in future versions of the POES-P, the results indicate that it is a promising instrument for assessing occupational engagement when used in a day centre context for people living with mental health issues. The POES-P requires further development and testing in different contexts and populations in future studies, for example, with individuals engaged in supportive employment. Additional psychometric properties, such as test-retest reliability, predictive validity, and further construct validation, also need to be evaluated.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section24-0008417413481956">
<title>Key Messages</title>
<p>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>The Profiles of Occupational Engagement in People with Severe Mental Illness: Productive Occupations (POES-P) can be a valuable measure in settings offering occupations analogous to work.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Clinically, the POES-P could serve as a basis for discussion, planning, and evaluation with clients engaged in productive occupations.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>By employing the POES-P, occupational therapists can enhance their knowledge of the individuals’ perspective of occupational engagement and thereby better assist clients on their journey toward recovery.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>The authors would like to kindly acknowledge the participation from day centre staff and visitors and to thank the occupational therapists who collected the data.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn1-0008417413481956">
<p>Funding: This study was financially supported by the Swedish Board of Health and Welfare.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Altman</surname>
<given-names>D. G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>Practical statistics for medical research</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Chapman and Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">American Psychiatric Association</collab>. (<year>1994</year>). <source>Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders</source> (<edition>4th ed</edition>.). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Arvidsson</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Test-retest reliability of the Camberwell Assessment of Need (CAN)</article-title>. <source>Nordic Journal of Psychiatry</source>, <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>279</fpage>–<lpage>283</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bejerholm</surname>
<given-names>U.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eklund</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Time use and occupational performance among persons with schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Occupational Therapy in Mental Health</source>, <volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1300/J004v20n01_02</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bejerholm</surname>
<given-names>U.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eklund</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006a</year>). <article-title>Construct validity of a newly developed instrument: Profile of Occupational Engagement in people with Schizophrenia, POES</article-title>. <source>Nordic Journal of Psychiatry</source>, <volume>60</volume>, <fpage>200</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1080/08039480600636239</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bejerholm</surname>
<given-names>U.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eklund</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006b</year>). <article-title>Engagement in occupations among men and women with schizophrenia</article-title>. <source>Occupational Therapy International</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>100</fpage>–<lpage>121</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1002/oti.210</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bejerholm</surname>
<given-names>U.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eklund</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Occupational engagement in persons with schizophrenia: Relationships to self-related variables, psychopathology, and quality of life</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Occupational Therapy</source>, <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.5014/ajot.61.1.21</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bejerholm</surname>
<given-names>U.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hansson</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eklund</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Profiles of Occupational Engagement in people with Schizophrenia (POES): The development of a new instrument based on time-use diaries</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Occupational Therapy</source>, <volume>69</volume>, <fpage>58</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Catty</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Burns</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Mental health day centres: Their clients and role</article-title>. <source>Psychiatric Bulletin</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>61</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Catty</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goddard</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Burns</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Social services and health services day care in mental health: The social networks and care needs of their users</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Social Psychiatry</source>, <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1177/0020764005053267</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>A power primer</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>112</volume>, <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>159</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cramer</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Howitt</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>The Sage dictionary of statistics: A practical resource for students in the social sciences</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Edgelow</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Krupa</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Randomized controlled pilot study of an occupational time-use intervention for people with serious mental illness</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Occupational Therapy</source>, <volume>65</volume>, <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>276</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.5014/ajot.2011.001313</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eklund</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Satisfaction with Daily Occupations: A tool for client evaluation in mental health care</article-title>. <source>Scandinavian Journal of Occupational Therapy</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>136</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1080/11038120410020700</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eklund</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gunnarsson</surname>
<given-names>A. B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Satisfaction with Daily Occupations: Construct validity and test-retest reliability of a screening tool for people with mental disorders</article-title>. <source>Australian Occupational Therapy Journal</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1111/j.1440-1630.2006.00586.x</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eklund</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gunnarsson</surname>
<given-names>A. B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Content validity, clinical utility, sensitivity to change and discriminant ability of the Swedish Satisfaction with Daily Occupations (SDO) instrument: A screening tool for people with mental disorders</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Occupational Therapy</source>, <volume>71</volume>, <fpage>487</fpage>–<lpage>495</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eklund</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hansson</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bejerholm</surname>
<given-names>U.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Relationships between satisfaction with occupational factors and health-related variables in schizophrenia outpatients</article-title>. <source>Social Psychiatry and Psychiatric Epidemiology</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.1007/s001270050293</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eklund</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sandqvist</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Psychometric properties of the Satisfaction with Daily Occupations (SDO) instrument and the Manchester Short Assessment of Quality of Life (MANSA) in women with scleroderma and without known illness</article-title>. <source>Scandinavian Journal of Occupational Therapy</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fuller</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The effectiveness of occupational performance outcome measures within mental health practice</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Occupational Therapy</source>, <volume>74</volume>, <fpage>399</fpage>–<lpage>405</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.4276/030802211X13125646371004</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grady</surname>
<given-names>K. E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <source>Self-report and other report: Research in health care settings</source>. <publisher-loc>Newbury Park, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hansson</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Björkman</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Svensson</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>The assessment of needs in psychiatric patients: Interrater reliability of the Swedish version of the Camberwell Assessment of Needs instrument and results from a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavia</source>, <volume>92</volume>, <fpage>285</fpage>–<lpage>293</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jonsson</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Josephsson</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kielhofner</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Narratives and experience in an occupational transition: A longitudinal study of the retirement process</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Occupational Therapy</source>, <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>424</fpage>–<lpage>432</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.5014/ajot.55.4.424</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Krupa</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Invited commentary: The occupational performance process model in one community mental health setting</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Occupational Therapy</source>, <volume>77</volume>, <fpage>80</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.2182/cjot.2010.77.2.3</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Krupa</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McLean</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eastabrook</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bonham</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Baksh</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Daily time use as a measure of community adjustment for persons served by assertive community treatment teams</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Occupational Therapy</source>, <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>558</fpage>–<lpage>565</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.5014/ajot.57.5.558</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Law</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cooper</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Strong</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stewart</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rigby</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Letts</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>The Person-Environment-Occupation model: A transactive approach to occupational performance</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Occupational Therapy</source>, <volume>63</volume>, <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Merryman</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Riegel</surname>
<given-names>S. K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The recovery process and people with serious mental illness living in the community</article-title>. <source>Occupational Therapy in Mental Health</source>, <volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1300/J004v23n02_03</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">National Board of Health and Welfare</collab>. (<year>2011</year>). <source>Nationella riktlinjer för psykosociala insatser vid schizofreni eller schizofreniliknande tillstånd 2011: Stöd för styrning och ledning</source> <comment>[National guidelines for psychosocial interventions for people with schizophrenia or related disorders, 2011: Support for control and management. Final report.]. Stockholm, Sweden: Socialstyrelsen</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pierce</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Occupation by design: Dimensions, therapeutic power, and creative process</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Occupational Therapy</source>, <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>249</fpage>–<lpage>259</lpage>. <comment>doi: 10.5014/ajot.55.3.249</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Polatajko</surname>
<given-names>H. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Davis</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stewart</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cantin</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Amoroso</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Purdie</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zimmerman</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Specifying the domain of concern: Occupation as core</article-title>. In E. A. Townsend &amp; H. J. Polatajko, <source>Enabling occupation II: Advancing an occupational therapy vision for health, well-being, and justice through occupation</source> (pp. <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Ottawa, ON</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CAOT Publications ACE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Startup</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jackson</surname>
<given-names>M. C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bendix</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The concurrent validity of the Global Assessment of Functioning (GAF)</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Clinical Psychology</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>422</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Streiner</surname>
<given-names>D. L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Norman</surname>
<given-names>G. R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Health measurement scales a practical guide to their development and use</source> (<edition>4th ed</edition>.). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Terwee</surname>
<given-names>C. B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bot</surname>
<given-names>S. D. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>de Boer</surname>
<given-names>M. R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>van der Windt</surname>
<given-names>D. A. W. M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Knol</surname>
<given-names>D. L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dekker</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names> </name>
<name>
<surname>de Vet</surname>
<given-names>H. C. W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Quality criteria were proposed for measurement properties of health status questionnaires</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Epidemiology</source>, <volume>60</volume>, <fpage>34</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1016/j.jclinepi.2006.03.012</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tjörnstrand</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bejerholm</surname>
<given-names>U.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eklund</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Participation in day centres for people with psychiatric disabilities: Characteristics of the occupations</article-title>. <source>Scandinavian Journal of Occupational Therapy</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>243</fpage>–<lpage>253</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.3109/11038128.2011.583938</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tjörnstrand</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bejerholm</surname>
<given-names>U.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Eklund</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Participation in day centres for people with psychiatric disabilities: A focus on occupational engagement</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Occupational Therapy, 76, </source>144–150.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tungström</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Söderberg</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Armelius</surname>
<given-names>B.-Å.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Relationship between the Global Assessment of Functioning and other <italic>DSM</italic> axes in routine clinical work</article-title>. <source>Psychiatric Bulletin</source>, <volume>56</volume>, <fpage>439</fpage>–<lpage>443</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wefald</surname>
<given-names>A. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Downey</surname>
<given-names>R. G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Construct dimensionality of engagement and its relation with satisfaction</article-title>. <source>Journal of Psychology</source>, <volume>143</volume>, <fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>111</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.3200/JRLP.143.1.91-112</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0008417413481956">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wennström</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>The Camberwell Assessment of Need as an outcome measure in community mental health care</source> (<comment>Doctoral dissertation</comment>). <publisher-name>Acta Universitatis Upsaliensis</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Uppsala, Sweden</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>