<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EHQ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spehq</journal-id>
<journal-title>European History Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0265-6914</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7110</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0265691411428783y</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0265691411428783y</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Ole Peter Grell, Andrew Cunningham and Jon Arrizabalaga, eds,<italic> Centres of Medical Excellence? Medical Travel and Education in Europe, 1500–1789</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lindemann</surname><given-names>Mary</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0265691411428783y">University of Miami</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>42</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>156</fpage>
<lpage>158</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0265691411428783y"><title>Ole Peter Grell, Andrew Cunningham and Jon Arrizabalaga, eds,<italic> Centres of Medical Excellence? Medical Travel and Education in Europe, 1500–1789</italic>, Ashgate: Farnham, 2010; 335 pp. 29 illus. and tables; 9780754666998, £70.00 (hbk)</title>
<p>A question mark can mean a lot, especially in a title where it often signals something new. The question mark in the first half of this book’s title serves just that function. Many (if not all) contributors problematize the concept of excellence in considering what constitutes a ‘centre of excellence’ and how early modern medical travellers identified them. Different perspectives are required to answer these questions because, as Toby Gelfand notes, such queries ‘resist unqualified generalisations’ (221).</p>
<p><italic>Centres of Medical Excellence</italic> thus presents a series of fresh views on a topic that has long held a prominent, even venerated, place in medical historiography: medical education. Certainly, there is no lack of studies on the development of medical education in early modern Europe. Much of that work, however, has focused on universities where historians have traditionally located ‘medical innovation’. Older medical historiography tended to regard particular localities as way stations on the road to the holy grail of modern medicine. While some essays continue to track that developmental pattern in speaking of, for instance, significant shifts in ‘medical science’ in the sixteenth century (51) or the lack of a ‘properly functioning medical faculty’ at most universities, the majority seek to complicate a simple story of medical progress and brachiate the neat migratory path of excellence from one institution to another. If, overall, the focus remains fixed on universities, the contributors acknowledge that not only universities could be centres of excellence; private medical teaching in major cities also assumed a critical role.</p>
<p>The collection directly addresses the overlap between the medical journey – the student’s <italic>peregrinatio medica</italic> – and medical education. Important here is not merely a matter of travelling from one university to another (driven or attracted by a variety of forces including the reputation of particular professors, pre-existing circles of friends and relatives, religious confession, the attractiveness of the location, and cost), but also a linked transfer of knowledge. These are provocative ideas, but the exact relationship between travel and knowledge requires somewhat better framing. The book lacks an introduction (and, for that matter, a conclusion) to guide the reader. As it is, the three opening articles stand in lieu of an introduction. Laurence Brockliss fearlessly grasps the methodological nettle; he considers how one can measure excellence or determine what constitutes a ‘centre’. His article is more forthright than some in considering the comparative dimensions and chronological evolution by, for example, delineating a shift by the eighteenth century from a ‘handful of centres… characterized by their mix of provincialism and cosmopolitanism’ to a greater ‘openness to a much broader medical constituency’ (45).</p>
<p>Part Two considers the <italic>peregrinatio medica</italic> in several geographic regions. The essays in this section follow two paths: either they examine individuals who travelled (such as the ‘Bavarian’ Pieter van Foreest or the Danes Henrik Fuiren and Hans Andersen Skovgaard) or survey groups of students. These several articles carefully dissect students’ motives and ambitions. Additionally, however, the authors illustrate how medical knowledge, too, travelled in a process that brought about a ‘direct conciliation of empiricism and book learning’ producing the ‘learned empiricism’ of the sixteenth century (168).</p>
<p>Part Three also questions a number of accepted views. Gelfand’s familiar work on Paris highlights the role surgeons and surgical instruction played, for instance. Or, to take another example, Rina Knoeff’s careful study of Boerhaave’s career at Leiden successfully shifts the ‘grounds for Boerhaave’s reputation’ while not denying it. Contrary to general belief, ‘practical medicine and bedside teaching’ were not Boerhaave’s ‘strong points’. Embedded in his method was indeed something new: he taught his students to be ‘independent doctors’ who did not work by merely ‘blindly following the ideas of others’ (285).</p>
<p>In sum, <italic>Centres of Excellence</italic> more successfully raises questions than advances generalizations or crafts overarching historical interpretations. Although the absence of an introduction and a conclusion leaves the reader to pull together the analytical parts, the collection presents nonetheless a wealth of material as well as penetrating insights into several aspects of medical history. While the familiar examples of Padua, Paris, London, and Edinburgh are well represented, so, too, are the experiences in Madrid, in Portugal, in the Netherlands, in the Germanies, and in Denmark. Medical education remains central, but the essays also address broader issues of what medical knowledge was, how people perceived it, how empiricism and book learning interacted, and so on. There are a few glitches, where, for instance, references direct the reader to the wrong pages in the text or footnotes are simply missing, all of which bespeak a rather cavalier editing process on the part of the press. But these are quibbles. <italic>Centres of Excellence’s</italic> real contribution is to revitalize and reorient the existing historiography on medical education by directing more attention to students and by explicating the dynamically interactive quality of learning in the early modern world.</p>
<p><bold>Mary Lindemann</bold>, <italic>University of Miami</italic></p>
</sec>
</body>
</article>