<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRW</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcrw</journal-id>
<journal-title>Community College Review</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0091-5521</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1940-2325</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0091552112458313</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0091552112458313</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Insider’s Guide to Community College Administration</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>Duane E.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0091552112458313">Arkansas State University–Newport, Newport, AR, USA</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>40</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>364</fpage>
<lpage>365</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Giles</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Insider’s Guide to Community College Administration</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Community College Press</publisher-name>. <page-count count="99"/> pp. <price>$38.00</price> (paperback). ISBN: <isbn>0871173751</isbn>.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">North Carolina State University</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In their book, <italic>The Insider’s Guide to Community College Administration</italic>, Jensen and Giles (2006) examine the process of seeking an administrative position at a community college. Although this publication has an academic tone at times, it usually reads like a conversation between a seasoned mentor and a promising junior mentee. The book offers readers a series of case studies that provide literary snapshots of different issues and problems encountered in obtaining and then holding an administrative position. The book also provides a rich and balanced picture of higher education administration and explains why a person must be aware of the pitfalls that surround the transition into leadership positions.</p>
<p>The content of each chapter is carefully presented to lay the groundwork for understanding the work that is critical for success at each level of administration and the challenges of this work. In spite of the challenges, Jensen and Giles leave no doubt in the reader’s mind that administrative work in a community college is very rewarding and satisfying. The Insider’s Guide to Community College Administration provides a set of detailed challenges that administrators have faced in their careers, but the book also describes the successful pathways that administrators have traveled, providing future administrators with examples and encouragement. The examples are presented by Jensen and Giles as opportunities for teaching, learning, and engaging rather than as cookie-cutter methods for application in every scenario.</p>
<p>In the first chapter, Jensen and Giles examine the choice of transitioning into an administrative position and the kind of plan needed to make the move up the educational management ladder. Subsequent examples provide a glimpse into the pitfalls and successes that may lie ahead for an administrator. Additionally in chapter 1, Jensen and Giles describe the characteristics necessary for the successful chief executive officer, and they explain how those characteristics are different for leaders at single-campus colleges and multicollege districts.</p>
<p>In chapters 2 and 3, Jensen and Giles offer insights into the daily lives of the administrator. These chapters are especially important to the individual considering a move into an administrative position. The authors make a good case for the claim that the division dean is the classic middle-management position at a community college. Jensen and Giles explain that the division dean oversees the important task of scheduling courses, and the dean must be tough enough to build a schedule that enables the institution to fulfill its mission of educating students. But, of course, the schedule also has important implications for the budget. Therefore, the schedule is critical to a successful college because it must provide students with courses they need, acknowledge the needs of the faculty, and accomplish all of this while aligning with the college’s budget priorities.</p>
<p>The remaining chapters (chapters 4 and 5) deal with presidential issues and the characteristics of good trustees. Jensen and Giles examine the issues a president must resolve in selecting members of a senior leadership team, and they discuss why a chief executive officer (CEO) must trust and believe in the people under his or her supervision. This means, of course, that the CEO must evaluate each of these people and make the decision about whether they should be retained or replaced. Considering the president’s interactions with the board, the authors remind readers about the importance of this relationship, and they then highlight some of the missteps that can cause problems down the road.</p>
<p>The greatest asset of this book is the authors’ success in informing and motivating the reader by giving real-life examples of tangible challenges and some successful solutions as well as some not-so-successful ones. One shortcoming of this book is the limited amount of information presented concerning the division dean. For most CEOs it is imperative to develop the next generation of administrators and help those motivated to become leaders. For many institutions, these potential leaders are positioned primarily at the division dean level.</p>
<p>The Insider’s Guide to Community College Administration would be useful to graduate students, especially faculty and professional staff members in community colleges, who want to investigate the possibility of moving up the management ladder at a community college. This book points out, in a very matter-of-fact way, the pitfalls and promises in choosing to become an administrator at the American community college.</p>
</body>
<back>
<bio>
<title>Bio</title>
<p><bold>Duane E. Doyle</bold> is an assistant professor of mathematics at Arkansas State University, Newport, AR.</p>
</bio>
</back>
</article>