<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CDP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcdp</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Curr Dir Psychol Sci</journal-id>
<journal-title>Current Directions in Psychological Science</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0963-7214</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1467-8721</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0963721411422055</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0963721411422055</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Risky Decisions</article-title>
<subtitle>Active Risk Management</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>Oswald</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0963721411422055">University of Fribourg</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0963721411422055">Oswald Huber, Department of Psychology, University of Fribourg, Route de Faucigny 2, CH-1701 Fribourg, Switzerland E-mail: <email>oswald.huber@unifr.ch</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>21</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>26</fpage>
<lpage>30</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© Association for Psychological Science 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Association for Psychological Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Decision behavior in realistic risky scenarios is quite different from that in gambles: Decision makers in the former are less interested in probability information than they are in the latter. Instead, they often attempt to actively manipulate the risk in an otherwise attractive alternative using a risk-defusing operator (RDO). An RDO is an action intended by the decision maker to be performed <italic>in addition</italic> to the risky but otherwise attractive alternative, and it is expected to decrease the risk (e.g., vaccination, insurance). The search for an RDO and the incorporation of a detected RDO into the alternative cannot be modeled with classical decision theories or heuristics. In this article I present risk-management-decision theory, which describes the decision process with and without RDOs, and give an overview about experimental research with RDOs. I discuss the consequences of the RDO concept for theories of decision behavior.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>decision making</kwd>
<kwd>risky decisions</kwd>
<kwd>risk defusing</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Rose Flaherty is a manager in a small firm producing water-purification installations. She has planned to travel to the capital of Burtengo tomorrow in order to conclude a contract with the local administration, vitally important for her firm. Now she learns that unexpectedly a dangerous infectious disease rages in Burtengo. Thus, Flaherty is faced with a <italic>risky decision</italic>. She has (at least) two alternative actions: To travel to Burtengo or to postpone the meeting. Each alternative leads to specific outcomes (consequences). For example, traveling to Burtengo has a desirable (positive) outcome: concluding the contract. However, it <italic>may</italic> result in an undesirable (negative) outcome: suffering from the dangerous disease. This negative outcome is uncertain. The existence of at least one uncertain (negative) outcome in at least one of the alternatives is a defining characteristic of risky decisions. When deciding, people assign subjective values to outcomes. They may also allocate degrees of uncertainty or probabilities to events and outcomes.</p>
<p>Psychological decision theory investigates risky decision making experimentally with the help of the gambling (lottery) paradigm: A decision maker has to choose between (at least) two gambles as alternatives. A gamble consists of a set of outcomes (gains, losses) and their probabilities, and all the outcomes and probabilities are known to the decision maker. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0963721411422055">Figure 1</xref> presents typical examples. In such experiments, the central factors determining decision behavior are the subjective values (utilities) of the outcomes and—often—their subjective probability. The most prominent decision theories founded on the gambling paradigm are subjectively expected utility theory (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0963721411422055">Fig. 1</xref>) and its descendants (e.g., prospect theory; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0963721411422055">Kahneman &amp; Tversky, 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0963721411422055">Baron, 2008</xref>, gives an overview). However, decision behavior is often explained better by heuristics than by such theories. Heuristics are strategies reducing the cognitive effort necessary to make a decision. The <italic>maximin</italic> heuristic (the decision maker first identifies for each alternative the worst outcome and then chooses the alternative with the <italic>relatively best</italic> worst outcome) is an example.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0963721411422055" position="float">
<label>Fig. 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Gambling paradigm. A decision maker has to choose between (at least) two gambles as alternatives. A gamble consists of a set of outcomes (gains, losses) and their probabilities, and all the outcomes and probabilities are known to the decision maker. In such experiments, the central factors determining decision behavior are the subjective values (utilities) of the outcomes and often their subjective probability. The gambling paradigm assumes that in <italic>all</italic> risky decision situations, decision makers represent the alternatives as gambles and that no other factors than the outcomes and their probabilities influence the decision.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0963721411422055-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The predominant use of the gambling paradigm recently has been challenged, however, by a number of experiments of our research group and of others (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0963721411422055">Bär &amp; Huber, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0963721411422055">Huber &amp; Huber, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0963721411422055">Huber, Huber, &amp; Bär, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0963721411422055">Tyszka &amp; Zaleśkiewicz, 2006</xref>; and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0963721411422055">Wilke, Haug, &amp; Funke, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0963721411422055">Huber, 2007</xref>, reviews the earlier results). In these experiments, realistic scenarios are presented instead of gambles, and the alternatives are not prestructured like a gamble by the experimenter. These experiments demonstrate that results from research within the gambling paradigm cannot be generalized to all decision tasks. Decision behavior in realistic scenarios differs in two respects from behavior in choices between gambles: (a) Most often, decision makers are content to know whether an outcome is possible or will occur with certainty—they are not actively interested in more precise probabilities—and (b) decision makers often search for an additional action, or risk-defusing operator (RDO), which eliminates the risk.</p>
<p>An RDO is an action anticipated by the decision maker to be performed <italic>in addition</italic> to an existing alternative and is expected to eliminate or decrease the risk. For example, the manager in the introductory example most likely will actively inquire whether a vaccination exists or whether an infection can be prevented (e.g., by killing the mosquitoes that carry the disease). These additional actions are RDOs. Another example quite common in everyday risky situations is buying insurance. If an acceptable RDO is detected with a promising alternative, that alternative is usually chosen. Different types of RDOs can be distinguished (cf., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0963721411422055">Huber, 2007</xref>): for example, those <italic>preventing</italic> a negative outcome (e.g., vaccination) or others <italic>compensating</italic> for a negative outcome (e.g., insurance).</p>
<p>In those experiments investigating the spontaneous use of probabilities or RDOs, most often the method of active information search has been employed: Participants first are presented a short description of the alternatives, and then they can pose questions to the experimenter in order to obtain more information. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0963721411422055">Huber, Huber, and Schulte-Mecklenbeck (2011)</xref> describe the method in detail and discuss its advantages and limitations. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0963721411422055">Shiloh, Gerad, and Goldman (2006)</xref> applied the method in real-life genetic-counseling decisions and confirmed the general results. The findings obtained with the active- information-search method are corroborated by thinking-aloud data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0963721411422055">Bär &amp; Huber, 2008</xref>). Furthermore, if decision makers have to justify their decisions, RDOs play a prominent role in the justifications (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0963721411422055">Huber, Bär, &amp; Huber, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>The concept of RDOs is ignored in classical decision research. This neglect seems to follow from the assumption that all risky decisions are gambles. In gambles, there is usually no room for RDOs. Therefore, gambles represent only a subset of risky decisions.</p>
<sec id="section1-0963721411422055">
<title>Incorporation of RDOs Into Alternatives</title>
<p>The search for an RDO often gives rise to cost (money, time, effort, etc.), and at the beginning it is not clear whether the search will be successful or not. Decision makers are much more likely to undertake an RDO search for attractive alternatives than for less attractive ones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0963721411422055">Huber et al., 2011</xref>). Search is more likely if the expectation of success is higher (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0963721411422055">Huber &amp; Huber, 2008</xref>). Context effects also are relevant: Search is more frequent under time pressure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0963721411422055">Huber &amp; Kunz, 2007</xref>) and when decision makers have to justify their decisions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0963721411422055">Huber et al., 2009</xref>). Furthermore, the type of risk and the domain affect the search (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0963721411422055">Wilke et al., 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>A detected RDO is not necessarily acceptable. The expected desirable effects of the RDO (prevention or compensation) have to be weighed against its costs (the premium of an insurance, time, undesirable side effects, etc.). The higher the cost of an RDO, the less likely it is accepted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0963721411422055">Williamson, Ranyard, &amp; Cuthbert, 2000</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0963721411422055">
<title>The Role of Probabilities</title>
<p>As mentioned above, most decision makers are satisfied with knowing whether an outcome is possible or will occur with certainty and are not interested in more precise probabilities. This result contradicts one of the fundamental assumptions of classical decision theory. The following explanations for this finding do not exclude each other:</p>
<list id="list1-0963721411422055" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>More precise probabilities are not necessary if the negative outcome of an alternative can be defused with an RDO.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Decision makers do not expect to get reliable and valid probability information (for example, about the state of economy 3 years from now).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Decision makers do not need more precise probabilities because they apply heuristics that do not require probabilities (e.g., maximin).</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>It should be noted that people do not <italic>generally</italic> recall or infer probabilities from their background knowledge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0963721411422055">Bär &amp; Huber, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0963721411422055">Huber &amp; Macho, 2001</xref>). Furthermore, the little interest in probability is not an artifact of the method of active information search, because if gambles are presented, most decision makers do search for probabilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0963721411422055">Huber, Huber, &amp; Bär, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0963721411422055">Huber &amp; Huber, 2008</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0963721411422055">
<title>Risk-Management-Decision Theory (RMDT)</title>
<p>In a nutshell, the RMDT model supposes that the decision maker first selects the most promising alternative from the set of all available ones, focusing primarily on positive outcomes. Then he or she minimizes the risk connected with the promising alternative—either actively, with an RDO, or passively, applying a heuristic like maximin. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0963721411422055">Figure 2</xref> describes the theory in more detail.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0963721411422055" position="float">
<label>Fig. 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Risk-management-decision theory. For all initially available alternatives, a rudimentary mental representation is constructed. This representation contains mainly the positive outcomes. The alternative with the best outcome is selected as a promising alternative and is inspected in more detail and the representation is elaborated. The decision maker looks in particular for negative outcomes. If a negative outcome has been detected, a decision has to be made (not necessarily consciously) of whether or not to search for a risk-defusing operator (RDO). The search decision is not required if an RDO comes into mind immediately. If an RDO has been found, the decision maker has to decide whether it is acceptable (based on cost–benefit ratio). If the RDO is acceptable, usually in more than 90% of cases the alternative with the RDO is chosen. If the negative outcome cannot be defused, decision makers choose among the available (promising) alternatives with one of the heuristics, usually one that allows risk minimization passively, like maximin. Which heuristic is used depends on, for example, situational factors, frames, or personality characteristics.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0963721411422055-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The main characteristics of the theory can be summarized as follows:</p>
<list id="list2-0963721411422055" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Active minimization of risk</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>RDOs are <italic>active</italic> means to defuse risk. Classical decision theory offers a number of heuristics and models describing <italic>passive</italic> risk minimization (e.g., maximin heuristic or prospect theory with adequate parameter values). However, none of these theories can model active risk minimization.</p>
<list id="list3-0963721411422055" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Decision makers pursue two goals</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The goals are choosing an alternative that has attractive positive outcomes and choosing an alternative that minimizes risk. At the beginning, and with several alternatives, selecting the alternatives with most attractive positive outcomes is more important. If such promising alternatives have been identified, risk minimization becomes the center of attention. Thus, most decision makers do not simply apply RDOs or, for example, maximin from the beginning, but risk minimizing is restricted to the subset of promising alternatives. Interindividual differences as well as context effects (e.g., time pressure, justification pressure, type of risk) may affect the relative weights of these goals.</p>
<list id="list4-0963721411422055" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Dynamic mental representation of alternatives</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>RMDT assumes that initially a minimal mental representation of each alternative, including one or very few outcomes, is constructed. This minimalist representation is elaborated during the process, mainly for promising alternatives, by incorporating additional outcomes, events, or RDOs. The uncertainty of outcomes and events <italic>usually</italic> is represented without probabilities, but probabilities can be included. Elaboration and evaluative processes are closely intermingled (in contrast to, e.g., prospect theory). For example, only the representations of attractive alternatives are expanded, and RDOs are incorporated for undesirable outcomes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0963721411422055">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>RMDT contradicts the central assumption of classical descriptive decision theory, namely that risky decisions generally can be modeled as gambles and that only the subjective values and probabilities of outcomes determine a decision. Otherwise, it has many components and aspects in common with other models. There is no room here to go into details, but examples are heuristics like maximin and evaluative processes for values, uncertainty, and so on. RMDT is compatible with many assumptions of other models—for example, different value functions for positive and negative outcomes in respect to a reference point (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0963721411422055">Kahneman &amp; Tversky, 1979</xref>) or emotional influences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0963721411422055">Loewenstein, Weber, Hsee, &amp; Welch, 2001</xref>). RMDT also can be integrated in general decision frameworks like, for example, Svenson’s differentiation-and-consolidation theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0963721411422055">Svenson, 1992</xref>). The RDO part of the RMDT can be formulated as an independent process module that could be included into other decision models.</p>
<p>Experimental research has revealed that gambles are a very specific type of risky task and that many results from experiments with gambles cannot be generalized to realistic scenarios. What distinguishes these types of risky tasks? <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0963721411422055">Huber and Huber (2008)</xref> made a first attempt to unify gambles and nongambling tasks. They identified experimentally two of the factors determining use of probabilities and RDOs: the expectation to get useful probability information and the expectation to get useful RDO information. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0963721411422055">Table 1</xref> presents a classification of decision tasks according to these two variables. Gambles are <italic>the</italic> prototypical example of tasks with high probability expectation and low RDO expectation.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0963721411422055" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Examples of Decision Situations With High or Low Expectations to Find Useful RDO or Probability Information</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0963721411422055" xlink:href="10.1177_0963721411422055-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Expectation to find useful RDO information</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Expectation to find useful probability information</th>
<th align="center">High</th>
<th align="center">Low</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>High</td>
<td>Travel into country with well-known infectious disease</td>
<td>Surgery (from point of view of patient)<break/>Choice between gambles (e.g., wheels of fortune)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Low</td>
<td>Economic investment in a developing country with unclear economic and political situation (envisaged RDO: compensation guarantee from own government)</td>
<td>Stock market</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0963721411422055">
<p>Note: Because expectations are subjective, different decision makers may categorize decision situations differently.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The importance of RDOs in risky decisions has been established by numerous experiments of our research group and others. Also, a number of factors that affect the search for and the acceptance of RDOs have been discovered.</p>
<p>However, there are many open questions, such as the following: In which manner are the alternatives represented mentally—for example, as decision trees or as mental causal models? Are there biases when people evaluate RDOs? For example, decision makers may overestimate the effect of an RDO with a very attractive alternative. Is the RMDT adaptable to situations in which risk elimination is not the decision maker’s goal (e.g., when a good chess player chooses an opponent)? Answers to these and other questions may further contribute to a future comprehensive theory of risky decision making.</p>
<sec id="section5-0963721411422055">
<title>Recommended Reading</title>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0963721411422055">Baron, J. (2008)</xref>. (See References). A comprehensive and clearly written introduction to decision theory.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0963721411422055">Huber, O. (2007)</xref>. (See References). A comprehensive review of research on risk defusing up to 2007.</p>
<p>Huber, O., Wider, R., &amp; Huber, O.W. (1997). Active information search and complete information presentation in naturalistic risky decision tasks. <italic>Acta Psychologica, 95</italic>, 15–29.The first paper raising the topic of risk-defusing operators.</p>
<p>Payne, J.W., Bettman, J.R., &amp; Johnson, E.J. (1993). <italic>The adaptative decision maker</italic>. New York, NY: Cambridge University Press. A classical text on heuristics in the decision process.</p>
<p>Shah, A.K., &amp; Oppenheimer, D.M. (2008). Heuristics made easy: An effort-reduction framework. <italic>Psychological Bulletin, 134</italic>, 207–222. An up-to-date thorough overview and analysis of decision and judgmental heuristics.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>I am very grateful to A.S. Bär and O.W. Huber (no relation) for many discussions. The introduction is based on our common papers.</p></ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The author declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The author received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0963721411422055">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bär</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Successful or unsuccessful search for risk defusing operators: Effect on decision behavior</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Cognitive Psychology</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>807</fpage>–<lpage>827</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0963721411422055">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Thinking and deciding</source> (<edition>4th ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0963721411422055">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Behavior in risky decisions: Focus on risk defusing</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Abdellaoui</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Luce</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Machina</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Munier</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Uncertainty and risk</source> (pp. <fpage>291</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Berlin, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0963721411422055">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bär</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>O.W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Justification pressure in risky decision making: Search for risk defusing operators</article-title>. <source>Acta Psychologica</source>, <volume>130</volume>, <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0963721411422055">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>O.W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Gambles vs. quasi-realistic scenarios: Expectations to find probability and risk-defusing information</article-title>. <source>Acta Psychologica</source>, <volume>127</volume>, <fpage>222</fpage>–<lpage>236</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0963721411422055">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>O.W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bär</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Information search and mental representation in risky decision making: The advantages first principle</article-title>. <source>Journal of Behavioral Decision Making</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>248</lpage>. doi:10.1002/bdm.674<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bdm.674</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0963721411422055">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>O.W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schulte-Mecklenbeck</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Determining the information participants need: Methods of Active Information Search</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Schulte-Mecklenbeck</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kühberger</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ranyard</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>A handbook of process tracing methods for decision research</source> (pp. <fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Psychology Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0963721411422055">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kunz</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Time pressure in risky decision-making: Effect on risk defusing</article-title>. <source>Psychology Science</source>, <volume>49</volume>, <fpage>415</fpage>–<lpage>426</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0963721411422055">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Macho</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Probabilistic set-up and the search for probability information in quasi-naturalistic decision tasks</article-title>. <source>Risk Decision and Policy</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0963721411422055">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kahneman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tversky</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>). <article-title>Prospect theory: An analysis of decision under risk</article-title>. <source>Econometrica</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>291</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0963721411422055">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Loewenstein</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>E.U.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hsee</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Risk as feelings</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>127</volume>, <fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>286</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0963721411422055">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shiloh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gerad</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Patients’ information needs and decision-making processes: What can be learned from genetic counseling?</article-title> <source>Health Psychology</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>219</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0963721411422055">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Svenson</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Differentiation and consolidation theory of human decision making: A frame of reference for the study of pre- and post-decision processes</article-title>. <source>Acta Psychologica</source>, <volume>80</volume>, <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0963721411422055">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tyszka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zaleśkiewicz</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>When does information about probability count in choices under risk?</article-title> <source>Risk Analysis</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0963721411422055">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilke</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haug</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Funke</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Risk-specific search for risk-defusing operators</article-title>. <source>Swiss Journal of Psychology</source>, <volume>67</volume>, <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0963721411422055">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ranyard</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cuthbert</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Risk management in everyday insurance decisions: Evidence from a process tracing study</article-title>. <source>Risk Decision and Policy</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>