<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TRS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptrs</journal-id>
<journal-title>Transfer: European Review of Labour and Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1024-2589</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1996-7284</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1024258913480605</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1024258913480605</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Main Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The impact of the economic crisis on collective bargaining in the Czech Republic</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Myant</surname>
<given-names>Martin</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1024258913480605"/>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1024258913480605"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1024258913480605">Senior Researcher, ETUI</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1024258913480605">Martin Myant, European Trade Union Institute, Bd du Roi Albert II, 5, 1210 Brussels, Belgium. Email: <email>mmyant@etui.org</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<issue-title>Central and eastern European industrial relations in the crisis: the rise of neoliberalism?</issue-title>
<fpage>185</fpage>
<lpage>194</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">European Trade Union Institute</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Economic crisis, starting in 2008, led to a double recession in the Czech Republic. Enterprise-sector employees were most affected in the first phase and public sector employees in the second. The latter protected their conditions largely through political protests with collective bargaining playing a smaller role. Collective bargaining in the enterprise sector had developed over the preceding decades and continued through the crisis, albeit with agreements less likely to include pay increases. There was no permanent shift in content, with pay increases back on the agenda as conditions improved. There may have been an increase in employment practices that weakened employees’ positions where bargaining did not exist. Two case studies from the motor-vehicle industry show union organizations accepting pay restraint, resisting management pressure for more flexible work practices and welcoming continued division into a core and peripheral labour force.</p>
</abstract>
<trans-abstract xml:lang="fr">
<p>La crise économique qui a démarré en 2008 a conduit à une double récession en République tchèque. Les travailleurs du secteur des entreprises ont été les plus touchés durant la première phase de récession et ceux du secteur public durant la seconde. Ces derniers ont essayé de défendre leurs conditions de travail notamment par des manifestations politiques, la négociation collective jouant un rôle moins important. La négociation collective dans le secteur des entreprises s’est développée au cours des décennies précédentes et s'est poursuivie à travers la crise, mais avec des accords moins susceptibles de comporter des augmentations de salaire. Il n'y a pas eu de changement durable sur le plan du contenu, puisque les augmentations salariales sont revenues à l'ordre du jour à mesure que les conditions de travail s’amélioraient. Il a bien pu y avoir une multiplication des pratiques en matière d'emploi qui a affaibli les positions des travailleurs là où la négociation n'existait pas. Deux études de cas relevés dans l'industrie automobile montrent que les syndicats ont accepté la modération salariale, qu’ils ont résisté à la pression de la direction pour davantage de flexibilité dans le travail et se sont réjouis du maintien de la distinction entre effectifs permanents et main-d’œuvre périphérique.</p>
</trans-abstract>
<trans-abstract xml:lang="de">
<p>Die Wirtschaftskrise, die 2008 einsetzte, hat in der Tschechischen Republik zu einer doppelten Rezession geführt. In der ersten Phase waren vor allem Arbeitnehmer privater Unternehmen betroffen, in der zweiten Phase die Beschäftigten des öffentlichen Sektors. Letztere sicherten ihre Bedingungen in erster Linie durch politische Proteste und weniger durch Tarifverhandlungen. In der Privatwirtschaft wurden die Tarifverhandlungen, die in den vorangehenden Jahrzehnten entwickelt worden waren, auch während der Krise fortgeführt, allerdings sahen die Tarifvereinbarungen meist keine Lohnerhöhungen mehr vor. Die inhaltlichen Änderungen waren auch nicht von Dauer, und sobald die Bedingungen sich verbessert hatten, lagen Lohnerhöhungen wieder auf dem Tisch. Es ist davon auszugehen, dass in nicht tariflich gebundenen Unternehmen Beschäftigungspraktiken zugenommen haben, die die Arbeitnehmerposition geschwächt haben. In zwei Fallstudien aus der Kraftfahrzeugindustrie werden Gewerkschaften dargestellt, die Lohnzurückhaltung akzeptiert, dem Druck der Unternehmensleitung für flexiblere Arbeitsabläufe standgehalten und die weitere Aufteilung in Kern- und Randbelegschaft begrüßt haben.</p>
</trans-abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Economic crisis</kwd>
<kwd>collective bargaining</kwd>
<kwd>Czech Republic</kwd>
<kwd>automotive industry</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1024258913480605">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The economic crisis hit the Czech Republic in the last months of 2008, affecting primarily export-oriented manufacturing where collective bargaining was well-established. After a short period of recovery, the economy turned down again following government spending cuts that depressed domestic demand. The pain was then felt mostly in the public sector where bargaining with the direct employer is secondary to lobbying and pressure on governments and parliament. Czech trade unions mounted major protests against cuts in public spending which included defence of public sector pay but were also considerably broader and are not covered here. They would fit under the heading of unions’ political involvement. This article concentrates on the enterprise sphere, following evidence on the extent and content of bargaining and how it changed through the crisis. Aggregate data are supplemented with case studies of branches of two, high-profile, export-oriented manufacturing companies, Bosch and Volkswagen. These have been leaders in trade union activity, the latter as a strong base from the start and the former as an enterprise in which union organization was only achieved against management opposition. These cases illustrate the issues arising in large-scale manufacturing and the extent of unions’ ability to protect employment conditions through collective bargaining.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1024258913480605">1</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1024258913480605">
<title>Economic crisis in the Czech Republic</title>
<p>The course of the economic crisis in the Czech Republic is indicated in broad outline in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1024258913480605">Table 1</xref>. GDP fell in 2009, primarily because falling exports led to lower output in manufacturing industry. Government spending actually increased as did pay in the non-enterprise sphere, broadly the public sector following decisions made in 2008. Total employment fell, but significantly less than output and average real wages continued to increase, even in the crisis-hit enterprise sphere. This was largely an arithmetic oddity as those losing their jobs were mostly the lowest paid, automatically increasing the average.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1024258913480605" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Indicators of Czech economic performance through the crisis, 2008–2011, % changes.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1024258913480605" xlink:href="10.1177_1024258913480605-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th>2008</th>
<th>2009</th>
<th>2010</th>
<th>2011</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>GDP</td>
<td>2.5</td>
<td>−4.1</td>
<td>2.3</td>
<td>1.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Industrial output</td>
<td>−0.3</td>
<td>−15.9</td>
<td>9.8</td>
<td>7.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Construction output</td>
<td>0.0</td>
<td>−0.9</td>
<td>−7.1</td>
<td>−3.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Government spending</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>4.8</td>
<td>0.5</td>
<td>−1.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Employment</td>
<td>1.6</td>
<td>−1.4</td>
<td>−1.0</td>
<td>0.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Real wages</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>2.3</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td>0.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Of which:</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Enterprise sphere</td>
<td>2.2</td>
<td>2.0</td>
<td>1.0</td>
<td>0.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Non-enterprise sphere</td>
<td>−2.0</td>
<td>3.6</td>
<td>−2.1</td>
<td>−1.8</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1024258913480605">
<p>Sources: Czech Statistical Office, <italic>Macroeconomic Indicators</italic>, www.czso.cz; <italic>Employment and Unemployment in the Czech Republic as Measured by the Labour Force Sample Survey</italic>, various issues, http://www.czso.cz/csu/2011edicniplan.nsf/p/3101-11; <italic>Registered Number of Employees and their Wages</italic>, various issues, http://www.czso.cz/csu/2011edicniplan.nsf/engp/3106-11.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Governments did little to counter the effects of the crisis. A right-wing coalition was in office in 2008 and responded initially by denying that the crisis was serious. Its subsequent anti-crisis plan gave a stimulus from genuinely new measures equivalent to 1.1 per cent of GDP, of which 74 per cent was from reductions in tax and social insurance obligations on business. The government was replaced after March 2009 by an interim government that consulted with social interests, leading to a 38-point anti-crisis package but this largely remained at the level of discussion. Instead, the government was guided by a determination to reduce the budget deficit first to 5 per cent of GDP – it was actually 5.8 per cent in 2009 – and then to the 3 per cent required for future accession to the euro area. Elections in May 2010 produced a clear majority for a right-wing coalition which pursued cuts with more vigour, reducing state benefits and cutting public sector pay and public investment projects.</p>
<p>Economic recovery was already under way in the latter part of 2009 and is reflected in GDP growth in 2010, but this slowed in 2011. GDP even declined slightly in the last two quarters and then fell by 1.0 per cent in the first half of 2012. This second depression was caused by the government policy of austerity, reflected in the fall in real wages in the non-enterprise sphere and the slower growth in the enterprise sphere, both of which are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1024258913480605">Table 1</xref>. The effect was to cut domestic demand and hence output. Construction continued to decline partly because of restricted credit but increasingly because of cuts in public spending on new infrastructure projects. Industry, heavily dependent on exports, grew rapidly enough to limit the slowdown in GDP growth, but was affected by stagnation in the country’s most important export markets – the EU accounted for 83 per cent of exports – at the end of 2011.</p>
<p>Over the period of the crisis total employment returned almost precisely to its 2007 level, but average weekly hours worked fell from 38.3 to 36.4, due to a reduction in the numbers working 40 hours per week and more. This is consistent with adjustment by reduced overtime and some negotiated reductions in the working week. In sectors where employment did decline – notably manufacturing which lost 8.3 per cent of its labour force between 2007 and 2010 – a core workforce was the best protected. The number on fixed-term contracts fell very slightly and the number of foreign citizens among the workforce fell from 5.7 per cent to 4.4 per cent from the peak year of 2008 to 2010. Employers were taking advantage of elements of numerical flexibility that had already been developed to cope with the effects of falling demand while minimizing the impact on jobs for their core workforces.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1024258913480605">
<title>The employment relations background</title>
<p>The activities and strength of Czech trade unions and the broad structure of collective bargaining are set out elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1024258913480605">Myant, 2010</xref>). The legal framework for employment relations was amended in laws passed at the end of 1990, in consultation with trade unions and international agencies, and is embodied in the Labour Code (<italic>Zákoník práce</italic>), a document which in its 2009 version ran to 396 paragraphs and almost 60 000 words. These provide quite detailed standards on work conditions, hours, holiday entitlements, overtime and weekend work and procedures for employment and dismissal. The main trade union centre (ČMKOS, Českomoravská konfederace odborových svazů, Czech-Moravian Confederation of Trade Unions) has considered it a considerable success that, despite changes in governments and frequent minor amendments to the Labour Code, the essential protections for employees against arbitrary management remain in place, alongside rights for trade union activity.</p>
<p>Bargaining takes place at the sectoral level in some sectors, often setting a floor for pay increases and some general conditions, but enterprise-level bargaining is more important in directly determining pay levels and other conditions. A tripartite body (RHSD, Rada sociální a hospodářské dohody, Council for Economic and Social Accord) brings together two significant union centres, with ČMKOS very much the most important, employers’ organizations and government. It is a consultative body only, playing no part in collective bargaining, and governments can ignore views expressed there when they so wish.</p>
<p>The place of the tripartite in trade union thinking has evolved with experience. It is seen as one part in a mechanism for influencing political decisions, providing a forum for discussion of government proposals and a forum for seeking agreement with employers against government. This has frequently proved possible when right-wing politicians have proposed changes to the Labour Code that would substantially weaken the position of employees, such as removing protections against arbitrary dismissal. However, unions have also relied on influencing parliamentary parties and individual MPs, frequently with some success when governments up to 2010 typically had very small parliamentary majorities. They have also periodically mobilized their members in public demonstrations and occasionally token general strikes. These are effective in gaining publicity, but positive results beyond that are difficult to demonstrate. However, mobilization has consistently proven easiest over issues of employment law and that has protected much of the legislation passed in 1990 including, for example, a legal framework that allows political strikes. It is noteworthy that, despite an amount of neoliberal rhetoric, changes to the Labour Code in the aftermath of the crisis were small. There was no rush to liberalize employment relations and some changes could be judged favourable to the employee side.</p>
<p>Without any precise data, a reasonable estimate of union membership is 10 per cent of the labour force in 2009 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1024258913480605">Myant, 2010</xref>: 53). The extent of collective bargaining coverage is undoubtedly higher, with union data pointing to a figure certainly over 30 per cent of employees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1024258913480605">Myant, 2010</xref>: 19). The Ministry of Labour and Social Affairs provides data suggesting that around 50 per cent of pay is determined by collective bargaining, but large and unexplained annual fluctuations cast doubt on the reliability of data coming from incomplete management responses. Moreover, information on the extent of bargaining can provide only a partial picture of the actual nature of employment relations. That also depends on the content and coverage, in terms of employment issues, of collective bargaining and on the situation in workplaces where unions and bargaining are not present. The following sections follow these themes, exploring how far the economic crisis led to any significant changes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1024258913480605">
<title>Bargaining in the economic crisis</title>
<p>The main source on the content of bargaining is an annual survey of collective agreements recorded by the Ministry of Labour and Social Affairs as reported by ČMKOS. Selected indicators are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1024258913480605">Table 2</xref>. Information is not comprehensive – not even all ČMKOS unions send in reports – and is not precisely comparable on a year-by-year basis as some agreements run for more than one year. It also does not give a complete picture of agreements between unions and management as many of those are outside the framework of the regular collective agreements.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1024258913480605" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Collective agreements recorded and the numbers that included reference to pay increases and to aspects of work flexibility. </p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1024258913480605" xlink:href="10.1177_1024258913480605-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th>2007</th>
<th>2008</th>
<th>2009</th>
<th>2010</th>
<th>2011</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Total number</td>
<td>1180</td>
<td>1448</td>
<td>1337</td>
<td>1316</td>
<td>1301</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pay increase considered</td>
<td>783</td>
<td>1071</td>
<td>752</td>
<td>558</td>
<td>730</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Average agreed pay increase (%)</td>
<td>4.0</td>
<td>6.5</td>
<td>4.4</td>
<td>3.0</td>
<td>2.9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Agency workers</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>flexikonto</td>
<td>278</td>
<td>443</td>
<td>415</td>
<td>472</td>
<td>479</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1024258913480605">
<p>Note: The figure for average pay increases is a weighted average across different methods used for agreeing pay increases.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-1024258913480605">
<p>Source: Ministerstvo práce a sociálních věcí, <italic>Informační systém o pracovních podmínkách</italic>, various years, www.mpsv.cz/cs/11758.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Despite these caveats, the data presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1024258913480605">Table 2</xref> show that the crisis was followed by little change in the number of agreements signed, but by a sharp drop in the number that covered wage increases at all, down from 74 per cent in 2008 to 56 per cent in 2009 and 42 per cent in 2010. Where wage increases were considered, their level was on average lower than in previous years. It was still higher than the average pay increases in those years for the economy as a whole, but the actual figure may have been lower owing to reductions in working hours below the anticipated level.</p>
<p>The background to this was a widespread willingness from the union side to comply with strong pressure from managements for wage freezes or pay reductions. Some employees lost their jobs quickly while others were laid off temporarily with greatly reduced pay. Workforces often accepted zero pay increases as preferable to reduced employment which, managements indicated, were the alternative. As one union representative put it, ‘our employees understood all these restrictions for the crisis and did not grumble at all’ (from the union representative in the enterprise Šroubárna Turnov, <italic>Kovák</italic>, 2011, No. 26).</p>
<p>Bargaining had always covered more than just pay and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1024258913480605">Table 2</xref> provides information on two issues that relate to labour flexibility, with agency working much more important than its low profile in bargaining agendas would imply. A total of over 2 000 registered agencies offered employees – mostly foreign citizens from Slovakia, Poland, Ukraine and, increasingly, Vietnam – to enterprises and this was one of the main means of overcoming a labour shortage in manufacturing industry and of achieving numerical flexibility in the labour force. Agency workers typically received significantly lower pay than core employees and large numbers were encouraged to return to their homelands as the crisis struck. Unions generally gave them no protection. Inclusion of the issue in collective agreements increased very slightly after the crisis, but not significantly enough to suggest a change in union organizations’ approach. This is explored below in relation to the Škoda car manufacturer.</p>
<p>The final row of the table shows agreements over the ‘flexikonto’, the system of flexible work accounts imported from Germany, and largely inspired by German companies. This is an important issue for employers in manufacturing industry that face fluctuations in demand leading to variations in their requirements for working hours. It enables them to reduce hours at a time of low demand and then compensate by requiring employees to work shifts later. This leaves difficult questions of what guaranteed pay there should be, even with no work, how much time can be built up in a flexible account, reasonable notice of extra shifts and the time period over which an account should run. A very short period is likely to be of no benefit to the employer as there may be no opportunity to compensate for down time with later extra shifts. The employer will then need to compensate employees with the full wage regardless.</p>
<p>Following vigorous lobbying from German companies, Czech employment law was amended in 2007 to allow for flexible work accounts that could run, with union agreement, over one year. Union organizations frequently found very strong opposition from their members, but were under strong pressure to make concessions to managements. Data in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1024258913480605">Table 2</xref> suggest some increase in flexible work accounts. This was most marked among agreements signed by the metalworkers’ union KOVO, representing employees in the foreign-dominated electronics and motor-vehicle sectors, where they were covered in 25 per cent of agreements in 2011 compared with 16 per cent in 2007.</p>
<p>It thus appears that collective bargaining largely continued through the economic crisis. Its content shifted, with less scope for continued pay rises, but probably a better base for defending employees’ positions than workplaces without collective agreements. That theme is pursued in the next section.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1024258913480605">
<title>Where unions were weakest</title>
<p>It is impossible to provide comprehensive data on how far employers abide by the provisions of employment law when there is no active union organization to keep them in check. However, it is possible to use reports from the SÚIP (Státní úřad inspekce práce, State Office of Labour Inspection) which show the kinds of transgressions that they uncover. Inspections were inevitably biased towards the bad cases, following up complaints and focusing on sectors with bad reputations. Nevertheless, they cover a large number of firms every year and their report for 2010 found 89 per cent of construction firms, 84 per cent of retail firms and 85 per cent of firms in hotels and catering in breach of one or more legal provision (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1024258913480605">SÚIP, 2011</xref>). Frequent transgressions were failure to given written information on working hours or pay, breaking rules on working hours and overtime and, albeit somewhat less frequently, failing to meet minimum wage requirements.</p>
<p>It is impossible to use such data to follow trends, but there is indirect evidence of an increase in the so-called Švarc system, named after a construction entrepreneur of the early 1990s Miroslav Švarc. He introduced the Czech Republic to the practice of using commercial contracts with individuals registered as self-employed in place of employment contracts. This enables employers to evade insurance contributions and obligations under employment law, including health and safety rules. The ‘employee’ could also be tempted, even with lower pay, because of favourable tax treatment for the self-employed. Clarification of the law in 1993 made this explicitly illegal and Švarc was imprisoned in 1994. However, the legal provision was complicated, transgressions difficult to prove and the SÚIP rarely took action. Some prominent politicians from the right occasionally advocated making the system fully legal, a move which, according to survey evidence, would have been very popular among business owners.</p>
<p>During the economic crisis there were media reports of a revival of the Švarc system with employees told to convert to a commercial contract or leave altogether. Estimates of the extent are inevitably guesses; typically around 2–4 per cent of the labour force. Following pressure through the RHSD from both trade unions and larger employers, complaining about the extent of evasion of tax and insurance contributions, changes to the Labour Code at the start of 2012 brought the Švarc system back within its remit. The number of inspectors was increased, as were visits to workplaces and imposition of fines – the usual practice had been only to give advice and a warning – but penalties for using the Švarc system did not figure in early reports of action. Indeed, legal loopholes still made it possible to continue to use commercial contracts with impunity and changes to tax and insurance obligations on the self-employed made use of the system even more favourable.</p>
<sec id="section6-1024258913480605">
<title>Case study 1: Bosch-Diesel</title>
<p>The German company Bosch had a number of plants in the Czech Republic, all with distinct collective agreements and working relations. There evidently had been no imposition of a universal company model, still less a universal German model. Each case depended on the personnel manager, usually sent from another branch of the company for a short period, and on the preferences from the union side. The biggest plant was in the small town of Jihlava, employing 6 000 by 2008 making components for Diesel engines.</p>
<p>The relative strengths of unions and management, and the tools available to them, were clarified in 2001. Responding to efforts from a few individuals to set up a union organization, the management helped to organize a demonstration which turned violent and disrupted the founding meeting. However, Bosch was soon hit by embarrassing coverage in the national daily press which, alongside interventions from leading union officials, persuaded the management to negotiate. A union organization was soon operating, albeit still facing some management hostility. Despite a subsequent split in the union organization, total membership soon reached about one-third of the workforce. This outcome confirmed that union recognition would be the norm in large multinational companies.</p>
<p>It also confirmed the basis of the two sides’ strengths and aims in the bargaining process. Unions never felt the need to stage strikes, but they did occasionally demonstrate support by public demonstrations of employees. A major weapon continued to be media publicity. The employers were prepared to agree to pay increases, raising the level of manual workers’ wages to the peak of any company in the Czech Republic, but in exchange they wanted a guaranteed flow of production, meaning low absenteeism, good time keeping and scope for flexibility to respond to demand fluctuations. Following union opposition, and unlike other plants of the same company, they employed no agency workers but relied instead on fixed-term contracts. Behind all bargaining was the veiled threat that they might pull out of the Czech Republic and relocate to a lower-wage area. Thus, although conflicts were frequent over aspects of employment conditions, both sides understood each other’s aims and strengths.</p>
<p>The economic crisis began to affect Bosch in Jihlava in May 2008 when some employees were sent home on 70–80 per cent pay. The union side recognized that a labour force reduction was inevitable, but was taken by surprise by the rapid dismissal of 430 core workers in September and ending of employment for 300 on fixed-term contracts. The management broke the law in its haste by not consulting with union representatives and subsequently had to pay individuals additional compensation for redundancy, as set out in the collective agreement (<italic>Kovák</italic>, 2009, No. 8). Overall, the labour force was reduced from an average level of 6 173 in 2008 to 4 770 in 2009 by voluntary and involuntary departures.</p>
<p>A two-year collective agreement had been signed for 2008 to 2009, but this was amended to allow for a 20 per cent reduction in the working week and a corresponding reduction in pay. Unions accepted this in the context of the firm’s continuing commitment to long-term expansion plans and to no further redundancies. A few employees refused to accept the changed conditions and did face redundancy. Over the following years the union successfully negotiated flat-rate pay increases that helped the lowest paid the most.</p>
<p>This should be seen as a union response to the crisis, helping those most likely to be union members at a time of lower wage increases. For their part employers pressed hard for flexible work accounts, but the unions conceded only a six-month period for evening out working hours, a lower level than that agreed in Bosch’s other major Czech plant. The preference from the unions at the plant level for achieving numerical flexibility remained the reliance on fixed-term contracts and this took them into conflict with their own union leadership. An amendment to employment law prevented indefinite renewal of fixed-term contracts – a measure intended to ensure that employees would be moved onto permanent contracts – and the union organization in Bosch Jihlava started a campaign for a reversal of that change.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1024258913480605">
<title>Case study 2: Volkswagen</title>
<p>Volkswagen came into the Czech Republic by buying the Škoda car manufacturer, bringing control over three production centres, the main one in Mladá Boleslav and two smaller branches in Vrchlabí and Kvasiny. Output increased to reach a peak of 623 291 vehicles in 2007. Union organizations were inherited from the communist past and recognition was never an issue. Membership remained high, at around 70 per cent of the core workforce in 2008, and union nominees were consistently elected by employees to one-third of the seats on the company’s Supervisory Board. As in the case of Bosch, although even more clearly, the management could use promises of plant modernization or threats of closure as warnings to the union side. Union strength, much more clearly than in Bosch, was demonstrated by strike threats and a short strike over pay in 2007. Also, as a major multinational company, Volkswagen was very sensitive to bad media coverage.</p>
<p>The economic crisis hit Škoda in the summer of 2008 at a time of expansion, just as the management was negotiating with the union organization for an agreement on voluntary extra shifts on Saturdays. Car production ultimately fell by 17 per cent from 2007 to 2009. However, the course of the crisis was complicated by fluctuations and instability. Early 2009 saw a sudden increase in demand following the introduction of the car-scrap scheme in Germany so that by April Škoda was back to full production and still not keeping up with orders. Demand fell back again in October, amid variations between individual models and plants. The issue of labour flexibility therefore became a central concern for management. That focused attention on the issues of agency workers and the flexikonto.</p>
<p>The number of agency workers had grown to an average of 4 680 in 2007, 16 per cent of the total workforce and a quite exceptional figure across the Volkswagen group for which the average was under 5 per cent. They were not popular with the regular workforce, because they were judged to be poor workers, in some cases responsible for petty crime and unhygienic habits, but the union position was that they were a better alternative than the loss of guaranteed permanent employment for the core workforce. The union did make some approaches to agency workers, but did not bargain on their behalf.</p>
<p>The issue received publicity that was potentially damaging to the company in early 2008 when, following a complaint from the Polish Ombudsman representing Polish agency workers, it was established that at least one agency had been systematically flouting the law, including paying wages below the legal minimum. The management’s reaction, in view of bad publicity, of doubts over the quality of agency employees and of the need for good relations with a stable core labour force at a time of falling demand, was to seek to reduce their numbers, at one point even setting a target of zero (<italic>Škodovácký odborář</italic>, 17 December 2008). Union representatives were actually not enthusiastic about this as a long-term solution, frequently referring to agency workers as a welcome ‘cushion’ and later arguing with their colleagues from western Europe that setting a maximum of 5 per cent of the workforce would not be realistic (<italic>Škodovácký odborář</italic>, 2 November 2011).</p>
<p>Nevertheless, they negotiated with management a short-term agreement whereby agency workers, mostly concentrated into unpleasant work, would be replaced from the core workforce in the first weeks of 2009. The number of agency workers fell rapidly to 600. Under a further agreement all agency workers were to come from one firm, Manpower, as of April 2010. Moreover, this firm would consult with the union organization over employment conditions and aim to hire mostly Czech employees. That opened the prospect of full union representation for agency workers and the company management opened up prospects of a better deal for agency workers, including the possibility of promotion to the core workforce. In practice, increasing demand for cars after the depths of the crisis led to renewed dependence on agency workers, their numbers rising back to 2 400 in mid-2011, and about half were still employed by firms other than Manpower.</p>
<p>The flexikonto issue was pressed through 2009 with management insisting – correctly as it turned out – that demand for individual models was still subject to unpredictable fluctuations. They claimed that the flexikonto existed in all but one other Volkswagen plant and the personnel manager behaved as if his career within Volkswagen – Škoda was only a temporary posting for senior managers – would be greatly helped if he could negotiate away this anomaly. The company had also been actively lobbying the government to allow for evening out of shifts over a four-year period, as operated in the Volkswagen plant in Slovakia.</p>
<p>The union response in late 2008 was hostile, but management was very insistent, implicitly linking acceptance of such a scheme to long-term investment plans and hence job stability. Opposition continued through early 2009, when down time was compensated at the rate of 75 per cent of average pay and extra shifts were paid extra at the time, but agreement was reached at the end of the year on a trial scheme for 2010. Following strong employee dissatisfaction, renegotiation for 2011 led to what the union side claimed to be the softest scheme in the whole Volkswagen combine, with shifts to balance out over four-month periods. Negotiating for 2012 the union starting point was that ‘in general we reject the flexikonto as a model’ (<italic>Škodovácký odborář</italic>, 15 December 2011).</p>
<p>It should be added that pay negotiations continued very much as normal, albeit with an emphasis on the union side for commitments to job security. They settled in February 2009 for a deal with a flat-rate one-off payment plus a percentage increase, meaning a move towards slightly greater pay equality. For 2010 the flat-rate element was bigger but the overall percentage increase was around 6 per cent for most employees. Thus, as in Bosch, an effect of the crisis was to increase union determination to protect the lower-paid employees who formed the core of their membership. Management’s priorities were the total wage bill and labour flexibility: they could therefore tolerate the narrowing of pay differentials.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1024258913480605">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The economic crisis led to important short-term changes in the content of collective bargaining, but its long-term effects will probably prove to be small. Where bargaining is well-established, there was an immediate shift towards protecting jobs of the core labour force at the expense of peripheral employees and pay increases. For the longer term, although there was discussion of issues relevant to labour flexibility and dualism in the labour market, there were also strong pressures on both management and union sides to return to the pre-crisis employment practices, with very little change. Even with a right-wing government securely in power, it is noteworthy that there has been no significant attempt to reduce existing legal protection of employee or trade union rights.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2-1024258913480605">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>Research for part of this article was undertaken within the EU Seventh Framework Programme project NEUJOBS, ‘Employment 2025: How will multiple transitions affect the European labour market’.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1024258913480605">
<label>1</label>
<p>Research for this part of the article was undertaken within the EU Seventh Framework Programme project NEUJOBS and included interviews with representatives of the Czech KOVO trade union and of the employers’ organization, the Union of Industry and Transport of the Czech Republic. More information on the cases is available in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1024258913480605">Beblavý et al., 2012</xref>.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1024258913480605">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Beblavý</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kureková</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Drahokoupil</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Linking Labour Regimes and Technological Innovation in Central and Eastern Europe: The Case of the Automotive and Software Industries</article-title>. <comment>NEUJOBS Working Paper No. 6.2. Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.neujobs.eu">www.neujobs.eu</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1024258913480605">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Myant</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Trade Unions in the Czech Republic</source>. <publisher-loc>Brussels</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ETUI</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1024258913480605">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">SÚIP (Státní úřad inspekce práce)</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Roční souhrnná zpráva o výslecích konrolních akcí provedených inspekcí práce za rok 2010</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Opava</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SÚIP</publisher-name>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.suip.cz/_files/suip-33ab1b4ed6d0886bdccc4a280aa44cc7/rsz_o_vysledcich_ka_2010.pdf">www.suip.cz/_files/suip-33ab1b4ed6d0886bdccc4a280aa44cc7/rsz_o_vysledcich_ka_2010.pdf</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>