<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CIN</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcin</journal-id>
<journal-title>China Information</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0920-203X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-590X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0920203X11436072c</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0920203X11436072c</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book review: Shanghai’s Dancing World: Cabaret Culture and Urban Politics, 1919–1954</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Gorfinkel</surname><given-names>Lauren</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0920203X11436072">University of Technology, Sydney, Australia</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>26</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>109</fpage>
<lpage>111</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>Andrew David</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <source>Shanghai’s Dancing World: Cabaret Culture and Urban Politics, 1919–1954</source>. <publisher-loc>Hong Kong</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Chinese University Press</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year>; <page-count count="364"/> pp.: <isbn>9789629963736</isbn>, <price>US$45.00</price> (hbk)</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>While the cosmopolitan metropolis of 21st-century Shanghai has developed its own aura in recent decades, its mystique is built upon an earlier reputation as the ‘Paris of the East’. As author Andrew David Field indulged in the clubs and bars of contemporary Shanghai, he developed a keen scholarly interest in understanding more deeply Shanghai’s ‘golden age’, upon which much of Shanghai’s contemporary reputation is based. <italic>Shanghai’s Dancing World</italic> brilliantly reconstructs this earlier period of a city in which the nightlife industry has played such an important role. Apart from the lucid text, the book is enriched with maps of the locations of cabarets, nightclubs, and ballrooms, as well as interior blueprints and photographs of extravagant ballrooms, band members, waitstaff, and tea boys, which combine to bring the old Shanghai alive.</p>
<p>In order to reconstruct the life of cabaret culture in Shanghai from the 1920s to the early 1950s, Field engages in a fine-grained historical and cultural analysis of old newspapers, magazines, and other Chinese-language documents drawn mainly from the archives of Shanghai Municipal Library and Beijing National Library. Rather than examine the era through the eyes of Westerners, Field’s aim is to examine the emergence, flourishing, and decline of the industry through the eyes of Chinese writers and to gather detailed stories of Chinese participants in the industry. He does a fine job of this, sharing in his writing a passion for and desire to get to know his story’s characters, who include hostesses, patrons, gangsters, police, and government officials.</p>
<p>The book is organized into two parts in roughly chronological order. Part 1 is divided thematically around different social aspects of cabaret culture in Shanghai from 1919 to 1937. Chapter 1 examines the popularity of jazz music and social dancing in the 1920s, beginning with its introduction by Westerners living in Shanghai’s international concessions. Chapter 2 then examines the development of the first Chinese cabarets and its popularity among upper- and middle-class Chinese. Chapter 3 is a fascinating account of the architecture and interior design of Shanghai’s exclusive Western-style and traditional Chinese-inspired ballrooms. Chapter 4 focuses on the lives of young cabaret hostesses (舞女), many of whom entered the concession from surrounding rural areas in the turmoil of Japanese raids, while Chapter 5 turns to an analysis of the male patrons of cabarets and ballrooms. Gender and class relations underlie much of this section. For instance, Field explains that dancing appeared to offer the girls a chance to develop sophisticated, urban identities, and many had hopes of raising their social status by finding a marriage partner in their male patrons. However, these were difficult goals to attain, and the girls held precarious positions between entertainment and prostitution.</p>
<p>Part 2 focuses on the politics of cabaret culture from 1937 to 1954. Chapter 6 provides an intriguing account of how nightclubs continued to operate in the neutrally zoned international settlements amidst the bombs and shrapnel that rained down on the city around them. Chapter 7 describes the Nationalist government’s attempt to restore order, clean up the city, and remove its vices after Japan’s defeat in 1945. As Chapter 8 describes, the Nationalist government attempted to ban cabarets nationwide, threatening thousands of workers’ jobs, and resulting in a dancers’ uprising in Shanghai in 1948, which eventually led to a repeal of the ban. Field claims his book to be the first time this significant sociopolitical event involving as many as 6,000 protesters and resulting in significant damage to government buildings, injuries of more than 40 policemen, and the arrests and trials of over 30 people, including workers, dancers, and leaders in the cabaret industry, has been discussed in detail in Western scholarship. Chapter 9 turns to the more successful demise of cabarets under the Chinese Communist Party (CCP). It was intriguing to learn that Mao Zedong himself loved ballroom dancing, despite banning it for the rest of the population. Field suggests that ballroom dancing could not be reformed to match the CCP’s goals as it took attention away from both the Party and its Great Helmsman, and placed it on one’s dancing partner instead. In the reform era, however, when the Mao cult subsided, ballroom dancing was one of the first practices to be reinvigorated in Shanghai life, this time seen in the ‘quaint pursuit of middle-aged to elderly Chinese in the parks and gardens of the city’ (p. 289).</p>
<p>Overall, this book is an impressive and stimulating historical work that successfully recreates for the reader a sense of what life was like in the cabarets and dance halls of Shanghai in the early to mid-20th century. The book effectively links the intimate details of the era to broader social and political events that shook China at the time. Moreover, it provides an important historical backdrop to the ongoing mystique of Shanghai as China’s most modern and cosmopolitan city today. There is enough in this book to titillate readers with a historical interest in a wide range of fields, including Chinese state–society relations, gender, class, architecture, city identities, nightlife, dance, music, and the media.</p>
</body>
</article>