<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CLA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcla</journal-id>
<journal-title>Clin-Alert®</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0069-4770</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1530-812X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0069477012462188</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0069477012462188</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reporting on Adverse Clinical Events</article-title>
</title-group>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p><bold>Clin-Alert</bold><sup>®</sup> (Print ISSN 0069-4770/Online ISSN 1530-812X)(J525) is published semimonthly by SAGE Publications, 2455 Teller Road,Thousand Oaks, CA 91320; telephone (805) 499-0721; fax/order line (805)375-1700; e-mail <email>order@sagepub.com</email>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sagepub.com">http://www.sagepub.com</ext-link>. Printed in the USA. Periodicals postage paid at Thousand Oaks, CA and additional mailing offices. Annual subscription rates: $1,008 USD per year, single issue: $116 USD. Disclaimer: The authors, editors, and publisher will not accept any legal responsibility for any errors or omissions that may be made in this publication. The publisher makes no warranty, expressed or implied, with respect to the material contained herein. The full text of this journal is also available through InfoTrac. Copyright © 2012 by SAGE Publications.</p>
<p>Trade names [ ] are applied by Clin-Alert as representative samples without regard for possible differences in bioavailability or bioequivalence.</p>
<p>POSTMASTER: Send address changes to Clin-Alert, c/o SAGE Publications, 2455 Teller Road, Thousand Oaks, CA 91320.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0069477012462188">
<label>*</label>
<p>= first report</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>50</volume>
<issue>17</issue>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>8</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 SAGE Publications</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>3, 4-Methylenedioxymethamphetamine* (227)</kwd>
<kwd>Amitriptyline (234)</kwd>
<kwd>Angiotensin-Converting Enzyme Inhibitors (231)</kwd>
<kwd>Angiotensin Receptor Blockers (231)</kwd>
<kwd>Adverse Drug Reactions (224, 236)</kwd>
<kwd>Ceftaroline (226)</kwd>
<kwd>Clarithromycin (233)</kwd>
<kwd>Dabigatran (225, 237)</kwd>
<kwd>Dietary Supplement (238)</kwd>
<kwd>Fluconazole (233)</kwd>
<kwd>Levetiracetam (235)</kwd>
<kwd>Minocycline (230)</kwd>
<kwd>Montelukast (233)</kwd>
<kwd>Psychotropics (232)</kwd>
<kwd>Rifampicin (225)</kwd>
<kwd>Sildenafil (229)</kwd>
<kwd>Tattoo Ink (228)</kwd>
<kwd>Warfarin (226)</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0069477012462188">
<title>Adverse Drug Reactions No. 224</title>
<sec id="section2-0069477012462188">
<title>Pediatric Reactions in Spanish Pharmacovigilance System</title>
<p>Data were reviewed in a Spanish pharmacovigilance database from 2004 to 2009 for adverse drug reaction reports for pediatric patients aged 0 to 17 years. A total of 4279 reports contained 8196 adverse drug reactions, with approximately 2 reactions per report. More than one third of the reports were considered serious (37%), defined as fatal, life-threatening, requiring/prolonging hospitalization, or causing permanent disability. Slightly more than half (51%) of all reports were in females, with 34% of the serious reports affecting females. The majority of reports were provided by physicians (63%) and came from the outpatient sector (75%). One third of the adverse drug reactions (34%) were general disorders and alterations occurring at the site of drug administration, 15% were skin and subcutaneous tissue reactions (eg, pyrexia, inflammation, urticaria), 14% were nervous system disorders, and 8% were gastrointestinal disorders. Approximately 58% of the reports were related to vaccines. Most of the reactions were known (85%) for the suspected drugs, but for 20% the reaction was not known. The 3 treatment groups most frequently associated with adverse drug reactions were anti-infectives, nervous system drugs, and respiratory system drugs.</p>
<p>The authors concluded that the adverse drug reaction reporting rate in the pediatric population has increased from 2004 to 2009, with a high rate of reports related to vaccines. The publication of safety reports by regulatory agencies was determined to be a causative factor in the increased number of reports.</p>
<p>Adverse Drug Reactions [Adverse Drug Reactions]</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Aldea A et al (A Aldea, Unidad Central de Investigacion Cinica y Ensayos Clinicos, Hospital Universitario de Canarias, Ofra, s/n. La Cuesta, 38320 San Cristobal de la Laguna, Santa Cruz e Tenerife, Spain; e-mail: <email>a.aldea@mail.com</email>) Paediatric adverse drug reactions reported to the Spanish Pharmacovigilance System from 2004 to 2009. <italic>Eur J Clin Pharmacol</italic> 68:1329–1338 (Sep) 2012</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0069477012462188">
<title>Dabigatran, Rifampicin No. 225</title>
<sec id="section4-0069477012462188">
<title>Drug Interaction: Decreased Dabigatran Bioavailability</title>
<p>An open-label pharmacokinetic study was performed on 24 healthy adults to evaluate the effect of rifampicin, a P-glycoprotein inducer, on serum exposure to dabigatran. Participants received a single 150-mg dose of dabigatran on days 1, 9, 16, and 23 and rifampicin 600 mg daily on days 2 through 8. Area under the concentration–time curve (AUC<sub>0-∞</sub>) and maximal plasma concentration (<italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub>) of total dabigatran (free plus conjugated) was assessed on days of administration. Pharmacokinetic parameters of dabigatran were decreased following the 7-day administration of rifampicin (67% reduction in AUC<sub>0-∞</sub>, geometric mean [gMean] ratio 33.0%, 90% confidence interval 26.5% to 41.2%; and 65.5% reduction in <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub>, gMean ratio 34.5%, 90% confidence interval 26.9% to 44.1%). Exposure returned to near baseline and was no longer significantly decreased after the 7-day washout period as measured on day 16 (18% reduction in AUC<sub>0-∞</sub>, gMean ratio 82.3.0%, 90% confidence interval 65.3% to 103.9%; and 20% reduction in <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub>, gMean ratio 81.4%, 90% confidence interval 65.2% to 101.5%). Exposure normalized further on day 23, after a 14-day washout period. Headache was the most frequently reported adverse event. All reported adverse events were mild or moderate with resolution by trial conclusion.</p>
<p>The authors concluded that administration of a potent P-glycoprotein inducer decreased exposure to dabigatran. They further claimed that this reduction may lead to clinically significant decreased systemic exposure and recommended avoiding use of P-glycoprotein inducers with dabigatran.</p>
<p>Dabigatran Etexilate [“Pradaxa”]</p>
<p>Rifampicin [“Rifampicin”]</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Hartter S et al (S Hartter, Boehringer, Ingelheim Pharma GmbH &amp; Co KG, Translational Medicine, Birkendorfer Strasse 65, 88397 Biberch/Riss, Germany; e-mail: <email>sebastion.heartter@boehringer-ingelheim.com</email>) Decrease in the oral bioavailability of dabigatran etexilate after co-medication with rifampicin. <italic>Br J Clin Pharmacol</italic> 74:490–500 (Sep) 2012</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0069477012462188">
<title>Warfarin, Ceftaroline No. 226</title>
<sec id="section6-0069477012462188">
<title>Drug Interaction: Hemarthrosis</title>
<p>An 85-year-old woman developed disabling arm and shoulder pain when initiated on ceftaroline (12 days) for cellulitis while on 4 weeks of stable warfarin therapy (2.5 mg daily) for venous thromboembolism. Concurrent medications included carvedilol (12.5 mg twice daily), simvastatin (20 mg at bedtime), aspirin (81 mg daily), anastrozole (1 mg daily), omeprazole (20 mg daily), and venlafaxine (37.5 mg daily). Adherence was confirmed by family interview. Additional medication and dietary changes were denied. Relevant findings included elevated white blood cell count (22/µL), decreased hemoglobin (7.9 mg/dL), and elevated international normalized ratio (4.35). Interpretation of shoulder ultrasound was limited by edema, but X-ray films revealed no acute osseous component. Aspiration of left shoulder joint produced grossly bloody fluid with 629 879 red blood cells/mm<sup>3</sup>. Warfarin and antibiotics were held and international normalized ratio trended down to 1.38 over 4 days. Hemoglobin and symptoms remained stable and warfarin was reinitiated.</p>
<p>The authors concluded that supratherapeutic international normalized ratio was caused by an interaction with ceftaroline, which precipitated hemarthrosis. The proposed mechanism of drug interaction was decreased gastrointestinal flora leading to decreased vitamin K production. The authors recommended assessing anticoagulation shortly after initiation of antibiotic therapy in patients stabilized on warfarin therapy.</p>
<p>Warfarin [“Coumadin”]</p>
<p>Ceftaroline [“Teflaro”]</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Bohm NM &amp; Crosby B (NM Bohm, Department of Clinical Pharmacy and Outcomes Sciences, College of Pharmacy, Medical University of South Carolina, Charleston, SC; e-mail: <email>bohm@musc.edu</email>) Hemarthrosis in a patient on warfarin receiving ceftaroline: a case report and brief review of cephalosporin interaction with warfarin. <italic>Ann Pharmacother</italic> 46:e19 (Jul) 2012</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0069477012462188">
<title>3,4-Methylenedioxymethamphetamine No. 227</title>
<sec id="section8-0069477012462188">
<title>Valvular Heart Disease (First Report<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0069477012462188">*</xref>)</title>
<p>A 33-year-old male developed shortness of breath and chest pain after prolonged exposure to 3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine (MDMA, “ecstasy”), claimed to be several pills per week for the preceding 16 years. No concomitant medications were consumed and the only risk factor was active tobacco use. A new systolic and diastolic mitral murmur was diagnosed and subsequent electrocardiogram revealed right bundle branch block. Echocardiogram was consistent with mitral valve disease with moderate to severe mitral stenosis associated with severe mitral regurgitation. Pulmonary hypertension without right heart failure was present. Treatment included resection of chordae tendineae and mitral valve replacement with mechanical prosthesis. Causes for valvular heart disease were ruled out, including rheumatic and Barlow disease, other common diseases (Osler endocarditis, carcinoid syndrome, rheumatic fever, and autoimmune disorders), and intake of additional drugs. One month later, chest pain recurred with fatigue and weight loss. Transthoracic echocardiography revealed paraprosthetic leak with prosthesis dehiscence, and reoperation was performed with fixation. No further complications arose on follow-up.</p>
<p>The authors concluded that valvular heart disease was due to long-term exposure to MDMA. The proposed mechanism was activation of 5-HT2B receptors similarly to appetite-suppressant-induced valvular heart disease.</p>
<p>3,4-Methylenedioxymethamphetamine [“MDMA,” “Ecstasy”]</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Montastruc F et al (JL Montastruc, Laboratoire de Pharmacologie, Medicale et Clinique, Faculte de Medecine, 37 allees Jule-Guesde, 31000 Toulouse, France; e-mail: <email>jean-louise.montastruc@univ-tsle.fr</email>) Valvular heart disease in a patient taking 3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine (MDMA, “Ecstasy”). <italic>Br J Clin Pharmacol</italic> 74:547–548 (Sep) 2012</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0069477012462188">
<title>Tattoo Ink No. 228</title>
<sec id="section10-0069477012462188">
<title><italic>Mycobacterium chelonae</italic> Infection</title>
<p>Based on a single case report of an initial outbreak of tattoo associated <italic>Mycobacterium chelonae</italic> skin and soft tissue infections in Rochester, New York, an investigation was performed to further evaluate the incidence and form of transmission of a possible cause–effect relationship. Based on the data collected between October and December 2011, raised erythematous rashes developed in 19 individuals (13 men, 6 women; mean age = 35 years) within 3 weeks of receiving a tattoo from a single artist who used premixed gray ink. Of the 19 cases identified, 14 were confirmed, 4 were considered probable, and 1 was suspected. The rashes were confined to the areas of the skin that were tattooed. Biopsy specimens obtained in 17 cases revealed sparse lymphohistiocytic infiltrates in the upper dermis in 12 of the cases. The Centers for Disease Control confirmed the isolation of <italic>Mycobacterium chelonae</italic> in the cases identified and in 1 of 3 unopened bottles of gray wash ink. As a result of the investigation, the manufacturer voluntarily recalled the ink. Appropriate antimicrobial therapy (macrolides, doxycycline, or both based on sensitivity) was initiated in 18 of the 19 patients resulting in improvement of symptoms.</p>
<p>The authors concluded that these patients experienced tattoo-associated <italic>Mycobacterium chelonae</italic> skin and soft tissue infections related to contaminated ink.</p>
<p>Tattoo Ink [Tattoo Ink]</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Kennedy BS et al (BS Kennedy, Monroe County Department of Public Health, 111 Westfall Rd, Room 950, Rochester, NY 14620; e-mail: <email>bkennedy@monroecounty.gov</email>) Outbreak of <italic>Mycobacterium chelonae</italic> infection associated with tattoo ink [published online August 22, 2012]. <italic>N Engl J Med</italic>. doi:10.1056/NEJMoal1205114.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0069477012462188">
<title>Sildenafil No. 229</title>
<sec id="section12-0069477012462188">
<title>FDA Safety Alert: Recommendation Against Use in Children</title>
<p>On August 30, 2012, the FDA notified health professionals regarding a significant labeling change for sildenafil related to new safety data. The FDA has recommended that this agent should not be prescribed to children (ages 1 through 17) for pulmonary arterial hypertension based on a recent long-term clinical pediatric trial. The study, a randomized, double-blind, multicenter, placebo-controlled, parallel-group, dose-ranging clinical trial, enrolled 234 pediatric pulmonary arterial hypertension patients with mild to moderate symptoms to receive either low-, medium-, or high-dose Revatio (sildenafil; administered 3 times per day) or placebo for 16 weeks of treatment. The main outcome was the effect of sildenafil on exercise capacity as measured by the Cardiopulmonary Exercise Test in patients who were developmentally able to perform the test (n = 115). After completing the 16-week controlled clinical trial, patients randomized to sildenafil remained on the same dose; patients originally randomized to placebo were rerandomized to low, medium, or high dose. After all patients completed 16 weeks of follow-up in the controlled clinical trial, the blind was broken and doses were adjusted as clinically indicated. Patients were followed for a mean of 3 years (range = 0-7 years) and a direct dose-related effect on mortality was observed with the highest dose having the worst outcome. The hazard ratio for high dose compared to low dose was 3.5 (<italic>P</italic> = .015).</p>
<p>Sildenafil [“Revatio”]</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>FDA Drug Safety Communication: FDA recommends against the use of Revatio in children with pulmonary arterial hypertension. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fda.gov/Drugs/DrugSafety/ucm317123.htm">http://www.fda.gov/Drugs/DrugSafety/ucm317123.htm</ext-link> (Aug 30) 2012</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0069477012462188">
<title>Minocycline No. 230</title>
<sec id="section14-0069477012462188">
<title>Fulminant Intracranial Hypertension</title>
<p>A 12-year-old girl developed headaches and progressive nausea within 1 week after starting minocycline (dosage not provided). Despite discontinuing the medication after 3 weeks of therapy, the headaches worsened and the patient noticed postural transient visual obscurations. Shortly after, the patient experienced bilateral vision loss. An ophthalmological exam 1 week later revealed a left relative afferent pupillary defect, bilateral abducens nerve palsies, and severe disc edema in both eyes. A magnetic resonance imaging of the brain demonstrated normal intracranial contents without hydrocephalus, bilateral transverse venous sinus stenosis, flattening of the posterior globes, and tortuous optic nerves in both eyes. A lumbar puncture demonstrated a cerebral spinal fluid opening pressure of 50 cm of water. The patient was hospitalized and therapy with acetazolamide (500 mg twice daily) was initiated. Though the headaches and nausea resolved, visual acuity worsened with only light perception. Severe disc edema with cotton wool spots and peripapillary hemorrhages were observed. Bilateral sequential optic nerve sheath fenestrations were performed and intravenous methylprednisolone was added to the acetazolamide therapy. A week after the second nerve sheath fenestration, visual acuity improved to 20/80 in the right eye with hand motions in the left eye. Three months after the initial presentation, the patient was neurologically stable with visual acuity stabilized at 20/50 in the right eye and counting fingers in the left eye.</p>
<p>The authors concluded that this patient experienced increased intracranial pressure with severe vision loss and progressive symptomatic deterioration despite improvement in pressures. They noted that the severity of vision loss and speed of onset suggested an involvement of ischemia affecting the optic nerve heads.</p>
<p>Minocycline [“Minocin”]</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Fraser CL et al (NJ Newman, Neurophthalmology, 1365 Clifton Rd, NE, Atlanta, GA 30322; e-mail: <email>ophtnjn@emory.edu</email>) Minocycline-induced fulminant intracranial hypertension. <italic>Arch Neurol</italic> 69:1067–1070 (Aug) 2012</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0069477012462188">
<title>Angiotensin-Converting Enzyme Inhibitors, Angiotensin Receptor Blockers No. 231</title>
<sec id="section16-0069477012462188">
<title>Risk of Pneumonia</title>
<p>A systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials and cohort and case–control studies evaluated the use of angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors and angiotensin receptor blockers and the risk of pneumonia (primary objective) and pneumonia-related mortality (secondary objective). A search of electronic databases yielded 807 published studies, of which 29 studies were included for analysis. In addition, 8 additional studies were identified in FDA regulatory documents. A total of 37 studies were included in the analysis: 18 randomized controlled trials, 11 cohort studies, 2 nested case–control studies, and 6 case-control studies. Primary outcome data for angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors or angiotensin receptor blockers compared with controls was available from 19 and 11 studies, respectively. Two trials compared angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors with angiotensin receptor blockers. Use of angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors was associated with a significant reduction in risk of pneumonia compared with controls (odds ratio = 0.66; 95% confidence interval = 0.55-0.80). However, the risk of pneumonia was not different in patients who used or did not use angiotensin receptor blockers (odds ratio = 0.95; 95% confidence interval = 0.87-1.04). In patients with stroke, the risk of pneumonia was also reduced with angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors (odds ratio = 0.46; 95% confidence interval = 0.34-0.62) and angiotensin receptor blockers (odds ratio = 0.42: 95% confidence interval = 0.22-0.80).</p>
<p>The authors concluded that, based on a review and analysis of published evidence, angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors but not angiotensin receptor blockers affect the risk of pneumonia in patients taking such therapy.</p>
<p>Angiotensin-Converting Enzyme Inhibitors [“Captopril,” “Lisinopril,” “Enalapril,” “Fosinopril”]</p>
<p>Angiotensin Receptor Blockers [“Losartan,” “Candesartan”]</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Caldeira D et al (J Costa, Portuguese Cochrane Centre, Faculty of Medicine, University of Lisbon; e-mail: <email>jncosta@fm.ul.pt</email>) Risk of pneumonia associated with use of angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors and angiotensin receptor blockers: systematic review and meta-analysis. <italic>BMJ</italic> 345:e4260 (Jul) 2012</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0069477012462188">
<title>Psychotropics No. 232</title>
<sec id="section18-0069477012462188">
<title>Risk of Hip Fracture</title>
<p>The association of hip fracture risk and psychotropic drug use in the elderly was evaluated in a meta-analysis of 24 studies: 14 related to antidepressant use and 10 related to antipsychotic use. The summary of odds ratio were 1.68 for first-generation or conventional antipsychotics (1.43-1.99), 1.30 (1.14-1.49) for second-generation (atypical) antipsychotics, 1.71 (1.43-2.04) for first-generation antidepressants, and 1.94 (1.37-2.76) for second-generation antidepressants.</p>
<p>The authors concluded that first-generation and second-generation antipsychotics and antidepressants are associated with an increased risk of hip fracture in older adults. They noted that there is some uncertainty regarding the role of medications as causal factors in falls in the elderly. Additional studies with a sufficient population of older patients taking these medications are needed.</p>
<p>First-Generation Antidepressants [“Amitriptyline,” “Nortriptyline,” “Pamelor,” “Desipramine”]</p>
<p>Second-Generation Antidepressants [“SSRIs,” “SRNIs,” “Bupropion,” “Mirtazapine,” “Trazodone”]</p>
<p>First-Generation Antipsychotics [“Haloperidol,” “Thorazine”]</p>
<p>Second-Generation Antipsychotics [“Apriprazole,” “Risperidone,” “Ziprasidone,” “Quetiapine”]</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Oderda LH et al (LH Oderda, Department of Pharmacotherapy, College of Pharmacy, University of Utah, Salt Lake City, UT; e-mail: <email>Lynda.oderda@hsc.utah.edu</email>) Psychotropic-related hip fractures: meta-analysis of first-generation and second-generation antidepressant and antipsychotic drugs. <italic>Ann Pharmacother</italic> 46:917–928 (Jul) 2012</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0069477012462188">
<title>Clarithromycin, Fluconazole, Montelukast No. 233</title>
<sec id="section20-0069477012462188">
<title>Drug Interaction: Effects on Montelukast Pharmacokinetics</title>
<p>The effects of clarithromycin and fluconazole on the kinetics of montelukast were evaluated in 12 healthy male volunteers in a 4-phase crossover study. A period of 2 weeks separated each study phase. In phase I, each participant received a single dose of oral montelukast (10 mg). In phase II, each participant received oral clarithromycin (1000 mg once daily) for 3 days with montelukast also administered on the third day. In phase III, a single oral dose of oral fluconazole (50 mg) was administered once daily for 7 days with concurrent montelukast administration on day 7. In phase IV, a single oral dose of fluconazole (150 mg) was administered once daily for 7 days with concurrent montelukast administration on day 7. The coadministration of clarithromycin with montelukast significantly increased the area under the curve (3.946 vs 9.663 µg/h/mL) and maximum concentration (0.473 vs 0.814 µg/mL) of montelukast compared with montelukast administration alone. In addition, coadministration of clarithromycin and montelukast resulted in a significant increase in the half-life of montelukast when compared with montelukast administration alone (7.101 vs 12.58 hours). In contrast, there was no significant effect on the time to maximum concentration with concurrent administration (3.375 vs 3.541 hours). Coadministration of fluconazole (either 50 or 150 mg) significantly decreased the area under the curve (2.41 vs 2.73 vs 3.94 µg/h/mL) and maximum concentration (0.26 vs 0.29 vs 0.47 µg/h) of montelukast compared with montelukast alone. In contrast, the time to maximum concentration of montelukast was significantly increased with coadministration of either dose of fluconazole (50 mg and 150 mg) compared with montelukast alone (4.83 vs 4.66 vs 3.37 hours).</p>
<p>The authors concluded that the coadministration of clarithromycin increased the plasma concentrations of montelukast and fluconazole reduced the plasma concentrations of montelukast. The mechanism of action beyond cytochrome P450 hepatic enzyme metabolism may be attributed to interference of the interacting drugs with transporters mediating the uptake of montelukast.</p>
<p>Clarithromycin [“Biaxin”]</p>
<p>Fluconazole [“Diflucan”]</p>
<p>Montelukast [“Singulair”]</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Hegazy SK et al (NO Mansour, Bioavailability Unit, Faculty of Pharmacy, Tanta University, Tanta 8310, Egypt; e-mail: <email>n2osama@hotmail.com</email>) Effect of clarithromycin and fluconazole on the pharmacokinetics of montelukast in human volunteers. <italic>Eur J Cin Pharmacol</italic> 68:1275–1280 (Sep) 2012</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-0069477012462188">
<title>Amitriptyline No. 234</title>
<sec id="section22-0069477012462188">
<title>Delayed Onset Seizure, Cardiac Arrest After Overdose</title>
<p>A 13-year-old patient developed delayed seizures and cardiac arrest after amitriptyline ingestion (unknown quantity). A repeat electrocardiogram, performed 7 hours postingestion, revealed mild intraventricular conduction delay, with a QRS interval of 102 ms. Approximately 19 hours postingestion, the patient experienced a tonic–clonic seizure and cardiac arrest. Treatment included sodium bicarbonate infusion, supplemental midazolam, epinephrine, magnesium sulfate, and intravenous lidocaine. Intravenous lipid emulsion was also started. An magnetic resonance imaging of the brain performed 7 days postingestion was normal. The patient developed substantial hypertriglyceridemia and pancreatitis after lipid emulsion therapy.</p>
<p>The authors concluded that this case represented delayed seizures and cardiac arrest with amitriptyline overdose, which when treated with lipid emulsion therapy also resulted in iatrogenic complications.</p>
<p>Amitriptyline [“Elavil”]</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Levine M et al (M Levine, Department of Emergency Medicine, Section of Medical Toxicology, University of Southern California, 1200 North State St, #1011, Los Angeles, CA 90033; e-mail: <email>mdlevine@usc.edu</email>) Delayed-onset seizure and cardiac arrest after amitriptyline overdose, treated with intravenous lipid emulsion therapy. <italic>Pediatrics</italic> 130:e432–e438 (Aug) 2012</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-0069477012462188">
<title>Levetiracetam No. 235</title>
<sec id="section24-0069477012462188">
<title>Drug Reaction with Eosinophilia and Systemic Symptoms Syndrome</title>
<p>A 31-year-old male developed fever and dyspnea while receiving levetiracetam (1 g twice daily for 49 days) for generalized tonic–clonic seizures associated with low-grade astrocytoma. Concurrent dexamethasone therapy (tapered from 12 mg daily) was discontinued on day 45 of levetiracetam therapy. On admission, vitals were significant for temperature of 39°C, heart rate 103 beats per minute, and blood pressure 106/60 mm Hg. Chest X-ray revealed bilateral interstitial pattern with vascular blurring, and computer tomography revealed mediastinal and subcarinal lymph nodes and bilateral peribronchial areas with patchy increased density. Significant laboratory results included elevated acute-phase reactants, lactate dehydrogenase, and leukocytosis (11.9/µL) with 81.4% neutrophils and 0.9% eosinophils. Treatment included dexamethasone 6 mg for 4 days followed by dexamethasone 4 mg for 2 days. Readmission occurred after 4 days due to fever, dyspnea, erythematous maculopapular rash involving face and upper trunk, and facial edema. Significant findings included chest X-ray revealing bilateral interstitial infiltration, hypoxemia (P<sc>o</sc><sub>2</sub> 73 mm Hg), hypotension (100/60 mm Hg), impaired liver function, and increased acute-phase reactants. Potential infectious and autoimmune etiologies were excluded. Due to suspicion of drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms syndrome, levetiracetam was discontinued and alternative anticonvulsant therapy with phenytoin was initiated. Acute symptoms resolved in the following week with complete resolution of laboratory values at 2-month follow-up.</p>
<p>The authors concluded that drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms syndrome was caused by levetiracetam therapy. They denied ability to comment on risk minimization; however, they advised to avoid rechallenge in patients with previous drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms syndrome hypersensitivity reaction to levetiracetam.</p>
<p>Levetiracetam [“Keppra”]</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Gomez-Zorrilla S et al (S Gomez-Zorrilla, Infectious Disease Service, Bellvitge University Hospital, Bellvitge Biomedical Research Institute, University of Barcelona, Spain; e-mail: <email>sgomez@bellvitgehospital.cat</email>) Levetiracetam-induced drug reaction with eosinophilia and systemic symptoms syndrome. <italic>Ann Pharmacother</italic> 46:e20 (Jul) 2012</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section25-0069477012462188">
<title>Adverse Drug Reactions No. 236</title>
<sec id="section26-0069477012462188">
<title>Analysis of Spontaneous European Reporting System: 2007-2009</title>
<p>In a retrospective observational study, data on the reporting activity of adverse drug reactions were evaluated in 26 European countries during the years 2007 through 2009. Data were collected primarily via questionnaires and annual reports. The reporting ratio was defined as the total number of adverse drug reaction reports received in a safety database per year related to population size, density of physicians, or expenditure on health. The mean number of recorded adverse drug reaction reports per year in the period 2007 though 2009 was 201 042 in EudraVigilance and 119 097 in the reporting countries reviewed. The number of spontaneous reports increased each year. The population-based reporting ratio was correlated to the total expenditure on health care, public expenditure on health, the density of physicians, and the expenditure on pharmaceuticals.</p>
<p>The authors concluded that the relevance of the population based reporting ratio measurement as a reporting activity is clearly supported by current findings. They also suggested that further study would be helpful in assessing the effectiveness of reporting systems at both the national and European levels.</p>
<p>Adverse Drug Reactions [Adverse Drug Reactions]</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Srba J et al (J Srba, U Vodojemu 1685, Nachod 547 01, Czech Republic; e-mail: <email>jindrich.srba@gmail.com</email>) Adverse drug reactions: analysis of spontaneous reporting system in Europe in 2007-2009. <italic>Eur J Clin Pharmacol</italic> 68:1057–1063 (Jul) 2012</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section27-0069477012462188">
<title>Dabigatran No. 237</title>
<sec id="section28-0069477012462188">
<title>Hemopericardium and Cardiac Tamponade</title>
<p>Two cases of dabigatran associated hemopericardium were described.</p>
<p><italic>Patient 1</italic>. A 70-year-old male was receiving dabigatran (150 mg twice daily) for 3 months for treatment of atrial fibrillation. Admission occurred due to mild cough, fatigue, and bloody stools. Concurrent medications included aspirin (81 mg daily) and pantoprazole (40 mg daily). Significant laboratory results included elevated serum creatinine (baseline 1.1 mg/dL, elevated to 6.26 mg/dL), serum potassium (8.2 mEq/L), and international normalized ratio greater than 6. A hemoccult stool test was positive, hemoglobin and hematocrit were at baseline (10.9 g/dL and 33.7%, respectively), and pleural effusion was revealed by chest X-ray and confirmed with bedside ultrasound. After progressing to respiratory failure, treatment with intubation, broad spectrum antibiotic therapy (vancomycin, piperacillin/tazobactam, and azithromycin), vasopressin, and norepinephrine was initiated with little improvement. A computed tomography revealed large hyperdense pericardial effusion. Pericardiocentesis with removal of 1000 mL hemorrhagic fluid was performed and led to hemodynamic improvement with weaning of vasopressors. Hemoglobin decreased to 6.7 mg/dL and was corrected with 2 units of packed red blood cells. Dabigatran was held during admission and switched to warfarin on discharge.</p>
<p><italic>Patient 2.</italic> A 77-year-old female received 6 doses of dabigatran (150 mg twice daily) for new onset atrial fibrillation. Concurrent medications included aspirin 81 mg. Admission initially occurred for health care–associated pneumonia and new onset atrial fibrillation was discovered on electrocardiogram. Laboratory values on admission revealed elevated white blood cell count (14.7/µL), serum creatinine at baseline (1.22 mg/dL), international normalized ratio 1.21, and hemoglobin 11.6 g/d. Treatment included piperacillin/tazobactam and vancomycin for health care–associated pneumonia and dabigatran for atrial fibrillation. Respiratory distress occurred with severe abdominal pain and progressed to shock. Treatment included intubation, intravenous 0.9% NaCl, dopamine, and norepinephrine. Antibiotic therapy was changed to linezolid and meropenem and subsequently discontinued after negative blood cultures. Echocardiogram revealed pericardial effusion with right ventricular diastolic compression leading to cardiac tamponade. Aspirin and dabigatran were discontinued. Over the following 7 days, a total of 2000 mL bloody pericardial fluid was removed and 8 units of packed red blood cells was transfused to maintain hemoglobin and hematocrit (nadir 7.5 g/dL and 22.8%, respectively). Hemodialysis was also initiated due to acute renal failure. Anticoagulation was not reinitiated on discharge.</p>
<p>The authors concluded that these cases demonstrated the potential of dabigatran to cause serious bleeding events, especially in the setting of acute renal failure.</p>
<p>Dabigatran [“Pradaxa”]</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Dy EA &amp; Shiltz DL (EA Dy, Department of Pharmacy, Indiana University Health, Department of Pharmacy Practice, College of Pharmacy and Health Sciences, Butler University, Indianapolis, IN; e-mail: <email>edy@iuhealth.org</email>) Hemopericardium and cardiac tamponade associated with dabigatran use. <italic>Ann Pharmacother</italic> 46:e18 (Jul) 2012</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section29-0069477012462188">
<title>Dietary Supplement No. 238</title>
<sec id="section30-0069477012462188">
<title>FDA Safety Alert: Undeclared Pharmacologically Active Ingredients</title>
<p>On August 31, 2012, the FDA announced a recall of a dietary supplement that contained ephedrine alkaloids, making it an unapproved drug. This recall affects all lot codes and use by dates of EphBurn 25. Adverse events reported with ephedrine alkaloids include elevated blood pressure, rapid heartbeat, nerve damage, muscle injury, and psychosis and memory loss. More serious effects have also been reported, including heart attack, stroke, seizure, and death.</p>
<p>Dietary Supplement [“EphBurn25”]</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>FDA Safety Alert: EphBurn 25 dietary supplement by Brand New Energy: Recall—Undeclared drug ingredient. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch/SafetyInformation/SafetyAlertsforHumanMedicalProducts/ucm317780.htm">http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch/SafetyInformation/SafetyAlertsforHumanMedicalProducts/ucm317780.htm</ext-link> (Aug 31) 2012</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
</article>