<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="product-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CSX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcsx</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Contemp Sociol</journal-id>
<journal-title>Contemporary Sociology: A Journal of Reviews</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0094-3061</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1939-8638</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0094306112457769p</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0094306112457769p</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Pesticide Drift and the Pursuit of Environmental Justice</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>McNall</surname><given-names>Scott G.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0094306112457769">California State University, Chico</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0094306112457769"><email>Smcnall@csuchico.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>41</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>639</fpage>
<lpage>640</lpage>
<product><source>Pesticide Drift and the Pursuit of Environmental Justice</source>, by <person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>Jill Lindsey</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The MIT Press</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>. <page-count count="277"/>pp. <price>$23.00</price> paper. ISBN: <isbn>9780262516280</isbn>.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© American Sociological Association 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">American Sociological Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Driving down from my home in the foothills of the Sierra mountain range, I can literally see the Valley air. In the spring time, when the almonds begin to blossom, there is a chemical haze over the landscape, made up of pollution from cars, dust from fields being tilled and from the toxic brew of chemicals spayed on fields and orchards. Driving south into the Central Valley where Jill Harrison did her field work, I can see the occasional small plane dumping its load of chemicals, and looking to either side of the major north-south freeway, I-5, I can see large tractors pulling machines that pour pesticides and herbicides on fields and on emerging crops in the agro-industry’s “war” on insects and weeds. Most consumers do not think about what goes on behind the scenes that provide them with a bounty of rice, lettuce, strawberries, peaches, plums, nectarines, almonds, apricots, and artichokes—and most have no idea that people who work in the fields tending and harvesting these crops are being poisoned.</p>
<p>Harrison conducted field research between 2001-2009 and talked to over 100 people from environmental justice movements, regulators, scientists, agro-industrialists, and field workers. California was of particular interest to Harrison, because it is not only an economic powerhouse producing agricultural products worth $40 billion a year, but also a leader in environmental regulations and sustainable agricultural practices. Nevertheless, pesticide drift has been responsible for frightening and sickening people for years. One of the first incidents Harrison describes was in Earlimart, California in 1999 when 170 residences experienced nausea, fatigue, dizziness, vomiting, and burning eyes and lungs. In 2000, 35 elementary school children in Ventura County were exposed to a cloud of chlorpyrifos (an endocrine disruptor and reproductive toxin), which had drifted in from a nearby lemon orchard. Those most affected in cases of pesticide use are field workers and the residents of the small communities in the heart of the Central Valley. Harrison demonstrates in the presentation of her rich data set and in the development of her argument how legal status issues, language barriers, political disenfranchisement, and the other forms of social marginalization that are widespread in farm communities conspire to obscure pesticide problems. Pesticide drift is one of those “invisible” problems which impacts hundreds of people but about which we are blissfully unaware, until it affects our children and our community.</p>
<p>Harrison’s argument is not a standard one, for she recognizes that “environmental inequalities stem not only from a lack of knowledge, care, or political will but also from many actors’ attempts to do the right thing” (p. 11). Simply put, there are different conceptions of what constitutes justice. From <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0094306112457769">David Schlosberg (2007)</xref>, she draws out four components of justice and their relationship. If there is to be a socially just approach to pesticide use, four things must hold: those affected must be recognized as having a voice, those affected must have a real role in identifying and solving the problem, they must have an equal voice, and finally, participation should strengthen community or enhance civic engagement. The book is an extended illustration of how this dynamic works itself out and why the voices of farm workers, as well as victims and movement activists, are stilled.</p>
<p>She wisely focuses her field work on the stories that people tell about the problem, the evidence they use to support their claims, and the context within which ideas about pesticide use develop. There have been other excellent sociological studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0094306112457769">Auyero and Swinsun 2009</xref>) focused on how confusion develops among those most affected by environmental pollutants and why people are often slow to mobilize. They may not act because they lack a clear understanding of what the problem is and they are befuddled by the conflicting promises about what will be done to help them. The same is true with Harrison’s participants: there are competing definitions of justice grounded in social inequalities and the oppressive social relationships that contribute to the pesticide poisoning.</p>
<p>An important regulatory problem that Harrison identifies is the failure of California, and by extension other states, to apply the precautionary principle as is done in Europe. If a chemical is seen as having only a five percent chance of harming human health, it is often used in the United States, because of the “greater good,” (the need to produce food). If it is used correctly, argues the chemical industry, then the risk is minimized. The precautionary principle would demand however, that compelling scientific evidence would have to be presented that a pesticide was not hazardous <italic>before</italic> use. To illustrate this point, she focuses on the use of methyl iodide, a soil fumigant used on strawberries. Methyl iodide was invented by the chemical industry to replace methyl bromide. The use of methyl bromide was phased out as part of the Montreal Protocol (1987), because it contributed a small amount to greenhouse gas emissions. Methyl iodide was substituted to solve one problem but in brushing aside the precautionary principle it caused another. It is a powerful neurotoxin causing movement disorders that resemble Parkinson’s disease.</p>
<p>Harrison hopes that “With appropriate leadership from Congress during the Farm Bill deliberations, the USDA could commit a substantial portion of the federal agricultural budget allocations to research into alternative pest management practices. . .that [would] support growers who practice such methods . . .”(p. 203). The strength of her work for me was her clear identification of the seriousness of the problem of pesticide drift, her understanding of the science, and the detail with which she shows how many of the concepts of justice we adopt lead to an unsustainable future.</p>
<p>The audience for this book can and should extend beyond the field of environmental justice to those who make and enforce policy. Toxic clouds, like greenhouse gases, know no boundaries; the problems Harrison identifies affect us all. After reading the book, I made sure our County’s Deputy District Attorney, who prosecutes environmental crimes, received a copy.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0094306112457769">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Auyero</surname><given-names>Javier</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swinsun</surname><given-names>Débora Alejandra</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <source>Flammable: Environmental Suffering in an Argentine Shantytown</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0094306112457769">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schlosberg</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2007</year>. <source>Defining Environmental Justice: Theories, Movements, and Nature</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>