<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">HHC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sphhc</journal-id>
<journal-title>Home Health Care Management &amp; Practice</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1084-8223</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-6739</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1084822312472055</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1084822312472055</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Holistic Health and People With Spinal Cord Injuries</article-title>
<subtitle>Results of a Pilot Study With Canadian Rehabilitation Health Care Providers</subtitle></title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Shroff</surname><given-names>Farah M.</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1084822312472055">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sahota</surname><given-names>Inderjeet S.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MSc</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1084822312472055">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1084822312472055"><label>1</label>University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1084822312472055"><label>2</label>Simon Fraser University, Burnaby, British Columbia, Canada</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1084822312472055">Farah M. Shroff, Department of Family Practice and School of Population and Public Health, Faculty of Medicine, University of British Columbia, Third Floor David Strangway Building, 5950 University Blvd., Vancouver, BC V6T 1Z3, Canada. Email: <email>farah.shroff@ubc.ca</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>25</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>64</fpage>
<lpage>72</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2013 SAGE Publications</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>We examined the perspectives of rehabilitation professionals in British Columbia on the use of holistic practices (HP) by their clients with spinal cord injury (SCI). This was a qualitative descriptive study with 13 rehabilitation professionals.Results show that health care practitioners serving those with SCI noted interest in and use of HP between 75% and 90% among their client groups. Most rehabilitation professionals already work in an interdisciplinary fashion with HP practitioners. Some were skeptical about HP, others saw a great benefit to their clients and others still only pursued HP when asked about it by their clients. Conclusions are that health care professionals are willing to acquire more knowledge about HP to provide the best available care. Participants showed interest in incorporating other aspects of health care to aid rehabilitation.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>spinal cord injury</kwd>
<kwd>holistic health</kwd>
<kwd>complementary and alternative medicine</kwd>
<kwd>rehabilitation</kwd>
<kwd>perspectives</kwd>
<kwd>health care professionals</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Spinal cord injury (SCI) is a life-changing condition that affects approximately 86,000 Canadians.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1084822312472055">1</xref></sup> SCI causes dramatic functional deficits in motor, sensory, and autonomic neural control, which often require long-term care and assistance both physically and psychologically.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1084822312472055">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1084822312472055">3</xref></sup> After sustaining an SCI, patients experience many forms of health care: from short-term, intensive care in the hospital to longer term rehabilitative care in both specialist rehabilitation centers after surgery and at home and within the community. The considerable medical problems affecting individuals postinjury and the limited treatments available for individuals with SCI serve as driving forces to seek and practice alternative methods in managing their health.</p>
<p>Some studies show individuals with SCI are more likely than most to access complementary and alternative services<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1084822312472055">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1084822312472055">5</xref></sup> for their health care. For the purposes of this article, holistic health (used interchangeably with <italic>alternative</italic> or <italic>complementary</italic> medicine) will be defined as approaches to well-being and treatment of illness that focus on mind and body. Holistic self-care encompasses practices such as yoga, meditation, Tai Chi, Chi Gung, and is typified by a number of elements, such as an emphasis on the unity of body, mind, and spirit as well as a view of health as a positive state, not merely the absence of disease.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1084822312472055">6</xref></sup> Interest in holistic care is growing among health professionals and the general public in Canada and around the world.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1084822312472055">7</xref></sup> Previous studies have suggested that it would be beneficial for rehabilitation professionals to obtain more holistic practices (HP) knowledge to make more informed decisions for their clients, particularly because the uptake of HP for people with SCI is higher than average.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1084822312472055">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1084822312472055">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>In Canada, allopathic medical services are publicly funded. Almost all Canadians who experience trauma will therefore be treated in an acute allopathic facility. Rehabilitation professionals who specialize in SCI, including such professionals as surgeons, specialized physicians, physiotherapists, occupational therapists and social workers, are a highly specialized group. They are present at all stages following injury, facilitating the transitions from acute care to rehabilitation to community reintegration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1084822312472055">8</xref></sup> They provide services, education, and recommendations to their clients, which then influence their clients’ health choices and well-being. This group of professionals, having close contact and experience with spinal cord injured clients, are a valuable resource for understanding trends in health care and self-administered care as it relates to SCI. They provide a rich and unique perspective based on generalized knowledge from a multitude of clients and many years of experience. As these professionals provide much of the information on treatments for individuals with SCI, we were interested in determining the degree of knowledge rehabilitation professionals who work with SCI had in regard to alternative HP. This study, therefore, examines the knowledge and perspectives of rehabilitation professionals on HP accessed by their clients with SCI. This article primarily considers the attitudes of allopathic health care providers working with people with SCI toward holistic practices and the knowledge they have as to the potential and actual uses of such practices among people living with SCI.</p>
<sec id="section1-1084822312472055" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<p>We interviewed rehabilitation practitioners who care for those with SCI in British Columbia’s lower mainland. We asked three general questions to the rehabilitation providers: their client’s interest, views, and behaviors regarding HP; their own approaches, attitudes, and experiences with HP; and the systems that currently exist that promote or hinder the use of HP by people with SCI. Participants were not compensated for their time.</p>
<p>Several services in the lower mainland provide care and support to people living with SCI such as hospitals, rehabilitation centers and clinics, and community living establishments. For this study, we collected a sample of health care providers by initially contacting facilities known for their programs for people living with SCI.</p>
<p>Ethical approval was obtained from the ethics committee of the BC Paraplegic Association.</p>
<sec id="section2-1084822312472055">
<title>Study Design</title>
<p>We designed a questionnaire with open and closed questions, which was divided into three sections: background demographic information, client’s health, and practitioners’ knowledge and opinion of their client’s use of HP. The interviewer used probing questions and encouraged open discussion and elaboration on topics and welcomed questions and tangents during the discussions. We pretested questions with 2 participants and asked them to provide feedback regarding the format and comprehensiveness of questions. Interviews were conducted at the professionals’ place of work, save one that was conducted at the participant’s home, by request. Participants received copies of the questions during the one-on-one interview. We provided all participants with a one-page handout defining HP and outlining several practices in detail. Prior to the interview, all participants provided informed consent and agreed to be tape-recorded during the interview process.</p>
<p>After initial telephone contact, we conducted 13 in-person interviews with rehabilitation professionals. In addition to audio-recording, the interviewer took notes throughout the interview to gather data. Interviews varied between approximately 30 and 90 minutes. Taped interviews were transcribed and data was analyzed using qualitative methods of coding, diagramming, and thematic analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1084822312472055">
<title>Subject Recruitment and Analysis</title>
<p>After contacting members of the SCI care teams at three facilities we recruited participants through a snowball sampling technique.</p>
<p>The sample consisted of 13 health care professionals of diverse backgrounds. Five were male and 8 were female. Nine participants were employed within an SCI Program while 3 worked at a hospital. Two additional participants were recruited: one from a rehabilitation facility and the other from a postsecondary educational institution. Five of the participants were trained and licensed physiotherapists. Of these, one was an educator, another was a clinical practice leader for an SCI program, and another was a researcher and professor specializing in rehabilitation of SCI. Two physicians (the directors of the programs) were also interviewed. Additionally, one representative was chosen from each of the following professions: dietitian, practical nurse, clinical nurse specialist, occupational therapist, and recreational therapist. Years of experience in the field of SCI varied from 2 years to 28 years.</p>
<p>Some of the selected health care professionals had backgrounds in HP alongside their conventional medical training. Within this group of health care professionals, two people practiced acupuncture as part of their physiotherapy (one of whom was also certified in Reiki and craniosacral therapy); one nurse was a trained reflexologist; another physiotherapist had training in counseling psychology; and another nurse was part of the Vancouver Energy Training Network and the Canadian Nurses Holistic Professional Practice Group as well as certified by the Canadian Holistic Nurses Association.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1084822312472055" sec-type="results">
<title>Results and Discussion</title>
<sec id="section5-1084822312472055">
<title>Participants’ Views of Their Clients’ Health</title>
<p>Based on the data gathered from this sample, a number of SCI-related health concerns were brought to light. Many physical and nonphysical health problems were mentioned by health care providers.</p>
<p>Many health care professionals identified that the health needs of their clients vary according to degree of injury (e.g., complete or incomplete SCI), health prior to injury, and level of psychosocial and sociocultural supports and services. Social barriers were often mentioned. Accessibility is a major barrier to participation in physical activity and social events for people with SCI and other wheelchair users in general,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1084822312472055">9</xref></sup> as noted by 1 participant who stated that
<disp-quote>
<p>with people who use wheelchairs, the onus tends to be more on society to provide accessibility because they may want to do these things and they know what is important for their health but, in most instances, it’s not possible—it’s not feasible for them to actually do.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>When asked what they thought were the most important things their clients could do for their health, answers again included a broad array of physical, psychological, and psychosocial issues. Many remarked on the universality of these needs in that they apply to people of all ability levels. Self-education regarding living with a SCI, empowerment, and being an “educated consumer” of health care was stressed by our participants. Another common theme was the acceptance of their injury and the ability to “move on” from it. Participants offered these priorities:
<disp-quote>
<p>I think that the most important things to improve your health are to engage in things that are socially and emotionally healthy for you . . .</p>
<p>Trying to get people to move so that they have an internal sense of control . . . make choices around their health . . . the more people have a sense of influencing their own life, the less they become pawns in the whole system.</p>
<p>For their overall health, I think to just be active, to get involved in their community, however that is. It doesn’t have to be sports, just getting back, getting involved, not becoming isolated . . .</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>According to the participants interviewed, the health status of individuals with SCI is strongly determined by their mental state. Our participants concurred that the mindset of people with SCI greatly impacted the trajectory of their rehabilitation.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Their acute concerns are the fact that they’ve had this major change in their lives and so their focus is what’s going on with them right now as well as is there anything that can be done to get them back to where they were before.</p>
<p>People have these plans in their lives and suddenly these are derailed and you’re left picking up the pieces.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1084822312472055">
<title>Holistic Health Care Trends</title>
<p>The overall trend among participants in this study is that when treating the individual they see the whole person, rather than just the SCI, and wish this was the norm in general health care. They also wish there was greater communication across the various health care fields, including between themselves and HP professionals. One participant stated that
<disp-quote>
<p>there seems to be a greater understanding [in health care] of how everything operates to make a person whole and not just the physical [condition] . . . so in terms of an overall trend in health care . . . people are starting to see the person as a whole person and not just a problem.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Our participants, as illustrated by the following statements, identified the need for communication between various disciplines:
<disp-quote>
<p>Do I want to be on a committee that brings all those practices together with the rest of us? Yes. Do I think that they should be included with all the research we’re doing? Yes.</p>
<p>If you’re looking at the whole being, you can’t separate emotional from physical healing.</p>
<p>When people hear that there isn’t a single answer or an easy answer [from conventional medicine], I think it definitely does open up the possibility for a lot of, I call them, complementary therapies to come up.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Participants very clearly viewed the entire spectrum of well-being as critical to the work they provide. Because the vast majority of their clients experience depression as part of their SCI, rehabilitation professionals are accustomed to working in the realm of integrated mental, emotional, physical, social, and economic health.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1084822312472055">10</xref></sup> Our participants told us that they would like to see a shift in the entire health care system so that patients’ and clients’ whole health is taken into account. Many of our participants were keen to be part of this shift. This health policy issue raises larger questions about the publicly funded Canadian health care system and its need to shift toward a model of health and wellness and be more comprehensive in the services it provides.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1084822312472055">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1084822312472055">12</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1084822312472055">
<title>Health Care Professionals’ Knowledge of Holistic Practices</title>
<p>Depending on their places of work, participants had different levels of access to education regarding HP. One of the province’s premier rehabilitation centers provides a great deal of information and training sessions for staff and clients. At this center, continuing education sessions are made available to staff to inform them about holistic health modalities that are available in the community and to keep them informed about current trends. It is the same site that offers acupuncture, counseling services, biofeedback, music, and art therapy as well many other alternative therapies. Other rehabilitation centers do not appear to offer comparable services for staff or clients.</p>
<p>Our participants had varying degrees of knowledge with regard to HP. In addition, many said they acquired holistic health information from various sources such as peer-reviewed medical journals, the media (news, magazines), other literature, seminars, and from word-of-mouth from colleagues, friends, and family. Most of them had tried one or more modalities themselves, the most popular being yoga. Iridology, Chinese or Indigenous medicines, Ayurveda, hypnosis, and bodywork were less popular modalities with which very few participants seemed familiar. When asked about the information they had on HP responses, participants stated,
<disp-quote>
<p>I haven’t actually interacted a great deal with holistic health practices.</p>
<p>I haven’t gone looking for a lot of information on holistic health care.</p>
<p>We have quite a bit of information on things like dance, music, art, energy healing, Tai Chi, martial arts, yoga, meditation, massage.</p>
<p>At one point in my life, I was training to be a practitioner of holistic health practices . . . I’ve been interested in it for years.</p>
<p>I was born into a family of alternative therapy . . . my parents studied natural health . . . all different kinds of therapies have always fascinated me.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>When examining the academic and vocational training of our participants, it became apparent from our small sample size that different professions integrate holistic health to different extents. Among our participants, recreation therapists seem to have the most resources and broad-based education on HP, while physiotherapists appear to have the most practical training in techniques such as massage and acupuncture. On the other hand, physicians and dietitians participants had the least amount of exposure to HP. This is illustrated by comments such as
<disp-quote>
<p>We certainly do massage within our [<italic>physiotherapy</italic>] practice.</p>
<p>Recreation therapists’ education includes holistic health practice . . . the whole mind, spirit, body is what we learn in school.</p>
<p>Medical school, as I knew it, didn’t do a great job at delivering the goods in terms of holistic medicine. We tend to look at complementary therapies or holistic therapies as they fit into things that Western medicine has, perhaps, identified them as being potentially useful for . . . we learn about little tidbits of what the holistic health care profession has to offer in terms of the problems that dominate Western medicine.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>All our participants said that they would like to learn more about HP. Some had specific questions that they would like to have answered while others wished that a more extensive body of information existed as well as more evidence-based research to allow for the evaluation of HP. The following statements provide an overview of these interests and the desire to fill knowledge gaps in the field of HP.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>In my role as a therapist, if it’s known that there are certain [<italic>holistic health</italic>] practices that are helpful, for the total wellness of people with SCI, well then yes, I would like to know that.</p>
<p>I’d like to know more about all of them [<italic>holistic health practices</italic>]!</p>
<p>I think that there are probably lots of things that we should learn more about and try out and it would be good to do some research on some of these things in SCI.</p>
<p>I think that it’s important to provide research.</p>
<p>When you provide information to someone on a proactive basis, it comes across as condoning or promoting that service, and I can’t be in a position to do that unless I know that it’s going to help someone.</p>
<p>I’m always a little bit concerned about our ability to make referrals in a rational way that anyone would find defensible.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Most participants were keen to further their understanding of HP although many raised concerns about the credibility of these practices and their usefulness in the rehabilitation process.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1084822312472055">
<title>The Role of Holistic Practices in Professionals’ Jobs</title>
<p>The role that HP plays in the rehabilitation provider’s interactions with people with SCI again varied greatly within and across professions and individuals. This may have been due to personal interests in the topic, with some participants choosing to seek out holistic practices of benefit when caring for people with SCI. Some participants actively incorporated HP within their work such as the physiotherapists trained in acupuncture. Some provided referrals (to activities or individual practitioners) or recommendations while others felt limited in their ability to endorse other types of services or practitioners. Others still dealt only with HP issues as they arose generally when their clients asked them for information on HP. The following responses illustrate the roles HP can play within conventional health care and the individual variety that exists within. Responses are divided, in order, into those participants who would actively talk to clients about HP, those participants who were aware of HP but not actively promoting it, and those participants who would only seek more information regarding HP if a client enquired.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>I do talk to people about relaxation, meditation, imagery, etc, for pain management as well as talking about the physiology behind it.</p>
<p>We use it as a way of promoting people to get involved again in their community or health . . . [HP] promote community integration as well as pain management and relaxation.</p>
<p>I know that people in the hospital have those things [<italic>holistic health practices</italic>] done so I’m kind of around it on the outskirts but not directly involved in it . . . Although we don’t provide it formally, it’s certainly welcome.</p>
<p>If a client asked me about a specific holistic health practice, I would certainly go and resource them and find out as much as possible . . . and then come back and have a discussion with them about what I’d found.</p>
<p>I’m more than happy to look at information; I’m happy to help someone work through the information that they brought to me, but I don’t actively sell any particular treatment that I’m not familiar with.</p>
<p>If I feel able to assess the competency of a specific practitioner then I might pass their name on and if I’m really not able to, I won’t. It’s up to them [<italic>clients</italic>] to find out.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In general, to varying degrees, participants were keen to seek and/or promote HP services to clients if they felt it would be helpful. Those participants with more experience and knowledge of HP were keener than those without to promote HP services to their clients. All participants, however, were interested in seeking whatever treatment would be helpful for their client, regardless of whether these treatments were those traditionally used in Western allopathic medicine or used as complementary and alternative medicines.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1084822312472055">
<title>Approaches Taken by Health Care Providers When Considering Holistic Health Practices</title>
<p>The majority of respondents said that it was important to maintain good rapport with their clients to better help them make informed decisions about their health care. Some participants in the sample actively promoted HP while others sought out information or encouraged clients to find and assess therapies for themselves. There was an overall view that clients “need to find what works for them” and that “whatever works is good.” When asked to define their approaches to HP and SCI, our participants gave responses that fit into 5 general categories: (a) HP are something all patients can engage in to aid their treatment, (b) rehabilitation professionals should maintain an open mind in the context of HP and care, (c) HP can play a role in rehabilitation, (d) HP should be screened by the basis of their scientific merit, and (e) HP should be used with caution. The participants had the following to say.</p>
<list id="list1-1084822312472055" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>1. HP are something all patients can engage in to aid their treatment:</p></list-item></list>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Holistic health practices are becoming more prevalent in our society in general and I think that they have a lot to offer to everybody—especially people that do have physical issues.</p>
<p>I promote it because I think that Western medicine has typically, over the years, totally been ignorant of the benefits of Eastern medicine which has been used and proven and utilized for thousands of years; but we, in our innate wisdom, don’t want to take anything that isn’t Canadian or American . . . I believe that they [<italic>Western and Eastern medicine</italic>] should work hand-in-hand.</p>
<p>I’m quite open-minded to a lot of alternative therapies.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<list id="list2-1084822312472055" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>2. Rehabilitation professionals should maintain an open mind in the context of HP and care:</p></list-item></list>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>You can’t be limiting in your approach with people as a professional. You can’t say: “this is all that we do, this is all that we promote” . . . I hope that it doesn’t get lost—the alternative ways of health promotion and teaching people how to lead healthy lives.</p>
<p>With a lot of holistic health practices, I think there’s a lot of really healthy ways and philosophies of looking at your body . . . a lot of them, not all of them, put you more in tune with your body and not be passive and let some health practitioner just give them drugs to take . . .</p>
<p>I would encourage people to try different things but I would encourage them to do so in a more customer savvy way . . . I am certainly not opposed . . . I think that there are things outside the mainstream medical system that are so different that can be really valuable.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<list id="list3-1084822312472055" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>3. HP can play a role in rehabilitation:</p></list-item></list>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>I think that it can play a role for any patient who wants to engage in that.</p>
<p>If someone believes that something works for them, you can’t discount the power of believing in something.</p>
<p>I think that it’s an important aspect of people’s health, or can be . . . it’s a valid area to search out but I think within everyone they have to find what works for them.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<list id="list4-1084822312472055" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>4. HP should be screened by the basis of their scientific merit:</p></list-item></list>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Basically, I ask them to take a scientific approach in whichever system they look at whether it’s conventional medicine or expectations for rehabilitation or the holistic alternative and complementary approaches.</p>
<p>A lot of them can be really helpful in combination with more conservative biomedical medicine.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<list id="list5-1084822312472055" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>5. HP should be used with caution:</p></list-item></list>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>I think that I’m certainly not opposed . . . I think that I’m cautiously interested.</p>
<p>In general I say with a healthy degree of skepticism, I’m open to anything as long as it doesn’t cause them damage . . . I’m able to try any of those [<italic>holistic health practices</italic>]. I don’t see why anybody else shouldn’t.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Some respondents, although in general, open to the idea of HP use during rehabilitation, urged caution in using them. If HP were not causing their patients harm these respondents were open to the idea of their clients using alternative therapies. One quote in particular echo the sentiment of most respondents who participated in this study; namely, as no outright cure for SCI is currently available, perhaps it is wrong to deny patients access to HP which may help curb some of the long-term effects of the injury and treatments
<disp-quote>
<p>If they are paying for them and they think they’re working, you can’t take hope away from someone and if it is working, hey! If conventional medicine isn’t necessarily working and if they are seeing an improvement [with HP], who am I to say “no?”</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Other participants offered concerns regarding HP practitioners not being able to deliver on some of their concerns.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>People who have had an injury badly want to recover and if someone promises those kinds of things, I think that there is a vulnerability there and I have some reservations . . . if all of these people are ethical in terms of the way they provide services and they don’t make promises that will not be delivered on then I fully encourage people . . . holistic care can provide some things that conventional, Western medicine does not provide.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In general, participants perceived HP to be a positive addition to an individual’s rehabilitation and were open to their patients using such therapies provided they were not causing harm.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1084822312472055">
<title>Concerns of Health Care Providers With Regard to Holistic Practices and Clients With SCI</title>
<p>Health care providers voiced several concerns regarding HP throughout the interviews. Overall, these concerns arose from their desire to ensure their clients received optimal care. They included lack of regulation of HP services and products, perceived lack of research substantiating the use of certain treatments, contraindications with conventional treatments, the promotion of “false hope,” and unethical practice by holistic health practitioners. None were opposed to HP but some concerns were evident—as exemplified by the following statements:
<disp-quote>
<p>I’m always just the tiniest bit skeptical in the amount of diligence with complementary medicine.</p>
<p>Some of my reluctance or resistance comes in the whole thing of that sense of who regulates it and makes sure that people aren’t taken advantage of.</p>
<p>And quite often with supplementation, I’m a little wary because it seems like people are being preyed on. They are very expensive supplements that are being marketed to people that may not have the financial means to be buying them, but the idea of hope and recovery suck them in.</p>
<p>Some people just go to weekend courses and get these little diplomas to stick up everywhere and say “I’m an authority at this” and it’s about getting as many of those so that if they don’t sell you on one thing, they can sell you on something else. They do so because they are just trying to make the bucks and because it’s nonregulated you can charge whatever you want. It doesn’t make for ethical practice and it can be very self-serving.</p>
<p>We’ve had a couple of cases where they’ve [<italic>holistic health therapies</italic>] contraindicated . . . and people have run into trouble.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>There is some literature that discusses the importance for users of HP to discuss HP use with their physicians.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1084822312472055">13</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1084822312472055"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1084822312472055">15</xref></sup> Currently, many individuals who access HP do not divulge to this their physicians.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1084822312472055">15</xref></sup> This lack of dialogue can create problems in people’s treatment plans partly because of the negative effects of combining HP and allopathic treatments and partly because all providers should have a complete picture of their patient’s health care choices to treat them effectively.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1084822312472055">15</xref></sup></p>
<p>The lack of regulation of some forms of HP is one of the greatest barriers to its legitimization in Canada. Homeopathy, for example, is virtually unregulated in Canada although efforts are now underway for it to be regulated in the province of Ontario.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1084822312472055">16</xref></sup> Anybody today can provide homeopathic services. This isn’t to state that there are no standards for homeopathic treatments in Canada; to the contrary, many homeopathic schools do exist with international educational standards. However, many lay people are unaware of how to check on this type of information. In general, the regulation of HP is an important step in increasing its legitimacy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1084822312472055">17</xref></sup> Ideally, all health professions should be regulated by their own College and Association. This kind of regulation serves to further protect the health and finances of Canadians. One particular point that was echoed by many of the respondents was the concern that some HP practitioners make in regard to curing SCI. As no cure for SCI currently exists, and given the traumatic nature of the injury, individuals with SCI, especially in the acute phase of injury, are a highly vulnerable population. Many are coming to terms with the adjustments they must make in life and are keen on attempting any therapy, no matter the cost, to continue functioning as they did before their injury. Any practitioners claiming to cure SCI, are therefore, likely unscrupulous and have dubious ethical standards.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>One product isn’t necessarily equivalent to the next either because we have a very unregulated supplement industry out there.</p>
<p>My concern is whether or not the outside practitioners [<italic>holistic health practitioners outside of our facilities</italic>] are acting in the best interest of their clients.</p>
<p>I have a lot of trouble with practitioners saying “I can offer you this” when they can’t prove that they can offer them that. You’re dealing with a very vulnerable group of people at that point in time [<italic>acute</italic>] . . . I think that it’s important for those practitioners to put a leash on themselves with regards to what their claims are—which goes the same for conventional or holistic health care.</p>
<p>My main gripe with the holistic health professions are the people who will make false claims or claims that are to the contrary of the mainstream [<italic>Western</italic>] health care providers.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Due to the marginalized nature of some HP, HP practitioners may feel compelled to overstate the benefits of their therapies. This is often because they feel victimized as the “outsiders” in a medical marketplace which labels them as “witchdoctors” or worse.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1084822312472055">6</xref></sup> Unfortunately, the social dynamics related to “legitimate and illegitimate” systems in health care in Canada leads some health care practitioners in the latter camp to make outlandish claims to secure a client base for themselves.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1084822312472055">6</xref></sup></p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>But unfortunately, when there’s room for that in an unregulated situation, it also leaves room for a lot of potential mis-advertising about what might or might not be possible.</p>
<p>Conventional Western medicine and SCI included, there isn’t a lot of really well-done research surrounding a lot of the things that we do . . . Unfortunately, with holistic health practices, it’s difficult to find the randomized, double-blind, study that we tend to look for to rule out placebo response.</p>
<p>. . . until we do the studies that actually demonstrate benefit or lack of benefit, my concern is that it’s still very much a Snake-oil man’s domain.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>These kinds of statements are not uncommon in discussions with non-HP practitioners about HP. Given the burgeoning amount of good quality, peer-reviewed literature on HP it is unfortunate that comments on HP such as those stated above are still made by people with inadequate knowledge of the HP literature.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1084822312472055" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<sec id="section12-1084822312472055">
<title>Health Care Professionals’ Views on the Use of HP by Individuals With SCI</title>
<p>According to the majority of participants sampled in this study, people with SCI frequently seek out holistic therapies to meet a variety of health concerns that accompany this type of injury and disability. Health care professionals perceive their clients’ health needs to be related not only to physical issues but also to psychological, social, and cultural issues. They believe this broad array of issues must be addressed to promote clients’ overall health. Acceptance of the reality of disability and empowerment through self-education are viewed as important aspects of clients’ behavior needed for clients to “move on” and achieve greater health. Clients’ interest and engagement with HP vary according to individual desire, lifestyle, and the stage of the injury. HP is commonly sought to relieve symptoms, promote well-being, decrease multiple medication use, or find a cure to the injury.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1084822312472055">5</xref></sup> This last aspect generates concern among health care providers who see their clients as searching for unrealistic solutions to their health problems. Some health care professionals consider this behavior to be counterproductive to the client’s rehabilitation as it is believed to demonstrate that the client is unable to accept their injury, adapt to their disability, and achieve closure. As a result, the attitudes of health care practitioners working with the spinal cord injured population were mixed in regard to HP. Many see the value of HP, while some practitioners worry about holistic health practitioners taking advantage of vulnerable spinal cord injured clients who will sometimes “try anything” to be healed.</p>
<p>Health care practitioners in this study report that those individuals who practiced HP as part of their lifestyle prior to the injury most commonly requested or practiced HP after SCI. In the early stages, people tend to focus on the physical characteristics of injury rather than the long-term aspect or whole picture of wellness. Later, as people with SCI reintegrate themselves into their communities and begin to function independently, they tend to seek out a variety of conventional and holistic health practices. This correlates well with responses from people with SCI.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1084822312472055">5</xref></sup> Newly injured people were interested and open to trying HP when they had influences in their life that encouraged this. Those who had lived in a wheelchair longer were often self-motivated to actively seek out wellness opportunities. The benefits of using HP perceived by the clients can vary depending on the modalities used and the clients’ expectations. For some clients, different physical and social benefits were reported, whereas for others it may not be as beneficial. The high cost of HP services was a major concern as well.</p>
<p>Our participants had varying degree of knowledge and views on HP for people living with SCI. Some participants incorporate HP in their lives and work through their belief systems, personal self-care, practical skills, hands-on work with clients, or through referrals and educational opportunities. The majority of the professionals in the sample had some experience with clients enquiring or using holistic therapies and most are supportive of a range of modalities. Participants stated that they would like to be able to learn more about HP and provide accurate and informed information to their clients. However, when looking at problematic aspects of HP, some participants are skeptical or have concerns about the effectiveness and cost of such treatments. Concerns regarding HP that arose frequently with our participants include lack of regulation, lack of information and quality of research, practitioner’s expertise and ethics, as well as conflicting treatment information and lack of communication between conventional and holistic health care systems.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1084822312472055">
<title>Greater Acceptance of HP in Canada</title>
<p>Given the burgeoning amount of research in the rehabilitation field it is difficult for professionals to keep current with all of this literature. However, there is a growing body of literature that shows the benefits of acupuncture in particular in rehabilitation post-SCI.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1084822312472055">18</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1084822312472055"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1084822312472055"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1084822312472055">21</xref></sup> Therefore, lack of peer-reviewed medical literature on HP should no longer be the reason health care professionals are reluctant to promote these practices. A more likely reason for any reluctance among health care practitioners to promote HP to their clients is limited knowledge of HP due to time constraints in keeping up with the literature. Additionally, professional turf protection may be an unspoken reason for this reluctance. As health care professionals are already heavily overworked in maintaining their practice and reviewing other literature pertinent to their profession, reviewing more literature on HP is challenging.</p>
<p>Health care in Canada is changing. In many ways, the dominant medical model continues to evolve toward a multifaceted approach to health.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1084822312472055">22</xref></sup> HP have become increasingly popular and accepted as seen by their inclusion in extended health plans and their increased marketing. HP concepts of balance, energy, and happiness are central to laypeople’s understanding of health, which could partially explain the increasingly high uptake of HP within the general public.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1084822312472055">23</xref></sup> The vast majority of people interested in HP use them in combination with conventional therapies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1084822312472055">22</xref></sup> Effective care now necessitates exploration of holistic medicine by clients and their health care providers.</p>
<p>A pilot study of people with SCI in BC’s lower mainland found that 87% seek the services of HP practices, which is higher than the Canadian average.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1084822312472055">5</xref></sup> This concurred with our participants’ estimations that 75% to 90% of their clients seek HP. Health care providers in this sample possess a range of knowledge and experience on HP for clients with SCI. Many of them also have concerns regarding the effectiveness and cost of HP treatments. However, they felt they could benefit from receiving more information about holistic health practices and how they might relate to their clients with SCI. Most express a willingness to explore these issues more in-depth, partly because of the high demand by clients for more information about HP and partly because they feel that more knowledge would give them a better idea of the range of health care practices available in the lower mainland of BC—the center of HP in Canada.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We would like to thank the rehabilitation providers who kindly shared their ideas as study participants.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>Dr. Shroff received some funding from the British Columbia paraplegic association for collecting this data and writing a preliminary report.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1084822312472055">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Farry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>The Incidence and Prevalence of Spinal Cord Injury in Canada: Overview and Estimates Based on Current Evidence</source>. <publisher-loc>Vancouver, BC, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rick Hansen Institute</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1084822312472055">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Furlan</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fehlings</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cardiovascular complications after acute spinal cord injury: pathophysiology, diagnosis, and management</article-title>. <source>Neurosurg Focus</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>E13</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1084822312472055">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sahota</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ravensbergen</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Claydon</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cerebrovascular responses to orthostatic stress after spinal cord injury</article-title>. <source>J Neurotrauma</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>2446</fpage>-<lpage>2456</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1084822312472055">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matheis</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Agostinelli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shifleft</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The use of complementary and alternative therapies for chronic pain following spinal cord injury: a pilot survey</article-title>. <source>J Spinal Cord Med</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>-<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1084822312472055">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shroff</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Holistic health and people with spinal cord injuries</article-title>. <source>J Spinal Cord Med</source>. In press.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1084822312472055">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shroff</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Conceptualizing holism in international interdisciplinary critical perspective: toward a framework for understanding holistic health</article-title>. <source>Soc Theor Health</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>244</fpage>-<lpage>255</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1084822312472055">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McFarland</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bigelow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newsom</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Complementary and alternative medicine use in Canada and the United States</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>1616</fpage>-<lpage>1618</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1084822312472055">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Saulino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Rehabilitation of persons with spinal cord injuries</article-title>. <year>2012</year>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://emedicine.medscape.com/article/1265209-overview">http://emedicine.medscape.com/article/1265209-overview</ext-link>. <access-date>Accessed Jan 30, 2012</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1084822312472055">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vissers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van den Berg-Emons</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sluis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bergen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stam</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bussmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Barriers to and facilitators of everyday physical activity in persons with a spinal cord injury after discharge from the rehabilitation centre</article-title>. <source>J Rehabil Med</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>461</fpage>-<lpage>467</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1084822312472055">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Depression following spinal cord injury</article-title>. <source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>816</fpage>-<lpage>823</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1084822312472055">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Naylor</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Health care in Canada: incrementalism under fiscal duress</article-title>. <source>Health Aff (Millwood)</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1084822312472055">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shroff</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>New Directions in Canadian Health Policy: Lessons From Holistic Medicine</source>. <publisher-loc>Toronto, Ontario, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Toronto</publisher-name>; <year>1996</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1084822312472055">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Advising patients who seek alternative medical therapies</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>127</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>-<lpage>69</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1084822312472055">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Elder</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gillcrist</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Minz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Use of alternative health care by family practice patients</article-title>. <source>Arch Fam Med</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>181</fpage>-<lpage>184</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1084822312472055">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pappas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perlman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Complementary and alternative medicine. The importance of doctor-patient communication</article-title>. <source>Med Clin North Am</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>86</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1084822312472055">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>“Hodge-podge” regulation of alternative medicine in Canada</article-title>. <source>CMAJ</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>182</volume>:<fpage>E569</fpage>-<lpage>570</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1084822312472055">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marchand</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scheder</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Themes of holism, empowerment, access, and legitimacy define complementary, alternative, and integrative medicine in relation to conventional biomedicine</article-title>. <source>J Altern Complement Med</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>937</fpage>-<lpage>947</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1084822312472055">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dorsher</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reimer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nottmeier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Treatment of urinary incontinence due to incomplete spinal cord injury with acupuncture and percutaneous electrical nerve stimulation: Two cases and literature review</article-title>. <source>Medical Acupuncture</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1084822312472055">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ayas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leblebici</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sozay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bayramoglu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Niron</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effect of abdominal massage on bowel function in patients with spinal cord injury</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys Med Rehabil</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>85</volume>:<fpage>951</fpage>-<lpage>955</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1084822312472055">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yune</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Acupuncture-mediated inhibition of inflammation facilitates significant functional recovery after spinal cord injury</article-title>. <source>Neurobiol Dis</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>272</fpage>-<lpage>282</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1084822312472055">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cardenas</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Pain after spinal cord injury: a review of classification, treatment approaches, and treatment assessment</article-title>. <source>PM R</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>1077</fpage>-<lpage>1090</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1084822312472055">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shroff</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Ayurvedic medicine</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Dei</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>Indigenous Knowledge</source>. <publisher-loc>Toronto, Ontario, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>; <volume>2000</volume>:<fpage>215</fpage>-<lpage>233</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1084822312472055">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shroff</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Power politics and the takeover of holistic health in North America: an exploratory historical analysis</article-title>. <source>Pimatisiwin: A Journal of Aboriginal and Indigenous Community Health</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>-<lpage>152</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>