<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JIV</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjiv</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Interpers Violence</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Interpersonal Violence</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0886-2605</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-6518</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0886260512441261</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0886260512441261</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Patterns of Injury and Reported Violence Depending on Relationship to Assailant in Female Swedish Sexual Assault Victims</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Möller</surname><given-names>Anna Sofia</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0886260512441261">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0886260512441261">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Bäckström</surname><given-names>Torbjörn</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0886260512441261">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Söndergaard</surname><given-names>Hans Peter</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0886260512441261">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0886260512441261">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Helström</surname><given-names>Lotti</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0886260512441261">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0886260512441261">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0886260512441261"><label>1</label>Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm, Sweden</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0886260512441261"><label>2</label>Stockholm South General Hospital, Stockholm, Sweden</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0886260512441261"><label>3</label>Umeå University, Umeå, Sweden</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0886260512441261"><label>4</label>Danderyds Hospital, Stockholm, Sweden</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0886260512441261">Anna Sofia Möller, Department of Clinical Science and Education, Karolinska Institutet, Södersjukhuset, Stockholm 118 83, Sweden Email: <email>Anna.moller@sodersjukhuset.se</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>27</volume>
<issue>16</issue>
<fpage>3131</fpage>
<lpage>3148</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Earlier studies have explored the differences between known-assailant sexual assaults and stranger assaults and reported the stranger assaults as being more violent. Only a few studies have discriminated between sexual assaults by intimate partners from assaults by other known assailants when comparing with assaults by strangers. In this study, we explored differences in the extent of violence and physical injury in sexual assaults committed by intimate partners compared with assaults by strangers and acquaintances. Medical and forensic records of 690 consecutive women attending a sexual assault center in Stockholm, Sweden were reviewed. The final sample included in the analysis consisted of 503 patients. Our results showed that women sexually assaulted by their intimate partners more frequently reported physical violence (<italic>OR</italic> = 4.1) than women assaulted by strangers (<italic>OR</italic> = 2.0) and acquaintances (<italic>OR</italic> = 1.0). Genital injuries were not found to be related to the victim–assailant relationship in this study. Extragenital injuries showed a tendency toward being more frequently found after intimate partner assaults compared with stranger and acquaintance assaults; however, this was not found to be significant in adjusted analyses. Previous history of sexual assault was more common, and seeking medical care within 72 hr as well as being under the influence of alcohol during the assault was less frequent among intimate partner victims. These results support the conclusion that sexual assaults committed by intimate partners, contradictory to earlier studies, are likely to involve more physical violence and result in injuries just as often as assaults committed by strangers.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>sexual assault</kwd>
<kwd>rape</kwd>
<kwd>injuries</kwd>
<kwd>assailant</kwd>
<kwd>violence</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The number of sexual assaults reported to the Swedish police has increased dramatically, more than tripling during the past two decades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0886260512441261">Grevholm, Nilsson, &amp; Carlstedt, 2005</xref>). In Swedish population-based surveys, 12% to 34% of Swedish women have been exposed to some kind of sexual assault during their lifetime (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0886260512441261">Levin, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0886260512441261">Lundgren, Heimer, Westerstrand, &amp; Kallioski, 2003</xref>). In these surveys, a sexual assault was defined according to the Swedish law, as sexual intercourse or any kind of sexual act forced by violence, any sexual intercourse or sexual act with someone below the age of 15, and sexual intercourse or sexual act with someone who is unable to consent.</p>
<p>Several studies have been published during the recent years examining genital and nongenital injuries in female sexual assault victims. Sexual assaults by strangers have been reported as more violent and associated with more injuries than assaults by a person known to the victim (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0886260512441261">Jones, Wynn, Kroeze, Dunnuck, &amp; Rossman, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0886260512441261">Palmer, McNulty, Déste, &amp; Donovan, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0886260512441261">Slaughter, &amp; Brown, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0886260512441261">Stermac, Du Mont, &amp; Kalemba, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0886260512441261">Sugar, Fine, &amp; Eckert, 2004</xref>). However, a majority of all sexual assaults actually are committed by an assailant known to the victim (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0886260512441261">Grossin et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0886260512441261">Logan, Cole, &amp; Capillo, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0886260512441261">Maguire, Goodall, &amp; Moore, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0886260512441261">Slaughter &amp; Brown, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0886260512441261">Ullman &amp; Siegel, 1993</xref>).</p>
<p>Only a few studies have discriminated between sexual assaults by intimate partners from assaults by other known assailants when comparing with assaults by strangers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0886260512441261">Haugen, Slungård, &amp; Schei, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0886260512441261">Hilden, Schei, &amp; Sidenius, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0886260512441261">Logan et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0886260512441261">Murphy, Potter, Pierce-Weeks, Stapleton, &amp; Wiesen-Martin, 2011</xref>). Contradictory to earlier studies, these four studies suggested that more violence was being used in both assaults committed by intimate partners and acquaintances compared with assaults by strangers. Both <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0886260512441261">Logan et al. (2007)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0886260512441261">Murphy et al. (2011)</xref> indicated that there were significant differences in genital injury prevalence between the assailant groups, with more women assaulted by intimate partners having genital injuries than women assaulted by acquaintances, and more women assaulted by acquaintances having injuries than women assaulted by strangers. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0886260512441261">Hilden et al. (2005)</xref> however indicated that assaults committed by acquaintances had the highest genital injury prevalence followed by intimate partners and strangers. Similarly, extragenital injuries were more frequently found in intimate partner assaults than in stranger assaults in the study by Logan and colleagues while as Murphy and colleagues found the opposite results.</p>
<p>Moreover, victim and assault characteristics depending on victim–assailant relationship showed deviating results. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0886260512441261">Logan et al. (2007)</xref> stated that there were no differences between the groups in time lapse between the assault and the examination and previous history of sexual assault. Two other studies, however, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0886260512441261">Haugen et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0886260512441261">Murphy et al., 2011</xref>) showed that victims of intimate partners accessed care later, and information about prior sexual assaults were not mentioned. Both <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0886260512441261">Haugen et al. (2005)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0886260512441261">Logan et al. (2007)</xref> found victims of intimate partners less often being under the influence of alcohol compared with victims of strangers and acquaintances, a question Murphy and colleges did not answer.</p>
<p>None of the mentioned studies found any ethnic differences between the groups of victims. One earlier study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0886260512441261">Stermac, Del Bove, and Addison (2001)</xref>, however, had seen a significant trend, indicating that women of color were overrepresented in the spousal victim group compared with victims of other known assailants.</p>
<p>Another interesting observation is that in none of these studies, exploring injuries by type of assailant, genital injury prevalence had been adjusted for the time of the examination. Considering the finding in other studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0886260512441261">Grossin et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0886260512441261">Maguire et al., 2009</xref>) about the importance of an early forensic examination to be able to detect injuries, we would like to raise the question about the feasibility to draw conclusions from these results.</p>
<p>As the literature is showing discrepant results, and study populations being fairly small, a new study investigating injuries and other factors based on the victim–assailant relationship is motivated. In the region of Stockholm, all sexual assault victim care is centralized to one unit open 24 hr, which reduces selection bias. By exploring a large population of consecutive patients from a major catchment area, focusing on the victim–assailant relationships, with a structured method and extended statistical analyses, the study will clarify some of the discrepancies in the literature.</p>
<p>The aim of this study was to explore if the degree of violence and injury patterns in sexual assaults differ depending on the victim’s relationship to the assailant. We especially wanted to address differences in intimate partner assaults compared with other known-assailant assaults and to sexual assaults by strangers. Genital injury, extragenital injury, and multiple violence were used as main outcomes.</p>
<p>Our main hypothesis was that (a) sexual assaults committed by intimate partners involve more physical violence and (b) more frequently are associated with injuries than after assaults by strangers in Sweden. Furthermore, we hypothesized that (c) victims of intimate partner assaults are uniquely different from the two other groups when considering age, substance use, prior history of sexual assault, ethnicity, and victim presentation information that are helpful for health workers when treating women in abusive relationships. We predicted that women sexually assaulted by their intimate partner are older, more often are of foreign origin and less often are under the influence of alcohol during the time of the assault compared with victims of strangers and acquaintances. It was further predicted that victims reporting intimate partner assaults are more likely to have a previous history of sexual assaults and that the time lapse between the assault and examination is greater than in the two other groups.</p>
<sec id="section1-0886260512441261" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Material and Method</title>
<p>This retrospective study took place at The Emergency Clinic for Raped Women in Stockholm. The Emergency Clinic for Raped Women opened in October 2005 within the obstetrics and gynecology department at Stockholm South General Hospital, and about 600 women are seen every year. Women who have been referred from other health care clinics, emergency departments, and police, as well as those presenting themselves are met at the clinic. All sexual assault victim care in Stockholm is centralized to The Emergency Clinic for Raped Women, and the clinic is open 24 hr a day. The victims are offered medical and forensic examination within 1 month after the sexual assault. About 65% of the women have reported their assault to law enforcement; however, it is not mandatory for care. Patient files and forensic examinations of all women attending the clinic during a period of 13 months in 2007 and 2008 were reviewed. All patients had been examined by a specialist or a resident in obstetrics and gynecology who had received special training in forensic examination after sexual assaults. All data were selected by standardized interviews and documented in structured sexual assault charts. Injuries were measured and documented with the aid of photographs.</p>
<p>Descriptive variables based on information given by the women included the victim’s relationship to the assailant, type of sexual assault, reports of physical violence, detection of genital and nongenital injuries and their location, previous history of sexual assault, the influence of alcohol during the assault, and the time lapse between the sexual assault and the examination. The study was approved by the local medical ethics committee in Stockholm.</p>
<sec id="section2-0886260512441261">
<title>Definitions</title>
<p>The various assailants were categorized in to six different groups: (a) <italic>intimate partner</italic> (husband/cohabiter, partner, ex-partner), (b) <italic>family member</italic> (other than intimate partner), (c) <italic>acquaintance</italic> (an assailant known by the victim but not as an intimate partner or family member), (d) <italic>stranger</italic> (single assailant), (e) <italic>group</italic> (more than one assailant), and finally (f) <italic>uncertain</italic> (the victim had amnesia and could not recall).</p>
<p>The different types of assault were defined as penetration (with penis, hand, or foreign object) <italic>vaginal, oral, anal</italic> or a combination of the three, alternatively <italic>others</italic> when no penetration was involved but other kinds of touching or kissing had occurred (involving genitals or body parts). Violence was defined as <italic>hitting, kicking, holding, attempts of strangulation</italic>, or <italic>by other means</italic>. If two or more types of violence were used it was defined as <italic>multiple violence</italic>. Injuries to the head, neck, trunk, and extremities were defined when bruises, redness, swelling, or tears were apparent.</p>
<p>Genital injuries were defined when swelling (oedematous tissues), redness (erythemous skin), ecchymoses (skin or mucous membrane discolorations, known as <italic>bruising</italic>), tears (breaks in tissue including fissures, cracks, cuts and lacerations), and several (more than one of the above mentioned injuries) were observed. The different genital injury locations are defined as <italic>vulva, introitus, labia minora, posterior fourchette, hymen</italic>, and <italic>vagina</italic>.</p>
<p>Information about previous history of sexual assault was based on the women’s answer to the question, “Have you ever before been sexually assaulted?” Furthermore, the women were told about the definition of a sexual assault according to the Swedish law, as sexual intercourse or any kind of sexual act forced by violence, any sexual intercourse or sexual act with someone under the age of 15 years of age, and sexual intercourse or sexual act with someone who is unable to consent.</p>
<p>Information about the influence of alcohol during the sexual assault was based on information given by the women, and the amount of alcohol was not quantified. She was asked the question, “Were you under the influence of alcohol during the time of the sexual assault?”</p>
<p>Time lapse between the sexual assault and the forensic examination was defined as within 72 hr (&lt;72 hr) or later than 72 hr (&gt;72 hr).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0886260512441261">
<title>Sample Size and Statistical Analysis</title>
<p>The medical records of 690 consecutive sexually assaulted women were evaluated. Of the 690 cases, 21 cases were excluded due to incomplete documentation, 3 did not indicate their relationship to the assailant, and 11 were incorrectly registered as emergency visits. In 655 cases, the women had been asked about her relationship to the assailant. The women sexually assaulted by a stranger, an acquaintance, or an intimate partner were selected and resulted in a final sample size of 503 patients.</p>
<p>Pearson’s chi-square test was used for categorical data and ANOVA for continuous data to compare assault and victim characteristics by type of assailant. If the assumptions for the chi-square test, no more than 20% of the expected counts less than 5 and no expected counts less than 1, were not fulfilled, Fisher’s exact test was used.</p>
<p>The three main outcomes, multiple physical violence, genital injury, and extragenital injury were analyzed using logistic regression. Our model strategy was as follows: First, crude associations between each of the outcomes and each factor were studied in univariable models. Second, we used multivariable models to study adjusted associations. Variables were considered significant if the Wald test resulted in a <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. The associations are presented as odds ratios (<italic>OR</italic>) with 95% confidence intervals (CI). Hosmer-Lemeshow goodness-of-fit test was used to examine if the model adequately fitted the data.</p>
<p>All analyses were performed in SPSS 20.0.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0886260512441261" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section5-0886260512441261">
<title>Study Population</title>
<p>The victim–assailant relationships are listed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0886260512441261">Figure 1</xref>. Among the 655 included women, 406 (62%) were sexually assaulted by a known assailant. Among those 406 known assailants, 71% were described as acquaintances, 25% were intimate partners or ex-partners, and 4% involved other family members. A single-stranger assailant was reported in 17% of all assaults. A remarkably large group of all women (10%) reported amnesia in conjunction with the assault and could not recall who the assailant was.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0886260512441261" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Relationship of assailant to victim</p>
<p>Note: Flow diagram of study population. The victims’ relationship to the assailant is listed in percentages of all included victims.</p>
<p><sup>a</sup>Percentages of known assailants.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0886260512441261-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The three groups, intimate partner assaults, stranger assaults, and acquaintance assaults, resulted in a final sample size of 503 patients. The mean age was 25 years (median 21 years, range 11-95). Twenty-five percentage were below the age of 18 at the time of the sexual assault. A majority of the patients (78.9%) were of Swedish ethnicity, 2.2% were from the other Nordic countries, 3.2% from Europe, and 15.7% were from countries outside Europe.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0886260512441261">
<title>Patient and Assault Characteristics by Type of Assailant</title>
<p>As seen in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0886260512441261">Table 1</xref>, women sexually assaulted by their intimate partners were significantly older than women assaulted by strangers and acquaintances. In the groups assaulted by strangers and acquaintances, a majority of the women were born in Sweden, whereas in the assaults committed by intimate partners, the proportion of victims of Swedish and foreign origin were equal, indicating an overrepresentation of immigrant victims. Alcohol intake prior to the rape was least common in cases where the assailant was an intimate partner (29%). Furthermore, a history of sexual assault was twice as common in the group assaulted by intimate partners compared with the group assaulted by strangers (64% vs. 33%).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0886260512441261" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Characteristics of Women Sexually Assaulted by Intimate Partners Versus Strangers or Acquaintances</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0886260512441261" xlink:href="10.1177_0886260512441261-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Intimate Partner (<italic>n</italic> = 102)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0886260512441261">b</xref></sup></th>
<th align="center">Stranger (<italic>n</italic> = 114)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0886260512441261">b</xref></sup></th>
<th align="center">Acquaintance (<italic>n</italic> = 287)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0886260512441261">b</xref></sup></th>
<th align="center">Intimate Partner Versus Stranger <italic>p</italic><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0886260512441261">a</xref></sup></th>
<th align="center">Intimate Partner Versus Acquaintance <italic>p</italic><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0886260512441261">a</xref></sup></th>
<th align="center">Stranger Versus Acquaintance <italic>p</italic><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0886260512441261">a</xref></sup></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Mean age (<italic>SD</italic>)</td>
<td>32.9 (±12.7)</td>
<td>24.2 (±12.0)</td>
<td>23.8 (±10.3)</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td><italic>ns</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Victim’s ethnicity (% Swedish)</td>
<td>54/102 (53%)</td>
<td>98/114 (86%)</td>
<td>234/287 (82%)</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td><italic>ns</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Victim under influence of alcohol</td>
<td>27/94 (29%)</td>
<td>79/110 (72%)</td>
<td>204/280 (73%)</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td><italic>ns</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Previous history of sexual assault</td>
<td>61/96 (64%)</td>
<td>34/102 (33%)</td>
<td>113/276 (41%)</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td><italic>ns</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Time between assault and examination</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ≤72 hr</td>
<td>66/102 (65%)</td>
<td>96/114 (84%)</td>
<td>223/287 (78%)</td>
<td>.001</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td><italic>ns</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> ≥72 hr</td>
<td>36/102 (35%)</td>
<td>18/114 (16%)</td>
<td>64/287 (22%)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0886260512441261">
<p>Note: <italic>ns</italic>, not statistically significant.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0886260512441261">
<label>a</label>
<p>Pearson’s chi-square test or Fisher’s exact test for categorical variables, ANOVA for continuous variables.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0886260512441261">
<label>b</label>
<p>Variable analyses were based on differing denominators as determined by missing data.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Women assaulted by their intimate partners also sought help later and were less likely to be examined within 72 hr than women assaulted by strangers and acquaintances.</p>
<p>The frequencies listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0886260512441261">Table 2</xref> add to more than 100% as a majority of the assaults involved more than one type of act. Both vaginal and anal penetration was more often performed in sexual assaults committed by intimate partners compared with assaults in the two other groups. Attempts and other kind of sexual assaults, involving kissing and touching, were more often seen in stranger assaults.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0886260512441261" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Assault Characteristics</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0886260512441261" xlink:href="10.1177_0886260512441261-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Intimate Partner (<italic>n</italic> = 102)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0886260512441261">b</xref></sup></th>
<th align="center">Stranger (<italic>n</italic> = 114)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0886260512441261">b</xref></sup></th>
<th align="center">Acquaintance (<italic>n</italic> = 287)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0886260512441261">b</xref></sup></th>
<th align="center">Intimate Partner Versus Stranger <italic>p</italic><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0886260512441261">a</xref></sup></th>
<th align="center">Intimate Partner Versus Acquaintance <italic>p</italic><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0886260512441261">a</xref></sup></th>
<th align="center">Stranger Versus Acquaintance <italic>p</italic><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0886260512441261">a</xref></sup></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Type of assault</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Vaginal</td>
<td>82/102 (80%)</td>
<td>61/114 (54%)</td>
<td>197/287 (69%)</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>.03<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-0886260512441261">c</xref></sup></td>
<td>.03<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-0886260512441261">c</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Anal</td>
<td>26/102 (25%)</td>
<td>7/114 (6%)</td>
<td>41/287 (14%)</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Oral</td>
<td>25/102 (25%)</td>
<td>14/114 (12%)</td>
<td>59/287 (21%)</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td><italic>ns</italic></td>
<td>.05<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-0886260512441261">c</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Vaginal + other</td>
<td>31/102 (30%)</td>
<td>15/114 (13%)</td>
<td>66/287 (23%)</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td><italic>ns</italic></td>
<td><italic>ns</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Attempt</td>
<td>2/102 (2%)</td>
<td>22/114 (19%)</td>
<td>11/287 (4%)</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td><italic>ns</italic></td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Others</td>
<td>6/102 (6%)</td>
<td>20/114 (18%)</td>
<td>28/287 (10%)</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td><italic>ns</italic></td>
<td>.03<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-0886260512441261">c</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Type of violence</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Any violence</td>
<td>91/101 (90%)</td>
<td>88/110 (80%)</td>
<td>159/287 (55%)</td>
<td><italic>ns</italic></td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Attempts of strangulation</td>
<td>21/102 (21%)</td>
<td>9/114 (8%)</td>
<td>2/287 (1%)</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Kick</td>
<td>17/91 (19%)</td>
<td>3/88 (3%)</td>
<td>0/287 (0%)</td>
<td>.001</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Multiple</td>
<td>49/101 (49%)</td>
<td>32/110 (29%)</td>
<td>41/287 (14%)</td>
<td>.004</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Holding</td>
<td>28/102 (27%)</td>
<td>52/114 (46%)</td>
<td>101/287 (35%)</td>
<td>.04<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-0886260512441261">c</xref></sup></td>
<td><italic>ns</italic></td>
<td>.04<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-0886260512441261">c</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0886260512441261">
<p>Note: <italic>ns</italic>, not statistically significant.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-0886260512441261">
<label>a</label>
<p>Pearson’s chi-square test or Fisher’s exact test.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn6-0886260512441261">
<label>b</label>
<p>Variable analyses were based on differing denominators as determined by missing data.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn7-0886260512441261">
<label>c</label>
<p>Not statistically significant according to the Bonferroni correction.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0886260512441261">
<title>Violence</title>
<p>As seen in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0886260512441261">Table 2</xref>, violence and coercion was more frequently reported when the assailant was an intimate partner or stranger compared with acquaintance. Violence performed in intimate partner assaults were often of a varying kind, with a higher prevalence of kicks, hits, and attempts of strangulation. In half of these assaults, multiple violence was performed. However, among assaults committed by strangers and acquaintances, the violence more often consisted solely of holding the victim.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0886260512441261">Table 3</xref> shows factors associated with multiple violence. In the crude analysis factors associated with an increased risk of being exposed to multiple violence were; assailant being either a stranger or an intimate partner, the victim being above 45 years old, not being of Swedish ethnicity, and not having been under the influence of alcohol during the time of the assault. Furthermore, findings of extragenital injury and assaults consisting of multiple sexual acts were associated with an increased risk of being exposed to multiple violence. When adjusting for all factors in the multivariable model only the assailant being an intimate partner (<italic>OR</italic> = 4.1) and extragenital injury (<italic>OR</italic> = 5.0) were associated with multiple violence.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0886260512441261" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Factors Associated With Multiple Violence During the Sexual Assault</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0886260512441261" xlink:href="10.1177_0886260512441261-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Multivariable<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Crude Measures<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Univariable<hr/></th>
<th align="center">Adjusted for All Factors in the Univariable Model<hr/></th>
<th/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="center">Level</th>
<th align="center"><italic>N</italic></th>
<th align="center">Percentage With Multiple Violence</th>
<th align="center"><italic>OR</italic> (95% CI)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
<th align="center">OR (95% CI)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Type of assailant</td>
<td>Acquaintance</td>
<td>278</td>
<td>14.7</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Stranger</td>
<td>110</td>
<td>29.1</td>
<td>2.4 [1.4, 4.0]</td>
<td>.001</td>
<td>2.0 [0.9, 4.7]</td>
<td>.09</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Intimate partner</td>
<td>101</td>
<td>48.5</td>
<td>5.4 [3.3, 9.1]</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>4.1 [1.9, 9.0]</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age (years)</td>
<td>&lt;45</td>
<td>446</td>
<td>22.9</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>&gt;45</td>
<td>42</td>
<td>47.6</td>
<td>3.1 [1.6, 5.8]</td>
<td>.001</td>
<td>1.6 [0.6, 4.4]</td>
<td>.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Victim’s ethnicity Swedish</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>377</td>
<td>19.6</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>No</td>
<td>112</td>
<td>42.9</td>
<td>3.1 [2.0, 4.8]</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>1.4 [0.7, 2.7]</td>
<td>.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Time between assault and examination</td>
<td>&lt;72 hr</td>
<td>375</td>
<td>24.0</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>&gt;72 hr</td>
<td>114</td>
<td>28.1</td>
<td>1.2 [0.8, 2.0]</td>
<td>.4</td>
<td>1.6 [0.8, 3.3]</td>
<td>.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Victim under influence of alcohol</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>302</td>
<td>19.2</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>No</td>
<td>173</td>
<td>34.7</td>
<td>2.2 [1.5, 3.4]</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>1.1 [0.5, 2.1]</td>
<td>.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Coexisting extra genital injuries</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>255</td>
<td>36.9</td>
<td>5.0 [3.0, 8.4]</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>5.0 [2.6, 9.5]</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>No</td>
<td>200</td>
<td>10.5</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Type of assault</td>
<td>Vaginal</td>
<td>224</td>
<td>21.4</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Vaginal + other</td>
<td>111</td>
<td>35.1</td>
<td>2.0 [1.2, 3.3]</td>
<td>.008</td>
<td>1.8 [1.0, 3.2]</td>
<td>.06</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn8-0886260512441261">
<p>Note: Hosmer and Lemeshow Test: 0.52. <italic>OR</italic> = odds ratio; CI = confidence interval.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0886260512441261">
<title>Ano-genital Injuries</title>
<p>The total genital injury prevalence was 20% in this study. Genital injuries were most commonly located in the posterior fourchette in 35%, in the vulva in 13%, in the labia minora in 12%, and injuries in several locations in 19%. The injuries were most often small lacerations. The genital injury prevalence was almost tripled in the women examined within 72 hr compared with after 72 hr (23.7% vs. 8.3%, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001). The logistic regression, with genital injury as outcome, showed that the victim–assailant relationship was not associated with genital injury (not shown in table). The increased risk of having genital injuries after sexual assaults by a stranger (<italic>OR</italic> = 1.1, 95% CI [0.5, 2.4]) or an acquaintance (<italic>OR</italic> = 1.4, 95% CI [0.8, 2.7]) compared with after an assault by an intimate partner were not found to be significant. The adjusted analysis showed that the only association between the risk of presenting at the clinic with genital injuries was to be examined within 72 hr after the assault (<italic>OR</italic> = 6.4, 95% CI [2.4, 17.4], <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001).</p>
<p>Anal injuries were more likely to be found when examining victims of intimate partners (<italic>OR</italic> = 9.3, 95% CI [1.2, 50], <italic>p</italic> = .04) and acquaintances (<italic>OR</italic> = 7.5, 95% CI [1.0, 56], <italic>p</italic> = .05) compared with victims of strangers. This association remained after having adjusted for the time lapse between the assault and the examination.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0886260512441261">
<title>Extragenital Injuries</title>
<p>In general, extragenital injuries were almost three times as common as genital injuries, 58% (263/465) compared with 20% (90/450).</p>
<p>Injuries to extremities were apparent in 52% (263/503) of the cases, to the head in 21% (107/503), and to the trunk in 25% (115/462). Injuries to the head were reported in 34% of the intimate partner assaults and in 29% of the stranger assaults, to be compared with 17% in the assaults committed by acquaintances (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001).</p>
<p>Using logistic regression (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0886260512441261">Table 4</xref>), the crude association between type of assailant and extragenital injuries was increased when the assailant was an intimate partner (<italic>OR</italic> = 1.7, 95% CI [1.1, 2.8], <italic>p</italic> = .03) compared with acquaintance. The increased risk of sustaining from extragenital injuries during assaults by strangers compared with acquaintances (<italic>OR</italic> = 1.5, 95% CI [0.9, 3.4], <italic>p</italic> = .09) were not found to be significant. In the adjusted analysis, the only factors that remained significantly associated with extragenital injury were the examination to be performed within 72 hr (<italic>OR</italic> = 2.5, 95% CI [1.4, 4.5], <italic>p</italic> = .002) and reports of physical violence (<italic>OR</italic> = 5.5, 95% CI [3.0, 10.4], <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001).</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-0886260512441261" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Factors Associated With Extragenital Injuries After Sexual Assault</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0886260512441261" xlink:href="10.1177_0886260512441261-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Multivariable<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Crude Measures<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Univariable<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Adjusted for All Factors in the Univariable Model<hr/></th>
<th/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="center">Level</th>
<th align="center"><italic>N</italic></th>
<th align="center">Percentage With Injuries</th>
<th align="center"><italic>OR</italic></th>
<th align="center">95% CI</th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>OR</italic></th>
<th align="center">95% CI</th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Type of assailant</td>
<td>Acquaintance</td>
<td>267</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Stranger</td>
<td>104</td>
<td>62</td>
<td>1.5</td>
<td>[0.9, 3.4]</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>0.7</td>
<td>[0.4, 1.4]</td>
<td>.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Intimate partner</td>
<td>94</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>1.7</td>
<td>[1.1, 2.8]</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>1.4</td>
<td>[0.7, 2.7]</td>
<td>.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age (years)</td>
<td>&lt;45</td>
<td>425</td>
<td>54.6</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>&gt;45</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>76.9</td>
<td>2.8</td>
<td>[1.3, 6.0]</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>2.0</td>
<td>[0.7, 5.7]</td>
<td>.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Victim’s ethnicity Swedish</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>359</td>
<td>54.0</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>No</td>
<td>106</td>
<td>65.1</td>
<td>1.6</td>
<td>[1.0, 2.5]</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>1.5</td>
<td>[0.8, 3.0]</td>
<td>.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Time between assault and examination</td>
<td>&lt;72 hr</td>
<td>366</td>
<td>60.4</td>
<td>2.1</td>
<td>[1.3, 3.2]</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>2.5</td>
<td>[1.4, 4.5]</td>
<td>.002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>&gt;72 hr</td>
<td>99</td>
<td>42.4</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Victim under influence of alcohol</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>294</td>
<td>56.5</td>
<td>1.05</td>
<td>[0.7, 1.5]</td>
<td>.81</td>
<td>1.6</td>
<td>[0.9, 2.8]</td>
<td>.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>No</td>
<td>161</td>
<td>55.3</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Physical violence (any)</td>
<td>Yes</td>
<td>316</td>
<td>65.8</td>
<td>5.3</td>
<td>[3.3, 8.5]</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
<td>5.5</td>
<td>[3.0, 10.4]</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>No</td>
<td>112</td>
<td>26.8</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Type of assault</td>
<td>Vaginal</td>
<td>213</td>
<td>49.8</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td>Reference</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Vaginal + other</td>
<td>107</td>
<td>59.8</td>
<td>1.5</td>
<td>[0.9, 2.4]</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>1.2</td>
<td>[0.7, 2.1]</td>
<td>.4</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn9-0886260512441261">
<p>Note: Hosmer and Lemeshow Test: 0.49. <italic>OR</italic> = odds ratio; CI = confidence interval.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0886260512441261" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The major finding in this study was the high incidence of physical violence in sexual assaults committed by intimate partners compared with both assaults committed by other known assailants and by strangers. The frequency of genital injuries was not found to be related to the victim–assailant relationship. Extragenital injuries showed a tendency toward being more frequently found after intimate partner assaults compared with stranger and acquaintance assaults, however this was not found to be significant in adjusted analyses.</p>
<p>Our results, establishing that only a minority of female sexual assault victims have clinical evidence of genital injuries, are supported by previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0886260512441261">Grossin et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0886260512441261">Maguire et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0886260512441261">Palmer et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0886260512441261">Sugar et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0886260512441261">White &amp; McLean, 2006</xref>). Genital injury is most often present as small lacerations, located in the posterior fourchette of the vaginal opening. The genitoanal area has a remarkable healing capacity resulting in injuries disappearing quickly. One of the most important factors in the forensic examination is therefore the time lapse between the sexual assault and the examination. An examination after 72 hr will not show minor lacerations that might have been present earlier.</p>
<p>Genital injury prevalence was not related to the victim–assailant relationship in this study. However, as victims assaulted by intimate partners sought help later than victims assaulted by strangers it could be assumed that the prevalence of injuries would be higher if intimate partner victimized women would seek earlier. This is in line with our results as the only factor showing an association with genital injury was the time lapse between the assault and the examination.</p>
<p>In the stranger assaults, we found the prevalence of genital and especially extragenital injuries considerably low, compared with international studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0886260512441261">Jones et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0886260512441261">Logan et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0886260512441261">Stermac et al., 1995</xref>). This might be explained by the well-known fact that the victim, when she realizes that the assailant is prepared to use violence, commonly reacts by surrendering to the assailant to minimize further and possible life-threatening violence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0886260512441261">Moskowitz, 2004</xref>). A possible explanation could be that Swedish women might be more likely to report sexual violence than other Western women. In Swedish crime statistics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0886260512441261">Grevholm et al., 2005</xref>), a substantially larger proportion of sexual assault cases are reported than in other Western countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0886260512441261">Tjaden &amp; Thoennes, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0886260512441261">Walby &amp; Allen, 2004</xref>). Another explanation might be that sexual assaults committed by strangers actually are less violent in the Nordic countries.</p>
<p>The victim’s relationship to the assailant is consistent with earlier international studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0886260512441261">Grossin et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0886260512441261">Logan et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0886260512441261">Maguire et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0886260512441261">Slaughter &amp; Brown, 1992</xref>), and the majority of all assaults were committed by a person known to the victim. Rapes committed by a stranger comprise 17% in this study population, which is in accordance with the two Nordic studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0886260512441261">Haugen et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0886260512441261">Hilden et al., 2005</xref>) but somewhat lower, 23% to 45%, when compared with studies from the United Kingdom and the United States (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0886260512441261">Jones et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0886260512441261">Maguire et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0886260512441261">Stermac et al., 1995</xref>). Most previous studies have explored the differences between known-assailant assaults and stranger assaults and reported the stranger assaults as being more violent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0886260512441261">Jones et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0886260512441261">Stermac et al., 1995</xref>). As mentioned earlier, only a few studies have explored the assault characteristics among the known-assailant group assaulted by intimate partners when comparing with stranger assaults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0886260512441261">Haugen et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0886260512441261">Hilden et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0886260512441261">Logan et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0886260512441261">Murphy et al., 2011</xref>). In consistence with these studies, we found that physical violence was being more frequently reported when the assailant was an intimate partner than a stranger, and violence was reported in almost all (90%) of these cases. The violence reported in intimate partner assaults compared with stranger assaults more often contained multiple violence and reports of kicks and attempts of strangulation. Violence in stranger and acquaintance assaults, however, more often consisted solely of holding the victim. Our results suggest that sexual assaults committed by intimate partners in Sweden are more violent than assaults committed by strangers.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the assaults by intimate partners were more likely to involve more than one type of assault, and more often involved a combination of vaginal and anal assault, compared with assaults by strangers. Anal injuries were more frequently reported in assaults by intimate partners and acquaintances compared with assaults by strangers. This is in accordance with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0886260512441261">Stermac et al. (1995)</xref> who suggested that known assailants have a tendency toward committing more anal sexual assaults than unknown assailants.</p>
<p>Two thirds of women in this study had used alcohol around the time of the assault that is similar to what was found by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0886260512441261">Hilden et al. (2005)</xref>. As mentioned earlier, a remarkably large group of all women reported amnesia in conjunction with the assault. As suspicions of “date rape” drugs were not confirmed by toxicology, the amnesia was most likely caused by a combination of psychological reactions and/or alcohol. This is consistent with our data that 92% of the women who reported having amnesia in conjunction with the assault also reported having been under the influence of alcohol.</p>
<p>The finding of higher self-reported alcohol use in the women assaulted by a stranger or acquaintance compared with assaults by an intimate partner is probably explained by the fact that a majority of these assaults take place during or after social interactions where alcohol often is being served. Acquaintance assailants may have used alcohol as an aid to isolate victims, a strategy not necessary for intimate partner assailants. Use of alcohol can impair an individual’s judgment, and our findings are consistent with the supposition that alcohol is a risk factor for acquaintance as well as stranger rape (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0886260512441261">Jones et al., 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>Finally, our finding of an overrepresentation of immigrant victims in the group of women assaulted by an intimate partner is interesting. To our knowledge, this has not earlier been presented in studies comparing victim–assailant relationships. For health workers, working in immigrant-dense areas this information could be helpful. Further research focusing on intimate partner assaults in minority groups is clearly warranted.</p>
<p>This study has some limitations and strengths that need to be mentioned. The study is retrospective, and the choice of variables was limited. Data collection was dependent on victim’s report, and it is not clear how reliable it is to collect data within the context of a forensic examination shortly after a sexual assault because of peritraumatic dissociation. Some women did not recall or were unwilling to relate assault details. Although no more than 17% of responses were missing for any one variable, it is possible that these missing data could have affected study findings. Data are collected from one hospital that in most cases probably would reduce generalizability, but as all sexual assault victim care in the region of Stockholm are centralized to one unit, these are the circumstances that give strength to the study. Victims from both suburban and urban areas are seen at the clinic. Our sample of sexual assault victims also consists of a wide variety of racial and age groups. As the study population consisted of all consecutive women seeking help at The Emergency Clinic for Raped Women during 1 year, we thereby also reduced the risk of selection bias. However, the results are still biased by not having any information on women who did not seek any help. As many as two out of three intimate partner victims had a previous history of sexual assault, compared with less than half in the whole study population and one in three in the group sexually assaulted by a stranger. Further details of the victim–assailant relationship and current status and duration of the relationship and previous abuse within the relationship would have added more information to the study.</p>
<p>The overall result of this study demonstrates the severity of sexual assaults committed by intimate partners. Women who have been sexually assaulted by their intimate partners are most often exposed to repetitive assaults, and physical violence is just as common as sexual assaults in these relationships (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0886260512441261">Lundgren et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0886260512441261">Stermac et al., 2001</xref>). The escalation of violence promotes the woman to finally seek help, with maybe only bruises on their arms and legs as “proof,” yet very important to document accurately. Our conclusion from these statistics is to advise examiners to look at the entire body. The epidemiology of sexual assaults in intimate partner relationships is uniquely different when compared with women assaulted by other known assailants and by strangers. The tendency to view sexual assaults by known assailants as “less serious” than those committed by strangers may have led to a lack of appropriate care for some of the women assaulted by intimate partners. With the knowledge that these assaults are just as violent, if not more, they should be taken just as seriously as those committed by strangers. Improved victim services and prevention strategies should be built on this knowledge.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<title>Bios</title>
<p><bold>Anna Sofia Möller</bold>, MD, is a doctoral student in the Department of Clinical Science and Education, Obstetrics and Gynecology at Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm South General Hospital. Her research interests include intimate partner violence, risk factors for posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD), and stress-related steroid hormones in rape victims.</p>
<p><bold>Torbjörn Bäckström</bold>, MD, PhD, is a professor in the Department of Clinical Science, Obstetrics and Gynecology at Umeå University. He is also head of Umeå Neurosteroid Research Center. His main research is concerning the role of neuroactive stress and sex steroids in the brain.</p>
<p><bold>Hans Peter Söndergaard</bold>, MD, PhD, is an associate professor in the Department of Clinical Neuroscience at Karolinska Institutet. He is also a clinical psychiatrist and senior consultant at the Crisis and Trauma Center at Danderyds Hospital, Sweden. His main research field is stress research and psychotraumatology.</p>
<p><bold>Lotti Helström</bold>, MD, PhD, is an associate professor in the Department of Clinical Science and Education at Karolinska Institutet. She is head of the Emergency Clinic for Raped Women at Stockholm South General Hospital and her current research is about posttraumatic stress disorder after rape.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0886260512441261">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grevholm</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carlstedt</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>National study of rapes reported to the police</source> (Report No. 7, pp. <fpage>48</fpage>-<lpage>52</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Stockholm, Sweden</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Council for Crime Prevention</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0886260512441261">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grossin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sibille</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lorin de la Grandmaison</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Banasr</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brion</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Durigon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Analysis of 418 cases of sexual assault</article-title>. <source>Forensic Science International</source>, <volume>131</volume>, <fpage>125</fpage>-<lpage>130</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0886260512441261">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haugen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Slungård</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schei</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Sexual assault against women: Injury pattern and victim–perpetrator relationship</article-title>. <source>Tidsskr Nor Laegeforen</source>, <volume>125</volume>, <fpage>3424</fpage>-<lpage>3427</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0886260512441261">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hilden</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schei</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sidenius</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Genitoanal injury in adult female victims of sexual assault</article-title>. <source>Forensic Science International</source>, <volume>154</volume>, <fpage>200</fpage>-<lpage>205</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0886260512441261">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wynn</surname><given-names>B. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kroeze</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunnuck</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rossman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Comparison of sexual assaults by strangers versus known assailants in a community-based population</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Emergency Medicine</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>454</fpage>-<lpage>459</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0886260512441261">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Sexuella övergrepp: Sex i Sverige</source> [<trans-source xml:lang="en">Sexual assaults: Sex in Sweden</trans-source>] (pp. <fpage>271</fpage>-<lpage>281</lpage>), <publisher-loc>Stockholm, Sweden</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Folkhälsoinstitutet</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0886260512441261">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>T. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Capillo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Differential characteristics of intimate partner: Acquaintance, and stranger rape survivors examined by a sexual assault nurse examiner</article-title>. <source>Journal of Interpersonal Violence</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>1066</fpage>-<lpage>1076</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0886260512441261">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Lundgren</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heimer</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Westerstrand</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kallioski</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.). (<year>2003</year>). <source>Slagen dam: Mäns våld mot kvinnor i jämställda Sverige—En omgångsundersökning</source> [<trans-source xml:lang="en">Captured Queen: Men’s violence against women in “egual” Sweden—A prevalence study</trans-source>] (p. 8). <publisher-loc>Stockholm, Sweden</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Fritzes offentliga publikationer</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0886260512441261">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maguire</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goodall</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Injury in adult female sexual assault complainants and related factors</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology and Reproductive Biology</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>149</fpage>-<lpage>153</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0886260512441261">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moskowitz</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>“Scared stiff”: Catatonia as an evolutionary-based fear response</article-title>. <source>Psychological Review</source>, <volume>111</volume>, <fpage>984</fpage>-<lpage>1002</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0886260512441261">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pierce-Weeks</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stapleton</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wiesen-Martin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>An examination of SANE data: Clinical considerations based on victim-assailant relationship</article-title>. <source>Journal of Forensic Nursing</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>137</fpage>-<lpage>144</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0886260512441261">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McNulty</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Déste</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Genital injuries in women reporting sexual assault</article-title>. <source>Sex Health</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>-<lpage>59</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0886260512441261">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Slaughter</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Colposcopy to establish physical findings in rape victims</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology</source>, <volume>166</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>83</fpage>-<lpage>86</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0886260512441261">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Slaughter</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Patterns of genital injury in female sexual assault victims</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology</source>, <volume>176</volume>, <fpage>609</fpage>-<lpage>616</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0886260512441261">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stermac</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Del Bove</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Addison</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Violence, injury, and presentation patterns in spousal sexual assaults</article-title>. <source>Violence against women</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>1218</fpage>-<lpage>1233</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0886260512441261">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stermac</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Du Mont</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalemba</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Comparison of sexual assaults by strangers and known assailants in an urban population of women</article-title>. <source>Canadian Medical Association Journal</source>, <volume>153</volume>, <fpage>1089</fpage>-<lpage>1094</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0886260512441261">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sugar</surname><given-names>N. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fine</surname><given-names>D. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eckert</surname><given-names>L. O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Physical injury after sexual assault: Findings of large case series</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology</source>, <volume>190</volume>, <fpage>71</fpage>-<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0886260512441261">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tjaden</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thoennes</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>Full report of the prevalence, incidence and consequences of violence against women: Findings from the National Violence Against Women Survey</source> (NCJ 183781). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Institutes of Justice, Center for Disease Control</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0886260512441261">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ullman</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Victim-offender relationship and sexual assault</article-title>. <source>Violence &amp; Victims</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>121</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0886260512441261">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Walby</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Domestic violence, sexual assault and stalking: Findings from the 2001 British crime survey</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Home Office Research, Development and Statistics Directorate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0886260512441261">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>White</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Adolescent complainants of sexual assault: Injury patterns in virgin and non-virgin groups</article-title>. <source>Journal of Forensic and Legal Medicine</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>172</fpage>-<lpage>180</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>