<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MSJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spmsj</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mult Scler</journal-id>
<journal-title>Multiple Sclerosis Journal</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1352-4585</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-0970</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1352458511419702</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1352458511419702</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Papers</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Benign multiple sclerosis: a new definition of this entity is needed</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Correale</surname><given-names>Jorge</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1352458511419702">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Peirano</surname><given-names>Isabel</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1352458511419702">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>Lucas</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1352458511419702">2</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1352458511419702"><label>1</label>Department of Neurology, Institute for Neurological Research Raúl Carrea, FLENI, Buenos Aires, Argentina.</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1352458511419702"><label>2</label>Neurology Department, Hospital Privado de Comunidad, Mar del Plata, Argentina.</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1352458511419702">Jorge Correale, Raúl Carrea Institute for Neurological Research, FLENI, Montañeses 2325, (1428) Buenos Aires, Argentina. Email: <email>jcorreale@fleni.org.ar</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>18</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>210</fpage>
<lpage>218</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>1</day>
<month>6</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>11</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>18</day>
<month>7</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p><bold>Background:</bold> To study a cohort of benign multiple sclerosis (BMS) patients beyond physical disability, including the evaluation of cognitive and social function, as well as fatigue, pain and MRI studies.</p>
<p><bold>Methods:</bold> A cohort of 342 patients was prospectively followed for 10.9 ± 0.71 years. Forty-three patients (12.5%) met the BMS diagnosis criteria [Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS) &lt; 3 after at least 10 years’ disease duration], undergoing full neurological examination every 6 months. Neuropsychological status, pain, fatigue, social functioning and work-related disability, as well as brain MRIs, were assessed yearly.</p>
<p><bold>Results:</bold> By the end of follow-up, 20 of 43 BMS patients (47%) had suffered cognitive impairment and 23 (53.3%) referred depression. Furthermore, 21 (48.8%) reported significant changes in pain intensity, with fatigue and environmental severity scores significantly increasing over time in 33–35% of patients. Finally, 32 BMS patients (74%) showed significant increase in the number of new or enlarging T2 lesions, gadolinium-enhanced lesions, and persistent black holes, without changes in EDSS. Thirty-five of 43 patients (81%) fulfilling the BMS diagnostic criteria showed significant worsening of cognitive function, fatigue, pain or depression during the 10-year follow-up.</p>
<p><bold>Conclusions:</bold> Currently accepted criteria for BMS diagnosis may cause overestimation of true prevalence, underscoring the need for routine monitoring of non-motor symptoms and imaging studies, to help physicians improve diagnostic accuracy as well as therapeutic decision-making in this subgroup of MS patients.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>MRI</kwd>
<kwd>multiple sclerosis</kwd>
<kwd>neuropsychological assessment</kwd>
<kwd>prognosis</kwd>
<kwd>quality of life</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1352458511419702" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Multiple sclerosis (MS) is a disease characterized by a wide range of progression. There is a subgroup of patients who show little or no disease progression and minimal disability many years after initial symptoms are diagnosed; this form is referred to as benign MS (BMS). Prevalence estimates of BMS vary widely in the literature, with authors quoting figures ranging between as low as 5% and as high as 64% of all MS cases.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1352458511419702">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1352458511419702">8</xref></sup> This is probably due to the use of different definitions, of different study designs (e.g. population-based cohorts vs. hospital-based cohorts), and on whether or not mortality estimates are included in estimation calculations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1352458511419702">9</xref></sup></p>
<p>Although there is lack of consensus and much heterogeneity, the most widely used definition of BMS is an Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS) &lt; 3 after a minimum of 10 years’ disease duration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1352458511419702">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1352458511419702">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1352458511419702">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1352458511419702">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1352458511419702">10</xref></sup> Nevertheless, when applying this score to monitor disease progression, one should bear in mind that it shows relatively low reliability and poor responsiveness to disease-related changes, because it is heavily weighted towards motor disability, in particular ambulation, and not influenced by the presence or severity of other debilitating symptoms such as depression, fatigue, pain or cognitive impairment, which also affect quality of life. Incorporating imaging results would contribute to better characterize BMS, as lower lesion accrual rates and less severe tissue damage would be expected in this disease subtype.</p>
<p>This study aims at a more comprehensive understanding of BMS, beyond physical disability, by providing a more thorough assessment of cognitive function, fatigue, pain, imaging studies and social functioning in a clinical cohort of patients fulfilling the current criteria accepted for BMS definition.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1352458511419702" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="section3-1352458511419702">
<title>Subjects and study design</title>
<p>A prospective study was conducted based on the analysis of longitudinal clinical and radiological data acquired from a cohort of MS outpatients between 1 April 1997 and 30 April 2009, consecutively selected while undergoing follow-up at the Institute for Neurological Research Raúl Carrea [Fundación para la Lucha contra las Enfermedades Neurológicas de la Infancia (FLENI)]. Inclusion was based on the diagnosis of clinically definite relapsing–remitting MS (RRMS) according to the Poser criteria. The study included all MS patients with onset of disease since 1 April 1997. This onset period potentially allowed all patients to reach 10 or more years of disease duration. All of the patients were relapse-free and had not taken steroids for at least 3 months before the assessment. All scheduled outpatient follow-up evaluations were conducted by the same neurologist (JC) and included complete neurological examination and EDSS rating every 6 months.</p>
<p>Neuropsychological testing, pain and fatigue severity, and degree of work-related disability and social functioning were assessed once a year as described below. MS was defined as benign in patients presenting an EDSS score &lt; 3, 10 years after the clinical onset of the disease as a minimum. The Lublin and Reingold criteria<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1352458511419702">11</xref></sup> were applied to establish whether the clinical course was RRMS or secondary progressive MS (SPMS). A particular EDSS score was considered irreversible if it remained unchanged after 12 months of observation. Thirty-five age- and gender-matched healthy volunteers were also studied, 24 women and 11 men, mean age: 37.5 ± 6.2 years (range 26–52 years). None referred previous neurological or systemic diseases potentially affecting central nervous system (CNS) function, and the neurological exam was normal in all cases. Of these individuals, 30 also agreed to come for the same follow-up evaluations (86%; 21 women, 9 men; mean age: 37.3 ± 6.1) as established for BMS patients.</p>
<p>The study was approved by the local ethics committee and all subjects were required to sign written informed-consent forms prior to study entry.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1352458511419702">
<title>Neuropsychological evaluation</title>
<p>All patients included in the study underwent neuropsychological evaluation exploring the following cognitive domains: (a) attention, concentration and speed of information processing [Paced Auditorial Serial Attention Test 3 seconds (PASAT-3)];<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1352458511419702">12</xref></sup> (b) immediate and recent memory [Digit Span (DS) and 7/24 Spatial Recall Test (SRT)];<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1352458511419702">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1352458511419702">14</xref></sup> (c) executive function [Wisconsin Card Sorting Test (WCST)];<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1352458511419702">15</xref></sup> and (d) visual-spatial skills [Visual Form Discrimination Test (VFDT)].<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1352458511419702">16</xref></sup> Test failure was defined as a score at least 2 SDs below mean normative values. Patients failing at least three tests were considered cognitively impaired. Finally, depression was examined using the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1352458511419702">17</xref></sup> Participants requiring psychoactive drugs or other substances potentially affecting neuropsychological performance were excluded.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1352458511419702">
<title>Pain evaluation</title>
<p>To assess pain, participants were asked: ‘Are you currently experiencing, or have you in the past 3 months experienced any pain?’. Patients responding affirmatively were then evaluated using the Brief Pain Inventory-Long Form (BPI-LF).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1352458511419702">18</xref></sup> Pain syndromes evaluated included: neuropathic pain (trigeminal neuralgia, Lhermitte’s sign, dysesthetic pain), somatic pain (back pain and painful tonic spasms) and visceral pain. Headache, acute pain due to optical neuritis or somatic pain (with the exception of back pain and tonic spasms) are not included.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1352458511419702">
<title>Other evaluations</title>
<p>Fatigue severity was measured using the Fatigue Severity Scale (FSS).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1352458511419702">19</xref></sup> For handicap in work and social activities the Environmental Status Scale (ESS) was employed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1352458511419702">20</xref></sup> All evaluations were carried out during relapse-free periods, in patients off steroids for at least 6 months.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1352458511419702">
<title>MRI</title>
<p>Brain MRIs were performed using the same protocol in all patients, at least once a year on a 1.5-T Signa Unit (GE Healthcare, Milwaukee, WI, USA). Five-millimeter axial slices were obtained with T2-weighted, proton density, fast spin echo, fluid attenuation inversion recovery, and T1-weighted sequences, before and after administration of gadolinium (Gd)-diethylene triamine pentaacetic acid (DTPA) (0.1 mmol/kg). Post-contrast images were completed within 15 min after Gd injection. Changes in number of new or enlarging T2 lesions, new Gd-enhanced lesions or persistent black holes were diagnosed in each patient by a single observer, blind to patient clinical status.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1352458511419702">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>Group comparisons were assessed using the non-parametric Mann–Whitney test. To correlate patient demographics and clinical characteristics, the Spearman’s coefficient <italic>r</italic> was used. Potential BMS prognostic factors were analyzed first by logistic regression, followed by univariate analysis to identify possible variables associated with a benign course, and then by multivariate analysis to identify the independent effects of the prognostic factors studied. In all cases <italic>p</italic> values &lt; 0.05 were taken as significant.</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section9-1352458511419702" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>A cohort of 342 Hispanic patients was prospectively studied during a 10.9 ± 0.71 year period (range 10–12 years). One hundred and ninety-five non-benign MS patients (57%) presented with RRMS, and 104 patients (30.4%) with SPMS. Forty-three patients (12.5%) met the criteria for BMS diagnosis (EDSS &lt; 3 after at least 10 years’ disease duration). Main clinical and demographic cohort characteristics are described in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1352458511419702">Table 1</xref>. No significant differences in terms of age at onset, sex, disease duration, baseline EDSS, or symptoms at onset were observed between patients with non-benign disease and BMS patients. The only predictive factor associated with benign status was a low number of relapses in the first 5 years (<italic>p</italic> = 0.02). The evaluations of these 43 BMS patients are described in subsequent sections of this article.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1352458511419702" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Clinical and demographic characteristics of the study sample<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1352458511419702">a</xref></sup></p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1352458511419702" xlink:href="10.1177_1352458511419702-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Total sample (<italic>n</italic> = 342)</th>
<th align="left">Benign MS (<italic>n</italic> = 43)</th>
<th align="left">Non-benign MS (<italic>n</italic> = 299)</th>
<th align="left"><italic>p</italic> value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Gender (men/women)</td>
<td>137/205</td>
<td>15/28</td>
<td>114/185</td>
<td>ns</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age (years)</td>
<td>38.5 ± 8.3</td>
<td>37.2 ± 7.1</td>
<td>37.5 ± 6.2</td>
<td>ns</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Education (years)</td>
<td>13.8 ± 3.0</td>
<td>14.01 ± 2.2</td>
<td>15.4 ± 2.1</td>
<td>ns</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age at onset (years)</td>
<td>26.3 ± 9.1</td>
<td>27.5 ± 7.3</td>
<td>25.3 ± 8.1</td>
<td>ns</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Disease duration (years)</td>
<td>10.9 ± 0.71</td>
<td>10.8 ± 0.58</td>
<td>10.9 ± 0.82</td>
<td>ns</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Baseline EDSS</td>
<td>1.7 ± 1.0</td>
<td>1.6 ± 0.8</td>
<td>1.8 ± 0.9</td>
<td>ns</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Initial symptoms, <italic>n</italic> (%)</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>Motor</italic></td>
<td>41 (12%)</td>
<td>6 (15%)</td>
<td>39 (13%)</td>
<td>ns</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>Sensory</italic></td>
<td>164 (48%)</td>
<td>19 (45%)</td>
<td>137 (46%)</td>
<td>ns</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>Optical</italic></td>
<td>82 (24%)</td>
<td>11 (26%)</td>
<td>69 (23%)</td>
<td>ns</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> <italic>Cerebellar/brainstem</italic></td>
<td>41 (12%)</td>
<td>4 (10%)</td>
<td>33 (11%)</td>
<td>ns</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Number of patients on DMT (treated/not treated)</td>
<td>239/103</td>
<td>32/11</td>
<td>221/78</td>
<td>ns</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1352458511419702"><p>MS: multiple sclerosis; DMT: disease modifying therapy, EDSS: Expanded Disability Status Scale, ns: not significant.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-1352458511419702"><label>a</label><p>Values are expressed as mean values ± SD.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section10-1352458511419702">
<title>Cognitive impairment in BMS patients</title>
<p>Cognitive impairment is increasingly recognized as a common and burdensome manifestation of MS, adversely affecting quality of life. By the end of follow-up (at least 10 years), 20 of the 43 BMS patients (47%) were diagnosed as cognitively impaired (failed at least three tests). Of the remaining 23 (53%) with preserved cognitive function, two showed changes on a single test (5%), and 21 patients (49%) showed no changes on any of the three tests. Groups did not differ in terms of main clinical or demographic characteristics. Frequencies with which specific domains were affected are shown on <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1352458511419702">Table 2</xref>. Values observed at the end of the study were significantly lower than those observed at baseline for all the domains (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1352458511419702">Table 3</xref>), indicating patient worsening during follow-up (<italic>p</italic> = 0.001– &lt; 0.0001).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1352458511419702" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption><p>Neuropsychological test results in 43 benign MS patients</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1352458511419702" xlink:href="10.1177_1352458511419702-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Cognitive domains and tests</th>
<th align="left">Number of patients with an abnormal performance at year 10 or later (%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="2"><bold>Attention</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> PASAT-3</td>
<td>20 (46.5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2"><bold>Memory</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Digit Span forward</td>
<td>19 (44.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Digit Span backward</td>
<td>20 (46.5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 7/24 Spatial Recall Test</td>
<td>20 (46.5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2"><bold>Executive functions</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Wisconsin Card Sorting Test</td>
<td>19 (44.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2"><bold>Visual-spatial skills</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Visual Form Discrimination Test</td>
<td>18 (41.8)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1352458511419702"><p>MS: multiple sclerosis; PASAT-3: Paced Auditorial Serial Attention Test 3 seconds.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table3-1352458511419702" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption><p>Scores in neuropsychological tests, Beck Depression Inventory, Fatigue Severity Scale, and Environmental Status Scale at baseline and 10 or more years later in 43 benign MS patients</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1352458511419702" xlink:href="10.1177_1352458511419702-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="left">Basal score</th>
<th align="left">Score at year 10 or later</th>
<th align="left"><italic>p</italic> value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>EDSS</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean ± SD</td>
<td>1.58 ± 0.80</td>
<td>1.66 ± 0.81</td>
<td rowspan="3">ns</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median</td>
<td>1.5</td>
<td>1.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Range</td>
<td>0–3</td>
<td>0–3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>PASAT<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1352458511419702">a</xref></sup></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean ± SD</td>
<td>32.81 ± 4.09</td>
<td>28.06 ± 5.3</td>
<td rowspan="3">&lt; 0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Range</td>
<td>23–39</td>
<td>20–39</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>Wisconsin<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1352458511419702">a</xref></sup></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean ± SD</td>
<td>3.88 ± 1.11</td>
<td>2.88 ± 1.05</td>
<td rowspan="3">0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Range</td>
<td>1–5</td>
<td>1–5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>Visual form<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1352458511419702">a</xref></sup></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean ± SD</td>
<td>29.69 ± 2.44</td>
<td>25.55± 5.1</td>
<td rowspan="3">0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Range</td>
<td>23–33</td>
<td>15–33</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>7/24 Spatial Recall Test<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1352458511419702">a</xref></sup></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean ± SD</td>
<td>28.55 ± 2.56</td>
<td>24.19 ± 3.12</td>
<td rowspan="3">0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Range</td>
<td>22–34</td>
<td>16–34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>Digit Span forward<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1352458511419702">a</xref></sup></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean ± SD</td>
<td>6.27 ± 0.09</td>
<td>4.55 ± 2.20</td>
<td rowspan="3">0.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Range</td>
<td>5–7</td>
<td>2–7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>Digit Span backward<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1352458511419702">a</xref></sup></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean ± SD</td>
<td>5.72 ± 0.45</td>
<td>4.04 ± 1.77</td>
<td rowspan="3">&lt; 0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Range</td>
<td>5–6</td>
<td>2–6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>Beck Depression Inventory<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1352458511419702">b</xref></sup></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean ± SD</td>
<td>3.25 ± 5.59</td>
<td>20.35 ± 12.21</td>
<td rowspan="3">&lt; 0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Range</td>
<td>0–29</td>
<td>3–48</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>Fatigue Severity Scale<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1352458511419702">b</xref></sup></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean ± SD</td>
<td>18.90 ± 7.22</td>
<td>25.62 ± 11.57</td>
<td rowspan="3">0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Range</td>
<td>9–33</td>
<td>9–46</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>Environmental Status Scale<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1352458511419702">b</xref></sup></bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean ± SD</td>
<td>7.97 ± 2.65</td>
<td>11.37 ± 5.69</td>
<td rowspan="3">0.01</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Range</td>
<td>4–16</td>
<td>5–23</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-1352458511419702"><p>MS: multiple sclerosis; EDSS: Expanded Disability Status Scale, ns: not significant, PASAT: Paced Auditorial Serial Attention Test.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-1352458511419702"><label>a</label><p>Lower values represent worst performance; <sup>b</sup>Higher values represent worst performance.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Depression is commonly observed in MS patients and has been negatively associated with quality of life scores. Using a BDI cut-off score of 21, two of 43 BMS patients (4.6%) were classified as depressed at baseline, although none as suffering severe depression (BDI score &gt; 29). As for cognitive performance, depression rates were significantly higher at the end of the study, with 23 of 43 BMS patients (53.5%) diagnosed as depressed (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001), and five of these (21.8%) as severely depressed (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1352458511419702">Table 3</xref>). No correlation was found between BDI scores and MRI parameters in patients who worsened by depression.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1352458511419702">
<title>Pain frequency and severity in BMS patients</title>
<p>Another symptom not adequately rated by the EDSS score is pain, increasingly recognized as causing significant handicap to MS patients. Only five BMS patients (11.6%) reported pain at baseline or in the 3 months preceding evaluation. Average pain intensity for the group as a whole was 0.20 ± 0.63, for a 0–10 scale, with weak functional interference score (1.30 ± 4.18). As shown on <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1352458511419702">Table 4</xref>, results were similar in healthy controls (0.17 ± 0.51 and 1.34 ± 3.81, respectively). After 10 or more years follow-up, 21 of 43 BMS patients (48.8%) reported bothersome pain in the last 3 months prior to evaluation, in contrast to only four of 30 healthy controls (13.3%) reporting mild pain. Mean pain intensity score for the whole BMS group was 3.09 ± 3.31, significantly higher both to the score observed at baseline (<italic>p</italic> = 0.0005) and to the score observed in healthy subjects re-evaluated at this time (<italic>p</italic> = 0.002; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1352458511419702">Table 4</xref>). Of the BMS patients who reported pain, 30% ranked it as severe (score 7–10). Similarly, at the end of the study the average pain interference level was also significantly higher in BMS (20.76 ± 24.09) compared to baseline values (<italic>p</italic> = 0.0008) and healthy controls (1.8 ± 4.7; <italic>p</italic> = 0.004; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1352458511419702">Table 4</xref>). Overall, after 10 years’ disease duration, a four-fold increase is observed in the level of pain referred by BMS subjects compared to disease onset. Moreover, both pain intensity and interference scores significantly increased over time despite the absence of changes in EDSS score.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-1352458511419702" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption><p>Values of pain intensity score and pain interference score at baseline and at year 10 or later in benign MS patients and healthy controls</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1352458511419702" xlink:href="10.1177_1352458511419702-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Score</th>
<th align="left">Basal score</th>
<th align="left">Score at year 10 or later</th>
<th align="left"><italic>p</italic> value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>Pain intensity score</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Benign MS patients</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mean ± SD</td>
<td>0.20 ± 0.63<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1352458511419702">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>3.09 ± 3.31<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-1352458511419702">b</xref></sup></td>
<td rowspan="3">0.0005</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Range</td>
<td>0–3</td>
<td>0–9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Healthy controls</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean ± SD</td>
<td>0.17 ± 0.51</td>
<td>0.24 ± 0.63</td>
<td rowspan="3">ns</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Range</td>
<td>0–2</td>
<td>0–2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>Pain interference score</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Benign MS patients</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean ± SD</td>
<td>1.30 ± 4.18<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-1352458511419702">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>20.76 ± 24.09<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-1352458511419702">c</xref></sup></td>
<td rowspan="3">0.0008</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Range</td>
<td>0–16</td>
<td>0–66</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4">Healthy controls</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean ± SD</td>
<td>1.34 ± 3.81</td>
<td>1.8 ± 4.70</td>
<td rowspan="3">ns</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Range</td>
<td>0–13</td>
<td>0–16</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn6-1352458511419702"><p>MS: multiple sclerosis; ns: not significant</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn7-1352458511419702"><label>a</label><p>Not significant compared with healthy controls.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn8-1352458511419702"><label>b</label><p><italic>p</italic> = 0.002 compared with values observed in healthy controls.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn9-1352458511419702"><label>c</label><p><italic>p</italic> = 0.004 compared with values observed in healthy controls.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1352458511419702">
<title>Changes in fatigue score and the ESS</title>
<p>Fatigue is one of the most disabling symptoms of the disease, significantly limiting daily activities. Nonetheless, it is only minimally evaluated in the EDSS score. At baseline, the mean FSS score for the 43 BMS patients was 18.90 ± 7.22. None presented severe fatigue (score &gt; 36). In contrast, after 10 years or more, mean FSS scores increased considerably (25.62 ± 11.57; <italic>p</italic> = 0.01; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1352458511419702">Table 3</xref>). FSS score progression was observed over time in 14 BMS patients (33%); of these 13 (93%) had severe fatigue. The frequency and intensity of fatigue was not significantly different between patients treated with disease-modifying therapies or untreated patients. Moreover, fatigue severity was independent of BDI. As for fatigue evaluation, at disease onset BMS patients had lower ESS scores (7.97 ± 2.65), compared to 10 or more years later (11.37 ± 5.69; <italic>p</italic> = 0.01; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1352458511419702">Table 3</xref>). Fifteen BMS patients (35%) had progressively worse ESS scores, particularly for items exploring social activities and work status. Additional analysis showed ESS scores were higher in cognitively impaired BMS patients (<italic>p</italic> = 0.01). ESS scores were also higher for BMS patients with depression (BDI &gt; 21) than those without depression (<italic>p</italic> = 0.03).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1352458511419702">
<title>MRI in BMS patients</title>
<p>Thirty-two BMS patients (74%) significantly increased the number of new or enlarging T2 lesions, Gd-enhanced lesions, and persistent black holes from baseline to last follow-up (10 years or later; <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1352458511419702">Table 5</xref>) despite not presenting changes in EDSS. As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-1352458511419702">Table 6</xref>, BMS patients without cognitive impairment showed less progression in the number of new or enlarging T2 lesions, Gd-enhanced lesions, or persistent black holes than patients with cognitive impairment or patients with non-benign MS (both RRMS and SPMS; <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001). Conversely, when BMS patients with cognitive impairment were compared with non-benign MS patients, no significant differences were found in the number of new or enlarging T2 lesions and Gd-enhanced lesions. However, progression from baseline to last follow-up for the number of persistent black holes was lower (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) in BMS patients than in SPMS subjects.</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-1352458511419702" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption><p>MRI measures at baseline and at year 10 or later in 43 benign MS patients</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-1352458511419702" xlink:href="10.1177_1352458511419702-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="left">Basal</th>
<th align="left">Year 10 or later</th>
<th align="left"><italic>p</italic> value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>New or enlarging T2 lesions</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean ± SD</td>
<td>8.09 ± 2.6</td>
<td>14 ± 7.97</td>
<td rowspan="3">&lt;0.0001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median</td>
<td>8.0</td>
<td>10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Range</td>
<td>5–15</td>
<td>5–33</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>Gd-enhanced lesions</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean ± SD</td>
<td>1.48 ± 1.18</td>
<td>4.23 ± 3.21</td>
<td rowspan="3">0.0002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median</td>
<td>2.0</td>
<td>3.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Range</td>
<td>0–4</td>
<td>0–9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="4"><bold>Persistent black holes</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean ± SD</td>
<td>0.32 ± 0.56</td>
<td>2.60 ± 2.76</td>
<td rowspan="3">0.0002</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Range</td>
<td>0–2</td>
<td>0–9</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn10-1352458511419702"><p>Gd: gadolinium.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table6-1352458511419702" position="float">
<label>Table 6.</label>
<caption><p>Changes in MRI measures in benign MS patients with and without cognitive impairment, RRMS, and SPMS patients</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table6-1352458511419702" xlink:href="10.1177_1352458511419702-table6.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th rowspan="2"/>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Benign MS patients</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">Non-benign MS patients</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Without cognitive impairment <italic>N</italic> = 23</th>
<th align="left">With cognitive impairment <italic>N</italic> = 20</th>
<th align="left">RRMS <italic>N</italic> = 195</th>
<th align="left">SPMS <italic>N</italic> = 104</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Changes in the number of new or enlarging T2 lesions</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean ± SD</td>
<td>1.8 ± 1.9</td>
<td>12.5 ± 3.1</td>
<td>13.8 ± 4.1</td>
<td>14.0 ± 4.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Range</td>
<td>0–5</td>
<td>9–19</td>
<td>7–22</td>
<td>5–22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Changes in the number of Gd-enhanced lesions</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean ± SD</td>
<td>0.7 ± 1.0</td>
<td>5.2 ± 1.4</td>
<td>5.6 ± 2.4</td>
<td>4.9 ± 2.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Range</td>
<td>0–3</td>
<td>2–8</td>
<td>0–12</td>
<td>0–10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Changes in the number of persistent black holes</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mean ± SD</td>
<td>0.3 ± 0.7</td>
<td>4.6 ± 1.9</td>
<td>4.6 ± 2.5</td>
<td>9.7 ± 3.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Median</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Range</td>
<td>0–3</td>
<td>1–9</td>
<td>1–9</td>
<td>4–18</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn11-1352458511419702"><p>Gd: gadolinium, RRMS: relapsing–remitting multiple sclerosis, SPMS: secondary progressive multiple sclerosis.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table7-1352458511419702">Table 7</xref> summarizes the number of individuals who worsened for each evaluation. Of the 43 patients originally classified as BMS, only eight (18.6%) did not show impairment in cognitive function, MRI changes, or significant variation in PBI-LF, FSS or ESS scores.</p>
<table-wrap id="table7-1352458511419702" position="float">
<label>Table 7.</label>
<caption><p>Number of subjects who worsened by the end of follow-up according to the evaluation parameter used in 43 benign MS patients</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table7-1352458511419702" xlink:href="10.1177_1352458511419702-table7.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Evaluation</th>
<th align="left">Number (%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Cognitive impairment<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn13-1352458511419702">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>20 (47)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Depression (BDI)</td>
<td>23 (53.5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pain (BPI-LF)</td>
<td>21 (48.8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fatigue (FSS)</td>
<td>14 (33)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Environmental status (ESS)</td>
<td>15 (35)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MRI changes</td>
<td>32 (74)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn12-1352458511419702"><p>MS: multiple sclerosis; BDI: Beck Depression Inventory, BPI-LF: Brief Pain Inventory-Long Form, ESS: Environmental Status Scale, FSS: Fatigue Severity Scale.</p></fn>
<fn id="table-fn13-1352458511419702"><label>a</label><p>Patients failed at least three tests.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1352458511419702" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The definition of BMS has changed over time and remains controversial. The most frequently used one is an EDSS score &lt; 3 after at least 10 years from disease onset.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1352458511419702">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1352458511419702">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1352458511419702">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1352458511419702">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1352458511419702">10</xref></sup> However, different cut-offs for disease duration and disability EDSS levels have been used.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1352458511419702">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1352458511419702">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1352458511419702">21</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1352458511419702">23</xref></sup> These definitions are all based on retrospective evaluations, and for the time being no strong clinical, demographic, genetic, laboratory or radiological prognostic markers predicting a benign course exist.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1352458511419702">23</xref></sup> Indeed, longitudinal studies have frequently shown that patients with BMS can develop a secondary progressive course, or suffer more severity and accumulate disability over time,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1352458511419702">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1352458511419702">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1352458511419702">23</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1352458511419702">25</xref></sup> thus leading physicians to treat early rather than for the clinical outcome to manifest.</p>
<p>This report provides prospectively acquired, longitudinal clinical, environmental, and MRI data from BMS patients. In this cohort, BMS incidence was 12.5% after 10.9 ± 0.71 years follow-up. However, 35 of 43 patients (81%) meeting the BMS definition criteria significantly showed worsened cognitive functions, fatigue, pain, or depression over the years, ultimately mirrored by significant changes in the ESS, with a negative impact on items exploring social activities and work status in particular. Moreover, of 43 patients defined as BMS, 32 (74%) showed MRI disease progression over time (new or enlarging T2 lesions, Gd-enhanced lesions, and persistent black holes) similar to those findings in RRMS or SPMS patients.</p>
<p>Our results are in line with previous studies suggesting that cognitive impairment, fatigue and depression may be relevant in patients with BMS, despite relative sparing of motor abilities. In a recent study conducted in 163 BMS patients, cognitive dysfunction, significant fatigue and depression were found in over 45% of patients, with negative impact on social and work activities.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1352458511419702">26</xref></sup> Interestingly, these rates were comparable to those reported in MS patients at large. Moreover, neuropsychological testing results and brain MRI measurements showed that risk of progression in BMS patients was enhanced by male gender, baseline cognitive impairment and baseline T1 lesion burden.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1352458511419702">27</xref></sup> This is an important observation which confirms neuropsychological functioning as another important measure of brain integrity. In contrast to our prospective study, most of these investigations had a cross-sectional design. To assess the temporal evolution of structural and functional changes, prospective assessments are more accurate than cross-sectional studies with retrospective assessments.</p>
<p>In line with our observations, several MRI studies have not been able to show major differences in the number of brain T2 lesions in patients with BMS and RRMS or SPMS, despite major differences in disability.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1352458511419702">28</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1352458511419702">30</xref></sup> Two factors have been proposed as responsible for these findings. First, lesion location in eloquent CNS regions,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1352458511419702">31</xref></sup> and second, lower accumulation rate of disease burden in BMS patients, which might increase efficiency of cortical reorganization mechanisms following MS injury.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1352458511419702">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1352458511419702">32</xref></sup></p>
<p>Considerable effort has been undertaken to identify prognostic factors in MS. The only one we found associated with benign status was a low number of relapses in the first 5 years. In line with this finding, natural history studies have reported a significant association between the number of relapses in the early years of the disease and the subsequent development of disability.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1352458511419702">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1352458511419702">34</xref></sup> However, others have failed to find any association between the number of attacks in early MS and disability outcome,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1352458511419702">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1352458511419702">36</xref></sup> and the debate over this issue continues. Some authors have indicated that younger age at onset, optic neuritis as first attack, female gender, and longer first remission are significantly associated with a benign course of MS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1352458511419702">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1352458511419702">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1352458511419702">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1352458511419702">37</xref></sup> However, we did not find onset symptoms to have a predictive effect on disease severity, as was also the case for other authors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1352458511419702">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1352458511419702">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1352458511419702">39</xref></sup> Likewise, age at onset<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1352458511419702">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1352458511419702">38</xref></sup> and sex<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1352458511419702">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1352458511419702">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1352458511419702">38</xref></sup> were not significantly associated with benign status in our study when other factors are controlled for.</p>
<p>There are of course some limitations to this study. First, it was not population-based and patients may not entirely reflect the overall group of BMS subjects. Nevertheless, although our population was clinic-based and a potential selection bias towards more severe cases cannot be ruled out, this does not alter the core finding, namely that patients included in the study met the current BMS criteria. Furthermore, because of the longitudinal design of the study, structural and functional changes in the cohort were clearly demonstrated over time. Second, because this study was started in 1997, not all patients were evaluated with the more contemporary cognitive test batteries such as the Minimal Assessment of Cognitive Function in Multiple Sclerosis (MACFIMS), however, the tests included still assessed attention, concentration and speed of information processing, immediate and recent memory, executive function and visual-spatial skills, which are the most commonly affected cognitive domains in MS patients. Finally, recent years have seen the introduction of several new MRI techniques, improving the limited correlation between T2-weighted images and patient clinical disability.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1352458511419702">40</xref></sup> Given that this study was initiated over 10 years ago, the most recent MRI techniques have not been included. However, no changes in scanner hardware or software were introduced during the follow-up period. Results of recent MRI studies indicate that while there appear to be no differences between BMS and RRMS patients in terms of T2-lesion load, there are in fact differences in other MRI parameters such as magnetization transfer,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1352458511419702">41</xref></sup> magnetic resonance spectroscopy,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1352458511419702">42</xref></sup> diffusion tensor MRI,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1352458511419702">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1352458511419702">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1352458511419702">44</xref></sup> functional MRI,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1352458511419702">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1352458511419702">45</xref></sup> and general brain atrophy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1352458511419702">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1352458511419702">46</xref></sup> These studies used cross-sectional design or only had very short follow-up periods, and consequently their results do not allow assessment of changes over time. Therefore, caution is needed before drawing firm conclusions on MS dynamics, and longitudinal studies are warranted to confirm these findings.</p>
<p>Overall, the results of this study indicate that although our patients met currently accepted criteria for BMS, clinical symptoms as well as radiological images progressed over time, causing major impact on everyday life activities. Nevertheless, it is also true that a certain number of MS patients remain free of long-term physical or cognitive disability. Indeed, subclinical cases of MS have been described in sibling studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1352458511419702">47</xref></sup> and post-mortem examinations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1352458511419702">48</xref></sup> These observations suggest that a less aggressive form of MS may exist, but harder to identify and more complex than previously thought.</p>
<p>It is likely that the currently accepted criteria for BMS may cause overestimation of its true incidence, underscoring the need for routine monitoring of non-motor symptoms and of CNS imaging. A need to reassess the current clinical definition of BMS clearly exists. This information would in turn optimize patient management and provide clues to improve therapeutic decision-making in this subgroup of patients.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>Dr. Correale is a board member of Merck-Serono Argentina, Biogen-Idec LATAM, and Merck-Serono LATAM. Dr. Correale has received reimbursement to develop educational presentations for Merck-Serono Argentina, Merck-Serono LATAM, Biogen-Idec Argentina, and TEVA-Tuteur Argentina as well as professional travel/accommodations stipends. Dr Peirano has no disclosures to report. Dr Romano has no disclosures to report.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1352458511419702">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Poser</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wikström</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clinical data and the identification of special forms of multiple sclerosis in 1271 cases studied with a standardized documentation system</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Sci</source> <year>1979</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>159</fpage>–<lpage>168</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1352458511419702">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brazil</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feighery</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A clinical and laboratory study of benign multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Q J Med</source> <year>1986</year>; <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1352458511419702">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McDonell</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Benign multiple sclerosis? Clinical course, long term follow up and assessment of prognostic factors</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>148</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1352458511419702">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Benedikz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stefánsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guomundsson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jónasdóttir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fossdal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gulcher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The natural history of untreated multiple sclerosis in Iceland. A total population-based 50 year prospective study</article-title>. <source>Clin Neurol Neurosurg</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>208</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1352458511419702">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pittock</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McClelland</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mayr</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weinshenker</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Noseworthy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical implications of benign multiple sclerosis: a 20-year population-based follow-up study</article-title>. <source>Ann Neurol</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>303</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1352458511419702">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sayao</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Devonshire</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tremlett</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Longitudinal follow-up of “benign” multiple sclerosis at 20 years</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>496</fpage>–<lpage>500</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1352458511419702">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Costelloe</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tubridy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Long-term clinical relevance of criteria for designating multiple sclerosis as benign after 10 years of disease</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>1245</fpage>–<lpage>1248</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1352458511419702">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Glad</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nyland</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aarseth</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Riise</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Myhr</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Long-term follow-up of benign multiple sclerosis in Hordaland County, Western Norway</article-title>. <source>Mult Scler</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>942</fpage>–<lpage>950</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1352458511419702">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ramsaransing</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Keyser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Benign course in multiple sclerosis: a review</article-title>. <source>Acta Neurol Scand</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>113</volume>: <fpage>359</fpage>–<lpage>369</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1352458511419702">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Glad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nyland</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Myhr</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Benign multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Acta Neurol Scand</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>183</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1352458511419702">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lublin</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reingold</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Defining the clinical course of multiple sclerosis: results of an international survey. National Multiple Sclerosis Society (USA) Advisory Committee on Clinical Trials of New Agents in Multiple Sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>1996</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>907</fpage>–<lpage>911</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1352458511419702">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gronwall</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Paced auditory serial addition task: a measure of recovery from concussion</article-title>. <source>Percept Mot Skills</source> <year>1977</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>367</fpage>–<lpage>373</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1352458511419702">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Manual for the Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale Revised</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Psychological Corporation</publisher-name>, <year>1981</year>. <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>156</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1352458511419702">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hammeke</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McQuillen</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khatri</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Memory disturbance in chronic progressive multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Arch Neurol</source> <year>1984</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>625</fpage>–<lpage>631</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1352458511419702">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heaton</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Wisconsin Card Sorting Test Manual</source>. <publisher-loc>Odessa, Florida</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Psychological Assessment Resources</publisher-name>, <year>1981</year>; <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>230</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1352458511419702">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Benton</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamsker</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Varney</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spreen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Contributions to neuropsychological assessment: a clinical manual</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press (USA)</publisher-name>, <year>1983</year>; <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>165</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1352458511419702">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mendelson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mock</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Erbaugh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>An inventory for measuring depression</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source> <year>1961</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>561</fpage>–<lpage>571</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1352458511419702">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cleeland</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Pain assessment: global use of the Brief Pain Inventory</article-title>. <source>Ann Acad Med Singapore</source> <year>1994</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1352458511419702">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krupp</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>LaRocca</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muir-Nash</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The fatigue severity scale. Application to patients with multiple sclerosis and systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title>. <source>Arch Neurol</source> <year>1989</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>1121</fpage>–<lpage>1123</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1352458511419702">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mellerup</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fog</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raun</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The socio-economic scale</article-title>. <source>Acta Neurol Scand</source> <year>1981</year>; <volume>64</volume> (<issue>Suppl 87</issue>): <fpage>130</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1352458511419702">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lauer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Firnhaber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiological investigations into multiple sclerosis in Southern Hesse. V. Course and prognosis</article-title>. <source>Acta Neurol Scand</source> <year>1987</year>; <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1352458511419702">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pappalardo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Macchia</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Civalleri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paolillo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Predictors of quality of life among patients with multiple sclerosis: an Italian cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Sci</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>252</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage>–<lpage>129</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1352458511419702">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Glad</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aarseth</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nyland</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Riise</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Myhr</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Benign multiple sclerosis: a need for a consensus</article-title>. <source>Acta Neurol Scand</source> Suppl <year>2010</year>; <volume>122</volume> (<issue>190</issue>): <fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1352458511419702">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weinshenker</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bass</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Noseworthy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carriere</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baskervielle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The natural history of multiple sclerosis: a geographically based study. I. Clinical course and disability</article-title>. <source>Brain</source> <year>1989</year>; <volume>112</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>146</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1352458511419702">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hirst</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ingram</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swingler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Compston</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pickersgill</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Change in disability in patients with multiple sclerosis: a 20-year prospective population-based analysis</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>1137</fpage>–<lpage>1143</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1352458511419702">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Amato</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zipoli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goretti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Portaccio</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Caro</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ricchiuti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Benign multiple sclerosis: cognitive, psychological and social aspects in a clinical cohort</article-title>. <source>J Neurol</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>253</volume>: <fpage>1054</fpage>–<lpage>1059</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1352458511419702">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Portaccio</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stromillo</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goretti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zipoli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Siracusa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Battaglini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Neuropsychological and MRI measures predict short-term evolution in benign multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>498</fpage>–<lpage>503</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1352458511419702">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Koopmans</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grochowsky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cutler</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paty</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Benign versus chronic progressive multiple sclerosis: magnetic resonance imaging features</article-title>. <source>Ann Neurol</source> <year>1989</year>; <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>74</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1352458511419702">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Filippi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Horsfield</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sacares</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Macmanus</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Benign and secondary progressive multiple sclerosis: a preliminary quantitative MRI study</article-title>. <source>J Neurol</source> <year>1994</year>; <volume>241</volume>: <fpage>246</fpage>–<lpage>251</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1352458511419702">
<label>30.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Filippi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Campi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mammi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martinelli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Locatelli</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scotti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Brain magnetic resonance imaging and multimodal evoked potentials in benign and secondary progressive multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source>. <year>1995</year>; <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1352458511419702">
<label>31.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Filippi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Campi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martinelli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baratti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A spinal cord MRI study of benign and secondary progressive multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>J Neurol</source> <year>1996</year>; <volume>243</volume>: <fpage>502</fpage>–<lpage>505</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1352458511419702">
<label>32.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rocca</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ceccarelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rodegher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Misci</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Riccitelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Falini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Preseved brain adaptive properties in patients with benign multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>142</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1352458511419702">
<label>33.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weinshenker</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bass</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Noseworthy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carriere</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baskervielle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The natural history of multiple sclerosis: a geographically based study. 2. Predictive value of the early clinical course</article-title>. <source>Brain</source> <year>1989</year>; <volume>112</volume>: <fpage>1419</fpage>–<lpage>1428</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1352458511419702">
<label>34.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Confavreux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vukusic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adelaine</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Early clinical predictors and progression of irreversible disability in multiple sclerosis: an amnesic process</article-title>. <source>Brain</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>770</fpage>–<lpage>782</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1352458511419702">
<label>35.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fog</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Linnemann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The course of multiple sclerosis in 73 cases with computer-designed curves</article-title>. <source>Acta Neurol Scand Suppl</source> <year>1970</year>; <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>175</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1352458511419702">
<label>36.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patzold</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pocklington</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Course of multiple sclerosis. First results of a prospective study carried out of 102 MS patients from 1976–1980</article-title>. <source>Acta Neurol Scand</source> <year>1982</year>; <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>248</fpage>–<lpage>266</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1352458511419702">
<label>37.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Runmarker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prognostic factors in a multiple sclerosis incidence cohort with twenty-five years of follow-up</article-title>. <source>Brain</source> <year>1993</year>; <volume>116</volume>: <fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1352458511419702">
<label>38.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kurtzke</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beebe</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nagler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kurland</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Auth</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Studies on the natural history of multiple sclerosis – 8. Early prognostic features of the later course of the illness</article-title>. <source>J Chronic Dis</source> <year>1977</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>819</fpage>–<lpage>830</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1352458511419702">
<label>39.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tremlett</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paty</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Devonshire</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Disability progression in multiple sclerosis is slower than previously reported</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>172</fpage>–<lpage>177</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1352458511419702">
<label>40.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rovaris</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barkhof</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Calabrese</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Stefano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fazekas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>MRI features of benign multiple sclerosis: toward a new definition of this disease phenotype</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>1693</fpage>–<lpage>1701</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1352458511419702">
<label>41.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Amato</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Portaccio</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stromillo</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goretti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zipoli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Siracusa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cognitive assessment and quantitative magnetic resonance metrics can help to identify benign multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>632</fpage>–<lpage>638</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1352458511419702">
<label>42.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rigotti</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gonen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Babbs</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Falini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Benedetti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Global N-acetylaspartate declines even in benign multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>AJNR Am J Neuroradiol</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>204</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1352458511419702">
<label>43.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rovaris</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Riccitelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Judica</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Possa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caputo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ghezzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cognitive impairment and structural brain damage in benign multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>1521</fpage>–<lpage>1526</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1352458511419702">
<label>44.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Benedetti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rocca</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rovaris</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caputo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zaffaroni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Capra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A diffusion tensor MRI study of cervical cord damage in benign and secondary progressive multiple sclerosis patients</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1352458511419702">
<label>45.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Giorgio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Portaccio</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stromillo</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zipoli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Battaglini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cortical functional reorganization and its relationship with brain structural damage in patients with benign multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Mult Scler</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1326</fpage>–<lpage>1334</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1352458511419702">
<label>46.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gautier</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liptak</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Egorova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buckle</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rate of brain atrophy in benign vs early multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Arch Neurol</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>234</fpage>–<lpage>237</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1352458511419702">
<label>47.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tienari</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salonen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wikström</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Valanne</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Familial multiple sclerosis: MRI findings in clinically affected and unaffected siblings</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source> <year>1992</year>; <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>883</fpage>–<lpage>886</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1352458511419702">
<label>48.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Forms of benign multiple sclerosis. Report of two “clinical silent” cases discovered at autopsy</article-title>. <source>Arch Neurol</source> <year>1967</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>588</fpage>–<lpage>600</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>