<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="en">
  
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TBT</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptbt</journal-id>
      <journal-title>The Bible Translator</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">2051-6770</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2051-6789</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0260093513481144</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0260093513481144</article-id>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>How Could Something So Right Be So Wrong? OT References to the Left and Right
          Hand</article-title>
        <subtitle>Implications for Translation in Africa<sup>1</sup></subtitle>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Zogbo</surname>
            <given-names>Lynell</given-names>
          </name>
          <aff id="aff1-0260093513481144">United Bible Societies, Faculté de Théologie Evangélique
            Alliance Chrétienne, Abidjan</aff>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="corresp1-0260093513481144">Lynell Zogbo. Email:
            <email xlink:type="simple">lynellzogbo@gmail.com</email>.</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>64</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <issue-title>Special Issue: Papers in honour of Roger Omanson, Part I</issue-title>
      <fpage>36</fpage>
      <lpage>53</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder content-type="other">United Bible Societies</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cross-culturally the left hand is considered the lesser member of the right-left pair,
          giving rise to right- and left-based linguistic expressions favoring the right hand. In
          West Africa, left-handedness has positive and negative connotations: while often evoking
          virility and military prowess, it also connotes impurity, weakness, awkwardness, and
          sometimes stupidity. After exploring literal and figurative uses of the right and left in
          the OT, we ask, How does/can an African audience interpret the favoring of the right hand
          in biblical texts? What are possible readings of the left-handed Benjaminites in the Book
          of Judges? What are the implications for translation and translator helps?</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Left-handedness</kwd>
        <kwd>purity</kwd>
        <kwd>West Africa</kwd>
        <kwd>right and left in the Bible</kwd>
        <kwd>Judges</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>It is well known that the human species is asymmetric, with specializations of the right and
      left cerebral hemispheres resulting in right- and left-handedness. Many scientists link this
      universal phenomenon to the emergence of the human race, with left–right differentiation
      distinguishing homo erectus from homo sapiens, and homo sapiens from other mammals. While some
      researchers claim left-handedness is currently on the rise,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0260093513481144">2</xref></sup> most believe that percentages of right- and
      left-hand use have remained constant since the stone age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0260093513481144">Klass 2011</xref>):<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0260093513481144">3</xref></sup> 90 percent of the population is right-handed, 10
      percent, left (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0260093513481144">Foley 1977</xref>). While a
      gene has been linked to left-handedness,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0260093513481144">4</xref></sup> the majority of scholars admit that no one really knows why individuals
      are born one way or the other.</p>
    <p>Right- and left-handedness are linked to another interesting phenomenon: in most cultures,
      right-handedness carries a positive connotation and left-handedness a negative one. Without a
      doubt, in Scripture, “the right hand” is the place of favor, power, and strength. By default,
      the left hand is either neutral or viewed in a more negative light. Indeed, throughout history
      and around the world, being left-handed is often associated with abnormality, criminality,
      violence, and in some places, with witchcraft and the devil!<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0260093513481144">5</xref></sup> Because of these negative connotations, many
      societies regularly attempt to impose right-handedness on left-handers. This may go from
      forcing left-handed school children to use their right hand,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0260093513481144">6</xref></sup> to beating left-handers with sticks, tying the
      left hand behind the back, or, in some parts of Africa, actually inflicting wounds on the left
      hand to prevent its use.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0260093513481144">7</xref></sup></p>
    <p>Despite the persistence of these traditional beliefs, research reveals that left- and
      right-handers show no difference in IQ, and there is certainly no proof that the left-handed
      minority is morally inferior to the right-handed majority. Today researchers coming to the
      defense of left-handers underline the fact that left-handers are often gifted athletes, citing
      baseball heroes such as Babe Ruth, and “southpaw” boxers, along with left-handed swimming,
      fencing, and tennis champs. Some note left-handers are independent by nature, creative
      thinkers, and powerful leaders, citing Julius Caesar, Michelangelo, Leonardo da Vinci, along
      with Bill Clinton and Barak Obama!</p>
    <p>How does the Bible, especially the Old Testament, treat left-handedness? How do current
      cultures view this feature? And how does this component of worldview interact with Bible
      translation? Does it affect our view of Scripture, the translation itself, its comprehension
      and acceptance among readers and hearers?</p>
    <sec id="section1-0260093513481144">
      <title>The Stigma of the Left Hand</title>
      <p>In most cultures across Western and Central Africa, the right hand is favored, while the
        left hand is considered of lesser status. From Dakar to Kinshasa, eating, gesturing, or
        pointing with the left hand is forbidden, being considered extremely impolite or even a sign
        of insult. For example, in the northern Songhai and Hausa cultures (Niger), to name only
        two, objects must be offered and accepted by the right hand only. Throughout this region, no
        one shakes with the left hand. If the right hand is dirty or occupied, one rather extends
        the right arm for a “shake” or greeting.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-0260093513481144">8</xref></sup> For Lingala speakers (DRC), being served or greeted by the left hand
        could be an evil omen: a sign something bad could happen that day.</p>
      <p>Popular wisdom has it that the left hand is impure because it is used to carry out “dirty”
        activities (toilet, feminine hygiene, wiping babies, etc.). While some might link such
        attribution to Muslim beliefs, the left-hand stigma is present even in cultures with little
        or no Muslim influence. In the Bete culture of Côte d’Ivoire, for instance, no woman would
        dare to cook with her left hand: the food would be inedible. In a church service, a gesture
        with the left hand by a priest or pastor might cause parishioners to get up and leave!
        According to traditional Bete beliefs, persons using the left hand in gesture call down a
        curse upon themselves.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-0260093513481144">9</xref></sup>
        Among the Didas (Côte d’Ivoire), pointing to one’s village with the left hand means one has
        no respect for one’s birthplace. Among the Gangam (Togo), to kick a child with the left foot
        is a particular sign of disdain.</p>
      <p>The right/left-hand distinction governs numerous beliefs, customs, and practices worldwide.
        In several West African cultures, left-handedness is associated with dexterity, prowess, and
        virility. In Gbaya (Cameroon), a proverb claims “the left hand never misses.” In Baatonum
        culture (Benin), a left-handed man is considered skillful and brave. People respect but also
        fear him, because he might have special occult powers. He is also unpredictable: no one ever
        knows which hand he will use. But despite this semi-special status, the Baatonu left-hander
        can never become a chief or king because he is not “pure”: he belongs to the category of the
        “infirm” (blind, lepers, a child born after twins, etc.). He has a spirit of war and thus is
        thought not to be a reliable leader.</p>
      <p>In Gurmanche culture (Burkina Faso), left-handedness is also associated with virility, and
        extends into the domain of lovemaking. It is the left hand that is the favored hand in
        moments of intimacy, the hand used to caress one’s wife. To this day, in many villages, men
        are buried on their right side, with their face turned to the east, so they can—still in
        death—continue to reach out and caress their wife! Similarly in Nyarafolo culture (Côte
        d’Ivoire), people are buried on their left side, so the right hand is free to bless and not
        curse. In other cultures, the left and right also play a significant role in burial customs.
        For example, in northern Togo, among the Gangam peoples, one never sits on the left side of
        a house, since this place is reserved during funerals for the body of the deceased.
        Especially in cases of “bad death,”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-0260093513481144">10</xref></sup> gravediggers are to touch the body only with the left foot. In ritual
        contexts, that is, the offering of traditional sacrifices, the offering must often be made
        only by the right hand. In Musgum culture (Cameroon), a left-handed person cannot carry out
        a sacrifice. Transfer of authority among this same ethnic group is also “hand-sensitive,”
        carried out by placing the right hand on the person’s head or pointing with the right to
        this person. Other ritual acts such as blessing and taking an oath also must be carried out
        by the right hand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0260093513481144">Assinga 2007</xref>,
        71–72, 75).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="section2-0260093513481144">
      <title>Language and the Left Hand</title>
      <p>Cultural views on the left hand often significantly impact language forms and use. For
        example, the very names used to refer to the left and right hand may reflect their status.
        In Lingala (DRC), the left hand is known as the “hand of the female,” while in Yaka (also
        DRC), one speaks of the “hand of the father” (right) and “the hand of the mother” (left).
        These associations are very common throughout west and central Africa. In Musgum (Cameroon)
        there is not even a word for “right”: “right hand” is <italic>tin a wus</italic> “hand of
        man,” also known as “the good hand,” or simply “the hand,” while the left is “the hand of
        the woman,” the “bad,” or even “the inside-out hand” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0260093513481144">Assinga 2007</xref>, 64–65)!<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-0260093513481144">11</xref></sup> In Bete, the right hand is also associated
        with maleness and the left with femaleness (being the weaker of the two), though in this
        language the right hand is formally called “hand with which one eats,” and the left, simply
        “the left hand.”</p>
      <p>Beliefs concerning the left hand impact the creation of idioms and euphemisms. In Baatonum,
        “to put the left hand” is a euphemism for requesting sex. Thus, to say “She put her left
        hand on me, but I refused” means “She wanted to make love, but I said no.” In Gurmanche,
        mentioned above, a man who is constantly running after other women will be labeled
        (pejoratively) “the one whose left (hand) is leading.”</p>
      <p>More frequently, reference to the left evokes very negative behavior or personality traits.
        In Bete, for example, saying “you are left” or “you have a left hand” means you are out of
        line or not addressing a situation correctly. In Ngambai (Chad), “Are you left-handed?” is a
        serious reprimand. The left hand is often associated with a lack of ability to reason, as
        reflected in the Ngambai proverb, “It is better to have to do with a drunk than with a
        left-handed person.” In Lele (Chad), “his word is left” means the person is not making
        sense. Left can also mean “wrong.” In Kisie culture (Guinea), if a child puts her left hand
        in the cooking, her mother might say, “you’re working with your foot” or “take your foot out
        of the pot.”</p>
      <p>This same linguistic phenomenon is of course present outside Africa. In English, for
        example, awkward behavior is called “gauche” (a word borrowed from French meaning “left”). A
        person who is bumbling may be described as “having two left feet.” In contrast, in many
        languages worldwide, it is the “right” side that is positive, indicating correctness,
        properness: “You’re <italic>right</italic>!” “That’s the <italic>right</italic> answer.”
        “He’s the <italic>right</italic> man for the job.” And so on. In many languages, right is
        also the unmarked element of the right–left word pair, with the right–left order being used
        when citing examples.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="section3-0260093513481144">
      <title>The Right and the Left Hand in Biblical Literature</title>
      <p>In the Hebrew Bible (as well as in the later intertestamental and New Testament periods),
        references to right and left are common. In the Old Testament, the Hebrew words for right
          (<italic>yāmîn</italic>) and left (<italic>śĕmō’l</italic>), often cited together, can be
        understood quite literally, designating the physical right and left. In such contexts, both
        words appear to be completely neutral in meaning:<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-0260093513481144">12</xref></sup>
        <disp-quote>
          <p>The Israelites went into the sea on dry ground, the waters forming a wall for them
              <italic>on their right and on their left</italic>. (Exod 14.22)</p>
          <p>Then Samson reached toward the two central pillars on which the temple stood. Bracing
            himself against them, <italic>his right hand</italic> on the one and <italic>his left
              hand</italic> on the other. (Judg 16.29)</p>
          <p>Now all the people and all the warriors were <italic>on his</italic> [King David’s]
              <italic>right and on his left</italic>. (2 Sam 16.6)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13-0260093513481144">13</xref></sup></p>
        </disp-quote></p>
      <p>The order of appearance in such unmarked cases is usually right–left, but there are
        instances when this is not true, as when Abram speaks to Lot or Job expresses his
            frustration:<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14-0260093513481144">14</xref></sup>
        <disp-quote>
          <p>If you go <italic>to the left</italic>, I’ll go <italic>to the right</italic>;</p>
          <p>if you go <italic>to the right</italic>, I’ll go <italic>to the left</italic>. (Gen
            13.9)</p>
        </disp-quote>
        <disp-quote>
          <p><italic>On the left</italic> he hides, and I cannot behold him;</p>
          <p>I turn <italic>to the right</italic>, but I cannot see him. (Job 23.9)</p>
        </disp-quote></p>
      <p>The Hebrew terms are regularly used to indicate cardinal directions, with right indicating
        the south and left the north, a phenomenon also found in other cultures and
            languages:<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15-0260093513481144">15</xref></sup>
        <disp-quote>
          <p>Your elder sister is Samaria, who lived with her daughters to the north
              [<italic>left</italic>] of you; and your younger sister, who lived to the south
              [<italic>right</italic>] of you. (Ezek 16.46)</p>
        </disp-quote></p>
      <p>But the pair is also used as a merism, meaning “everywhere”:<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16-0260093513481144">16</xref></sup>
        <disp-quote>
          <p>For you will spread out to <italic>the right and to the left</italic>,</p>
          <p>and your descendants will possess the nations</p>
          <p>and will settle the desolate towns. (Isa 54.3)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17-0260093513481144">17</xref></sup></p>
        </disp-quote></p>
      <p>In a few such cases, especially in figurative language, left as well as right gets an
        almost positive reading: <disp-quote>
          <p>Long life is <italic>in her right hand;</italic></p>
          <p><italic>in her left hand</italic> are riches and honor. (Prov 3.16)</p>
        </disp-quote></p>
      <p>This word pair is also part of a common idiomatic expression in Hebrew, “not turning to the
        right hand or the left,” meaning “to go straight ahead”: <disp-quote>
          <p>[we will not turn] aside <italic>to the right hand or to the left</italic> until we
            have passed through your territory. (Num 20.17)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18-0260093513481144">18</xref></sup></p>
        </disp-quote></p>
      <p>More often this expression constitutes a powerful metaphor for obedience, that is,
        listening to, choosing, and doing the right thing. In the Hebrew Bible, this includes
        obedience to Yahweh and his commands or obedience to the words of a superior, for example, a
            king:<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19-0260093513481144">19</xref></sup>
        <disp-quote>
          <p>You must therefore be careful to do as the Lord your God has commanded you; <italic>you
              shall not turn to the right or to the left</italic>. (Deut 5.32)</p>
          <p>Only be strong and very courageous, being careful to act in accordance with all the law
            that my servant Moses commanded you; <italic>do not turn from it to the right hand or to
              the left</italic>, so that you may be successful wherever you go. (Josh 1.6)</p>
          <p>The king said, “Is the hand of Joab with you in all this?” The woman answered and said,
            “As surely as you live, my lord the king, one cannot <italic>turn right or left</italic>
            from anything that my lord the king has said.” (2 Sam 14.19)</p>
        </disp-quote></p>
      <p>While these examples show that left and right can have a more neutral reading, it is
        important to note that in the Hebrew Bible, references to the right far outnumber those to
        the left, and when appearing alone, the right has very positive connotations.</p>
      <sec id="section4-0260093513481144">
        <title>Ritual Use of the Right Hand</title>
        <p>In legal texts (Exodus and Leviticus) purification rituals involve the right side of the
          body: <disp-quote>
            <p>and you shall slaughter the ram, and take some of its blood and put it on the
                <italic>lobe</italic> of Aaron’s <italic>right ear</italic> and on the lobes of the
                <italic>right ears</italic> of his sons, and on the <italic>thumbs of their right
                hands</italic>, and on the <italic>big toes of their right feet</italic>, and dash
              the rest of the blood against all sides of the altar. (Exod 29.20)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20-0260093513481144">20</xref></sup></p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>Similar examples occur throughout Leviticus (7.32–33;<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21-0260093513481144">21</xref></sup> 8.23, 24, 31), especially in ch. 14. In
          some instances both hands are implicated in rituals, but it is always the right hand which
          is favored and more active than the passive left: <disp-quote>
            <p>[The priest will] dip his right finger in the oil that is in his left hand and
              sprinkle some oil with his [right] finger seven times before the Lord. (Lev 14.16)</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section5-0260093513481144">
        <title>Right as the Place of Honor and Strength</title>
        <p>Several scholars suggest that the predominance and special connotations of the right in
          the Hebrew Bible and in Israelite culture may be due to the influence of neighboring
          cultures. This is confirmed by artifacts found in ancient Asia Minor. For example, in a
          limestone relief from Iraq dating from 858–824 B.C.E., an Assyrian king extends his right
          hand to another king, symbolizing a formal agreement. In a set of Egyptian statues dating
          from 1345–1318 B.C.E., a pharaoh is portrayed as sitting at the right hand of the god
          Horus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0260093513481144">Schroer and Staubli
          2001</xref>, 151, 161).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22-0260093513481144">22</xref></sup> Baal is often portrayed as raising his right hand in a sign of power
          and victory, with his right also being a place of honor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0260093513481144">Assinga 2007</xref>, 6). It is thus likely that these
          peoples influenced the Israelites, but it is also possible that favoring the right hand is
          simply a general, regional, or near-universal feature reflecting biological realities.</p>
        <p>Whatever the origin of this semantic correlation, we know that from the earliest times,
          the Israelites referred to and praised the right hand of Yahweh. In the Song of the Sea,
          held to be one of the oldest poetic biblical texts, we read, <disp-quote>
            <p><italic>Your right hand</italic>, O Lord, glorious in power—</p>
            <p><italic>your right hand</italic>, O Lord, shattered the enemy. (Exod 15.6)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23-0260093513481144">23</xref></sup></p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>In later songs, as well, the Lord’s right hand or arm is extolled.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24-0260093513481144">24</xref></sup> It is especially associated
          with Yahweh’s power and strength leading to deliverance and great victories over various
              enemies:<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25-0260093513481144">25</xref></sup>
          <disp-quote>
            <p>You have a mighty arm; strong is your hand,</p>
            <p>high your <italic>right hand</italic>. (Ps 89.14)</p>
          </disp-quote>
          <disp-quote>
            <p>Your hand will find out all your enemies;</p>
            <p><italic>your right hand</italic> will find out those who hate you. (Ps 21.9)</p>
          </disp-quote>
          <disp-quote>
            <p>For not by their own sword did they win the land,</p>
            <p>nor did their own arm give them victory;</p>
            <p>but <italic>your right hand, and your arm</italic>,</p>
            <p>and the light of your countenance, for you delighted in them. (Ps 45.5)</p>
          </disp-quote>
          <disp-quote>
            <p>Now I know that the Lord will help his anointed;</p>
            <p>he will answer him from his holy heaven</p>
            <p>with mighty victories <italic>by his right hand</italic>. (Ps 20.7)</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>The right side is also the place of blessing and honor,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26-0260093513481144">26</xref></sup> offered to those whom the Lord favors: <disp-quote>
            <p>You show me the path of life.</p>
            <p>In your presence there is fullness of joy;</p>
            <p>in your <italic>right hand</italic> are pleasures forevermore. (Ps 16.11)</p>
          </disp-quote>
          <disp-quote>
            <p>The [Lord] said to my Lord, “Sit at <italic>my right side</italic>,</p>
            <p>until I make your enemies into a footstool for you.” (Ps 110.1)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27-0260093513481144">27</xref></sup></p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>The right side is a place of protection as well, where believers seek and find refuge: <disp-quote>
            <p>Wondrously show your steadfast love,</p>
            <p>O savior of those who seek refuge from their adversaries</p>
            <p><italic>at your right hand</italic>. (Ps 17.7)</p>
          </disp-quote>
          <disp-quote>
            <p>You have given me the shield of your salvation,</p>
            <p>and <italic>your right hand</italic> has supported me;</p>
            <p>your help has made me great. (Ps 18.36)</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>In an interesting twist, it is Yahweh himself who at times stands at the right of human
          beings (King David and other followers), where he provides protection, stability, and
          deliverance from enemies: <disp-quote>
            <p>I keep the Lord always before me;</p>
            <p>because he is <italic>at my right hand</italic>,</p>
            <p>I shall not be moved. (Ps 16.8)</p>
          </disp-quote>
          <disp-quote>
            <p>For he stands <italic>at the right hand</italic> of the needy,</p>
            <p>to save them from those who would condemn them to death. (Ps 109.31)</p>
          </disp-quote>
          <disp-quote>
            <p>The Lord is <italic>at your right hand</italic>;</p>
            <p>he will shatter kings on the day of his wrath. (Ps 110.5)</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>However, this position of force and prominence is not restricted to Yahweh. The right is
          cited in other poetic contexts as the place of activity and source of strength of evil
          men, even of Satan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0260093513481144">Assinga
          2007</xref>, 18): <disp-quote>
            <p>Do not sweep me away with sinners,</p>
            <p>nor my life with the bloodthirsty,</p>
            <p>those in whose hands are evil devices,</p>
            <p>and whose <italic>right hands</italic> are full of bribes. (Ps 26.9–10)</p>
          </disp-quote>
          <disp-quote>
            <p>Then he showed me the high priest Joshua standing</p>
            <p>before the angel of the Lord,</p>
            <p>and Satan standing <italic>at his right hand</italic> to accuse him. (Zech
                  3.1)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28-0260093513481144">28</xref></sup></p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>Another right-hand scenario involves the swearing of oaths. While there is at least one
          instance of a two-handed oath (Dan 12.7), most often it is the right hand which is
          associated with making a solemn promise:<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29-0260093513481144">29</xref></sup>
          <disp-quote>
            <p>The Lord has sworn <italic>by his right hand</italic> and by his mighty arm: “Never
              again will I . . . (Isa 62.8)</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>Thus the right hand in Scripture emerges by sheer frequency of appearance and by its many
          occurrences in contexts of favor, power, and honor, as the positive member of the
          right–left word pair. As noted by Schroer and Staubli (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0260093513481144">2001</xref>, 160), no direct mention is ever made of God’s
          left hand.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30-0260093513481144">30</xref></sup> And in at
          least one instance in the Old Testament, the left is directly associated with folly: <disp-quote>
            <p>The heart of the wise inclines <italic>to the right</italic>,</p>
            <p>but the heart of a fool <italic>to the left</italic>. (Eccl 10.2)</p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>By default, then, the left is imbued, at best, with lower status and, at worst, with
          extremely negative connotations. Coming back to the literal or physical meaning of right
          and left, note that when Joseph brings his children to Jacob for a blessing (Gen
          48.13–14), though both hands are used to bless, the right hand carries the higher
          blessing. The narrator uses careful chiastic structuring to underline the fact that
          despite Joseph’s attempts to help his father perform the blessing in the proper way, Jacob
          seemingly intentionally places his right hand of blessing on the younger of the two,
          rather than the elder: <disp-quote>
            <p>And Joseph took both of them</p>
            <p> Ephraim in his <italic>right</italic> on Israel’s <italic>left</italic></p>
            <p> And Manasseh in his <italic>left</italic> on Israel’s <italic>right</italic>.</p>
            <p>And he brought [them] to him.</p>
            <p>And Israel stretched out</p>
            <p>his <italic>right</italic> and put [it] on the head of Ephraim and he was the
                <italic>younger</italic></p>
            <p>And his <italic>left</italic> on the head of Manasseh</p>
            <p>He crossed his hands</p>
            <p>    though Manasseh was the <italic>firstborn.</italic></p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>Another context where the right seems preferred over the left is in lovemaking (contrary
          to the African practice noted above). In the Song of Songs, the following lines form a
          kind of inclusio, appearing in the beginning and ending sections of the book (2.6; 8.3): <disp-quote>
            <p>O that <italic>his left hand</italic> were under my head,</p>
            <p>and that <italic>his right hand</italic> embraced me!<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31-0260093513481144">31</xref></sup></p>
          </disp-quote></p>
        <p>While both references are positive, we recognize the characteristic active–right and
          passive–left associations seen above in legal texts. Is it going too far to imagine the
          caresses are coming from the favored or even pure hand?</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="section6-0260093513481144">
        <title>Special Focus on the Left Hand</title>
        <p>There are not many instances of the left hand appearing alone in Scripture, but the most
          important and intriguing example comes from the book of Judges. This book has been
          redacted in a most astounding way (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0260093513481144">Arnold 1995</xref>), with several leitmotifs occurring throughout the book. One motif
          is “hand” which occurs around ninety times, and another, occurring far less frequently, is
          “left” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0260093513481144">Zogbo 2003</xref>). The latter
          clearly occurs at key points in the narrative, where the left hand is explicitly or
          implicitly mentioned: Ehud’s left-handed victory over Eglon (3.15, 21), Gideon’s attack on
          the Midianites (7.20), and Samson’s suicide-victory (16.29).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32-0260093513481144">32</xref></sup> More significantly, there are two passages
          forming a kind of inclusio around the book (occurring towards the beginning and at the
          end) where the words “right” and “left” create a kind of “zone of turbulence,”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33-0260093513481144">33</xref></sup> that is, a specially
          highlighted and or marked account (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0260093513481144">Zogbo 2003</xref>): <list id="list1-0260093513481144" list-type="bullet">
            <list-item><p><italic>Ehud the left-handed warrior</italic> (3.15–25)</p></list-item>
          </list></p>
        <p>
          <disp-quote>
            <p>The LORD raised up for them a deliverer, Ehud <italic>son</italic> of Gera, the
              Benjaminite [<italic>son of <bold>right</bold> hand</italic>], a left-handed man
                [<italic>man bound of <bold>right</bold> hand</italic>]. The Israelites
                [<italic>sons of Israel</italic>] sent tribute by him [by <italic>his hand</italic>]
              to King Eglon of Moab. Ehud made for himself a sword with two edges, a cubit in
              length; and he fastened it on his <italic>right</italic> thigh under his clothes. Then
              he presented the tribute to King Eglon of Moab. Now Eglon was a very fat man. When
              Ehud had finished presenting the tribute, he sent the people who carried the tribute
              on their way. . . . Ehud came to him, while he was sitting alone in his cool roof
              chamber, and said, “I have a message from God for you.” So he rose from his seat. Then
              Ehud reached with his <italic>left</italic> hand, took the sword from his
                <italic>right</italic> thigh, and thrust it into Eglon’s belly; the hilt also went
              in after the blade, and the fat closed over the blade, for he did not draw the sword
              out of his belly; and the dirt came out. Then Ehud went out into the vestibule and
              closed the doors of the roof chamber on him, and locked them.</p>
            <p>After he had gone, the servants came. When they saw that the doors of the roof
              chamber were locked, they thought, “He must be relieving himself in the cool chamber.”
              So they waited until they were embarrassed [Heb.: “until shame”]. When he still did
              not open the doors of the roof chamber, they took the key and opened them. There was
              their lord lying dead on the floor.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34-0260093513481144">34</xref></sup></p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p>
        <list id="list2-0260093513481144" list-type="bullet">
          <list-item>
            <p><italic>Civil war: left-handed Benjaminites against Israelites</italic>
              (20.12–17)</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
        <p>
          <disp-quote>
            <p>The tribes of Israel sent men through all the tribe of Benjamin [<italic>son of
                  <bold>right</bold></italic>], saying, “What crime is this that has been committed
              among you? Now then, hand over those scoundrels in Gibeah, so that we may put them to
              death, and purge the evil from Israel.” But the Benjaminites [<italic>sons of son of
                  <bold>right</bold></italic>] would not listen to their kinsfolk [Heb.:
                <italic>“brothers”</italic>], the Israelites. The Benjaminites [<italic>sons of son
                of <bold>right</bold></italic>] came together out of the towns to Gibeah, to go out
              to battle against the Israelites. On that day the Benjaminites [<italic>sons of son of
                  <bold>right</bold></italic>] mustered twenty-six thousand armed men from their
              towns, besides the inhabitants of Gibeah. Of all this force, there were seven hundred
              picked [<italic>chosen</italic> 2x] men who were <italic>left-handed</italic>
                [<italic>bound of the <bold>right</bold> hand</italic>]; every one could sling a
              stone at a hair, and not miss. And the Israelites [men of Israel], apart from Benjamin
                [<italic>son of <bold>right</bold></italic>], mustered four hundred thousand armed
              men, all of them warriors.</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p>
        <p>While these passages make it clear that in biblical literature, left-handedness and/or
          ambidexterity is associated with military prowess and skill,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35-0260093513481144">35</xref></sup> there is clearly more behind these words.
          The zones of turbulence created by repeated themes (“hand,” “bound by/of the right hand,”
          “right,” “left,” “son,” “sons of son of right,” “chosen”) express biting irony<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36-0260093513481144">36</xref></sup> as these “sons of the right”
          refuse to do what is right.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="section7-0260093513481144">
      <title>Implications for Exegesis, Translation, Scripture Reception, and Translation
        Helps</title>
      <p>This study raises a number of issues which touch on how exegesis is done, what translators
        bring to the text prior to translation, and how translations are interpreted. It also leads
        us to ideas about how to create better translation helps.</p>
      <p>First of all, our study shows that non-Western readers and translators can contribute in a
        unique and original way to the exegesis of biblical texts. Looking at the Ehud episode
        through non-Western eyes offers important complementary interpretations. In this passage,
        African readings underline not only the obvious military prowess associated with the left
        hand, but link the text to the notion of pure and impure. Clearly, the “juicy bits” of the
        story of Ehud will be far more accessible to a West or Central African reader than to a
        European or American one. Besides the turbulence created by the right–left wordplay (at
        times available only to those with access to the Hebrew), the text creates a humorous
        “toilet scene” with the fat “calf” King Eglon,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37-0260093513481144">37</xref></sup> stabbed in the belly by an unclean (impure)
        left hand, and his excrement spilling out. His servants think he is indisposed (in the
        restroom), while in fact, he lies dead, sprawled on the floor. What better way for
        Israelites to ridicule an impure pagan king?</p>
      <p>Surely this background understanding can be carried over to one of the final scenes of
        Judges, where “sons of son of right” use their left-handed skill to kill their own brethren.
        Is the narrator not using all means at his disposal (wordplay, repetition,
            alliteration,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38-0260093513481144">38</xref></sup>
        cultural background) to show the epitome of horror now taking place in Israel? From episodes
        of victory described in the beginning of the book, Israel now has descended into the pit of
        utter chaos and civil war. The prominence of the “left” (referred to figuratively in both
        cases as “tied” or “impeded of the right hand) in these two highly dramatic episodes is a
        key rhetorical device which contributes to the meaning and tone of the text, a fact that
        should somehow be highlighted in the translation (or in some kind of note).</p>
      <p>Given that some translators come to the text with insights a Western mind cannot provide,
        we wonder about methods (past and future) used in the creation of translation helps. Would
        it not be helpful to seek out non-Western wisdom,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39-0260093513481144">39</xref></sup> that is, to allow a larger circle of
        contributors, in both biblical exegesis and discussion of translation issues?</p>
      <p>Whatever form translation helps may take (wiki or printed, access through paratext or
        through published books), it also seems very clear that there is no need to treat the same
        exegetical and translation issues over and over in multiple places, as in the
            past.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40-0260093513481144">40</xref></sup> In the case of
        the left and the right, what is called for is a general “help,” covering the subject of
        right and left. The users of Bible translation helps could easily click first on a global
        explanation of right and left, and then, as needed, on individual books and individual
        verses for more precise information.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41-0260093513481144">41</xref></sup></p>
      <p>There will of course be a need for more localized helps, dealing with specific translation
            issues.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42-0260093513481144">42</xref></sup> In the case
        of the translation of left and right in Musgum (Cameroon), though these concepts have
        similar connotations to those outlined above, many biblical passages with “right hand”
        rendered literally are barely understood! In this language group, being “<italic>next
          to</italic>” or “<italic>on the side</italic> of the chief” is a far more powerful way to
        express the meaning behind a literal “at the right hand” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0260093513481144">Assinga 2007</xref>, 91, 95).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43-0260093513481144">43</xref></sup> How can helps be created so that those with
        similar problems can read about translation solutions that have worked?</p>
      <p>One may be tempted to ask, Is the question of the left and right hand yet another case in
        which “corrective measures” must be taken?<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44-0260093513481144">44</xref></sup> This question arises since some suggest that
        the Bible’s (over)emphasis on “the right hand” has played a role in perpetuating prejudice
        against left-handers! Would new and more natural renderings help solve the problem? In Jonah
        4.11, for example, where Nineveh’s 120,000 inhabitants “don’t know their right from their
        left,” CEV ends up saying these people “cannot tell <italic>right from wrong</italic>.” Do
        such renderings solve, avoid, or rather complicate the problem? Such questions can perhaps
        only be answered locally, within and by the community for whom the translation is being
        done.</p>
      <p>Although the focus of this study has been the Hebrew Old Testament, it is obvious that many
        of our observations carry over into the Greek Deuterocanon and New Testament. Given the
        widespread adoption of Old Testament images in these other parts of Scripture,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45-0260093513481144">45</xref></sup> perhaps notes and other types
        of explanations would be appropriate in published Bibles. Certainly where there is a
        “cultural match,” more literal renderings will be understood and appreciated and no notes
        will be required. However, where connotations of the left are less understood, might it not
        be better to create and include general notes explaining important points of Bible
        background?</p>
      <p>In a project sponsored by the Alliance Biblique de Côte d’Ivoire, we are producing a Baoule
        study Bible which, in a simple and inexpensive way, adds framed material highlighting shared
        customs (naming people and places to remember important events or send important messages to
        the community) and explaining potential clashes of culture and meaning (e.g., the word
        “rock” immediately evoking fetish worship, instead of God as a place of refuge; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0260093513481144">Zogbo 2011</xref>). It is easy to see how a
        culturally pertinent frame for right- and left-handedness could be effective in helping
        readers better pick up on cues and connotations embedded in the text.</p>
      <p>It is perhaps time that in our global village we begin to understand that all peoples of
        all cultures know that other cultures exist and have practices and beliefs different from
        their own. Should the translation pendulum stay stuck on domesticated renderings, as we
        cater to those who cannot understand? Or should we give today’s readers the benefit of the
        doubt, believing they are sophisticated enough <italic>to recognize, accept, and even
          appreciate</italic> the foreignness of a text coming from another time and place?</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <notes>
      <fn-group>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0260093513481144">
          <label>1</label>
          <p>I am grateful to many friends who supplied so many fascinating examples for this study:
            Abdou Maiga (Songhai), Athangba Jean Marc (Dida), Seri Emile (Bete), Pierre Barassounon
            (Batanom), Dingamou Enoch (Ngamgbai), Robert Iffono (Kisiei), Stanislas Nzita (Lingala),
            Mbadoum (Lele), Phil Noss (Gbaya), N. Pakdembè Ntouame (Gangam), Abdoulaye Ouattara
            (Nyarafolo), Abraham Tankoano (Gulmancema), and Assinga Thomas (Musgum). We found this a
            fitting topic for our dear friend and colleague Roger Omanson, a left-hander who has
            done so much to further Bible translation in Africa.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0260093513481144">
          <label>2</label>
          <p>The current rate in Britain is claimed to be 13 percent left-handed men and 11 percent
            left-handed women (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0260093513481144">McManus
              2004</xref>). About 1 percent of the human race is ambidextrous.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0260093513481144">
          <label>3</label>
          <p>These conclusions are drawn from particular features of cave paintings and
            wear-and-tear on molar remains.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0260093513481144">
          <label>4</label>
          <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0260093513481144">Klass (2011)</xref> cites Clyde
            Francis (2007), showing that possessors of the gene LRRTMI are more likely to be
            left-handed. Research reveals left-handedness is more common among males. Curiously,
            some identical twins are born with one being right-handed and the other left-handed, a
            fact that has yet to be explained.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0260093513481144">
          <label>5</label>
          <p>In several European cultures, the devil and witches are believed to be or are portrayed
            as left-handed. Devils “bless” with their left hand. Throwing salt over the left
            shoulder, where evil spirits lurk, is a way to escape evil influence. The practice of
            wearing the wedding band on the left hand apparently goes back to a Greek and/or Roman
            belief that such ornaments ward off evil spirits. Note that there are exceptions to left
            symbolism. In Zuni (American Indian) culture, the left hand is associated with luck,
            age, and wisdom.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0260093513481144">
          <label>6</label>
          <p>Tankoano reports that today among the Gurmanche peoples (Burkina Faso), it is difficult
            to find a single older person who writes with the left hand, though among the younger
            generation, children now write with the left hand.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-0260093513481144">
          <label>7</label>
          <p>In Godie culture (Côte d’Ivoire), in the past, the palm of a child’s left palm was
            subjected to tiny cuts. Crushed chili pepper was placed in the wound and the hand was
            then bound, forcing the child to use the right hand. Among the Ngambai (Chad) a plaster
            cast is made out of clay and placed on the left hand, for a similar result.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-0260093513481144">
          <label>8</label>
          <p>Among the Lele of Chad, giving an object with the left hand shows the bearer has some
            evil intent. In Kisei culture, if someone is obliged to give an object with the left
            hand, rules of politeness oblige the giver to say something equivalent to “pardon” or
            “excuse me.”</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-0260093513481144">
          <label>9</label>
          <p>Some say this gesture means your mother will die.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-0260093513481144">
          <label>10</label>
          <p>In many West African cultures, there is a distinction between “good death” and “bad
            death.” Suicide, death in childbirth, and drowning are often considered bad death.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-0260093513481144">
          <label>11</label>
          <p>The woman may not bless anyone with a hand gesture. This task is reserved for the man
            who blesses with “the hand of the man” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0260093513481144">Assinga 2007</xref>, 73).</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-0260093513481144">
          <label>12</label>
          <p>Unless marked otherwise all Scripture quotes come from NRSV.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn13-0260093513481144">
          <label>13</label>
          <p>See also Num 22.26; 1 Kgs 7.21, 39, 49; 22.19; 2 Kgs 11.11; 2 Chr 3.17; 4.6–8; 18.18;
            23.10; Neh 8.4; Ezek 1.10; Zech 4.3, 11. In the deuterocanonicals in Greek, see 1 Macc
            5.46, and in the New Testament, Matt 27.38.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn14-0260093513481144">
          <label>14</label>
          <p>One is tempted to suggest that the marked order left–right may be foreshadowing or
            associated with some unhappy event, as in the cases cited. This needs further
            investigation, since counter-examples seem to exist.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn15-0260093513481144">
          <label>15</label>
          <p>In Songhai (Niger), left is north and right is south.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn16-0260093513481144">
          <label>16</label>
          <p>A similar use is attested in Zech 12.6 and in Greek, 1 Macc 6.45, with soldiers killing
            people “right and left.”</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn17-0260093513481144">
          <label>17</label>
          <p>See also Ezek 21.21; Isa 9.19 (where the meaning is literally “left and right” or
            possibly “everywhere”).</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn18-0260093513481144">
          <label>18</label>
          <p>See also Deut 2.27; 1 Sam 6.12; 2 Sam 2.19; Ps 107.7.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn19-0260093513481144">
          <label>19</label>
          <p>See also Deut 17.11, 20; 28.14; Josh 23.6; 2 Kgs 22.2; 2 Chr 34.2; Prov 4.27. In the
            deuterocanonicals, see 1 Macc 2.22.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn20-0260093513481144">
          <label>20</label>
          <p>A similar practice is noted among the Musgum, where those concerned may be asked to dip
            their right toe into the blood poured out in sacrifice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0260093513481144">Assinga 2007</xref>, 72).</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn21-0260093513481144">
          <label>21</label>
          <p>René Péter-Contesse and John Ellington (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0260093513481144">1990</xref>) note at this verse “the importance of the
            right side among the people of Israel.”</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn22-0260093513481144">
          <label>22</label>
          <p>See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0260093513481144">Zogbo 2003</xref>.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn23-0260093513481144">
          <label>23</label>
          <p>See also Exod 15.12.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn24-0260093513481144">
          <label>24</label>
          <p>In Hebrew, the form is simply “right,” a very common way to refer to the right hand,
            arm, or side. Here “hand” is supplied by NRSV, while CEV proposes “arm”: “With the
            tremendous force of your right arm, our [Lord], you crushed your enemies.” In many
            African languages, a single word designates both “arm” and “hand.” Note that in this
            song, the Hebrew word “hand” occurs explicitly in Exod 3.20, and “arm” in 15.16.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn25-0260093513481144">
          <label>25</label>
          <p>In the Deuterocanon, God strengthens David’s right hand, enabling him to defeat the
            enemy (Sir 47.5). Note also when the Jews defeat Nicanor, they cut off his head and “his
            right hand that he had so arrogantly stretched out” (1 Macc 7.47).</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn26-0260093513481144">
          <label>26</label>
          <p>In Sirach, learning is like a chain (manacle) on the right hand of a fool, but for the
            wise, like a golden bracelet placed on the right arm (21.19, 21). Compare also Sir
            49.11: “How shall we magnify Zerubbabel? He was like a signet ring on the right
            hand.”</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn27-0260093513481144">
          <label>27</label>
          <p>This image is carried over and quoted extensively in the Gospels. See Matt
            22.43–44.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn28-0260093513481144">
          <label>28</label>
          <p>See also Ps 109.6.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn29-0260093513481144">
          <label>29</label>
          <p>See also the Greek text of 2 Macc 14.33: “he [Nicanor] stretched out his right hand
            toward the sanctuary, and swore this oath: ‘If you do not hand Judas over to me as a
            prisoner, I will level this shrine of God to the ground.’”</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn30-0260093513481144">
          <label>30</label>
          <p>However, even if he does not have a left hand per se, he does seem to have a left
            “side,” a coveted position in the New Testament, as in Matt 20.21–23 and related
            passages: “And he said to her, ‘What do you want?’ She said to him, ‘Declare that these
            two sons of mine will sit, <italic>one at your right hand and one at your left</italic>,
            in your kingdom.’” Schroer and Staubli (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0260093513481144">2001</xref>, 163) note that in a Syrian wall fresco from
            250 B.C.E. two hands appear above biblical scenes, presumably the hands of God. The
            right points to the Israelites going through the Sea of Reeds, the left to the
            destruction of the Egyptian army.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn31-0260093513481144">
          <label>31</label>
          <p>The CEV rendering, “Put your left hand under my head and embrace me with your right
            arm,” seems awkward. While some say “put your arm around my waist” (FC), it is easier to
            imagine the lover’s <italic>hand</italic> caressing his lover.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn32-0260093513481144">
          <label>32</label>
          <p>Interestingly, in the Jael episode, the Hebrew text says she “took the tent peg and the
            hammer in her hand,” with the left being elided and “her hand” designating the
            right.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn33-0260093513481144">
          <label>33</label>
          <p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0260093513481144">Longacre (1985)</xref> notes that
            points of climax and text leading up to story climax are marked by various rhetorical
            features. Here the repetition of a lexical item and/or theme creates such an effect.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn34-0260093513481144">
          <label>34</label>
          <p>The “right–left” motif ends here but the “hand” motif continues as Ehud later says to
            the Israelites, “‘Follow after me; for the LORD has given your enemies the Moabites into
            your <italic>hand</italic>.’ So they went down after him, and seized the fords of the
            Jordan against the Moabites, and allowed no one to cross over. At that time they killed
            about ten thousand of the Moabites, all strong, able-bodied men; no one escaped. So Moab
            was subdued that day under the <italic>hand</italic> of Israel. And the land had rest
            eighty years” (Judg 3.28–30).</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn35-0260093513481144">
          <label>35</label>
          <p>See 1 Chr 2.12: “They were archers, [who] could shoot arrows and sling stones with
            either the right hand or the left; they were Benjaminites, Saul’s kindred.”</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn36-0260093513481144">
          <label>36</label>
          <p>It is well known that in Hebrew and many other languages the repetition of a name can
            signal extreme disdain and is often used to portray the story’s villain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0260093513481144">Marchese n.d</xref>.; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0260093513481144">Zogbo 2009</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0260093513481144">forthcoming</xref>).</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn37-0260093513481144">
          <label>37</label>
          <p>The king’s name means “fat calf” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0260093513481144">Ogden and Zogbo Forthcoming</xref>).</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn38-0260093513481144">
          <label>38</label>
          <p>The incredible <italic>bĕnê binyāmin</italic>, “sons of son of right.”</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn39-0260093513481144">
          <label>39</label>
          <p>This is a call for more “out of house” help, as in the recent Spanish handbooks. In the
            case of French handbooks, we have tried to find African authors who can provide helps
            from a more localized base.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn40-0260093513481144">
          <label>40</label>
          <p>For over forty years, each handbook has been written by separate authors, meaning each
            one addresses similar issues, even if some effort has been made over the years to re-use
            or adapt what is already present (glossary entries, discussions of poetry, names of God,
            etc.).</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn41-0260093513481144">
          <label>41</label>
          <p>In the Song of Songs handbook (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0260093513481144">Ogden and Zogbo 1998</xref>), the following was made explicit: “In many cultures
            there is an important distinction between the functions of the right and the left hands.
            The right hand is used for eating, shaking hands, touching, and caressing, while the
            left hand is reserved for ‘unclean’ tasks. This probably applied in biblical times, so
            it is only logical that the young man’s left hand is under the woman’s head, while his
            right hand caresses her. It is important, therefore, to keep this distinction in the
            translation, especially where the same cultural norms apply.”</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn42-0260093513481144">
          <label>42</label>
          <p>It would be interesting, even imperative, to examine, for example, non-Muslim Asian
            views of left and right. In the literature available to us, the expression “at the right
            of” does not appear. In one writing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0260093513481144"><italic>Handful of Leaves</italic> 2007</xref>) we read, “‘Sit down, Blessed One.
            This seat has been prepared.’ So the Blessed One sat on the prepared seat. Potthapada,
              <italic>taking a lower seat, sat to one side</italic>” (italics mine).</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn43-0260093513481144">
          <label>43</label>
          <p>Other adaptations will also need to be made. In Dan 12.7, it would be extremely awkward
            to say, “he raised his hand of man and his hand of woman to the sky.” A much better
            solution would be “he raised both hands” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0260093513481144">Assinga 2007</xref>, 85, 86). Exodus 15.6, “your right
            (hand/arm),” could not be rendered literally but rather in a way that would omit
            reference to the “right,” for example “your power.” It may even be necessary to call
            Benjamin “son of blessing” since “son of right” has no meaning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0260093513481144">Assinga 2007</xref>, 89, 90).</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn44-0260093513481144">
          <label>44</label>
          <p>I am thinking of the downplaying of negative connotations associated with references to
            the Jews in the Gospel of John or the careful attempts to make neutral or masculine
            pronouns inclusive of women.</p>
        </fn>
        <fn fn-type="other" id="fn45-0260093513481144">
          <label>45</label>
          <p>The dominance of the right in the New Testament is seen in the many prophecies
            attributed to Christ: “But I say to all of you, you will see the Son of Man sitting
              <italic>at the right hand</italic> of the Mighty One” (Matt 26.64), as well as in his
            parable of the sheep and the goats in Matt 25: “Then the king will say to those at his
              <italic>right hand</italic>, ‘Come, you that are blessed by my Father, inherit the
            kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world’ ... he will say to those at
            his <italic>left hand</italic>, ‘You that are accursed, depart from me into the eternal
            fire prepared for the devil and his angels’.” See also Rev 10.2. The epistles add to our
            inventory with “giving <italic>the right hand</italic> of fellowship” (Gal 2.9), a Greek
            expression somewhat similar to one found frequently in the Deuterocanon: 1 Macc 6.58;
            11.50, 62, 66; 13.45, 50; 2 Macc 4.34; 12.11.</p>
        </fn>
      </fn-group>
    </notes>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="bibr1-0260093513481144">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name>
          </person-group>. <year>1995</year>. <source>Ces mystérieux héros de la foi</source>.
            <publisher-loc>Saint-Leger</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Editions
            Emmaus</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr2-0260093513481144">
        <citation citation-type="thesis" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Assinga</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name>
          </person-group>. <year>2007</year>. <source>Le concept de “droite” dans les langues
            bibliques et chez les Mousgoum. analyse en vue de la traduction de la Bible</source>.
          M.A. Thesis, <publisher-name>FATEAC</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr3-0260093513481144">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>William A.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1977</year>. <source>Anthropological Linguistics: An Introduction</source>.
            <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>:
          <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr4-0260093513481144">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <source>Handful of Leaves, Vol. 5: An Anthology from the Five Nikayas</source>.
            <year>2007</year>. Translated by <person-group person-group-type="translator">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Thanissaro</surname><given-names>Bhikkhu</given-names></name>
          </person-group> (Geoffrey DeGraff). <publisher-loc>Santa Cruz</publisher-loc>:
            <publisher-name>Metta Forest Monastery</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr5-0260093513481144">
        <citation citation-type="web" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Klass</surname><given-names>Perri</given-names></name>
          </person-group>. <year>2011</year>. “<article-title>On the Left Hand, There Are No Easy
            Answers</article-title>.” <source>New York Times</source>, <month>March</month>
          <day>6</day>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/03/08/health/views" xlink:type="simple">www.nytimes.com/2011/03/08/health/views</ext-link>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr6-0260093513481144">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Longacre</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>
          </person-group>. <year>1985</year>. “<article-title>Discourse Peak as Zone of
            Turbulence</article-title>.” Pages <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage> in <source>Beyond
            the Sentence: Discourse and Sentential Form</source>. Edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Wirth</surname><given-names>Jessica R.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <publisher-loc>Ann Arbor</publisher-loc>:
          <publisher-name>Karoma</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr7-0260093513481144">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Marchese</surname><given-names>Lynell</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <year>N.d.</year> “<article-title>Apercu sur un conte folklorique godié</article-title>.”
          In <source>Traditions Orales</source>. Edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Ehivet-Gbagbo</surname><given-names>Simone</given-names></name>
          </person-group>. <publisher-loc>Abidjan</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Annales
            ILA</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr8-0260093513481144">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>McManus</surname><given-names>Chris</given-names></name>
          </person-group>. <year>2004</year>. <source>Right Hand, Left Hand: The Origins of
            Asymmetry in Brains, Bodies, Atoms and Cultures</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge,
            MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University
          Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr9-0260093513481144">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <year>1991</year>. “<article-title>Special Features of a Story: A Study of Judges
            3.12–30</article-title>.” <source>The Bible Translator</source>
          <volume>42/4</volume>:<fpage>408</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr10-0260093513481144">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Zogbo</surname><given-names>Lynell</given-names></name>
          </person-group>. <year>1998</year>. <source>A Handbook on the Song of Songs</source>.
            <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>:
          <publisher-name>UBS</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr11-0260093513481144">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Zogbo</surname><given-names>Lynell</given-names></name>
          </person-group>. <year>forthcoming</year>. <source>A Handbook on the Book of
            Judges</source>. <publisher-loc>Reading, UK</publisher-loc>:
            <publisher-name>UBS</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr12-0260093513481144">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Péter-Contesse</surname><given-names>René</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Ellington</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name>
          </person-group>. <year>1990</year>. <source>A Handbook on Leviticus</source>.
            <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>:
          <publisher-name>UBS</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr13-0260093513481144">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Schroer</surname><given-names>Silvia</given-names></name>
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Staubli</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name>
          </person-group>. <year>2001</year>. <source>Body Symbolism in the Bible</source>.
          Translated by <person-group person-group-type="translator">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Maloney</surname><given-names>Linda M.</given-names></name>
          </person-group>
          <publisher-loc>Collegeville</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Liturgical
            Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr14-0260093513481144">
        <citation citation-type="confproc" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Zogbo</surname><given-names>Lynell</given-names></name>
          </person-group>. <year>2003</year>. “<article-title>Right- and Left-handedness in the Old
            Testament: The ‘Hand’ Motif in the Book of Judges</article-title>.” <conf-name>Paper
            presented at UBS Triennial Translation Workshop</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Iguaçu Falls,
            Brazil</conf-loc>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr15-0260093513481144">
        <citation citation-type="confproc" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Zogbo</surname><given-names>Lynell</given-names></name>
          </person-group>. <year>2009</year>. “<article-title>Walk the Walk and Talk the Talk:
            Infinitive Absolutes in Biblical Hebrew, a Challenge for Bible
            Translators</article-title>.” <conf-name>Paper presented at SBL</conf-name>,
            <conf-loc>New Orleans</conf-loc>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr16-0260093513481144">
        <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Zogbo</surname><given-names>Lynell</given-names></name>
          </person-group>. <year>2011</year>. “<article-title>And Who Is a Rock Except Our
            God?</article-title>” <source>Review and Expositor</source>
          <volume>108</volume>:<fpage>279</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>. Issue edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Omanson</surname><given-names>Roger</given-names></name>
          </person-group>. <publisher-loc>Louisville</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sheridan
            Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bibr17-0260093513481144">
        <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name name-style="western"><surname>Zogbo</surname><given-names>Lynell</given-names></name>
          </person-group>. <year>forthcoming</year>. <source>Approche globale à la traduction de la
            Bible</source>.</citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>