<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PSI</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppsi</journal-id>
<journal-title>Psychological Science in the Public Interest</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1529-1006</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1539-6053</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1529100612459637</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1529100612459637</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>About the Authors</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>13</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>104</fpage>
<lpage>104</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Association for Psychological Science</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Winthrop Professor <bold>Stephan Lewandowsky</bold> is a cognitive scientist at the University of Western Australia. He was an Australian Professorial Fellow from 2007 to 2012, and he received a Discovery Outstanding Researcher Award from the Australian Research Council in 2011. He held a Revesz Visiting Professorship at the University of Amsterdam in 2012. His research examines memory, decision making, and knowledge structures, with a particular emphasis on how people update information in memory. He has published over 120 scholarly articles, chapters, and books, including numerous papers on how people respond to corrections of misinformation. (See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cogsciwa.com">www.cogsciwa.com</ext-link> for a complete list of scientific publications.) Professor Lewandowsky is an award-winning teacher and was Associate Editor of the <italic>Journal of Experimental Psychology: Learning, Memory, and Cognition</italic> from 2006 to 2008. His research has been funded continuously since 1990 by public agencies in five countries, but he has no commercial interests or affiliations. He has also contributed numerous opinion pieces to global media outlets on issues related to climate-change skepticism and the coverage of science in the media. A complete list of his public essays can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.shapingtomorrowsworld.org/inthemedia.htm">http://www.shapingtomorrowsworld.org/inthemedia.htm</ext-link>.</p>
<p><bold>Ullrich Ecker</bold> is an Australian Postdoctoral Fellow of the Australian Research Council and an Assistant Professor at the University of Western Australia’s School of Psychology. His research examines memory integration and memory-updating processes, and he has recently focused on the question of how and why people are continuously affected by information they know to be incorrect. He was recently awarded a research grant from the Australian Research Council to work on computational models of memory. Ecker received the University of Western Australia’s Outstanding Young Investigator Award in 2011, as well as an award for Excellence in Coursework Teaching in 2012.</p>
<p><bold>Colleen Seifert</bold> is an Arthur F. Thurnau Professor of Psychology at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, and a Research Professor at the Research Center for Group Dynamics, Institute for Social Research. Her research examines the interplay of memory and cognition, including the correction of misinformation in memory, the role of past experience in problem solving and intention, and the facilitation of creativity. She is a past President and past Executive Officer of the Cognitive Science Society and a Fellow of the American Psychological Society. She has served on the editorial boards of <italic>Cognitive Science, the Journal of the Learning Sciences, Memory and Cognition, the Journal of Educational Psychology</italic>, and the <italic>Journal of Experimental Psychology: Learning, Memory, and Cognition</italic>. Her research has been funded by the National Science Foundation, the Office of Naval Research, and the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration. Seifert has received the University of Michigan’s Faculty Recognition Award.</p>
<p><bold>Norbert Schwarz</bold> is the Charles Horton Cooley Collegiate Professor of Psychology at the University of Michigan, where he also holds appointments at the Institute for Social Research and the Ross School of Business. His research interests focus on the socially situated and embodied nature of cognition; the interplay of feeling and thinking; and the implications of basic cognitive and communicative processes for public opinion, consumer behavior, and social science research. His contributions have been recognized through election to the American Academy of Arts and Sciences and the German National Academy of Science <italic>Leopoldina</italic>, and he has received scientific-contribution awards from scholarly societies in psychology, public-opinion research, and consumer behavior.</p>
<p><bold>John Cook</bold> is the Research Fellow in Climate Change Communication at the Global Change Institute, University of Queensland. His research interests include the biasing influence of worldview on how people process scientific information, the effectiveness of refutations in correcting misinformation, and the role of social media in public education. He coauthored the 2011 book <italic>Climate Change Denial</italic> with environmental scientist Haydn Washington and maintains the Web site Skeptical Science (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.skepticalscience.com">www.skepticalscience.com</ext-link>), which won the 2011 Australian Museum Eureka Prize for Advancement of Climate Change Knowledge.</p>
</body>
</article>