<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EJT</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spejt</journal-id>
<journal-title>European Journal of International Relations</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1354-0661</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1460-3713</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1354066110380966</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1354066110380966</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>‘Global law’ and governmentality: Reconceptualizing the ‘rule of law’ as rule ‘through’ law</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Rajkovic</surname><given-names>Nikolas M.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1354066110380966">Austrian Academy of Sciences, Vienna, Austria</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1354066110380966">Nikolas Milan Rajkovic, Austrian Academy of Sciences, Strohgasse 45/DG, 1030 Vienna, Austria. Email: <email>nikolas.rajkovic@eui.eu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio1-1354066110380966">
<p>Nikolas M. Rajkovic is a postdoctoral researcher at the Institute for European Integration Research of the Austrian Academy of Sciences. He was Assistant Professor at Kyung Hee University, South Korea, lecturing in International Law and Relations. His interdisciplinary research focuses on Global Governance, Global Constitutionalism, EU compliance, and International Legal and Relations Theory. In 2009, he completed his PhD. in Political and Social Sciences at the European University Institute, Florence, Italy. In 2008, Nikolas was nominated for the Wildenmann Prize for best paper by a young scholar at the ECPR Joint Sessions in Rennes, France. In 2005, he received the Outstanding Academic Achievement Award from the Central European University, Budapest, Hungary.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>18</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>29</fpage>
<lpage>52</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© European Consortium for Political Research, SAGE Publications 2010</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">European Consortium for Political Research, SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article challenges the optimism common to liberal IR and IL scholarship on the ‘rule of law’ in global governance. It argues that the concept of the ‘rule of law’ is often employed with sparse inquiry into the politics of its practical meaning. Specifically, the article focuses on liberal research that advocates the emergence of a ‘global’ judiciary, and the claim that judicial governance will marginalize state power and authority. Rather than employ a zero-sum conception of power, this article regards a prospective global legal system less as a constraint on state power and more as a rationale for rule ‘through’ law by vested actors. To make the argument, Michel Foucault’s concept of ‘governmentality’ is combined with Barnett and Duvall’s notion of ‘productive power’ to denote how legal techniques of power are integral to the construction of social ‘truth’ and consequently the governance of conduct. This is further associated with Koskenniemi’s critical scholarship on the power of law’s perceived objectivity and universality. In this vein, the article questions how liberal scholars use the American judicial model (the Marbury ideal) to claim that an institutionalization of ‘global’ judicial authority can deliver the rule of ‘no one’ in global governance. A governmentality perspective is then applied which suggests that the lack of supreme constitutional rules at the global level makes judicial governance less a check than a means to propagate normative standards conducive to dominant state power.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>global governance</kwd>
<kwd>global institutions</kwd>
<kwd>liberalism</kwd>
<kwd>power</kwd>
<kwd>rule of law</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1354066110380966" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The ‘rule of law’, as a concept, has generated considerable enthusiasm within the contemporary practice and academic study of world affairs.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1354066110380966">1</xref></sup> This conceptual ascendancy has been propelled by a rising liberal literature in both International Relations (IR) and International Law (IL) which has emphasized the role of law as a structural constraint on state behaviour. The outcome has been a discursive climate where the ‘rule of law’ commands a rhetorical zeal unmatched in current political speech, and where it is difficult for anyone to credibly and persuasively contest the imperative that domestic and international politics should be subject to the ‘rule of law’. Within a liberal academia, the ‘rule of law’ concept commands a powerful research agenda which claims a realignment of world governance from an international to a now more ‘global’ regime (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1354066110380966">Abbott et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1354066110380966">Bass, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1354066110380966">Ikenberry and Slaughter, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1354066110380966">Keck and Sikkink, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-1354066110380966">Risse et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1354066110380966">Simma and Paulus, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-1354066110380966">Slaughter, 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-1354066110380966">2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-1354066110380966">2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-1354066110380966">2007</xref>).</p>
<p>Varied kinds of historical events and political practices have been touted as confirming such a ‘rule of law’ trajectory. First and foremost, the September 2001 attacks on the United States inaugurated a wave of legislative and executive responses which established an extra-legal ‘counter-terror’ regime (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1354066110380966">Fitzpatrick, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1354066110380966">Heug and McDonagh, 2008</xref>); a move endorsed by the United Nations with Security Council Resolution 1373. Second, international courts of criminal justice have risen to prominence, initiated by the UN Security Council with ad hoc courts for the Former Yugoslavia, Rwanda, Cambodia and Sierra Leone, and then followed by the Rome Treaty establishing the International Criminal Court (ICC). Third, a movement for ‘transnational justice’ is said to be manifest, loosely populated by various state, judicial and non-state actors, pushing an accountability agenda on ‘human rights’ beyond the state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1354066110380966">Finnemore and Sikkink, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1354066110380966">Keck and Sikkink, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-1354066110380966">Risse et al., 1999</xref>); some even allege that a ‘global community of courts’ has emerged which integrates international and national law into a unifying ‘global’ system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-1354066110380966">Slaughter, 2003</xref>). Fourth, we see an increased resort to legalistic discourse and justifications that accompany foreign policy actions and pronouncements, with themes such as ‘legality’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1354066110380966">Abbott et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1354066110380966">Falk, 2005</xref>) and ‘human rights’ regularly clothing the actions of state and non-state actors.</p>
<p>Yet, this article is not about announcing an established trend or substantiating the relevance of the ‘rule of law’ in contemporary international affairs. The ‘rule of law’ has indeed arrived in world affairs, and the aim of this article is to prompt critical reflection on key assumptions which now gird the ‘rule of law’ topos in academic and practical understandings. I argue that there are three interwoven claims which guide mainstream liberal understandings of the ‘rule of law’ in the practice of world affairs. First, that international law has more or less emerged as a significant factor in the actual and discursive practice of international affairs. Second, the alleged ascendancy of law has given structural salience to non-state actors, such as international courts and transnational advocacy groups. Third, the institutionalization of political authority in world affairs has begun to shift from a state-centric structure to that of a ‘global’ regime governed by ‘global’ legal actors and laws which increasingly direct political conduct.</p>
<p>This article takes critical aim at these assumptions, to challenge the bright-eyed optimism common to research programmes on the ‘rule of law’ in world affairs. I argue, first, that the concept of the ‘rule of law’ is often employed with sparse inquiry into the politics of its actual meaning; and thus, while varied literatures have identified the ‘rule of law’ as a salient concept (or efficient ‘variable’), insufficient analysis has been directed at what the ‘rule of law’ actually means as a practical concept and how its conceptualization is a subject for political scrutiny. Second, theorizing on the ‘rule of law’ has promoted a zero-sum conception of power, where it is alleged that deference to law and legal entities (e.g. international courts) translates into a subsequent marginalization of state power and authority. Third, studies on the ‘rule of law’ in world affairs have served to obfuscate our understanding of global governance vis-a-vis law, by utilizing an analytical framework which identifies authority with either the state or a ‘global’ legal regime. Lost is an appreciation of how rule can be constituted and conducted through plural and complex relations between state actors, international laws and nonstate legal actors.</p>
<p>These three stated criticisms provide motive to consider an alternative manner of theorizing the ‘rule of law’ in world affairs. How we explain the relationship between state actors and an alleged ‘global legal system’ necessitates an approach, I argue, that perceives law not as a self-contained and panacea-like universe but rather as a practice of government aimed at directing human conduct. In this way, I assert that the ‘rule of law’ topos is an analytical red herring, and political analysts would gain more insight by treating the association between politics and law in world affairs as rule ‘through’ law.</p>
<p>This proposed revision is about more than semantics, as the following considerations attest. First, key sources of international law, such as treaties and customs, did not arise independent of politics, but rather were made by and between different kinds of states — thus according to particular political advantages. Second, different types of international legal institutions, credited with an active role in global governance (e.g. the ICC or the WTO), did not arise in a political vacuum either: they owe their existence and continued function to the support and funding of key states. Indeed, such aspects are readily acknowledged by IR and IL scholars as taken-for-granted. Yet, this may be the analytical problem: what has been missing is a theoretical approach which emphasizes ‘the mechanisms of power’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-1354066110380966">Sending and Neumann, 2006</xref>: 652), and domination implied in such relations, as a regime of practice and government. Such a manner of theorizing, I argue, becomes possible with reference to Michel Foucault’s concept of ‘governmentality’.</p>
<p>Foucauldian ‘governmentality’ provides us with two potential insights for assessing the role of law in global governance. First, governmentality can be used to treat the emergence of a ‘global legal system’ as a rationality of government; whereby legal norms and legal entities are characterized not in opposition to state power but rather as a means for government by dominant states. Such a perspective challenges the popular assumption that deference to law and legal actors is evidence of a transfer of power from an inter-state to a genuinely global structure of governance; to appreciate how governance through law can be a key asset for political rule and domination. Second, drawing upon Mitchell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1354066110380966">Dean’s (1999)</xref> notion of ‘mentalities’ of government, governmentality highlights the significance of collective thought in conditioning how we think about the exercise of authority in world affairs; and here the prescriptive force of legality should be considered potent as it provides meaning and signification capable of governing perceptions of ‘just’ rule in world affairs. Taken together, these two aspects of governmentality applied to law in world affairs provide a perspective which turns a popular understanding on its head, identifying the ‘rule of law’ not in opposition to politics but rather as a powerful ordering rationality and hence means for government.</p>
<p>In sum, this article applies Foucauldian ‘governmentality’ to the role of law in global governance, and the article is structured in three parts. The first discusses the analytical significance of Foucault’s governmentality concept regarding how conduct can be directed and redirected through regimes of ‘truth’. In the second part, I try to connect this Foucauldian insight with the way in which the ‘rule of law’ topos has been used to promote a belief that ‘global law’ can serve to check state power and provide even-handed accountability. Specifically, I scrutinize juridical governance thinking a la Slaughter which prescribes the constitutional rationale of the <italic>Marbury</italic> v. <italic>Madison</italic> decision in the United States as the basis for global judicial governance. In the third and final part, I apply governmentality to the notion of global law and justice by scrutinizing key areas of international law — the law of war and international criminal adjudication — commonly cited as examples of how the ascendancy of the ‘rule of law’ in world affairs will produce more just and accountable global governance.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1354066110380966">
<title>Governmentality and ‘techniques of power’</title>
<p>Michel Foucault put forward the concept of ‘governmentality’ as an introductory lecture in his course ‘Security, Territory, Population’ at the College of France in the winter of 1978. What interested Foucault was a conceptual transformation he noted between the mid-16th and the late 18th centuries, where a series of treatises on the exercise of power ‘attempted to articulate a kind of rationality that was intrinsic to the art of government’ but yet radically autonomous from ‘the transcendental singularity of Machiavelli’s prince’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1354066110380966">Foucault, 2000a</xref>: 204–206). This ‘art of government’, Foucault asserted, was related to ‘practices’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1354066110380966">2000a</xref>: 205) that did not aim to impose ‘sovereignty’ or obedience over a territory, but rather directed the flow of ‘the population’ into ‘certain regions or activities’ without ‘the full awareness of the people’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1354066110380966">2000a</xref>: 217). Thus, for Foucault, the activity of government was not about imposing law on men ‘but of disposing things: that is, of employing tactics rather than laws, and even of using laws themselves as tactics — to arrange things in such a way that, through a certain number of means, such-and-such ends may be achieved’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1354066110380966">2000a</xref>: 211).</p>
<p>In this way, Foucault’s formulation of ‘governmentality’ intended to articulate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1354066110380966">2000a</xref>: 219–220; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1354066110380966">Burchell et al., 1991</xref>: ix) this change in the practice of government since the early modern state. Further, the concept sought to promote an understanding of ‘the state’ beyond that of a formalistic and territorial unity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1354066110380966">Foucault, 2000a</xref>: 219–220) to that of a ‘rationality of government’ manifested as ‘a way or system of thinking about the nature of the practice of government … capable of making some form of that activity thinkable and practicable both to its practitioners and to those upon whom it was practiced’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1354066110380966">Gordon, 1991</xref>: 3). In effect, what Foucault desired, with the advent of ‘governmentality’, was an alternative manner of analysing ‘the art of government’, fixated not upon institutional ‘centres’ of power but rather on reconstructing certain ‘techniques of power’, as Colin Gordon explains:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>State theory attempts to deduce the modern activities of government from essential properties and propensities of the state, in particular its supposed propensity to grow and swallow up or colonize everything outside itself. Foucault holds that the state has no inherent propensities; more generally, the state has no essence. The nature of the institution of the state is, Foucault thinks, a function of changes in practices of government, rather than the converse. Political theory attends too much to institutions, and too little to practices. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1354066110380966">Gordon, 1991</xref>: 4)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Thus, within the scheme of governmentality, analysis is directed at the broader web of processes and practices which order people and things towards ‘a convenient end’, which Foucault specified as an ‘economy’ of political practice.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1354066110380966">2</xref></sup> This notion of ‘economy’ was intrinsic to Foucault’s understanding of government, as he asserted the ‘main objective’ of the art of government was to exercise power ‘in the form of economy’. This implied an economy of ‘truth’ which directed social, cultural and political understandings towards ‘the right disposition of things’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1354066110380966">Gordon, 1991</xref>); and, as Mitchell Dean explains, this dynamic became the ultimate concern for Foucauldian governmentality: ‘thought as it becomes linked to and is embedded in technical means for the shaping and reshaping of conduct and in practices and institutions’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1354066110380966">Dean, 1999</xref>: 18).</p>
<p>However, receptive IR and politics scholars have suffered from a general hesitancy within Foucauldian interpretive scholarship to explore and identify specific techniques and mechanisms of power which seem central to governmentality’s emphasis on practices versus properties of government. In other words, if Foucault asserted that the nature of the institution of the state resided not in its properties but in its practices, the theoretical need arises to elaborate on ‘the <italic>how</italic> of exercising power’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1354066110380966">Merlingen, 2003</xref>: 366) beyond the inspiring, but no less abstract, direction that ‘we govern and are governed within different regimes’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1354066110380966">Dean, 1999</xref>: 23, 28–29).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1354066110380966">3</xref></sup></p>
<p>Recent development in IR theory, I argue, offers potential to fill that gap within governmentality theorizing. I refer specifically to the pivotal work of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1354066110380966">Barnett and Duvall (2005)</xref> on ‘productive power’ which draws from Foucault’s pre-governmentality writings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1354066110380966">Foucault, 1971</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1354066110380966">1984</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1354066110380966">1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1354066110380966">2000b</xref>) and offers guidance on how to elaborate the association between governmental power and regimes of thought. Barnett and Duvall define ‘productive power’ as ‘socially diffuse production of subjectivity in systems of meaning and signification’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1354066110380966">2005</xref>: 43); and they argue that key practices of world politics centre upon the ‘discursive production of … subjects, the fixing of meanings, and the terms of action’. Barnett and Duvall note the salience of ‘productive power’ as exemplified in socially contested efforts to assign asymmetric categories of social relations, most observable in the use of consequential political (e.g. civilized/uncivilized, Western/non-Western and democratic/non-democratic) and legal categories (e.g. civilian versus combatant) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1354066110380966">Barnett and Duvall, 2005</xref>: 56).</p>
<p>Barnett and Duvall’s articulation of ‘productive power’, I contend, feeds into Foucauldian governmentality by virtue of its emphasis on structures and discourses of meaning, and how they shape thought and consequently conduct. In other words, the concept of ‘productive power’ provides a theoretical addendum which helps articulate ‘techniques of power’ implicated in the production of social ‘truth’. For the purposes of this article, ‘productive power’ becomes useful for theorizing <italic>legal techniques of power</italic> in the practice of global governance. Such legal techniques are not newly identified but rather derived from work done on the ‘instrumental’ use of law by critical scholars in both IR and IL (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr85-1354066110380966">Trimble, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1354066110380966">Kennedy, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1354066110380966">Kinsella, 2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1354066110380966">2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1354066110380966">Mégret, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-1354066110380966">Scott and Ambler, 2007</xref>); with the essential premise of this scholarship being that law has the capacity to propagate political ends through the seeming objectivity of legal methods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1354066110380966">Koskenniemi, 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1354066110380966">1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1354066110380966">2004</xref>). I argue that IR scholarship would gain considerable insight by bringing these concerns of critical legal scholarship together with Foucauldian governmentality to make more visible the ‘techniques of power’ resident in the recent propagation of global (judicial) law.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1354066110380966">
<title>‘Global law’ and <italic>legal</italic> techniques of power</title>
<p>The concept of ‘governmentality’ enhances our analysis of law’s rule in global governance<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1354066110380966">4</xref></sup> by virtue of how governmentality stresses the importance of thought for the steering of human conduct. In this regard, the symbolic and productive capacity of law to influence human perceptions of just and legitimate action seems innately related to the Foucauldian notion of techniques and tactics used for the disposition of political ends. In the analytical vein of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1354066110380966">Barnett and Duvall (2005)</xref>, law wields productive power because it provides systems of meaning and signification capable of influencing social conceptions of just rule. Related to governmentality, law provides ‘techniques of power’ because its structures of meaning and practices of discourse grant the capacity to objectify and thus ‘govern’ the substance of what we believe to be ‘just’ conduct on a global scale.</p>
<p>The critical legal work of Martti Koskenniemi touches upon this effect using the notion of ‘hegemonic contestation’ in international law, where international actors are held to craft legal rules and principles to accord with partial political claims but yet retain the appearance of universal preference (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1354066110380966">Koskenniemi, 2004</xref>: 199). Building on Koskenniemi, I claim we need to take this analysis one step further to identify a symbolic dimension which liberal IR and IL scholars rely upon to promote the virtue of a global legal system relative to state power. I refer to the ‘rule of law’ topos and its contrast to the ‘rule of men’, or, as Paul Kahn states, ‘the rule of law is the rule of no one’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1354066110380966">Kahn, 1997</xref>: 22; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1354066110380966">Haltern, 2003</xref>). The rule of law topos, I argue, has played a central role in shaping perceptions of equity for a global legal regime directed by supranational courts, transnational activists and ‘universal’ values. What my ensuing discussion does therefore is attack this line of thought in a threefold manner. First, I discuss how the imputed meaning of the rule of law topos is tied to the specific legal-cultural project of American constitutionalism. Second, I argue that an incomplete reading of that constitutional ‘model’ has led to false assumptions on the applicability of American constitutionalism for a similar global legal system. Third, I apply governmentality to suggest that the ‘rule of law’ topos provides a key asset for (state) power as it facilitates the crafting of normative perceptions of just conduct in global governance through law’s apparent objectivity and universality.</p>
<sec id="section4-1354066110380966">
<title>Topos revisited: The rule of law and the rule of ‘no one’</title>
<p>When studying the ‘rule of law’ topos one should appreciate that the concept manifests a long and varied lineage. Its use extends to Ancient Greece, and many place emphasis on Aristotle’s passage that ‘law should rule rather than any single one of the citizens’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1354066110380966">1972</xref>: 1287a, 1–7); notwithstanding that Aristotle did make the caveat that the rule of (good) law was dependent upon the rule of (good) men (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1354066110380966">Frank, 2007</xref>). Further, an extended line of thinkers and traditions, inclusive of Aristotle, the Stuart Parliamentarians (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1354066110380966">Skinner, 2003</xref>: 12–15), Rousseau, Montesquieu, the American founders, the advocates of the <italic>rechtstaat</italic> and the more contemporary works of Friedrich Hayek, John Rawls, Lon Fuller and Theodore Lowi, have all grappled with this general imperative that ‘rule be by law’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1354066110380966">Flathman, 1994</xref>: 302–303).</p>
<p>Yet, this is not to suggest that the ‘rule of law’ topos is a product of an ‘enlightened’ progression over time: ‘perfected’ so to speak from Aristotle through to its current transcendental manifestation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1354066110380966">Kratochwil, 2009</xref>). Rather it is to note that what ‘law’ and the ‘rule of law’ have meant through recorded history has not been universal both across and within civilizations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-1354066110380966">Supiot, 2007</xref>), and this despite consistencies which could be drawn between some understandings. Notwithstanding, we remain witnesses to a political present where the meaning of the ‘rule of law’ has been proclaimed as a ubiquitous and ‘natural’ formulation, especially among those which point to the emancipating potential of ‘global law’ versus state power. In fact, as E.H. Carr attests, such a notion of law as emancipator is a familiar imperative for students of IR:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>There is, among many people interested in international affairs, a strong inclination to treat the law as something independent of, and ethically superior to, politics. ‘The moral force of law’ is contrasted with the implicitly immoral methods of politics. We are exhorted to establish ‘the rule of law’, to maintain ‘international law and order’ or to ‘defend international law’; and the assumption is made that, by so doing, we shall transfer our differences from the turbulent political atmosphere of self-interest to the purer, serener air of impartial justice. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1354066110380966">Carr, 1939</xref>: 170)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>To understand how the ‘rule of law’ topos has become associated with a singular emancipatory meaning, I argue, we need to appreciate how the American legal and constitutional project has contributed to what now seems a ubiquitous and transnational imperative; as, indeed, much of what is said about the ‘rule of law’ in IR and IL owes a great deal to the influence of American political and legal culture regarding the ideal conduct of domestic and international politics. How the American legal tradition becomes significant for contemporary understandings of the ‘rule of law’ in world affairs requires an appreciation of the imaginative force generated regarding law’s liberating effect from partial rule. This is hardly a novel observation, as both de Tocqueville<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1354066110380966">5</xref></sup> and Paine heralded the uniqueness of America as the land where law, and not man, was ‘King’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-1354066110380966">Paine, 1989</xref>: 28). As Kahn notes in his cultural study of American constitutionalism, it has been this dictum that has governed American legal thought and political imagination, as confirmed by the landmark United States Supreme Court decision in <italic>Marbury</italic> v. <italic>Madison</italic>: ‘The government of the United States has been emphatically termed a government of law, and not of men.’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1354066110380966">6</xref></sup></p>
<p>The extent to which the ‘rule of no one’ constitutes a statement of ‘fact’ versus an ‘aspiration’ for American legal and political life is indeed a point of contestation — be it regarding the present day or when Chief Justice Marshall presided over the Supreme Court. Yet, it is important to note that analytical scrutiny of the claim proves somewhat redundant. As Kahn rightly notes, regardless of the actual ‘truth’ of <italic>Marbury</italic>, generations of Americans and non-Americans have, through ‘aggregation of ideas, values and symbols’, come to believe and take for granted that, ‘[America] is a government of law and that through law the people rule’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1354066110380966">Kahn, 1997</xref>: 2). Flowing from this ‘collective’ belief, the ‘rule of law’ as the rule of ‘no one’ has been elaborated into a ‘rational’ model, constituting an ‘ideal of governance under rules that meet conditions of publicity, generality, coherence and nonretroactivity’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1354066110380966">Kahn, 1997</xref>: 3).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1354066110380966">
<title>Revisiting constitutional theory and the ‘rule of no one’</title>
<p>One of the things that makes <italic>Marbury</italic> a powerful conceptual ideal<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-1354066110380966">7</xref></sup> is its intuitive value for those (lawyers and non-lawyers alike) with experience in ‘common law’ traditions, such as in the United States, Britain, Canada or Australia.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-1354066110380966">8</xref></sup> The constitutional and normative architecture of the ‘common law’, in contrast to the positive law<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-1354066110380966">9</xref></sup> underpinnings of Roman and civil law traditions, emphasizes a separation of the judiciary from the state by means of ‘case’ or ‘judge-made’ law: where ‘through … <italic>stare decisis</italic> … each decision of the court would represent a rule of law’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1354066110380966">Glenn, 2007</xref>: 246). Thus, the rule of law as expressed by ‘case law’ fosters a belief that judges occupy a unique place relative to government,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-1354066110380966">10</xref></sup> such that a system of <italic>law qua judges</italic> — responsible for the administration of ‘justice’ — is distinguishable from the ‘rule’ of <italic>law qua legislation</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1354066110380966">Glenn, 2007</xref>: 249).</p>
<p>However, this notion of judges standing in conceptual distinction from government was considerably modified within the US ‘common law’ following James Madison’s assertion that courts were an integral <italic>participant</italic> in a process of American government: ‘[a] government without a proper executive and judiciary would be the mere trunk of a body, without arms and legs to act or move’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-1354066110380966">11</xref></sup> Subsequently, the <italic>Marbury</italic> decision was taken to have symbolically and substantively affirmed that vision of judges as being an innate part of what constituted good government, the effect of which was to consolidate a view where courts were seen as possessing a ‘unique role in expressing the rule of law’ as integral to the process of government.</p>
<p>Thus, the <italic>Marbury</italic> decision amounted to a unique adaptation of the common law tradition, where the distinction between <italic>the judge</italic> and <italic>the legislator</italic> became blurred, and courts were formally recognized as exercising a constitutional function of governmental oversight. It was an innovative formula where courts were regarded as ‘independent’, as per common law thinking, but yet assigned major powers of ‘supervision’ and control so as ‘to establish general rules … of conduct for those in power’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1354066110380966">David and Brierley, 1985</xref>: 442). Legal analysis has long noted the significance of this development because of its civil law import into the US constitution.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-1354066110380966">12</xref></sup> Yet, cultural analysis highlights perhaps the most notable feature of <italic>Marbury</italic> beyond the blending of legal traditions: the decision constructed a powerful and omnipotent ‘court’ which became a symbol for public order, and conflated government and the ‘rule of law’ within a unified perception. As Paul Kahn notes, it was this synthesis of government and the ‘rule of law’ within the body of the court that influenced the contemporary legal and political psyche; and, consequently, defined what many believe a ‘modern’ manifestation of law’s rule <italic>should look like</italic>, both domestically and now globally.</p>
<p>However, surprisingly little attention has been paid to the actual source of authority that gives the American court its celebrated political, legal and social force. Even a magisterial work such as Kahn’s suggests that the question of ‘why courts should have this ultimate power’ is mostly explained by reference to the sacred rather than through fuller constitutional explanation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1354066110380966">Kahn, 1997</xref>: 4). This has been unfortunate, I argue, because it reveals a failure to note the key constitutional tenet which has made empowered courts and judicial review both institutionally effective and politically legitimate within the American context: ‘constitutional rules [which are] widely held to be higher or more fundamental than law in the usual sense’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-1354066110380966">Onuf, 1994</xref>: 14).</p>
<p>In the instance of American constitutionalism, those constitutional rules were recorded in the US constitution and further underwritten by an intersubjective understanding associated with Madison’s formulation that a constitution was ‘established by the people and unalterable by the government’, as against ‘a law established by the government and alterable by the government’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-1354066110380966">Onuf, 1994</xref>), the result being that American courts gained jurisdiction, authority and political legitimacy because they became designated as the guardians of the supreme and highest law as set forth by the people. The significance of this separation of powers for American constitutionalism is neglected by those who suggest that the furtherance of the ‘rule of law’ in world affairs is realized with the mere institution of an American-style ‘global’ judiciary. As implied, the latter logic puts the cart before the horse as it fails to appreciate the relationship between a supreme law, judicial governance and the rule of law, leaving a political vacuum at the core of the liberal vision for a global legal system. Based upon the constitutional framework of the United States, supreme constitutional rules become essential for a system of judicial review which maintains the rule of the higher law, and thus figuratively the rule of ‘no one’. The absence of a similar constitutional regime at the global level, combined with the proliferation of powerful international courts, creates a constitutional situation where the symbolic force of the ‘rule of law’ topos remains in use while the substance of the ‘rule of no one’ is left for exposition.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1354066110380966">
<title>‘In [courts] we trust’?<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13-1354066110380966">13</xref></sup> The Marbury ideal and global (judicial) governance</title>
<p>Notwithstanding this constitutional void, an incomplete account of the <italic>Marbury</italic> ideal remains influential in a liberal push for a global legal system. This is most prominent in the global governance scholarship of Anne-Marie Slaughter and her book, <italic>A New World Order</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-1354066110380966">2004</xref>). Slaughter prescribes the making of a ‘global legal system’ which draws from ‘US regulatory, judicial and legislative approaches’, and demonstrates a history of ‘powerful attraction’ for foreign emulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-1354066110380966">2004</xref>: 5). Among various governance themes, Slaughter emphasizes judicial governance as a crowning achievement of American government, and exalts the coming reality of ‘judicial globalization’ as reflective of this ‘best practice’. She praises how ‘judges around the world are coming together in various ways … [to construct] a formal global legal system’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-1354066110380966">2004</xref>: 102), and, further, that such networks of judges, conceived of as a ‘community of courts’, are developing a rough system of ‘checks and balances’ which counter a ‘centralized hierarchy’ of authority.</p>
<p>Slaughter’s advocacy of a global judiciary is a project with profound constitutional implications. The idea that global governance should be furthered by a ‘global’ network of courts and judges represents a departure from conventional international law as constituted by a society of states. The reasoning behind such a constitutional move appears influenced by the presumed success of American judicial government as attributed to the <italic>Marbury</italic> ideal. Slaughter, in fact, makes this direct association in a later book <italic>The Idea that is America</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-1354066110380966">2007</xref>), where the <italic>Marbury</italic> ideal is acknowledged as the philosophical basis for empowering ‘courts’ as the guardians of the ‘rule of law’ and above all ‘just’ government across the world. As Slaughter asserts:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>It may seem deeply paradoxical that in a country that prides itself on our democratic traditions as much as the United States does, we nevertheless turn to courts rather than to Congress to decide issues ranging from gun control to birth control, wetlands to welfare, antitrust to affirmative action, and countless others. Yet in many ways, the power we invest in our judges makes our lawmaking more democratic.…</p>
<p>Americans genuinely believe, as John Adams wrote into the Massachusetts Constitution, that we are ‘a government of law and not of men’. Although our courts sometimes fail, they often succeed — speaking truth to power and standing firm against the forces of politics. Our system of judicial review has been adopted in liberal democracies all over the world as a fundamental check on the power of the legislature and the executive. And our system of public interest litigation, whereby individuals and organizations can sue to enforce or overturn laws that help or harm them, has proven attractive to activists around the world. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-1354066110380966">2007</xref>: 119–120)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Yet, this suggested ‘export’ of the <italic>Marbury</italic> ideal as ‘best practice’ for global governance, I argue, prompts questions on the extent to which judicial governance on a global scale would alter actual relations of international power, where Slaughter’s court-centred panacea might not produce the radical disaggregation of authority from state power as implied by grafting the symbolic legacy of <italic>Marbury</italic> onto a global plane. Such a doubt is sustainable with reference to the discussed constitutional framework that has underwritten the <italic>Marbury</italic> ideal in the practice of American constitutional government: judicial governance, and thus a ‘rule of law’, obtains its collective credence and force in reliance upon supreme constitutional rules.</p>
<p>One could suggest that Slaughter’s prescription of inserting ‘judicial nodes’ to rival ‘state nodes’ of power overlooks this second-order logic which is intrinsic to a genuine judicial order that functions in accordance with the esteemed American archetype. In other words, the prescriptive stance taken by Slaughter to herald ‘global courts’ as the instillers of a global ‘rule of law’ speaks only to an institutionalization of political authority without reference to a requisite constitutional mandate.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14-1354066110380966">14</xref></sup> This lack of attention to supreme constitutional rules, I argue, suggests that the institutionalization of global courts, or even a global judicial network, is unlikely to produce the pervasive supervision of state power sought because such judicial apparatuses will lack the empowering constitutional directive that distinguishes the American model. What is more, such judicial supervision offers the prospect of putative opposition which merely restrains flagrant excesses of state power while lacking the constitutional scope to challenge those instances which speak to the asserted coherence and equity of the politico-legal regime itself.</p>
<p>To appreciate how Slaughter’s institutional optimism becomes vulnerable to political subversion, we need to return to our discussion on the association between governmentality and productive power in relation to the socio-cultural significance of law as an artefact of perceived ‘truth’. As Haltern has noted, ‘the rule of law is a shorthand expression for the imaginative construction of a complete social-political order. It is a way of perceiving events and actors, and a framework of understanding that makes it possible to perceive legal meaning in every event’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1354066110380966">2003</xref>: 19). Within domestic contexts, this idea that law (through legislation and legal institutions) conditions hierarchical relations vis-a-vis the ‘psychic trappings of lawfulness’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1354066110380966">Jochnik and Norman, 1994</xref>: 57) is readily acknowledged. Yet, at the international level, the role so-called ‘global law’ could play in structuring perceptions of ‘legality’, ‘justice’ and order is less examined for its partial political implications.</p>
<p>The appearance of ‘legality’ becomes crucial, I argue, when considering the institutionalization of global judicial governance. As previously noted, the law provides powerful symbolic and conceptual tools to shape human perceptions of just and legitimate action; a capacity which prompted Foucault to characterize law as a ‘discursive regime’, ‘an institutional edifice with specific precepts, rules and conventions of behaviour’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1354066110380966">Foucault, 1980</xref>: 133; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1354066110380966">Kelsall, 2006</xref>: 589). This ‘productive’ capacity of the law to create social ‘truth’ becomes reflected in discursive practices where claims of ‘legality’ constitute normative requisites for legitimate (in)action, which is exemplified in the growth of ‘international’ courts, declarations of ‘lawful’ invasion<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15-1354066110380966">15</xref></sup> or careful reliance upon international laws that govern ‘equitable’ conduct in economic exchange and military force. It is this faith in ‘legality’ that girds Slaughter’s optimism in how judicial governance of state power will deliver more just and equitable conduct in world affairs, and ultimately a global ‘rule of law’.</p>
<p>Yet, the shortcoming of the ‘global law’ approach a la Slaughter rests in its failure to consider how judicial governance may end up reproducing the politics that it is intended to deny; where global judicial governance is not the promised end of state power but rather a new and sophisticated vehicle through which state power can be propagated in world affairs. In this light, governmentality proves instructive because it challenges a dichotomy that separates the supposed constraints of ‘global law’ from the imperatives of vested power. Through the lens of governmentality, a global legal system provides techniques of power via its complex of symbols, knowledge, thinking and language, that serve to interlock legality with power. Moreover, what the governmentality perspective would further suggest is that the appearance of change in the institutional locus of power might be nothing other than a change in the activity of governing, where a politico-legal regime is reinvented and made practicable by the governing for the governed.</p>
<p>In the final part of this article, I take this notion of a global legal system as a form of governmentality into empirical consideration; to relate some of the observations and concerns of critical legal scholarship to support the argument that juridical legality can serve as a tactic for the political imperatives of vested actors. In particular, the optimism that surrounds judicial governance is challenged by raising awareness of the ways in which international adjudication can be constituted to facilitate a kind of <italic>patrons’ justice</italic>. In this way, as opposed to representing a structural corrective to state power, the emergence of judicial governance can enable the crafting of normative standards and institutional oversight which obfuscates accountability and thus encodes domination through an ‘economy’ of justice shaped by dominant power.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1354066110380966">
<title>Institutional constraint or a judicial technique of power? The rise of international adjudication</title>
<p>When one thinks of a United Nations court or any institution bearing the designation ‘court’, an almost intuitive imagery and legitimacy is triggered. ‘Courts’, with their robes, protocols and chambers, command the secular mind and imagination as few modern institutions do; a role and symbolism so powerful in fact that it dampens our sense of critical inquiry vis-a-vis the origin and validity of professed judicial authority.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16-1354066110380966">16</xref></sup> Further, the operation of a court under a ‘collective’ banner, such as the UN flag, and perhaps located in The Hague, adds extra measures of symbolic legitimacy vis-a-vis the lore of international and collective approval. In this way, not only are the performative requisites of a robe-cloaked and judgement-issuing body fulfilled, but also the veneer of international recognition and consensus are presented as well.</p>
<p>It is this conflation of authority and adjudication, I argue, that has been significant in the recent turn to international courts in the past two decades; where as many as 125 international bodies with judicial or quasi-judicial functions are now said to exist dealing with a range of political issues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1354066110380966">Koskenniemi, 2007</xref>: 1). Yet, this growth of ‘international’ adjudicative bodies conveys more than an intriguing statistic when one appreciates how that trend overlaps with a cultural and professional sensibility, the kind of which was discussed earlier in relation to the <italic>Marbury</italic> ideal: there is an Anglo-American tradition of legalism which vests confidence in judge-made rule, where ‘the court’ is seen to be the guarantor of legal integrity and good government (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1354066110380966">Koskenniemi, 2007</xref>: 16).</p>
<p>Within American law, this belief is easily identified with the seminal work of Ronald Dworkin in <italic>Law’s Empire</italic>, where the question of ‘what is law’ is addressed with this short but substantial reply: ‘it matters how judges decide cases’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1354066110380966">1986</xref>: 1). The statement is a significant one because it reflects a structure of belief girded upon a number of socio-political postulates: the straightforward and determined quality of rules; the equity and balance of a lawyer class; and the propensity of adjudication — in contrast to arbitration — to ‘apply strict law’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1354066110380966">Koskenniemi, 2007</xref>: 17). Yet, beyond our earlier discussion of Slaughter’s work on ‘judicial globalization’, it is important to recognize how a court-centred vision of US law and government has long animated American visions of global governance. In fact, as Martti Koskenniemi explains, this ideal that a ‘court’ should symbolize a ‘new way’ of international rule, which resembles rule as in the United States, was a hallmark of rising American leadership at the start of the 20th century:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>To study … an institution is to examine where it comes from, and what it is expected to achieve. International adjudication was an American project. True, lawyers and activists from many countries have supported it. But only the United States adopted it as an aspect of its foreign policy in the early years of the 20th century. American lawyers had experience of how to settle jurisdictional disputes by referring them to a Supreme Court. Their articles and arguments were full of domestic analogies. The proposal for a [Permanent Court of International Justice] is an aspect of the turn of the ‘old diplomacy’ to the ‘American century’ in which the assumptions of the US foreign policy elite would set the agenda for international reform. (2007: 3)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>These historical elements of foreign policy blend in with a kind of legal historicism that developed alongside the advent of international courts through the mid- to latter 20th century. Commencing with the International Military Tribunal (IMT) at Nuremberg (1946), a teleological line has been drawn asserting the historic march of international adjudication in the field of criminal law; continued by the International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia (ICTY) (1993), followed by the International Criminal Tribunal for Rwanda (ICTR) (1994) and capped off with the initiation of the International Criminal Court in 1998. It is a story, as Yves Beigbeder<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17-1354066110380966">17</xref></sup> illustrates, with profound rhetorical appeal:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>The probable creation of the [International Criminal Court] following the approval of its Statute in Rome in July 1998, is in itself an extraordinary event in the history of mankind. For the first time, a permanent international court will have authority to investigate and bring to justice individuals who commit the most serious crimes of concern to the international community, such as war crimes and crimes against humanity. Kofi Annan, the United Nations Secretary-General, saluted the approval of the Statute by 120 countries by declaring that this adoption was another giant step forward in the march towards universal human rights and the rule of law. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1354066110380966">Beigbeder, 2002</xref>: 1)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In fact, this combination of storied foreign policy, symbolic meaning and narrative historicism come together to significant effect by constructing an appearance of ‘international justice’ which is said to counterbalance state power (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-1354066110380966">Sadat, 2002</xref>: 109; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr86-1354066110380966">Weller, 2002</xref>: 700), in the sense that international courts and judges signify an independent, impartial and objective ‘rule of law’ in the conduct of world politics. Yet, I argue, firm belief in this aspiration could lead many analysts to misread the extent to which the ascendance of international adjudication is in fact an actual derogation of state power.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18-1354066110380966">18</xref></sup> Instead, I propose that we need to scrutinize the extent to which politics permeates the structures and practices of international law, whether that be in the content of <italic>jus in bello</italic> law or in the normative construction of judicial apparatuses and processes.</p>
<p>In this respect, while the emergence of international adjudication gives the impression of a diffusion of authority, I claim that a more grounded study of ‘the power at work’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-1354066110380966">Sending and Neumann, 2006</xref>: 654) in the design of such judicial practices reveals that relations of power between dominant states and many ‘international’ courts are less than antithetical. This can be observed most prominently with two tactics of court construction: first, the convocation of international courts requires dominant state approval and thus precipitates shrewd delineation of <italic>actual jurisdiction</italic>; second, dominant states can lessen the <italic>discretion</italic> of international courts with the use of selective prosecutorial appointments and strategic cooperation with prosecutorial activities. We will now discuss these aspects in relation to the contradictions that have emerged in recent ‘international’ criminal adjudication.</p>
<p>The convocation of war crimes tribunals rarely forsakes altruistic rhetoric, in the sense that the use of international criminal adjudication is often pronounced as the ‘bringing of justice’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1354066110380966">Moghalu, 2006</xref>: 6) into communal politics — a figurative ‘end of history’ to borrow Fukuyama’s phrase, where international tribunals like the IMT, ICTY and the ICC are portrayed as the institutional source for the ultimate provision of ‘global’ accountability and justice. However, a noted, historical discrepancy exists in the actual delivery of such expectations, in that international courts become established — in formal and practical terms — only with the backing of dominant states, ‘and only when those same states feel themselves aggrieved or victimized’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-1354066110380966">Smith, 2002a</xref>: 178). Further, when such war crimes courts are established, they come with strategic limitations on the scope of their practical jurisdiction.</p>
<p>For instance, the Nuremberg trials are often hailed for their accomplishments on the laws of war, crimes against peace and crimes against humanity. Yet, what is less discussed are the gaps of the IMT vis-a-vis its refusal to prosecute and convict all violations of the laws of war (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1354066110380966">Jochnik and Normand, 1994</xref>: 94). The IMT exercised selective jurisdiction on war crimes likely due to the ‘morale bombing’ conducted by the Allies against German and Japanese cities, which incurred hundreds of thousands of civilian casualties, and in all likelihood constituted war crimes. This practical legacy of selective scrutiny for war crimes established a Nuremberg precedent for so-called ‘normal’ wartime atrocities, where ‘international law tolerates massacres of civilians, including those by nuclear weapons’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1354066110380966">Jochnik and Normand, 1994</xref>: 94).</p>
<p>Turning to the contemporary practice of war crimes adjudication, a number of indicators can be identified which point to how (state) power is able to influence the origin and jurisdiction of war crimes tribunals, ranging from explicit to implicit tactics of governance. First, the victorious powers which drafted the UN Charter did not provide for the establishment of war crimes tribunals.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19-1354066110380966">19</xref></sup> In fact, ad hoc tribunals, such as the ICTY and ICTR, owe their existence to a ‘seismic’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-1354066110380966">Robertson, 2002</xref>: 194) reinterpretation of Chapter VII in the early 1990s, or more accurately a ‘reading-in’ of humanitarian law as a matter of ‘international peace and security’ (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1354066110380966">Kerr, 2004</xref>: 27); which gave the Security Council implied authority to constitute war crimes tribunals at the convenience of the great powers. However, a notable distinction between this ad hoc type of tribunal, versus a permanent war crimes court that could have been provided for under the UN Charter, relates to how the former kind is dominated by the Security Council and the power of the veto. Current US foreign policy actively supports this type of ad hoc war crimes adjudication relative to the latter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1354066110380966">Moghalu, 2006</xref>: 143).</p>
<p>Second, the establishment of the ICC, with the signature of 120 states in 1998, has been hailed a convocation of an independent and even-handed court, free of the taint of patrons’ justice attached to ad hoc adjudicative efforts in past decades. Yet, a more astute reading of the ICC negotiations, and the subsequent ICC Statute, yields the significance of productive power: the normative regime of ICC jurisdiction is conducive to the military practices of technologically advanced states (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-1354066110380966">Smith, 2002b</xref>). For instance, the ICC Statute is primarily directed at the criminalization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1354066110380966">Cohen, 1996</xref>: 13–15) and prosecution of so-called ‘machete murder’, by virtue of the fact that Western powers excluded ‘the use of weapons of mass destruction’ (foremost in the possession of Western military arsenals) from the ICC definition of ‘genocide’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-1354066110380966">Smith, 2002a</xref>: 178). Further, ‘crimes against peace’ and ‘aggressive war’, which the IMT characterized as the ‘supreme international crime’, were similarly withheld from the jurisdiction of ICC prosecution, owing to the efforts to entice a US signature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1354066110380966">Conso, 1999</xref>: 475). Finally, under the ICC Statute, members of the Security Council were granted key jurisdictional exemptions, such as an unlimited number of 12-month deferrals of ICC activities and a seven-year opt-out clause from the court’s jurisdiction over war crimes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-1354066110380966">Smith, 2002a</xref>: 180).</p>
<p>In sum, one cannot escape the impression that the hailed transfer of authority from state to ‘global’ judicial actors, in the context of contemporary war crimes adjudication, is difficult to assert based on scrutiny of stated and actual <italic>jurisdiction</italic>. However, the crafting of jurisdiction is only one normativity which governs the conduct of adjudication, a second and equally important aspect concerns the disposal of <italic>prosecutorial discretion</italic>. I discuss briefly this avenue with reference to the controversy it has inspired over the ICTY’s prosecutorial function.</p>
<p>One of the defining contests in the constitution of the ICTY did not revolve around whether the court should be created. Rather, where the great powers often struggled was over <italic>how</italic> the court should function and, in this respect, over the human and financial practices which would animate the ICTY’s operation. Security Council Resolution 827, passed on 25 May 1993, defined the ICTY’s legal and administrative parameters, and thus governed the work and scope of the Tribunal. Key among these parameters was that, one, the Security Council had direct control over the choice of Prosecutor and, two, the Tribunal could obtain direct support from any government and private (IO and NGO) organization in the form of ‘funds, equipment and services’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-1354066110380966">Morris and Scharf, 1995</xref>: 177–178). Put together, these provisions permitted space for state influence over the ICTY through an adept combination of astute prosecutorial appointments and ‘private’ judicial financing.</p>
<p>Thus, it should be no surprise that the Security Council needed 18 months to agree upon a candidate as the first Chief Prosecutor of the ICTY. The character of this contest was aptly described by Kingsley Chiedu Moghalu as a search not for ‘the best man or woman to do the job of prosecuting war crimes in the Balkans’ but rather to find the ‘lowest common denominator’ which ‘would be acceptable to all the great powers’ (2006: 55). Moghalu’s finding is perhaps understated, as the US held profound sway over the function of the Prosecutor’s office,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20-1354066110380966">20</xref></sup> through tactics such as prosecutor vetting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1354066110380966">Bass, 2000</xref>: 262; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-1354066110380966">Off, 2000</xref>: 276), well-timed financial ‘donations’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1354066110380966">Hazan, 2004</xref>: 113), mass staffing secondments (e.g. CIA and State Department officers) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1354066110380966">Bass, 2000</xref>: 262; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1354066110380966">Goldstone, 2000</xref>: 80; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1354066110380966">Hazan, 2004</xref>: 53) and select ‘intelligence’ provision (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1354066110380966">Mandel, 2004</xref>: 117–146). At the core of this involvement, while no doubt professed as following America’s commitment to the <italic>Marbury</italic> ideal, was more likely the power the Chief Prosecutor possessed as a magistrate of an international criminal court: he or she had the <italic>discretion</italic> to decide which crimes to prosecute (who, how and when), and which to not. Indeed such an observation could be written off as cynical but it is nonetheless grounded in the controversy generated by NATO spokesperson Jamie Shea, following his reply to a reporter’s question on whether NATO forces would be subject to an ICTY investigation for alleged war crimes committed during the 1999 bombardment of Yugoslavia:<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21-1354066110380966">21</xref></sup></p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>I think we have to distinguish between the theoretical and the practical. I believe that when Justice Arbour starts her investigation, she will because we [NATO] will allow her to…. If her court, as we want, is to be allowed access, it will be because of NATO…. NATO countries are those that have provided the finance to set up the Tribunal…. I am certain that when Justice Arbour goes to Kosovo and looks at the facts she will be indicting people of Yugoslav nationality and I don’t anticipate any others at this stage.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22-1354066110380966">22</xref></sup></p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>To close this section, and our discussion of international adjudication, it is fitting to presume that should the law appear as <italic>King</italic>, then the court must be its proverbial <italic>crown</italic>; and, as such, it becomes imperative that the ascendance of global courts is met with considerable <italic>political</italic> scrutiny of professed ‘legal’ ways. The ‘court’ on the world stage inherits an image, lore and reverence that makes it more than a powerful object distinct from state power; rather, the pliable character of any court’s construction, through the normative tactics we have just discussed, point to how ‘international’ courts can be a sophisticated ‘techne of government’ within the Foucauldian scheme of ‘governmentality’. Through the court’s perception as a guardian and fiduciary of ‘justice’, a practice of government can be identified which is foremost potent because it is above all quaint. It embellishes, for interwoven reasons of logic, imagination and faith, a judicial rationality with the capacity to make ‘practicable’ a regime of domination. This section therefore intended to stimulate that apprehension on the <italic>legal</italic> ways in which this was <italic>politically</italic> possible.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1354066110380966" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion: Governmentality, judicial governance and rule <italic>through</italic> law</title>
<p>This article has taken a critical approach towards an ascendant liberal scholarship in IR and IL that has heralded the imperative of the ‘rule of law’ in world affairs, and more specifically advocated the institution of a global legal system in succession to the ‘old’ international law of state power. At the heart of this agenda has been a kind of juridical and legal idolatry which has suggested that a new regime of ‘global law’, furthered by a network of courts, judges and lawyers, would mark a process where the archaic law of states was replaced by a more universal system of global judicial governance. Yet, missing in this exuberance has been recognition that law does possess a more conflicted nature: it is also an integral participant in rule.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23-1354066110380966">23</xref></sup> Thus, the hesitation to recognize the ‘rulership’ of law, as a subject of power, has meant a liberal interpretation of law’s relation to power which has failed to identify how law can be instrumental to rule and thus provide tactics of government.</p>
<p>What is more, the characterization of an emerging global legal system as being opposed to state power has clouded how law may not rule in its own right, but on behalf of political strategies which make and construct the practices of ‘global law’ that many have failed to question for their political implications. This point reflects a key aspect of Foucauldian analysis: the workings of law must be understood as blended and related to extra-legal processes and practices which exert a governing influence over law’s purposes and effects. In this light, the habitual manner of characterizing ‘global law’ as potential emancipator contrasts with a Foucauldian perceptive of law’s condition as being in ‘perpetual hyphenation’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1354066110380966">Golder and Fitzpatrick, 2009</xref>: 62–64), where politics figures prominently and the extent that law can exert autonomy is circumscribed by law’s role in the encoding of power.</p>
<p>Therefore, this article has sought to raise three key issues related to liberal advocacy for a global legal system. First, on the conceptual level, it has sought to challenge the imaginary line placed between global law and state power; to suggest that a move towards a global legal system is less likely to exorcize state power and more apt to (re)invent a politico-juridical regime which makes power more practicable because it can be construed as ‘legal’. Second, regarding judicial governance, this article has stressed an understanding of global adjudication beyond the simplicity of institutional topography towards an appreciation of the supreme constitutional rules required to ensure a genuine separation of powers for global governance. Third, with respect to governance policy, this article has suggested that the promotion of the <italic>Marbury</italic> ideal as the legal template for a global judicial order tempts political subversion because it neglects supreme constitutional rules which make the American constitutional schematic attractive. Consequently, the pretence of following the US constitutional ‘model’ at the ‘global’ level, minus its constitutional imperatives, promotes a formalistic approach to judicial authority that utilizes the productive power of the ‘rule of law’ topos to facilitate a practice of figurative political restraint.</p>
<p>This brings us to the key claim of the article: that we are better off speaking of a rule ‘through’ law as opposed to a ‘rule of law’ in global governance. Here, I argue that the lens of governmentality proves apt with its emphasis on practices of government which work to establish an economy of ‘truth’. With this perspective, we can reinterpret an emerging global legal system less as an institutional constraint on power and more as a rationality of government that uses techniques such as judicial legality to craft normative standards and oversight practices which can be amenable to political imperatives. This idea that a global legal system could facilitate an ‘economy’ of normative truth stands in stark contrast to the liberal picture of the ‘rule of law’ as defined by the judicial symbolism of the <italic>Marbury</italic> ideal, where the mere transposition of global courts and a global judiciary is suggested to be the source for impartial rule and accountability in world politics. In sum, scrutiny of ‘global law’ through governmentality yields a view where, despite an imagined (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1354066110380966">Anderson, 2006</xref>) facelessness, the rule of judicial law in global governance should be still understood as constituting rule in the political and partial sense. This then opens a new perspective upon the liberal vision of law’s rule in world politics: where instead of consigning our views of judicial governance to the sacred we undertake a more critical examination of this powerful politico-juridical model.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>I am indebted and very grateful to the comments of the anonymous reviewers, Tanja Aalberts, Rainer Baumann, Jin-Young Chung, Joerg Friedrichs, Stefano Guzzini, Rodney Hall, Friedrich Kratochwil, Rahel Kunz, Don Moon, Iver Neumann, Nicholas Onuf, Hannes Peltonen, Liliana Pop and Jason Sharman. I want to extend my love and thanks to my wife and family for their enduring support. Earlier versions of this paper were presented at the ECPR Joint Sessions in Lisbon (April 2009) and the Kyung Hee University ‘International Community and Global Governance’ conference (November 2009). Responsibility for this article remains indeed with the author.</p>
</ack>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1354066110380966">
<label>1.</label>
<p>The term ‘world affairs’ is used instead of ‘international relations’ or ‘international politics’ so as to provide a term open to IR and IL scholars.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1354066110380966">
<label>2.</label>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1354066110380966">Foucault (2000a</xref>: 207–208):</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>This, I believe, is the essential issue in the establishment of the art of government — introduction of economy into political practice.… The word ‘economy’, which in the sixteenth century signified a form of government, comes in the eighteenth century to designate a level of reality, a field of intervention, through a series of complex processes that I regard as absolutely fundamental to our history.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1354066110380966">
<label>3.</label>
<p>See also Michel Foucault’s discussion of ‘how’ questions in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1354066110380966">Foucault (2000b</xref>: 336–339).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1354066110380966">
<label>4.</label>
<p>At this juncture one should caution that both Foucault’s construal of law and how this relates to governmentality is a subject of evolving debate among Foucault’s interpreters. A key contextual reason for this resides in how Foucault revised and expanded upon his work continually over time and thus his premature death cut short elaboration he could have provided vis-a-vis both governmentality and law. For instance, the conventional interpretation on Foucault and law has been associated with the ‘expulsion thesis’: where Foucault is understood to have considered law as a passe form of monarchical power consistent with the Austinian model of the commands and coercive force of the sovereign. Some of Foucault’s interpreters, however, such as Francois <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1354066110380966">Ewald (1990)</xref>, have found this construal simplistic, and argue that Foucault was far more nuanced in his analysis as between the power of juridical and normative law, something which Foucault’s discussion of governmentality could support regarding the suggestion that law amounts to a tactic ‘for arrang[ing] things’. Nonetheless, the interpretive debate remains active, and the question of whether Foucault’s relational and instrumental understanding of politics and law could accommodate some degree of mutual constitution is well illustrated by the conventional instrumental (‘expulsion’) view as discussed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1354066110380966">Hunt and Wickham (1994)</xref> versus the attempt to introduce a more constitutive role for law within Foucauldian thought by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1354066110380966">Golder and Fitzpatrick (2009)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-1354066110380966">
<label>5.</label>
<p>Alexis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1354066110380966">de Tocqueville (1994</xref>: 268–269):</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>If you ask me where the American Aristocracy is found, I have no hesitation in answering that it is not among the rich, who have no common link uniting them. It is at the bar or the bench that the American aristocracy is found.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-1354066110380966">
<label>6.</label>
<p><italic>Marbury</italic> v. <italic>Madison</italic>, 5 US (1 Cranch) 137, 163 (1803). However, this American dictum does not originate from the Supreme Court, but rather was taken from two acknowledged sources: (1) the Massachusetts Constitution of 1780; and (2) the writings of Harrington in <italic>Oceana and Other Works</italic> (1747), 37: ‘An empire of laws and not of men.’</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-1354066110380966">
<label>7</label>
<p>As an artefact of ‘productive power’ used to fix the meaning of the ‘rule of law’: see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1354066110380966">Michael Barnett and Raymond Duvall (2005</xref>: 55–57).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-1354066110380966">
<label>8.</label>
<p>I understand ‘experience’ to include the actual lived and virtual, since the cultural transmission of the American common law has been extended for decades through the global distribution of American novels, movies and television series propagating images of the American court. We should not underestimate the socio-cultural significance of popular works such as <italic>To Kill a Mockingbird, Perry Mason, Law and Order, A Few Good Men</italic>, and <italic>Erin Brockovich</italic> to name a few. For discussion of the significance of American popular culture on public perceptions of legal administration, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1354066110380966">Asimow (2007)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1354066110380966">Goodman (2006)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-1354066110380966">
<label>9.</label>
<p>See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1354066110380966">Hart (1994)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-1354066110380966">
<label>10.</label>
<p>For a provocative discussion on the making and nature of the English common law, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1354066110380966">Cormack (2007)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-1354066110380966">
<label>11.</label>
<p>See Elliot J. (ed.) (1907) <italic>Debates on the Adoption of the Federal Constitution at the Convention held in Philadelphia</italic>, pp. 158, 159, as cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1354066110380966">Johnson (1993</xref>: 51).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-1354066110380966">
<label>12.</label>
<p>A considerable literature deals with the influence of civil law in the making of the ‘American’ common law, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1354066110380966">David and Brierley (1985)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr82-1354066110380966">Stein (1966</xref>: 403), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1354066110380966">Hoeflich (1992</xref>: 1723) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1354066110380966">Helmholz (1992</xref>: 1649).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn13-1354066110380966">
<label>13.</label>
<p>‘In God we trust’ is the official motto of the United States. The motto is inscribed on coinage issued by the United States. See: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/In_God_We_Trust">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/In_God_We_Trust</ext-link></p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn14-1354066110380966">
<label>14.</label>
<p>For valuable discussion on the issue of a supranational constitution, see Alec <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr83-1354066110380966">Stone (1994)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn15-1354066110380966">
<label>15.</label>
<p>For instance, the British government justified its participation in the 2003 invasion of Iraq as lawful, with reference to two previous UN Security Council Resolutions, UNSCR 678 and 687 (See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1354066110380966">David Armstrong and Theo Farrell, 2005</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn16-1354066110380966">
<label>16.</label>
<p>Regarding imagery attached to the role of ‘the judge’ see Martti <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1354066110380966">Koskenniemi (1989</xref>: 492–493):</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Traditionally, this has been a role of the impartial technician – the ‘judge’ – whose identity lies in his objectivity. The judge stays aside from social conflict and comes in only at determined points to perform the task of ascertaining law’s content in a neutral way.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn17-1354066110380966">
<label>17.</label>
<p>The symbolic weight of the following statement by Beigbeder is impressive as Beigbeder began his career as legal secretary to the French judge at the Nuremberg trials in 1946.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn18-1354066110380966">
<label>18.</label>
<p>This echoes the observations of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-1354066110380966">Sending and Neumann (2006)</xref> with regard to the global governance literature in general.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn19-1354066110380966">
<label>19.</label>
<p>See Yves Beigbeder, ‘The International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia’ (in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1354066110380966">Beigbeder, 2002</xref>: 93). This concern was also expressed by Brasil’s representative to the Security Council at the meeting which adopted Security Council Resolution 827 and brought the ICTY into formal existence:</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>The option of establishing the Tribunal exclusively through a resolution of the Security Council, which we did not favour, leaves unresolved a number of serious legal issues relating to the powers and competences attributed to the Council by the United Nations Charter. That fact will not and should not limit the effectiveness of the work of the International Tribunal. It does limit, however, in our understanding, the conclusions that could be drawn from the adoption of this resolution as regards the legal and political framework for the work of the Security Council. (S/PV.3217, Provisional Verbatim Record of the 3217th meeting, 25 May 1993, as cited by former International Court of Justice President, Mohammed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1354066110380966">Bedjaoui [1994</xref>: 49])</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn20-1354066110380966">
<label>20.</label>
<p>Michael P. Scharf, ‘Indicted for War Crimes, then what?’ <italic>Washington Post</italic>, 3 October 1999. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.publicinternationallaw.org/publications/editorials/Then%20What.htm">www.publicinternationallaw.org/publications/editorials/Then%20What.htm</ext-link> (accessed 18 March 2008); <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-1354066110380966">Scharf (1997)</xref>. During the Prosecutorial tenure of Richard Goldstone, UN Secretary-General Boutros Boutros-Ghali admonished Goldstone for his close workings with the US administration, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1354066110380966">Goldstone (2000</xref>: 78–82).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn21-1354066110380966">
<label>21.</label>
<p>By mid-April 1999, NATO bombing raids against Serbian civilians had drawn particular attention and scrutiny, notably from <italic>Amnesty International</italic> and <italic>Human Rights Watch</italic>. See <italic>Amnesty International</italic>, ‘Collateral Damage or Unlawful Killings?’&lt;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.amnesty.org/en/library/asset/EUR70/018/2000/en/dom-EUR700182000en.html">http://www.amnesty.org/en/library/asset/EUR70/018/2000/en/dom-EUR700182000en.html</ext-link>&gt; (February 19, 2009); <italic>Human Rights Watch</italic>, ‘Civilians Deaths in the NATO Air Campaign,’ &lt;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hrw.org/legacy/reports/2000/nato">http://www.hrw.org/legacy/reports/2000/nato</ext-link>&gt; (19 February 2009). In an unprecedented move, Louise Arbour created an internal committee of the ICTY Prosecutor’s office to review war crimes allegations made against NATO. Surrounded by controversy and tension, the final report of the committee made a negative recommendation. For a critical discussion of the legal and political intrigue related to the ICTY’s decision not to prosecute NATO, see Yves Beigbeder, ‘NATO’s “war crimes” in Kosovo’, in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1354066110380966">Beigbeder (2002</xref>: 87–96).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn22-1354066110380966">
<label>22.</label>
<p>NATO, ‘Press Conference: Given by NATO spokesman, Jamie Shea and SHAPE Spokesman, Major General Walter Jertz’, <italic>NATO Daily Briefing</italic>, 16 May 1999. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nato.int/Kosovo/press/p990516b.htm">www.nato.int/Kosovo/press/p990516b.htm</ext-link> (accessed 15 March 2008).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn23-1354066110380966">
<label>23.</label>
<p>Something which Nicholas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-1354066110380966">Onuf (1989)</xref> noted with respect to the notion of rule generally.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keohane</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moravscik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The concept of legalization</article-title>. <source>International Organization</source> <volume>54</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>419</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Imagined Communities: Reflections on the Origin and Spread of Nationalism</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Verso</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Aristotle</collab> (<year>1972</year>) <source>Politics</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <article-title>‘Force and Legitimacy in World Politics: Introduction’</article-title>, <source>Review of International Studies</source> <volume>31</volume>(<year>2005</year>):<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Asimow</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Popular culture and the adversarial system</article-title>. <source>Loyola of Los Angeles Law Review</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>653</fpage>–<lpage>682</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duvall</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Power in international politics</article-title>. <source>International Organization</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bass</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>Stay the Hand of Vengeance: The Politics of War Crimes Tribunals</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bedjaoui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <source>The New World Order and the Security Council: Testing the Legality of its Acts</source>. <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Martinus Nijhoff Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beigbeder</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Judging Criminal Leaders: The Slow Erosion of Impunity</source>. <publisher-loc>The Hague</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Kluwer Law International</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burchell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Preface</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Burchell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Foucault Effect: Studies in Governmentality</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvester Wheatsheaf</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1939</year>) <source>The Twenty Years’ Crisis, 1919–1939: An Introduction to the Study of International Relations</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Crime and politics: Spot the difference</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Sociology</source> <volume>47</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Conso</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Epilogue: Looking to the future</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>The International Criminal Court; The Making of the Rome Statute: Issues, Negotiations, Results</source>. <publisher-loc>The Hague</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Kluwer Law International</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cormack</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>A Power to Do Justice: Jurisdiction, English Literature, and the Rise of Common Law, 1509–1625</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>David</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brierley</surname><given-names>JEC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Law of the United States of America. In:</article-title> <source>Major Legal Systems in the World Today</source> (<edition>3rd edn</edition>). <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stevens and Sons Ltd</publisher-name>, <fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>452</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>Governmentality: Power and Rule in Modern Society</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>de Tocqueville</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <source>Democracy in America</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Fontana Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dworkin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <source>Law’s Empire</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Belknap Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ewald</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Norms, discipline, and the law</article-title>. <source>Representations</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>138</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Falk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Legality and legitimacy: The quest for principled flexibility and restraint</article-title>. <source>Review of International Studies</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Finnemore</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sikkink</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>International norm dynamics and political change</article-title>. <source>International Organization</source> <volume>52</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>887</fpage>–<lpage>917</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Speaking law to power: The war against terrorism and human rights</article-title>. <source>European Journal of International Law</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>241</fpage>–<lpage>264</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Flathman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Liberalism and the suspect enterprise of political institutionalization: The case of the rule of law</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>The Rule of Law</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New York University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Foucault</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1971</year>) <source>The Order of Things: An Archaeology of the Human Sciences</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pantheon</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Foucault</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>) <source>Power/Knowledge: Selected Interviews and Other Writings 1972–1977</source>, (ed.) <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pantheon Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Foucault</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>The juridical apparatus</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Legitimacy and the State</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New York University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Foucault</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <source>Discipline and Punish: The Birth of the Prison</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Vintage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Foucault</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000a</year>) <article-title>Governmentality</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Faubion</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Power: Essential Works of Foucault, 1954–1984</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The New Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Foucault</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000b</year>) <article-title>The subject and power</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Faubion</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Power: Essential Works of Foucault 1954–1984</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The New Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>326</fpage>–<lpage>448</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Aristotle on constitutionalism and the rule of law</article-title>. <source>Theoretical Inquiries in Law</source> <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>38</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Glenn</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A common law tradition: The ethic of adjudication</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Glenn</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Legal Traditions in the World</source> (<edition>3rd edn</edition>). <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goldstone</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>For Humanity: Reflections of a War Crimes Investigator</source>. <publisher-loc>New Haven, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Governmental rationality: An introduction</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Burchell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Foucault Effect: Studies in Governmentality</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvester Wheatsheaf</publisher-name>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Golder</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Foucault’s Law</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Approaches to law and popular culture</article-title>. <source>Law and Social Inquiry</source> <volume>31</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>757</fpage>–<lpage>784</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haltern</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Pathos and patina: The failure and promise of constitutionalism in the European imagination</article-title>. <source>European Law Journal</source> <volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>HLA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Positive law and positive science</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>HLA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Concept of Law</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Clarendon Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hazan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Justice in a Time of War: The True Story Behind the International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia</source>. <publisher-loc>College Station, TX</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Texas A&amp;M University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Helmholz</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Use of the civil law in post-revolutionary American jurisprudence</article-title>. <source>Tulane Law Review</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>1649</fpage>–<lpage>1684</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heug</surname><given-names>Y-K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McDonagh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The other war on terror revealed: Global governmentality and the Financial Action Task Force’s campaign against terrorist financing</article-title>. <source>Review of International Studies</source> <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>553</fpage>–<lpage>573</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hoeflich</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Roman law in American legal culture</article-title>. <source>Tulane Law Review</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>1723</fpage>–<lpage>1743</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wickham</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <source>Foucault and Law: Towards a Sociology of Law as Governance</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pluto Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ikenberry</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Slaughter</surname><given-names>A-M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Forging a World of Liberty under Law: US National Security in the 21st Century</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Woodrow Wilson School of Public and International Affairs, Princeton University</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jochnik</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>The legitimation of violence: A critical history of the laws of war</article-title>. <source>Harvard International Law Journal</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Historical and constitutional perspectives on cross-vesting of court jurisdiction</article-title>. <source>Melbourne University Law Review</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>51</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>The Reign of Law: Marbury v. Madison and the Constitution of America</source>. <publisher-loc>New Haven, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Keck</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sikkink</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Activists beyond Borders: Advocacy Networks in International Politics</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kelsall</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Politics, anti-politics, international justice: Language and power in the Special Court for Sierra Leone</article-title>. <source>Review of International Studies</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>587</fpage>–<lpage>602</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>The Dark Sides of Virtue: Reassessing International Humanitarianism</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>The International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia: An Exercise in Law, Politics and Diplomacy</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kinsella</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Discourses of difference: Civilians, combatants, and compliance with the laws of war</article-title>. <source>Review of International Studies</source> <volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>185</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kinsella</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Gendering Grotius: Sex and sex difference in the laws of war</article-title>. <source>Political Theory</source> <volume>34</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>161</fpage>–<lpage>191</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Koskenniemi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <source>From Apology to Utopia: The Structure of International Legal Argument</source>. <publisher-loc>Helsinki</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Finnish Lawyers’ Publishing Company</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Koskenniemi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>The police in the temple; order, justice and the UN: A dialectical view</article-title>. <source>European Journal of International Law</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>348</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Koskenniemi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>International law and hegemony: A reconfiguration</article-title>. <source>Cambridge Review of International Affairs</source> <volume>17</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>218</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Koskenniemi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The ideology of international adjudication</article-title>. <source>Working Paper of the Eric Castren Institute of International Law and Human Rights</source>, <month>September</month> <year>2007</year>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.helsinki.fe/eci/Publications/MKHague%201907-puheversio07a.pdf">http://www.helsinki.fe/eci/Publications/MKHague%201907-puheversio07a.pdf</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kratochwil</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Has the rule of law become a rule of lawyers?</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Palombell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Relocating the Rule of Law</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hart</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mandel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>How America Gets away with Murder: Illegal Wars, Collateral Damage and Crimes against Humanity</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pluto Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McDougal</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L-C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>) <source>Human Rights and World Public Order</source>. <publisher-loc>New Haven, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mégret</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>War? Legal semantics and the move to violence</article-title>. <source>European Journal of International Law</source> <volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>361</fpage>–<lpage>399</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Merlingen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Governmentality: Towards a Foucauldian framework for the study of IGOs</article-title>. <source>Cooperation and Conflict</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>361</fpage>–<lpage>384</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moghalu</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Global Justice: The Politics of War Crimes Trials</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Praeger Security International</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scharf</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <source>An Insider’s Guide to the International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia</source>, <volume>vol. 2</volume>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transnational Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Off</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>The Lion, the Fox and the Eagle: A Story of Generals and Justice in Rwanda and Yugoslavia</source>. <publisher-loc>Toronto</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Random House Canada</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Onuf</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <source>World of our Making: Rules and Rule in Social Theory and International Relations</source>. <publisher-loc>Columbia, SC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of South Carolina Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Onuf</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>The constitution of international society</article-title>. <source>European Journal of International Law</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Paine</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Common sense (1776)</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Kuklick</surname><given-names>Bruce</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Thomas Paine: Political Writings</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Risse</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ropp</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sikkink</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>1999</year>) <source>The Power of Human Rights: International Norms and Domestic Change</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Crimes against Humanity: The Struggle for Global Justice</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Penguin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sadat</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>The International Criminal Court and the Transformation of International Law: Justice for the New Millennium</source>. <publisher-loc>Ardsley, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transnational Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scharf</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Balkan Justice: The Story behind the First International War Crimes Trial Since Nuremberg</source>. <publisher-loc>Durham, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Carolina Academic Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ambler</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Does legality <italic>really</italic> matter? Accounting for the decline in US foreign policy legitimacy following the 2003 invasion of Iraq</article-title>. <source>European Journal of International Relations</source> <volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sending</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Governance to governmentality: Analyzing NGOs, states and power</article-title>. <source>International Studies Quarterly</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>652</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Simma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paulus</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The international community: Facing the challenge of globalization</article-title>. <source>European Journal of International Law</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>266</fpage>–<lpage>277</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>States and the freedom of citizens</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strath</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>States and Citizens</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>11</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Slaughter</surname><given-names>A-M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>International law in a world of liberal states</article-title>. <source>European Journal of International Law</source> <volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>503</fpage>–<lpage>538</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr77-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Slaughter</surname><given-names>A-M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A global community of courts</article-title>. <source>Harvard International Law Journal</source> <volume>44</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr78-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Slaughter</surname><given-names>A-M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>A New World Order</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr79-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Slaughter</surname><given-names>A-M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>The Idea that is America: Keeping Faith with Our Values in a Dangerous World</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr80-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002a</year>) <article-title>Moral hazard and humanitarian law: The International Criminal Court and the limits of legalism</article-title>. <source>International Politics</source> <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr81-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002b</year>) <article-title>The new law of war: Legitimizing hi-tech and infrastructural violence</article-title>. <source>International Studies Quarterly</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>–<lpage>374</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr82-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1966</year>) <article-title>The attraction of the civil law in post-revolutionary America</article-title>. <source>Virginia Law Review</source> <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>403</fpage>–<lpage>434</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr83-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>What is a supranational constitution? An essay in international relations theory</article-title>. <source>Review of Politics</source> <volume>56</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>441</fpage>–<lpage>474</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr84-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Supiot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Law’s dominion: Dura lex, sed lex</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Supiot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Homo Juridicus: On the Anthropological Functions of the Law</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Verso</publisher-name>, <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr85-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Trimble</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>International law, world order, and critical legal studies</article-title>. <source>Stanford Law Review</source> <volume>42</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>811</fpage>–<lpage>845</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr86-1354066110380966">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Undoing the global constitution: US Security Council action on the International Criminal Court</article-title>. <source>International Affairs</source> <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>693</fpage>–<lpage>712</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>