<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AAS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spaas</journal-id>
<journal-title>Administration &amp; Society</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0095-3997</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3039</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0095399711433695</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0095399711433695</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Building a Network Administrative Organization’s Social Base</article-title>
<subtitle>Lessons From the National Quality Forum</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Hoflund</surname><given-names>A. Bryce</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0095399711433695">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0095399711433695"><label>1</label>University of Nebraska at Omaha, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0095399711433695">A. Bryce Hoflund, School of Public Administration, University of Nebraska at Omaha, 6001 Dodge Street, CPACS 113-D, Omaha, NE 68182, USA Email: <email>ahoflund@unomaha.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>44</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<fpage>908</fpage>
<lpage>935</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 SAGE Publications</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Networks are an increasingly common aspect of administrative life. One organization in health care, the National Quality Forum (NQF), is attempting to address issues of health care quality in a new way by bringing together organizations from the public and private sectors to discuss and debate measures of quality and, ultimately, to effect change. Little, however, is known about a network leader’s tasks during the creation of an organization like the NQF. The purpose of this article is to discuss and elaborate on one critical task, building a social base, that the NQF’s president and CEO engaged in during the NQF’s formative stages.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>National Quality Forum</kwd>
<kwd>network organization</kwd>
<kwd>collaboration</kwd>
<kwd>network leadership</kwd>
<kwd>health care quality</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>It is the task of leadership, in embodying purpose,</p>
<p>to fit the aims of the organization to the spontaneous interests</p>
<p>of the groups within it, and conversely to bind parochial group egotism</p>
<p>to larger loyalties and aspirations.</p>
<attrib><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0095399711433695">Selznick (1984)</xref></attrib>
</disp-quote></p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>When organizations are created, the organizational entrepreneur works hard</p>
<p>to discover what incentive, or combination of incentives, will attract members.</p>
<attrib><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0095399711433695">Wilson (1995)</xref></attrib>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>It is common to hear stories of medical mishaps: stories about babies who were switched at birth, the doctor who operated on the wrong body part, or the patient who received the wrong dosage of medication or the wrong medication. The numbers and types of medical errors are staggering. In <italic>To Err is Human</italic>, the Institute of Medicine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0095399711433695">IOM; 1999</xref>) estimates that between 44,000 and 98,000 individuals die from medical errors each year, making medical errors the eighth leading cause of death in the United States. According to the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0095399711433695">IOM (1999)</xref>, “more people die in a given year as a result of medical errors than from motor vehicle accidents (43,458), breast cancer (42,297) or AIDS (16,516)”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0095399711433695">1</xref></sup> (p. 1). In addition, medical errors generate enormous financial costs with estimates ranging from between US$17 billion and US$29 billion annually. The health care system also pays for medical errors in terms of opportunity costs (e.g., funds that could be used for other purposes instead are used for the tests or drugs needed to counteract the adverse effects arising from medical errors; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0095399711433695">IOM, 1999</xref>).</p>
<p>Other high-risk industries including the aviation and nuclear power industries have implemented error-reporting systems to gather data about the occurrence of errors to increase safety (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0095399711433695">Perrow, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0095399711433695">Reason, 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0095399711433695">1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0095399711433695">Rees, 1994</xref>). The success of error-reporting systems in these industries demonstrates that the health care industry might benefit from such a system. For example, the chances of experiencing a medical error are much greater than being involved in an airline accident because the airline industry has spent much more time and money during the last 25 years to improve safety (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0095399711433695">IOM, 1999</xref>). The increased safety is due in part to the establishment of the Aviation Safety Reporting System (ASRS), which is an anonymous, voluntary, and self-reporting system run by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration for the Federal Aviation Administration. The ASRS monitors irregular incidents that may lead to accidents and shares that information with others to mitigate the occurrence of similar events.</p>
<p>Efforts to establish a medical error-reporting system, however, have been frustrated for many reasons including a lack of legal protection for those reporting incidents; disagreement about what constitutes an error and, consequently, which errors to report; disagreement about whether an error-reporting system should be mandatory or voluntary; and disagreement about who should collect, process, and disseminate information about incidents. For example, underreporting plagues the Joint Commission’s Sentinel Events program because there are no provisions to protect the confidentiality of individuals reporting events. More importantly, many of the existing error-reporting systems are narrow in scope, only collecting data on medical errors from specific types of health care institutions (e.g., hospitals) or on a specific aspect of health care (e.g., medication errors). For example, two programs administered by U.S. Pharmacopeia, the Medication Errors Reporting program and the MedMARx program, collect information from individuals and hospitals about medication errors. Although these programs collect useful information, the lack of a coordinated effort to disseminate and learn from the information gathered hinders the effectiveness of these systems.</p>
<p>The health care industry, plagued by medical errors and other quality problems, faces a “wicked” problem, one that is unwieldy in its scope and complicated by the existence of competing perspectives about how to address the issue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0095399711433695">Rittel &amp; Webber, 1973</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0095399711433695">Luke (1997)</xref> notes that in an interconnected environment “problems cross organizational and jurisdictional boundaries” and growing numbers of stakeholders have legitimate interests and rights to insert themselves in problem solving” (p. 31).</p>
<p>In response to these types of problems, we are witnessing the proliferation of networks. Many claim networks can reduce fragmentation by allowing public, private, and nonprofit organizations to share their diverse resources, thus facilitating the development of innovative solutions to policy problems by encouraging broad stakeholder groups to participate in decision making (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0095399711433695">Alter &amp; Hage, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0095399711433695">Jones, Hesterly, &amp; Borgatti, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0095399711433695">Powell, 1990</xref>).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0095399711433695">Provan and Milward (2001)</xref> assert that in more formal networks “network growth and maintenance is often led, coordinated, and governed by a central local administrative entity” (p. 418), which they refer to as a network administrative organization (NAO). In a 2007 article, Provan and Kenis further conceptualize the NAO model and compare it with two other types of network forms, participant-governed and lead organization-governed networks. They note that the basic idea of a NAO “is that a separate administrative entity is set up specifically to govern the network and its activities” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0095399711433695">Provan &amp; Kenis, 2007</xref>, p. 236). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0095399711433695">Provan and Kenis (2007)</xref> further explain,
<disp-quote>
<p>Unlike the lead organization model, the NAO is not another member organization providing its own services. Instead, the network is externally governed, with the NAO established either through mandate or by the members themselves for the exclusive purpose of network governance. The NAO may be a government entity or a nonprofit, which is often the case even when the network members are for-profit firms. (p. 236)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0095399711433695">Provan and Kenis (2007)</xref> identify three key aspects of a NAO. First, the network is externally governed by the NAO that has been established for the key purpose of “coordinating and sustaining the network” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0095399711433695">Provan &amp; Kenis, 2007</xref>, p. 236). Second, the NAO may take one of many forms including a nonprofit or for-profit organization or a government entity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0095399711433695">Provan &amp; Kenis, 2007</xref>). Finally, the NAO may be run by a single individual or as a formal organization<disp-quote>
<p>consisting of an executive director, staff, and board operating out of a physically distinct office. This latter form may be used as a mechanism for enhancing network legitimacy, dealing with unique and complex network-level problems and issues, and reducing the complexity of shared governance. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0095399711433695">Provan &amp; Kenis, 2007</xref>, p. 236)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The National Quality Forum (NQF) is a prime example of a NAO. Established as a 501(c)(3) organization in May 1999, the NQF’s founding mission was to improve American health care through endorsement of consensus-based national standards for measurement and public reporting of health care performance data that provide meaningful information about whether care is safe, timely, beneficial, patient-centered, equitable, and efficient. The health care industry created the NQF as a bold regulatory experiment designed to address quality problems in health care by coordinating the activities of various organizations involved in quality-improvement activities. It is centralized in that it can be considered the hub of the network; and surrounding it are the spokes, its approximately 400-member organizations comprised of representatives from the public and private sectors including health care purchasers, providers, consumers, and research and quality-improvement organizations. Thus, the NQF represents a major administrative experiment designed to overcome the issues that have frustrated other efforts to address medical errors and improve health care quality.</p>
<p>The question that drove this research asked what some of the critical tasks a network leader needed to engage in to build a NAO’s social base. Through a case study of the NQF, this research adds to and expands on the existing literature by elaborating on one critical task, building a NAO’s social base, which Dr. Kenneth W. Kizer, the NQF’s founding president and CEO, engaged in to create the NQF. More specifically, the purpose of this article is twofold: to outline some of the inducements that Kizer offered potential members and staff to build the NQF’s social base and to describe some of the challenges he faced in maintaining that base. This article argues that a network leader will need to offer a series of inducements to potential members and staff as a means of persuading them to participate in the NAO since the challenges associated with the construction and maintenance of a NAO’s social base are greater than those of a traditional hierarchical organization because the foundations are shaky and managing diverse interests is difficult. Therefore, Kizer had to find creative ways to overcome these challenges and encourage others to participate in the NQF. The lessons learned from this case study may offer suggestions for practitioners and researchers about how to build a NAO’s social base.</p>
<p>This article is divided into five sections. The first section provides an overview of the relevant network management literature while the second describes the study’s methodology. The next section describes how Kizer built the NQF’s social base, paying particular attention to the inducements he offered to recruit members and staff. Some of the challenges associated with maintaining the NQF’s social base are then discussed, followed by a conclusion comprising avenues for future research.</p>
<sec id="section1-0095399711433695">
<title>Overview of the Network Management Literature</title>
<p>Network organizations raise pressing questions for students of public administration, and the literature that addresses the strategies for managing networks is quite broad. Scholars have researched and theorized about how to manage uncertainty in networks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0095399711433695">Koppenjan &amp; Klijn, 2004</xref>), goal conflicts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0095399711433695">Winkler, 2006</xref>), the strategies managers may use for managing networks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0095399711433695">Agranoff &amp; McGuire, 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0095399711433695">1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0095399711433695">2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0095399711433695">Bardach, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0095399711433695">Goldsmith &amp; Eggers, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0095399711433695">Klijn, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0095399711433695">Mandell, 1999</xref>), the role of the state and the strategies the state may use to manage networks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0095399711433695">Hudson, Lowe, Oscroft, &amp; Snell, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0095399711433695">Sorenson, 2006</xref>), and the dimensions or processes that need to be managed for collaboration to be successful (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0095399711433695">Thompson &amp; Perry, 2006</xref>). Other scholars including <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0095399711433695">Luke (1997)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0095399711433695">Gage and Mandell (1990)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0095399711433695">Feyerherm (1994)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0095399711433695">Gray (1989)</xref> have written about the importance of leadership and leadership styles in networks.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0095399711433695">Agranoff and McGuire (2001)</xref> author the seminal piece that focuses on network management. They explore the applicability of traditional management processes to networks, and they conclude that different strategies are used in the management of networks and that “network management is in search of an equivalent to the hierarchical authority paradigm of bureaucratic management” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0095399711433695">Agranoff &amp; McGuire, 2001</xref>, p. 11). They provide the most illuminating discussion of the literature on network management behaviors and identify the four behaviors most commonly used by network managers: activation, framing, mobilizing, and synthesizing.</p>
<p><italic>Activation</italic> is part of the initial process of forming a network and involves identifying network participants and stakeholders as well identifying the resources, such as money, information, and expertise, that participants can bring to the network (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0095399711433695">Agranoff &amp; McGuire, 2001</xref>). Deactivation is also important and occurs when a network manager reorganizes the network often by introducing new players, so it functions more effectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0095399711433695">Agranoff &amp; McGuire, 2001</xref>).</p>
<p><italic>Framing</italic> involves establishing network rules, procedures, norms, and values (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0095399711433695">Agranoff &amp; McGuire, 2001</xref>). Like activation, framing can occur during the initial stages of network formation. To increase network effectiveness or stimulate action, a manager can introduce new ideas into the network, which may change the perceptions of the network participants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0095399711433695">Termeer &amp; Koppenjan, 1997</xref>). By introducing new ideas or offering different ways of thinking about an issue, a manager then can create a new vision of the network that all participants can share.</p>
<p>For a network to be effective, a manager must <italic>mobilize</italic> individuals and organizations to participate in the network. Mobilization involves gaining acceptance from network participants about their roles and the scope of network activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0095399711433695">Agranoff &amp; McGuire, 2001</xref>). For the network to be effective, managers must encourage individuals and organizations participating in the network to agree on the overall goals of the network and on the responsibilities of each organization participating in the network. In addition, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0095399711433695">Agranoff and McGuire (2001)</xref> argue, “The ability to manage networks is related to the internal support and cooperation of the manager's primary organization” (p. 15).</p>
<p><italic>Synthesizing</italic> involves encouraging cooperation and minimizing conflict between network participants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0095399711433695">Agranoff &amp; McGuire, 2001</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0095399711433695">Agranoff and McGuire (2001)</xref> state, “Relationships and interactions that result in achieving the network purpose—synthesis—are the aim of the network manager” (p. 15). The role of the manager in this process is to ensure that the various perspectives of network participants are represented while minimizing dissension. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0095399711433695">Klijn and Teisman (1997)</xref> maintain that the game metaphor best describes the activities and interactions of networks and argue that networks are like games in that managers can choose from different strategies to influence the rules of the game and achieve the desired outcomes.</p>
<p>The existing research does not focus on delineating and describing the leadership tasks associated with creating a NAO. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0095399711433695">Agranoff and McGuire (2001)</xref> argue that more empirical studies are needed to determine the actual management processes used by network managers. This study seeks to fill this gap by elaborating on the concepts discussed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0095399711433695">Agranoff and McGuire (2001)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0095399711433695">McGuire (2002)</xref> and, in particular, by identifying and describing one of the critical tasks a leader might engage in to create a NAO. In the next section, I discuss how I conducted this research.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0095399711433695" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<p>Because I was interested in exploring the phenomenon of network leadership and because there is little existing empirical research in this area, I chose to follow a naturalistic or qualitative approach, or more specifically the grounded theory method, to study the NQF (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0095399711433695">Dey, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0095399711433695">Eisenhardt, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0095399711433695">Glaser, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0095399711433695">Glaser &amp; Strauss, 1967</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0095399711433695">Strauss &amp; Corbin, 1998</xref>). Recently, scholars such as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0095399711433695">McGuire and Agranoff (2007)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0095399711433695">Agranoff (2004)</xref> explore the relevance of grounded theory as an approach to studying networks, noting that using grounded theory will help answer some of the “big questions” about network management by allowing researchers to delve more deeply into the “black box” of networks and to examine them from the inside out.</p>
<p>Leadership, furthermore, is an unexplored phenomenon, and many scholars contend leadership theory would be enhanced by the generation of theories that are “grounded” in what leaders are actually doing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0095399711433695">Parry, 1998</xref>). The applicability of grounded theory to leadership has been demonstrated in a number of studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0095399711433695">Hunt, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0095399711433695">Hunt &amp; Ropo, 1995</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0095399711433695">Hunt and Ropo (1995)</xref> argue that grounded theory can be effective as a means of studying social processes such as leadership because “grounded theory emphasizes dynamism, whereas mainstream analysis emphasizes static structure” (p. 381). Therefore, grounded theory allows one to understand the dynamic of “change” as it relates to leadership, as opposed to traditional approaches that study leadership at one point in time. As a result of the focus on quantitative methods, there have been increased calls issued for more qualitative work on leadership (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0095399711433695">Bryman, Stephens, &amp; Campo, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0095399711433695">Parry, 1998</xref>). More specifically, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0095399711433695">Parry (1998)</xref> advocates using grounded theory as an approach to studying leadership and maintains that grounded theory will allow researchers to investigate and understand the emergence and operation of leadership at different levels and in different contexts.</p>
<sec id="section3-0095399711433695">
<title>Case Selection</title>
<p>I chose the NQF as the focus for this study because it represents the type of network organization, an NAO, that many claim is increasingly seen in public administration. In <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0095399711433695">Stake’s (1998)</xref> terms, this is an instrumental case study, which is of interest to those who seek to understand an issue or refine a theory. It provided an excellent vehicle through which to explore and gain some understanding about network management strategies and, more specifically, network leadership.</p>
<p>Within the NQF, the Serious Reportable Events, or Never Events, project was examined for several reasons. It was the first project to go through the NQF’s consensus process. The goal of the project was to establish agreement on a set of serious preventable adverse events that might form the basis for a national state-based event reporting system that could lead to substantial improvements in patient care. The final report, <italic>Serious Reportable Events in Patient Safety: A National Quality Forum Consensus Report</italic>, identifies 27 medical errors that should never occur in health care today. Medical errors are a pressing public policy issue, and the project appears to have made some headway on developing some consensus around medical errors where others have not. In addition, the project was the NQF’s first and is appropriate for exploring network leadership during the formative stages of network development. I studied the NQF during its formative years from its inception in 1999 through 2005.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0095399711433695">
<title>Data Collection</title>
<p>I collected data about the NQF and the Never Events project by conducting in-depth, open-ended interviews, by examining written documents, and by observing two NQF annual meetings.</p>
<sec id="section5-0095399711433695">
<title>Interviews</title>
<p>Thirty-nine interviews informed this research. Of these, I conducted semi-structured interviews with 21 individuals who were active in the NQF during its formative years. Another colleague also was investigating aspects of the NQF as a network, and because our questioning was along the same lines, she and I shared the interviews that we had conducted and transcribed. She shared 18 interviews with me. I analyzed and coded these as I did my own interviews. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0095399711433695">Strauss and Corbin (1998)</xref> refer to this type of sharing and coding data sets as “secondary analysis” and state a “researcher building theory can code these materials as well, employing theoretical sampling in conjunction with the usual coding procedures” (p. 213).</p>
<p>The interviewees were representative of the diverse organizations that belong to the NQF and consisted of individuals who were involved at all levels of the NQF including NQF staff members and those who served on the Board of Directors, the Never Events Steering Committee, and each of the four Member Councils (Consumers, Purchasers, Providers, and Research and Quality Improvement Organizations).</p>
<p>The interviewees initially were contacted by phone or email about participating in the study. Whether by phone or email, I introduced myself, provided them with information about the project, and asked if they would be willing to participate in an interview. The interviews occurred either by phone or in person from 2002 to 2004. Each interview lasted approximately one hour and in many cases quite a bit longer. To ensure anonymity, I have not divulged the names of the individuals I interviewed or mentioned their names or positions in the text. I gathered additional contacts using snowball or chain sampling. In snowball sampling, interviewees are asked to provide the names of other individuals who know about the issue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0095399711433695">Caudle, 1994</xref>).</p>
<p>Different stages of theory development demand different interview techniques (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0095399711433695">Polit &amp; Beck, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0095399711433695">Wimpenny &amp; Gass, 2000</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0095399711433695">Glaser and Strauss (1967)</xref> state that during the initial period of data collection and analysis, interviews may take the form of unstructured conversations; and as the theory begins to emerge from the data, the interviews will become more focused and structured. During the initial phases of my data collection, the interviews tended to be more conversational and broadly focused. I developed an initial interview guide that reflected this and covered topics such as the NQF’s history, the key stakeholders involved in the NQF’s creation, the NQF’s Consensus Development Process, and project management. As the theory began to emerge, I developed an interview guide in which the questions were more focused than they were initially and covered topics such as the NQF’s relationship with its member organizations, the NQF’s organizational structure, staff recruitment, leadership style, and the NQF’s challenges and accomplishments. The interviews themselves became more semistructured. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0095399711433695">Fielding (1994)</xref> notes that some of the strengths of semistructured interviews are that they allow the researcher to ask questions in the same way each time while allowing for flexibility in the sequence of questions and the depth of exploration.</p>
<p>Throughout the process, I taped and transcribed each of the interviews after asking the participant for consent. All of the interviewees consented to being taped. After I completed each interview, I transcribed it into an MS Word document, uploaded it into QSR N6, and coded it.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0095399711433695">
<title>Written documents</title>
<p>I also examined numerous articles that Kizer wrote and speeches he gave for information about his thoughts on the NQF’s origins, mission, unique qualities, underlying philosophical precepts, role in the health care system, and challenges during its formative years. Specifically, I examined 2 NQF newsletters, 13 Power Point Presentations, 11 articles, and 13 “President’s Corner” web updates presented or written between 2000 and 2003. I also gathered and analyzed other documents related to the NQF including working papers about the Never Events project, minutes from Board meetings, and briefing materials. The interviews were used in tandem with the documents to determine whether they supported one another (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0095399711433695">Caudle, 1994</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0095399711433695">
<title>Observation</title>
<p>I also attended and observed the proceedings of two NQF annual meetings. The first one I attended was the NQF’s fourth annual meeting held September 29 and 30, 2003, in Washington, DC, and the second, the NQF’s fifth annual meeting held October 6 and 7, 2005, in Washington, DC. I attended the two meetings for several reasons. First, they gave me an opportunity to observe firsthand how the NQF conducts business. Second, I was able to meet people and question them informally about the NQF at these meetings. Third, as the research progressed and leadership became the focal point of the study, the meetings gave me a chance to observe Kizer in action and determine whether what I was observing matched with what I was hearing from the interviewees. Finally, the annual meetings gave me a chance to learn about and keep up-to-date on the various issues affecting the NQF and its operations. For example, implementation of the NQF’s various measures was discussed only briefly during the first annual meeting but was the “hot” topic by the second meeting.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0095399711433695">
<title>Building the Social Base</title>
<p>“Beyond the definition of mission and role lies the task of building purpose into the social structure of the enterprise . . . of transforming a neutral body of men into a committed polity” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0095399711433695">Selznick, 1984</xref>, p. 90). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0095399711433695">Selznick (1984)</xref> refers to a critical leadership task, building an organization’s social base, which closely relates to what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0095399711433695">Agranoff and McGuire (2001)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0095399711433695">McGuire (2002)</xref> refer to as <italic>activating</italic> and <italic>mobilizing</italic>. An organization’s social base can be thought of in terms of two related parts: individuals who are internal to the organization (e.g., staff) and individuals who are external to the organization (e.g., members). Although scholars recognize that building a strong social base is important for traditional, hierarchical organizations, few scholars have considered the activities and challenges a leader faces as he or she strives to build and maintain a NAO’s social base.</p>
<p>In building a NAO’s social base, a leader confronts the question of ends and means. A key question Kizer faced was how to design an organization that would address the challenges the health care industry faced in trying to improve quality. More specifically, he confronted three challenges related to building the NQF’s social base: (a) how he could acquire the expertise or distinctive competencies the organization needed to make headway in improving health care quality, (b) how he could acquire the financial resources necessary to develop and grow the organization without sacrificing its mission, and (c) how he could create a structure that was inclusive and would allow the NQF to overcome the fragmentation inherent in the health care industry. In an effort to overcome these and other challenges, Kizer relied on inducements as the means to recruit members and staff and to attract the necessary resources to the NQF.</p>
<p>The idea of “inducements” as a means to encourage others to participate in an organization was initially discussed by Barnard and elaborated on by Wilson in <italic>Political Organizations</italic> (1995). In <italic>The Functions of the Executive</italic>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0095399711433695">Chester Barnard (2001)</xref> discusses the idea of inducements or incentives as a means of holding an organization together: “From the viewpoint of the organization requiring or seeking contributions from individuals, the problem of effective incentives may be either one of finding positive incentives or of reducing or eliminating negative incentives or burdens” (p. 140). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0095399711433695">Barnard (2001)</xref> identifies two types of inducements: specific inducements and general inducements. Specific inducements are those that can be offered to individuals and include such material things as money and good working conditions and nonmaterial things such as prestige and power. General inducements are those that cannot be specifically offered to individuals and include the opportunity to engage in a cause larger than oneself and a feeling of compatibility with others involved in the organization.</p>
<p>Wilson built on Barnard’s original ideas about inducements and developed four categories of incentives: material incentives, purposive incentives, and specific and collective solidary incentives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0095399711433695">Wilson, 1995</xref>). Material incentives are tangible and include money, fringe benefits, and services that one would otherwise have to pay for. Purposive incentives, however, are intangible and generate a sense of satisfaction from being involved in a worthwhile cause. Specific and collective solidary incentives are also intangible rewards that can be provided to or withheld from either groups or individuals. Some examples of solidary incentives include honoring individuals for their association with the group and the sense of conviviality and exclusiveness shared by group members when they come together.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0095399711433695">Wilson (1995)</xref> notes that when an organization is in its developmental stages and access to material resources is limited, leaders will rely on solidary and purposive inducements to attract members. This study extends Barnard and Wilson’s analyses by applying their ideas about inducements to a network organization and discussing the types of inducements Kizer offered to member organizations and staff as a means of building the NQF’s social base.</p>
<sec id="section9-0095399711433695">
<title>Recruiting Members</title>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0095399711433695">Selznick (1984)</xref> argues,
<disp-quote>
<p>Among the critical decisions facing leadership, closely related to the definition of mission, is the selection of a clientele, market, target, allies, or other segment of the environment to which operations will be oriented. Personnel recruitment, public relations, and many other areas of decision will be affected by this key choice of an external “social base.” (p. 104)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>A social base can be defined as all of the resources (financial, technical, and organizational) that individuals and organizations external to the network bring to the organization. An NAO like the NQF depends on many different kinds of resources from its members including funding, expertise, experience, and legitimacy; different members bring different resources to the table. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0095399711433695">McGuire (2002)</xref> argues that determining which organizations and individuals have these and other types of resources and then strategically acquiring them are some of the main tasks of a network leader in building a NAO’s social base.</p>
<p>In recruiting members to the NQF, Kizer faced several challenges. One challenge was how to build a broad social base that would allow the NQF to acquire expertise from a wide range of sources and build on those to become a premier organization. Selznick refers to this as “distinctive competence,” which refers to the expertise an organization acquires over time that makes it stand out as the go-to organization among all others in a particular industry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0095399711433695">Selznick, 1984</xref>). An organization builds its distinctive competencies by bringing a variety of experts to the table and learning over time how to provide a service, how to develop a product, or how to implement a program. The different forms of knowledge, however, found in a network can create organizational and coordination challenges, a point that I elaborate on later.</p>
<p>Another challenge Kizer had to confront was how to secure funding for the NQF. One interviewee stated that Kizer
<disp-quote>
<p>hardly ever has a conversation without mentioning the funding issue. So it’s almost obsessive and he has just looked at every place he can for funding. He’s been pretty good about it. I mean, they have found project support but it has been absolutely relentless. I haven’t asked him but I bet he would say it’s 80 percent of his job right now.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Another interviewee states that Kizer has “really had to be very resourceful in order to find the funding and negotiate a project that could keep the funding going.”</p>
<p>Obtaining financial resources is often a challenge for networks organizations. Traditional bureaucratic organizations, for example, have a budgetary base each year to draw from that can be increased or decreased at the will of the President and/or Congress. Usually this budgetary base continues to grow, and frequently it is hard to get rid of an organization once it is created. This is not necessarily so with a network organization. Network organizations like the NQF depend on the word-of-mouth of their members to provide news of their good deeds and good work so they can get funding for projects that are important to network members. Network organizations are dependent on their members for funding and projects that will keep the network alive. In essence, building a social base is about building relationships and, therefore, increasing their chances of getting funding opportunities from those relationships.</p>
<p>Next, I discuss the four inducements Kizer offered to potential members to overcome these challenges and encourage them to join the NQF: a shared sense of purpose, providing access to elites, facilitating access to resources, and an opportunity to influence measure development through a seat at the table.</p>
<sec id="section10-0095399711433695">
<title>Inducement 1: A shared sense of purpose</title>
<p>The NQF’s public philosophy was crafted with one end in mind—to improve the quality of health care. The public philosophy creates a common purpose that ties the disparate groups together. Furthermore, “a sense of mission confers a feeling of special worth on the members, provides a basis for recruiting and socializing new members, and enables the administrators to economize on the use of other incentives” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0095399711433695">Wilson, 1991</xref>, p. 95). To put it in Barnard’s terms, the public philosophy serves as a general inducement that allows individuals to buy into a purpose larger than they are. In a sense, the public philosophy contributes to building a collaborative community in which each group is able to contribute the resources needed to accomplish the agreed-on ends. It allows an organization to develop the distinctive competencies it needs to engage in creative problem solving.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0095399711433695">McGuire (2002)</xref> states, “The presence of unclear program goals means that one of the first tasks the manager must attend to is facilitating goal consensus—indeed, some networks cannot (should not) proceed without some level of agreement on the ultimate objective” (p. 604). To create a shared sense of purpose, Kizer communicated the newly developed mission to a broad range of potential members and encouraged them to become members of the NQF. He disseminated the NQF’s newly developed public philosophy through journal articles and public speaking engagements. In 2000 alone, Kizer gave more than 100 speeches about the NQF to various health care stakeholders at conferences and workshops including those held by IOM, Virginians Improving Patient Care and Safety, the Colorado Patient Safety Coalition, the World Congress Leadership Summit on Health Care Quality and Pay-for-Performance Contracting, and the Hewlett-Packard Worldwide Health Symposium. Whether speaking or writing, Kizer consistently articulated the same message about the NQF to the various stakeholder groups—that the NQF valued diversity, participation, and cooperation and sought to institutionalize these values in its quality-improvement activities.</p>
<p>Kizer’s choice of the Never Events project as the NQF’s first project also created a shared sense of purpose among the disparate groups in health care interested in improving the quality of health care. Kizer thought that the choice of the Never Events project as the NQF’s project would signal that the NQF was serious about its goal of improving health care quality, and he recognized that the project’s significance would most likely attract broad participation from a number of groups.</p>
<p>The NQF’s mission enabled it to build a social base by communicating to potential members the various reasons for joining. How each member organization buys into the mission through translating and molding the mission to fit with its identity ultimately influences how that organization acts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0095399711433695">Heckscher &amp; Adler, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0095399711433695">Latour, 1988</xref>). Some organizations indicated that they joined the NQF because they identified with the NQF’s mission and quality-improvement goals for health care. According to one interviewee, “It really would have been illogical for us not to [join the NQF]. We share all the interest in promoting quality and patient safety that the Forum does.” Another interviewee pointed to the work that NQF is undertaking to reduce the fragmentation that has plagued the health care industry and noted, “If the Forum were to go away, we would just have total chaos out there.”</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0095399711433695">
<title>Inducement 2: Providing access to elites</title>
<p>One means Kizer used to attract organizations to the NQF was to focus on bringing high profile individuals in health care to serve on the NQF’s Board of Directors and as Steering Committee chairs. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0095399711433695">Agranoff and McGuire (2001)</xref> refer to this as <italic>activation</italic>. Activation involves identifying network participants and stakeholders as well identifying the resources that participants can bring to the network (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0095399711433695">Agranoff &amp; McGuire, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0095399711433695">McGuire, 2002</xref>). They argue, “Activation is a critical component of network management because resources like money, information, and expertise are the integrating mechanisms of networks” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0095399711433695">Agranoff &amp; McGuire, 2001</xref>, p. 13).</p>
<p>One can imagine a leader confronting this critical task and choosing between different paths or alternatives for whom to bring into the organization. After all, the decisions made during a network’s formative stages help shape the organization’s culture and influence its future direction. To do this effectively, Kizer according to one interviewee needed
<disp-quote>
<p>the vision to help identify people to serve on the committee and make sure that it was broadly representative of the constituencies of the Forum, but at the same time have sufficient expertise to be able to render a credible product.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>For example, Kizer purposefully recruited Lucien Leape, an internationally recognized leader of the patient-safety movement, to serve as chair of the Never Events Steering Committee. According to one interviewee, “The rest of the Committee were people who had various levels of technical expertise or represented important constituencies that needed to be at the table as we were debating it.”</p>
<p>In trying to “recruit the rock stars” of the health care industry, Kizer hoped that offering a specific inducement would contribute to members’ feelings of prestige and power through association with the NQF; the philosophy of “if you build it, they will come” would attract members and staff. Indeed, several interviewees mentioned that it was the quality of individuals involved in the NQF—many were nationally known leaders in health care—that motivated them to join the NQF initially. Another NQF member observes that having recognized leaders such as Gail Warden (then President and CEO of the Henry Ford Health System) serve on the Board and the fact that other well-recognized organizations such as the American Academy of Family Practice had joined the NQF already made a difference for those organizations that were thinking about joining.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0095399711433695">
<title>Inducement 3: Facilitating access to resources</title>
<p>The NQF membership consists of more than 400 members from a variety of sectors in the health care industry including purchasers, consumers, providers, and quality-improvement organizations. There are different kinds of resources that organizations can bring to the network including experience, expertise, information, and financial resources, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0095399711433695">McGuire (2002)</xref> argues, “The network manager needs to identify and include in the network the needed expertise and other resources to move a project forward” (p. 605).</p>
<p>One of the benefits a network like the NQF with such a large and diverse social base offers is a way to reduce the overall costs of developing performance measures and reporting systems if everyone shares the costs; that is, it reduces the transaction costs of each organization. To paraphrase one interviewee, one reason members joined the NQF is that they recognized that “it was understood that the quality issue was an important one . . . and getting more prominent.” Although they recognized the importance of quality improvement as an activity, they did not necessarily have their own resources to devote to it. However, some organizations were already pursuing work in quality improvement and saw the NQF’s work as relevant to what they were already doing in this area.</p>
<p>Another reason organizations decide to participate in a network is that it allows network members to engage in creative problem solving and participate in something larger. Being able to challenge routine and habit and to imagine new possibilities is key to pragmatist organizations, and networks are a pragmatic form of organizing. Networks allow participants to draw on a wealth of knowledge with which to experiment and to develop innovative solutions to unwieldy problems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0095399711433695">Werhane, 1999</xref>).</p>
<p>Each of the NQF’s member organizations brings a different perspective and varying tools to the quality debate. Several interviewees indicated that they found the diversity of experience and knowledge valuable in trying to address the quality problems that have plagued the health care industry. For example, the health care provider organizations that belong to the NQF such as the American Hospital Association (AHA), regional hospital associations, and individual hospitals bring, according to one NQF member, “a lot of intelligence about what is clinically significant and what is feasible to measure.” They also provide valuable input about the ease or difficulty with which the various quality measures under consideration can be implemented.</p>
<p>The research and quality-improvement organizations such as Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ), National Committee for Quality Assurance (NCQA), and the Joint Commission seek to improve the safety, quality, and effectiveness of medical care by researching and gathering data on various indicators of health care quality. They create and act as a repository for performance measures and are most likely to bring measures to the table for discussion and debate. They provide valuable input about their experiences with developing and testing measures and create the “evidence base” for health care outcomes, cost, and quality. They also accredit some of the health care providers and are in charge of oversight and monitoring of the services some of these providers deliver. So they are also on the front lines and need to be aware of how easy it might be to implement some of these measures and get reports on them.</p>
<p>Provider and research and quality-improvement organizations offer information and knowledge about the more scientific and technical aspects of performance measures to the NQF. Consumer and purchaser organizations bring a different perspective. According to one NQF member, consumer and purchaser organizations “put less emphasis on the scientific perfection of a particular measure” and, in general, bring their knowledge about the intersection of cost, quality, and consumer needs to the NQF.</p>
<p>Purchasers of health care including Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services (CMS) and General Motors (GM) emphasize the moral imperative of improving the quality of health care. Their commitment to improving health care quality arises from—according to one NQF participant—their “role in paying for the cost of poor quality not only [in terms of] mortality and morbidity but the cost of health care and what it’s doing to the liability of businesses.”</p>
<p>Consumer organizations such as AARP, the March of Dimes, and the American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO) bring an understanding of consumers’ needs and wants to debates about health care quality. For example, the March of Dimes brings expertise about child health care measures, whereas AARP brings expertise about what is important to the over-50 population. Consumer groups want to see quality improved and get involved in the NQF because consumers are demanding more for their money. They do not want to spend thousands of dollars on a surgery only to find that a sponge has been left inside someone or, worse, experience the death of a loved one because of a botched surgery. In essence, consumers are demanding that someone be held accountable for the quality or lack of it in the health care system today. Frugality and accountability seem to be the two keywords linked to consumers’ interest in the quality movement.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0095399711433695">
<title>Inducement 4: An opportunity to influence measure development through a seat at the table</title>
<p>A benefit of NQF membership is a “seat at the table” in national decision making. For example, providers want to get involved in the quality movement for several reasons. First, most providers care about the quality of care their patients receive and want to deliver good quality care. To provide good quality care, they must keep up with and implement cutting-edge medical knowledge. Providers are also the ones delivering health care so they offer a good perspective about whether certain quality measures are feasible. They are the street-level bureaucrats in terms of making decisions and exercising discretion about how to care for each patient. If they are going to be the ones implementing and being judged according to these measures, they do not want others making decisions for them; they want to maintain some sense of autonomy in this. So they want to have a hand in creating or examining the performance measures that they are going to have to implement. Providers want to make sure that their fees do not rise. In this sense, they are purely self-interested. Just like consumers who do not want to pay more for faulty health care, providers do not want to continue to pay more for malpractice insurance and raise their other fees, which might drive patients away. Providers are self-interested for another reason; as a means of ensuring industry self-regulation, the NQF allows the providers to maintain a certain amount of autonomy. Similarly, purchasers want to participate to help protect the interests of the organizations that buy health care. GM, for example, purchases a large amount of health care; and if quality continues to suffer, it will see its costs continue to skyrocket. If the costs continue to increase, they will have to cut back on the amount of health care they provide to their employees.</p>
<p>A network like the NQF relies on a strong social base to accomplish its goals. Because the organization was new, Kizer confronted significant challenges and questions from other organizations as to why they should join the NQF. To convince others to join the NQF, Kizer offered a number of inducements. By offering the incentives, he built a strong social base that consisted of a number of the different stakeholders in health care. Offering incentives to recruit members is one thing, but Kizer also had to ensure that he would be able to attract staff to the NQF.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0095399711433695">
<title>Recruiting Staff</title>
<p>Recruiting staff is just as important as recruiting members. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0095399711433695">Selznick (1984)</xref> states, “The creation of an institutional core is partly a matter of selective recruiting, and to this extent overlaps with the task of selecting a social base” (p. 105). That is, it is important to an organization that the staff reflects the dynamics of the external environment. As with recruiting members, Kizer had to face the dual tasks of activating and mobilizing individuals and encouraging them to bring their resources and expertise to the NQF as staff members.</p>
<p>In recruiting the NQF’s staff, Kizer had to consider the types of staff members that the organization needed to accomplish its mission. The NQF is a distinctive organization and requires a different set of skills for their employees than most other organizations. Kizer sought to recruit employees who embodied three characteristics. The staffers should have some clinical or research experience in the medical field. Kizer also sought staff who had expertise in a particular area, but would also be flexible enough once a project was completed to apply their expertise in other ways. Finally, staff members need to be politically astute and able to deal with the various stakeholders who are members of the NQF. According to one interviewee, “That’s what this place is – It’s about occasionally highly technical topics but it takes place in an extremely political, small ‘p’ political, environment where they’re negotiating things. You’re trying to mediate sometimes really contentious discussions.”</p>
<p>Although Kizer ideally sought to hire individuals that embodied these three characteristics, the reality was different; and he faced significant challenges in hiring staff. Funding served as the primary constraint. The NQF was a new and as yet unproven organization with limited financial resources. One interviewee painted a picture of the NQF’s stark offices during that start-up period: There was no furniture at all. Ken was working off of essentially a card table, and she [Robyn Nishimi] was doing the same, and another employee who had been hired at that point was working out of her house.” One interviewee noted that many times during the initial stages of hiring staff, the conversation never moved beyond salary. Staffing the NQF is particularly difficult because although it can offer salaries competitive with the federal government and other not-for-profit organizations, it cannot compete with consulting firms. The consequence was that the NQF often did not get its first choice of employees. A second challenge was to find individuals skilled in the science of performance measurement and consensus building. As one interviewee noted, “those are not skills that commonly come together.” Another challenge was to find some way to convince potential employees to leave their current jobs with pay and benefits—not to mention office furniture—and come to work at an organization that—to paraphrase one interviewee—offered no job description, no benefits during the start-up period, and no guarantee that the organization would exist for any long period of time. The same interviewee in referring to taking the job as the “ultimate job insecurity” conveyed the gravity of making that decision: “It was the first time I’ve ever asked in a job interview, ‘What are the chances you can actually cut me a paycheck 6 months from now?’” To overcome these and other challenges, Kizer offered potential staff a series of inducements.</p>
<sec id="section15-0095399711433695">
<title>Inducement 1: To become involved in a purpose larger than oneself</title>
<p>Just as finding its place in the larger society rewards an organization, participating in something larger than oneself also rewards individuals. One inducement, therefore, that Kizer used to recruit initial prospective NQF staff members was the vision that he crafted for the NQF. To put it in Barnard’s terms, many of the initial staff members felt that by working for the NQF, they had a chance to become involved in a purpose larger than themselves. The NQF’s mission communicated not only to potential members but also to potential staffers that it was serious about achieving quality improvement. One can also think about this as a type of <italic>mobilizing</italic> behavior that McGuire maintains is used to “develop commitment and support for network processes” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0095399711433695">McGuire, 2002</xref>, p. 603). One interviewee described her reaction to the NQF as “fascinating” because it was experimenting with something new to improve quality. Staff recognized that the other structures and attempts to improve health care quality were outmoded and outdated. However, the NQF according to one interviewee represented a completely different organizational structure, one that was “trying to achieve not just a diversity of input, but a balance among the diversity of inputs.” The NQF’s staff members, therefore, were intrigued and excited by the opportunity to be getting in on the ground floor of an organization that they sensed might be able to make a difference in health care quality.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0095399711433695">
<title>Inducement 2: To carve out a niche</title>
<p>Closely related to the idea of the gratification of serving a higher purpose is the notion that a job can offer individuals an intellectual and creative outlet. The NQF was a new organization, and as I mentioned earlier, there were no well-defined job descriptions for the positions. Because the NQF was sailing into uncharted territory and Kizer did not have the financial resources to offer to potential employees, he told applicants that they would have a chance to create their own jobs and emphasized that they would have the chance to work on something that had never been done before. And it worked. As one interviewee put it, “We all like inventing something.” While this served as an inducement and attracted many individuals to the organization, it also served as an important <italic>mobilizing</italic> tool because the initial employees had a hand in shaping the NQF’s long-term character and culture.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0095399711433695">
<title>Inducement 3: Kizer’s reputation as a change agent</title>
<p>Just as access to elites was an inducement Kizer offered to potential members, the chance to work with an elite like Kizer was an inducement for staff to work at the NQF. Kizer is known widely as a <italic>change agent</italic> in the health care industry and is thought of as a transformational leader. Transformational leadership is defined as a process that changes and transforms individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0095399711433695">Burns, 1978</xref>). It is concerned with how leaders inspire their followers to accomplish great things. Transformational leaders are known for moving and changing things “in a big way” by communicating to followers a special vision of the future and tapping into followers’ higher ideals and motives. They generate emotion, energy, and excitement and encourage followers to make significant personal sacrifices in the interest of the mission and to perform above and beyond the call of duty.</p>
<p>Kizer achieved this by communicating the NQF’s mission to potential staff and members. His passion and drive for improving health care quality is one reason that one staff member said, “Everyone works here because of him [Kizer].” When asked why staff members were drawn to the NQF, several noted that Kizer “walked the walk” and that he had a “track record of actually doing things and making change.” Furthermore, they also recognized that improving health care quality would be an achievable goal as long as he was involved.</p>
<p>The stages of organizational development are much like the stages associated with building and maintaining a house. A leader must first build an organization’s social structure much like one builds the foundation of a house. During the NQF’s formative years, Kizer was concerned with building the network’s social base. To do so, he offered a variety of inducements to potential NQF members and staff. Once a house is built, however, one must ensure that it remains livable. In the next section, I discuss how Kizer focused on creating a sustainable organization.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0095399711433695">
<title>Challenges of Maintaining the Social Base</title>
<p>It is challenging to sustain a level of high-quality participation on the part of member organizations; and this case study highlights some challenges of maintaining a membership that is vital, energized, and engaged. Power imbalances are one major impediment to participation. The NQF is supposed to level the playing field among the diverse interests in the quality debate; but differing levels of financial resources, however, have created imbalances among organizations that would like to participate in the quality debate. For example, the NQF is structured so that purchasers and consumers control 51% of the organization. Yet as one participant notes although many provider and research and quality organizations have the funds to join the NQF, keeping the balance of purchasers and consumers at 51% is a challenge because
<disp-quote>
<p>The consumers and business [i.e., purchasers] people keep their money a little closer to the vest and some of them, the consumer organizations in particular, don’t have a lot of money to spend . . . if you look at the people who show up to play from time to time, it’s not 51 percent consumers and purchasers. They just can’t get them to come.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>A consequence of this is a lack of creativity. One participant expressed concern that since not everyone can afford to participate in the NQF’s quality-improvement activities, creative proposals to address quality improvement might be stymied:
<disp-quote>
<p>They have the same players at the table all the time. I think that in order for health care to move where it needs to, it needs fresh ideas and not just the same old folks saying the same old thing.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The amount of time organizations must commit to the NQF is another impediment to participation. A major difference between a network organization and a bureaucratic organization is that employees in a bureaucratic organization are paid to work there, and leaders assume that this will ensure that they come to work everyday. The NQF’s members are busy individuals whose primary jobs are elsewhere. Thus, Kizer as a network leader must make a special effort to ensure a balance between maintaining a level of participation on the part of members that keeps the organization functioning and not overloading members so much that they refuse to participate or decide to leave the organization. This is quite a precarious position for a network leader. Member organizations put a lot of time and effort into reviewing and critiquing the products that go through the consensus process. One participant stated that some of
<disp-quote>
<p>the indirect costs, at least to members, have to do with the enormous amount of work that goes into responding to the various reports that come out. In creating comments, most of us because we are associations, ship the reports out to three or four other people for review. I’ve never tried to price it out, but if I did I’m sure it would be fairly costly per word for the responses.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Finally, the NQF also suffers from a free-rider problem that saps the energy of the process because some organizations are either slightly engaged or not engaged. Many participants note that some organizations participate in the NQF only to protect their own interests, whereas others limit their participation to their “pet” projects. However, one NQF member speculates that the laissez-faire attitude exhibited by some member organizations occurs because quality improvement is not their core business. They, therefore, cannot devote the time that is required to actively participate in a member organization such as the NQF. These examples illustrate the classic free-rider problem confronting many organizations; that is, members reap the benefits of belonging to an organization even though they may not invest a lot of time in the organization’s activities.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0095399711433695" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0095399711433695">Rethemeyer and Hatmaker (2007)</xref> urge researchers to undertake studies of a “year in the life” of network managers to determine how network managers do what they do to advance theory in this area. This article paints such a picture by presenting the results of an empirical study of how one network leader built a NAO’s social base during its formative years. It offers lessons for scholars and practitioners on how to activate and mobilize individuals to participate in the NAO and clarifies and broadens existing research by delineating some of the key tasks associated with building a NAO’s social base.</p>
<p>Kizer is known throughout the health care industry as an innovator and a transformer, and his experience prior to joining the NQF gave him a breadth of political and practical knowledge that was useful in bringing the diverse stakeholders together. Hiring someone with a proven track record and the political clout to accomplish the tasks the NQF set out to undertake was extremely important in getting the NQF started and in obtaining the initial buy-in from members of the health care community. Kizer built the NQF’s social base by providing inducements for members and staff to join the NQF. Kizer’s deep understanding of the larger picture of how to improve quality and the NQF’s role in achieving that goal allowed him to recruit members and staff who would elevate the NQF’s status from just another organization in health care to one that could do what others are not capable of doing, that is, engaging broad participation to develop consensus-based standards.</p>
<p>Since its establishment, the NQF has accomplished much. First, there is some evidence that the NQF is making some headway in institutionalizing the value of quality throughout the health care system. The best examples of this can be seen in the passage of laws in more than half the states and the requirement by several health care organizations for mandatory reporting on the 27 Never Events identified by the NQF as the most egregious. On May 27, 2003, Minnesota became the first state to sign the list into law. About 6 months later, Texas also passed a law that requires reporting of these events. Today more than half the states have laws requiring some form of reporting on medical errors. On July 29, 2005, President Bush signed the Patient Safety and Quality Improvement Act. The act creates a national database for the reporting of medical errors and near misses. Under the act, voluntary reports of medical errors or near misses may be submitted to the newly created private sector patient-safety organizations. Tri-Care, the Department of Defense’s (DOD) managed care organization, recently required all of its companies to report on these events, and the Joint Commission is also requiring its hospitals to report these events. Although progress is slow and the implementation different than initially envisioned, according to one interviewee, “This is going to get phased” in, but it’s going to be more circuitous than was originally envisioned. But, ultimately, we will have reporting on these things.” This accomplishment alone demonstrates that the goal of trying to improve health care quality is not hopeless. A second accomplishment is that the NQF has been able to do what no one has done before; that is, it has provided a forum for stakeholders with diverse perspectives to sit down together and discuss, debate, and develop consensus around measures in very contentious areas. A final accomplishment and perhaps the most significant one is that the NQF still exists. After all, the NQF was created as an experiment to address issues of quality in health care, and no one was quite sure how it would work out.</p>
<p>Despite these accomplishments, several significant challenges remain for the NQF. One of the challenges is what one NQF observer stated is the country’s “undetermined commitment to quality improvement.” Several interviewees indicated that although policy makers might pay lip service to improving health care quality, the goal of actually improving quality is not high on their agenda, and there is a reluctance to put money toward the effort. As it looks to the future, leadership and governance issues continue to present a challenge to the NQF. A key concern is the type of leadership style the NQF requires as it moves forward. The skills a leader possesses to start an organization may not be the skills needed to lead the organization into the future. In 2005, Kizer departed from the NQF, and Janet Corrigan took the helm as the NQF’s president and CEO.</p>
<p>This research suggests several avenues for future investigation. First, more empirical research needs to be conducted about the types of tasks network leaders engage in during an NAO’s formative stages. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0095399711433695">McGuire (2002)</xref> maintains, “It is necessary to hear from the managers themselves . . . the managers must be the ones who reveal their actions” (p. 608). This study represents a beginning but could be further buttressed by additional work.</p>
<p>Second, additional research could focus on delineating a leader’s tasks as an NAO moves through its organizational life cycle. Some of the questions to explore include the following: What are the critical tasks of a leader at each stage of an NAO’s life cycle? What type of leadership style is needed at each stage? Are the skills a leader needs to start an NAO the same that are needed to lead the organization into the future? Is leadership in an NAO always distributed? This study challenges the notion that leadership is distributed in an NAO—especially during its formative stages—and suggests that strong leadership is needed during an NAO’s developmental stages. But this may not always be the case. Further empirical research will contribute to a deeper understanding of these questions.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0095399711433695">
<label>1.</label>
<p>These estimates are subject to debate. In 2000, the <italic>Journal of the American Medical Association</italic> published two opposing articles outlining the debate. Three physicians from the Indiana University Center for Aging Research argue that the Institute of Medicine’s numbers are exaggerated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0095399711433695">McDonald, Weiner, &amp; Hui, 2000</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0095399711433695">Leape (2000)</xref> defends the numbers, arguing that they are too low.</p></fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Bio</title>
<p><bold>A. Bryce Hoflund</bold> is an assistant professor in the School of Public Administration at the University of Nebraska at Omaha. Her research focuses on networks, network management and leadership, and health care and food safety regulation. She received her PhD from the Center for Public Administration and Policy at Virginia Tech, her MPA from the Reubin O’D Askew School of Public Administration and Policy at Florida State University, and her BA in political science with a minor in public administration from American University.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Agranoff</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>, <month>March</month>). <source>Inside the network operation</source>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the annual conference of the American Society for Public Administration</conf-name>. <conf-loc>Portland, OR</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Agranoff</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Multinetwork management: Collaboration and the hollow state in local economic policy</article-title>. <source>Journal of Public Administration Research and Theory</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>67</fpage>-<lpage>91</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Agranoff</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Managing in network settings</article-title>. <source>Review of Policy Research</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>18</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Agranoff</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>After the network is formed: Process, power, and performance</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Mandell</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Getting results through collaboration: Networks and network structures for public policy and management</source> (pp. <fpage>11</fpage>-<lpage>29</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Westport, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Quorum Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Alter</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hage</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>Organizations working together</source>. <publisher-loc>Newbury Park, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bardach</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>).<source>Getting agencies to work together: The practice and theory of managerial craftsmanship</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brookings Institution</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barnard</surname><given-names>C. I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>The functions of the executive</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bryman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Campo</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>The importance of context: Qualitative research and the study of leadership</article-title>. <source>Leadership Quarterly</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>353</fpage>-<lpage>370</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>). <source>Leadership</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harper and Row</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Caudle</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Using qualitative approaches</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Wholey</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hatry</surname><given-names>H. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newcomer</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Handbook of practical program evaluation</source> (pp. <fpage>69</fpage>-<lpage>95</lpage>). <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>Grounding grounded theory: Guidelines for qualitative inquiry</source>. <publisher-loc>Burlington, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eisenhardt</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Building theories from case study research</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Review</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>532</fpage>-<lpage>550</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feyerherm</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Leadership in collaboration: A longitudinal study of two interorganizational rule-making groups</article-title>. <source>Leadership Quarterly</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>253</fpage>-<lpage>270</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fielding</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>).<article-title>Varieties of research interviews</article-title>. <source>Nurse Researcher</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>4</fpage>-<lpage>13</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gage</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mandell</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <source>Strategies for managing intergovernmental policies and networks</source>. <publisher-loc>Westport, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Praeger</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>B. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <source>Basics of grounded theory analysis: Emergence versus forcing</source>. <publisher-loc>Mill Valley, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sociology Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>B. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1967</year>). <source>The discovery of grounded theory: Strategies for qualitative research</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Aldine</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eggers</surname><given-names>W. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>).<source>Governing by network: The new shape of the public sector</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brookings Institution</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <source>Collaborating: Finding common ground for multiparty problems</source>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heckscher</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>The firm as a collaborative community: Reconstructing trust in the knowledge economy</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oscroft</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Snell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Activating policy networks</article-title>. <source>Policy Studies</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>-<lpage>70</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>Leadership: A new synthesis</source>. <publisher-loc>Newbury Park, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ropo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Multi-level leadership: Grounded theory and mainstream theory applied to the case of general motors</article-title>. <source>Leadership Quarterly</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>379</fpage>-<lpage>412</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Institute of Medicine</collab>. (<year>1999</year>). <source>To err is human: Building a safer health system</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Academy Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hesterly</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Borgatti</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>A general theory of network governance: Exchange conditions and social mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Review</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>911</fpage>-<lpage>945</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Klijn</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Analyzing and managing policy processes in complex networks: A theoretical examination of the concept policy network and its problems</article-title>. <source>Administration &amp; Society</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>90</fpage>-<lpage>119</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Klijn</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Teisman</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Strategies and games in networks</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Kickert</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klijn</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koppenjan</surname><given-names>J. F. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Managing complex networks: Strategies for the public sector</source> (pp. <fpage>98</fpage>-<lpage>118</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Koppenjan</surname><given-names>J. M. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klijn</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>).<source>Managing uncertainties in networks: A network approach to problem solving and decision-making</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Latour</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <source>Science in action: How to follow scientists and engineers through society</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leape</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Institute of Medicine medical error figures are not exaggerated</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Medical Association</source>, <volume>284</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>-<lpage>97</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Luke</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>Catalytic leadership: Strategies for an interconnected world</source>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mandell</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>).<article-title>Community collaborations: Working through network structures</article-title>. <source>Review of Policy Research</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>42</fpage>-<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Deaths due to medical errors are exaggerated in Institute of Medicine report</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Medical Association</source>, <volume>284</volume>, <fpage>93</fpage>-<lpage>95</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Managing networks: Propositions on what managers do and why they do it</article-title>. <source>Public Administration Review</source>, <volume>62</volume>, <fpage>599</fpage>-<lpage>609</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Agranoff</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>, <month>October</month>). <source>Answering the big questions, asking the bigger questions: Expanding the public network management empirical research agenda</source>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the 9th Public Management Research Conference</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Tucson, AZ</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>K. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Grounded theory and social process: A new direction for leadership research</article-title>. <source>Leadership Quarterly</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>85</fpage>-<lpage>105</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Perrow</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>Normal accidents: Living with high-risk technologies</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Polit</surname><given-names>D. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Nursing research: Principles and methods</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lippincott, Williams, &amp; Wilkins</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Neither market nor hierarchy: Network forms of organization</article-title>. <source>Research in Organizational Behavior</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>295</fpage>-<lpage>336</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Provan</surname><given-names>K. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kenis</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Modes of network governance: Structure, management, and effectiveness</article-title>. <source>Journal of Public Administration Research and Theory</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>229</fpage>-<lpage>252</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Provan</surname><given-names>K. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Milward</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Do networks really work? A framework for evaluating public-sector organizational networks</article-title>. <source>Public Administration Review</source>, <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>414</fpage>-<lpage>423</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reason</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <source>Human error</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reason</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>Managing the risks of organizational accidents</source>. <publisher-loc>Burlington, VT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>J. V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>Hostages of each other: The transformation of nuclear safety since Three Mile Island</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rethemeyer</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hatmaker</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Network management reconsidered: An inquiry into management of network structures in public sector service provision</article-title>. <source>Journal of Public Administration Research and Theory</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>617</fpage>-<lpage>646</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rittel</surname><given-names>H. W. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Webber</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>). <article-title>Dilemmas in a general theory of planning</article-title>. <source>Policy Sciences</source>, <volume>4</volume>,<fpage>155</fpage>-<lpage>169</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Selznick</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <source>Leadership in administration: A sociological interpretation</source> (rev. ed.). <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sorenson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Metagovernance: The changing role of politicians in processes of democratic governance</article-title>. <source>American Review of Public Administration</source>, <volume>36</volume>, <fpage>98</fpage>-<lpage>114</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stake</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Case studies</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Denzin</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lincoln</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Strategies of qualitative inquiry</source> (pp. <fpage>134</fpage>-<lpage>164</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Corbin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Basics of qualitative research: Techniques and procedures for developing grounded theory</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Termeer</surname><given-names>K. J. A. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koppenjan</surname><given-names>J. F. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Managing perceptions in networks</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Kickert</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klijn</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koppenjan</surname><given-names>J. F. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Managing complex networks: Strategies for the public sector</source> (pp. <fpage>79</fpage>-<lpage>97</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Collaboration processes: Inside the black box</article-title>. <source>Public Administration Review</source>, <volume>60</volume>, <fpage>20</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Werhane</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>Moral imagination and management decision-making</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>J. Q.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>Bureaucracy: What government agencies do and why they do it</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>J. Q.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source>Political organizations</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wimpenny</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gass</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Interviewing in phenomenology and grounded theory: Is there a difference?</article-title> <source>Journal of Advanced Nursing</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>1485</fpage>-<lpage>1492</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0095399711433695">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Network governance between individual and collective goals: Qualitative evidence from six networks</article-title>. <source>Journal of Leadership &amp; Organizational Studies</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>119</fpage>-<lpage>134</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>