<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JMQ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjmq</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journalism &amp; Mass Communication Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1077-6990</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">XXXX-XXXX</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1077699012462085</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1077699012462085</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Public Relations in Global Cultural Contexts: Multi-Paradigmatic Perspectives, edited by Nilanjana Bardhan and C. Kay Weaver</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Abazov</surname><given-names>Rafis</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-1077699012462085">Al Farabi Kazakh National University, Kazakhstan</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Nurpeiis</surname><given-names>Moldir</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-1077699012462085">Zhurgenov Kazakh National Academy of Arts, Kazakhstan</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>89</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>760</fpage>
<lpage>762</lpage>
<product><source>Public Relations in Global Cultural Contexts: Multi-Paradigmatic Perspectives</source>. <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Bardhan</surname><given-names>Nilanjana</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>C. Kay</given-names></name>
</person-group>, eds. <publisher-loc>New York and London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>. <page-count count="295"/> pages. <price>$40</price> pbk.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 AEJMC</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Association for Education in Journalism &amp; Mass Communication</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Editors Nilanjana Bardhan and C. Kay Weaver designed the book <italic>Public Relations in Global Cultural Contexts</italic> as a collection of articles targeting public relations professionals, schools of journalism and international relations specialists, both in the United States and around the world. It is also a noteworthy contribution to the growing body of literature on the impact of globalization on the development of intercultural communication and public relations work. The authors assess these and other issues from a cultural point of view and in the context of what they term a “multi-paradigmatic perspective.” Thus, the collection of articles brings together contributors from different professional and educational backgrounds, who discuss emerging trends in the PR profession from different angles.</p>
<p>Bardhan and Weaver are professors in the Department of Speech Communication at Southern Illinois University and Department of Management Communication at the University of Waikato in New Zealand, respectively. Both specialize in cultural and globalization aspects of public relations. The authors envisioned three main research goals in this book. First, they intended to explore public relations and globalization in a theoretical and “unpoliticized” way, as they claimed that the “phenomenon of globalization has not been addressed in all its complexity.” Second, they wanted to explore the concept of culture and its impact on public relations scholarship in the context of globalization. Third, they braved questioning dominant models (critical/cultural models of public relations, “glocal” strategies, etc.) and beliefs, offering alternative concepts and explanations on the intersection of public relations practice and globalization.</p>
<p>In ten chapters, the collective of authors—both scholars and practitioners—discuss the various aspects of public relations, offering a critical perspective in globalization of public relations, identifying intercultural typologies and offering some methodological arguments and directions. The issue of public relations and globalization has been covered quite intensively in Western literature over the past decade (Patricia Curtain and Kenn Gaither, 2007; Anthony Giddens, 2002; Krishnamurthy Sriramesh and Dejan Vercic, 2012, etc.). Yet the authors believe that there is room for “paradigm shifts within public relations scholarship.” They discuss the “growth of a critical postmodern paradigm in public relations,” including postcolonial “scholarship which highlights the western theoretical, methodological and cultural domination in the study of public relations,” and they focus on the “interpretive paradigm in studying the socially constructed nature of knowledge and communication in intercultural interaction in global public relations activity.”</p>
<p>All chapters in this book represent an attempt to theorize public relations and cultural contexts of globalization using various examples as case studies. For example, Michael Kent and Maureen Taylor argue that “…intercultural public relations is an interpretive communication activity that requires multiple, often simultaneous, frameworks for creating and changing relationships,” and review theories of intercultural communication, discussing how different approaches can impact general public and pubic information. They also discuss Geert Hofstede’s scholarship on cultural dimensions of communication and relationships, and use it as a platform to build their own more nuanced approach to intercultural communication. Co-editor Nilanjana Bardhan’s contribution deals with the cultural model of communication. However, she explores the roots of public relations successes in the professional multicultural setting by looking at building strategic partnerships between representatives of different cultures in dealing with a culturally diverse audience. Derina Holtzhausen believes that public relations practitioners, “even if they do not label oneself as postmodern, there might be certain tenets of postmodernism that practitioners might support and unconsciously adhere to, particularly because postmodern thought already has entered cultural practices in many ways,” and focuses on postmodernist theories and their approaches in explaining the role of public relations and specific ways of dissemination of information in the globalization process. She also uses several cases to illustrate the work of practitioners in a complex of interpersonal, intercultural, and national settings. Jensen Chung claims that a “cornerstone of Eastern philosophies” manifested in “harmony, long-term relationships, and unity of the universe [which] are some of the major principles within <italic>I-Ching</italic> (which translates into English as ‘The Book of Change’),” and deals with a more specific case of the impact of the East Asian philosophical concept of I-ching, explaining this concept looking at its Taoist and Confucian roots. She argues that this spiritual perception absorbs, harmonizes, and in a way even dissolves “Western” influences.</p>
<p>The strength of <italic>Public Relations in Global Cultural Contexts</italic> lies in the ability of the contributors to assess complex theoretical issues and discuss them within the specific context of public relations practice. The authors use some interesting examples to illustrate how the ever-evolving global culture impacts the works of practitioners in specific environments. Unfortunately, the work provides no comprehensive case studies, which would be very useful supplement to some highly theoretical chapters. Case studies like these would provide a template for students seeking to develop and apply their knowledge in specific geographic localities or professional settings.</p>
<p>Overall, Bardhan and Weaver’s book should be considered an important step in developing a major framework for discussions and studies of the cultural dimension of globalization and its impact on public relations approaches in dealing with the general public in different settings and different parts of the world. It also provides a methodological overview and conceptualizes ideas on ways to optimize dealing with information in different “glocalities.”</p>
</body>
</article>