<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JOC</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjoc</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Consumer Culture</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1469-5405</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-2900</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1469540512438156</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1469540512438156</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Long-haired, freaky people need to apply: Rock music, cultural intermediation, and the rise of the ‘company freak’</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>Devon</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1469540512438156"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1469540512438156">Drexel University, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1469540512438156">Devon Powers, Drexel University, Philadelphia, PA 19104, USA Email: <email>djp74@drexel.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>3</fpage>
<lpage>18</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article explores the phenomenon of the ‘company freak’ at American record labels of the late 1960s and early 1970s. It presents historical research on company freaks as well as theorizes how the concept of cultural intermediation might be recast as a means of complicating the standard narrative of rock’s commercial ‘co-optation’ during the period. In highlighting that company freaks were no simple appropriators, I argue that scholarship on consumer culture needs a sharper focus on historical instances of cultural intermediation in order to avoid gross caricatures of cultural commodification.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>1960s</kwd>
<kwd>commodification</kwd>
<kwd>counterculture</kwd>
<kwd>cultural intermediaries</kwd>
<kwd>rock music</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1469540512438156" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>‘At the moment, the concept of the ‘company freak’ is extremely popular,’ observed Jerry <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1469540512438156">Hopkins in a 1968</xref> <italic>Rolling Stone</italic> article on the music scene in Los Angeles. Also known as ‘house hippies,’ Hopkins described company freaks as ‘the record company’s equivalent of the “necessary Negro”’ – implying not only tokenism and subjugation but also acquiescent subservience. ‘They are there by invitation and although their titles are euphemistic at best, they are assigned specific responsibility – sometimes involving talent acquisition and producing, but always including flackery’, Hopkins continued. Through such ‘hip flackery’, the record industry more easily worked with underground newspapers and countercultural bands. ‘In LA, the so-called underground … and the Establishment indulge in a lot of mutual back-scratching’, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1469540512438156">Hopkins surmised (1968: 492–93)</xref>.</p>
<p>For a few years spanning the end of the 1960s and the beginning of the 1970s, a number of American record labels employed at least one ‘company freak’ – an unofficial, usually tongue-in-cheek, and at times pejorative designation for ‘hip’ personnel who worked on rock music within publicity, marketing, or promotions departments. During these years, both the title of ‘company freak’ and the people whom it described were signposts of the arrival of rock as a keystone of the expanding music industry. Yet, by the mid-1970s, the term had fallen out of favor, the duties freaks fulfilled rendered normal or obsolete, the freaks themselves departing the industry or, in some cases, ascending its ranks. To outward appearances, it would seem that the company freak is less a noteworthy artifact of rock’s rebellion than a curious relic of a groovier era. It should not surprise, then, that while specific individuals who worked as company freaks have figured into scholarly and journalistic accounts of the music industry of the period, the position itself has by and large escaped critical scrutiny or even mention within any of the potentially relevant disciplines, including popular music, cultural and media studies, marketing, and public relations.</p>
<p>At a moment when the music industry was flush with cash but unaccustomed to dealing with rock, labels began to explore strategies on how best to capitalize on the music and market it to its rightful audiences. The company freak was one such strategy: hired hands charged with bridging what was thought to be a troublesome gulf between the countercultural rock audience and the mainstream rock business. Yet while it would be easy to write off company freaks as ‘sellouts’ – phony accomplices of a hipper capitalism – the goal of this research is to transcend such reductive categorization. Based upon interviews with persons who held these jobs, historical research into the music industry, and a theoretical investigation of cultural intermediation and co-optation, I argue that company freaks complicate the standard narrative of rock music’s commercialization, still a widely contentious and sometimes misconstrued topic among scholars of music and popular culture. Taking such jobs seriously forces recognition not only of the motivations and sentiments of the people who prodded rock along its commercial path, but also the fits, starts, successes, and failures of an industry gambling on unpredictable cultural product.</p>
<p>A companion goal to sharing my empirical findings is to elaborate upon and re-imagine the nature of the cultural commodification or ‘co-optation’ of popular music, particularly as it played out during and immediately after the 1960s. In service of this goal, the next section argues for a focus on ‘cultural intermediation’ – a debatable concept for sure, but one I argue offers a promising path toward representing workers such as company freaks as more than loyal agents of capitalism. Following that discussion, I will present a historical analysis of company freaks in American music companies. The article will conclude with a reflection on how historical research on cultural intermediation is a necessary element of theorizing cultural commodification.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-1469540512438156"><title>Commodification, co-optation, and cultural intermediaries</title>
<p>Discomfort with commodification has a long history in critical examinations of the economy and culture, especially those stemming from Marxism and critical theory. Within this tradition, the extension of market logic into cultural production has been blamed for impoverishing the richness of culture, lessening cultural options and ‘co-opting’ cultural meaning. It is this last point, co-optation, that has held particular sway for popular music, notably rock music and especially that of the 1960s. As Frith has explained, ‘there was a moment [during the 1960s] when even the most mindless groups … had to present themselves as something other than “entertainers”’, though soon enough, ‘rock’s claims to be different from pop, to evade the logic of mass culture, turned out to be baseless’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1469540512438156">Frith, 1984</xref>: 61). A more recent argument from Garofalo expresses much the same sentiment. He writes:
<disp-quote>
<p>The 1960s may have been experienced by artists and audiences as a period of political awakening and cultural development, but for the music industry it was a period of commercial expansion and corporate consolidation. Far from disappearing, as the activists of the 1960s would have had it, capitalism simply became hipper. (1999: 337)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>The worry that ‘any ‘radical’ possibilities that might arise in the production of popular music are merely absorbed and ‘co-opted’ by a ruthless, cynical and exploitative commercial system’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1469540512438156">Negus, 1995</xref>: 318) – common among scholars, fans, and critics of popular music – draws not only from the ‘absurd reduction’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1469540512438156">Gitlin, 1993</xref>: xiii) to which the 1960s in general have been subjected. It also connects to early work from the field of cultural studies, notably Hebdige, whose <italic>Subculture: The Meaning of Style</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1469540512438156">1979</xref>) provides the basis for much subsequent thinking about non-mainstream cultural activity and influentially theorized the nature of co-optation. Hebdige defines ‘incorporation’ as a ‘continual process of recuperation’ through which subculture becomes little more than ‘a diverting spectacle within the dominant mythology from which it in part emanates’ (1979: 94). One of the chief mechanisms through which incorporation transpires is commodification, i.e. ‘the conversion of subcultural signs (dress, music, etc.) into mass-produced objects’; coupled with ‘the ideological form’ of incorporation, which involves the ‘(re)definition and digestion of subcultural resistance by dominant groups’, including the media (1979: 94), incorporation has the potential to stymie and de-fang subcultures of any stripe. For Hebdige, cultural resistance – and the degree to which that is a proxy for meaning itself – is no match against the agile power of capitalistic forces. The best option, according to his prescription, is to keep a few steps ahead of incorporation, but not to dodge the threat of it entirely.</p>
<p>Critics of this perspective argue instead that audiences, not producers, ultimately determine the meaning of a cultural product. For example, Grossberg, writing specifically on rock music, is more forgiving in his understanding of the market as a necessary component of music as mass-produced culture; his views of co-optation, as a result, are more compelling. Interested most in the productive capacity of ‘affective alliances’ among members of the rock audience, Grossberg argues for a limited view of co-optation, occurring only when rock music ‘loses that initial sense of its own struggle against something’ (1983/84: 114, 116). Yet by focusing so heavily on fan experience, Grossberg fails to adequately address the role of the industry in producing affect, characterizing an industrial emphasis as too ‘purely economic’ yet also ‘partially correct’ (1983/84: 115). By not acknowledging that the realm of the economic is likewise comprised of human relationships, affective alliances, and fan sentiments, it is easy to assume that consumption is still the main locus of meaning and salvo against the co-opting forces of the market. Views such as these uphold, rather than void, the idea that capitalism is all-powerful, through which it becomes ‘not an uncentered aggregate of practices but a structural and systemic unity’ that ‘is relatively impervious to ordinary political and cultural interventions’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1469540512438156">Gibson-Graham, 1996</xref>: 255–6).</p>
<p>What if, instead, we consider how the work of the economy can itself produce meaning? One means for accomplishing this is to consider cultural labor as among the ‘uncentered practices’ Gibson-Graham suggests provide a truer picture of economic activity. Critical of accounts ‘where class is reduced to two fundamental class positions’, Gibson-Graham instead advocates the embrace of ‘diverse class processes’ where ‘individuals may participate in a variety of class processes at one moment and over time’ (1996: 19). These views are especially useful when put toward thinking about cultural labor in general, and the notion of cultural intermediation more specifically. Originally conceived by Bourdieu as those whose ‘specific power’ derives from ‘control over the mass media’, Bourdieu identified ‘new cultural intermediaries’ as journalists, critics, television and radio producers, and the like, a subset within the ‘new petite bourgeoisie’ (1984: 323, 325, 354). Expansions on Bourdieu’s work have suggested that cultural intermediaries perform ‘information and knowledge intensive forms of work’ that are ‘increasingly central to economic and cultural life’ in our post-industrial, information-centric economy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1469540512438156">Nixon and du Gay, 2002</xref>: 496). Other scholarship has suggested that cultural intermediaries have a ‘rising trajectory within the social space’ and have been ‘numerically on the rise’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1469540512438156">Featherstone, 1987</xref>: 64); in relation to music in particular they have been called ‘the central object of the sociology of creation’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1469540512438156">Hennion, 1989</xref>: 403) and the true makers of records, shaping otherwise unformed acts into marketable products (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1469540512438156">Jones, 2002</xref>: 150).</p>
<p>Debate over the value and application of the concept of the term cultural intermediaries has accompanied, and in certain cases attempted to stave, the growing scholarly focus. Proposals to expand the term to include overlooked forms of symbolic work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1469540512438156">Negus, 2002a</xref>) have been met with criticism that ‘the confusing array of uses to which the term [cultural intermediary] has been put’ limits its use as a conceptual tool for analyzing cultural production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1469540512438156">Hesmondhalgh, 2006</xref>: 227), while historical work has questioned whether they are new to the culture industry after all (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1469540512438156">McFall 2002</xref>). Writing elsewhere, Hesmondhalgh has favored a return to the term ‘creative manager’ to describe those who ‘act as brokers or mediators between … the interests of owners and executives’ and the needs and desires of ‘creative personnel’ (2007: 64).</p>
<p>While these arguments have certainly produced useful scholarship, for my purposes here they are inadequately focused. I have traded the term ‘cultural intermediaries’ for ‘cultural intermediation’ as a means recasting the conversation, away from classifying kinds of work and toward making sense of the nature of power manifest in the processes of cultural production. Instead of attempting to enumerate who does or does not perform these acts in a widely heterogeneous and malleable culture industry, what Molloy and Larner call ‘cultural mediation is more productively thought of as a function of the multiplicity of activities and relationships organised around the new economic spaces … which are subject to the exigencies of capital accumulation’ (2010: 362). While labor processes certainly demand greater visibility, my use of cultural intermediation is meant to index the existing scholarship while underscoring the great degree to which these conversations turn on the nature of and embodiment of cultural authority. To this end, it is telling that Macguire and Matthews offer the following perspective (2010: 407):
<disp-quote>
<p>It is not only that cultural intermediaries use media to accomplish their promotional work, but that in doing so they are an effect of and contributor to the corporatization of the media … In the search for audiences and consumer markets, the work of mass production increasingly co-opts aspects of legitimate, restricted culture in order to lend cachet, legitimacy, value, and so forth … The cultural intermediary is the agent and mass media the conduit for the strategic migration and translation of ‘restricted’ culture into the field of larger-scale production.</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>The argument that cultural intermediaries are the ‘agents’ of co-optation is useful in so far as it understands cultural commodification as embodied practice rather than a faceless, autocratic force. Yet their conception also reproduces many of the problems apparent in theorizations on co-optation explored above, as well as the reductive, binary construct of capitalism Gibson-Graham so convincingly questions. As per Macguire and Matthews, cultural intermediaries are little more than cogs who keep the wheels of commodification turning, straightforwardly reproducing the desires of the greater system in which they labor. What results is therefore only a slight improvement on the agentless views of co-optation, giving us very little by way of how actual people work, what motivates them to do their jobs, and the conflicts that arise, both knowingly and unintentionally, in doing it.</p>
<p>More open and realistic views about the nature of this intermediating power articulate the complex positioning and uncertain outcomes of work within the culture industries. For instance, Cronin’s work on advertising professionals explains that they not only mediate the relationship between producers and consumers (as the description of them as ‘agents’ and ‘translators’ would suggest) but instead occupy a ‘dual status as producers (of ads) and consumers (of ads and products)’ (2004: 353) mired in the confusion of cultural trends rather than omnisciently directing them or cunningly absorbing them (2004: 354). Cronin’s point supports my thesis that cultural labor is always trickier than the selling/selling out characterization implies, as well as that cultural intermediation results in manifold allegiances that only <italic>sometimes</italic> emerge as conflicts. Moreover, Taylor’s discussion of the use of electronic music in advertising brings to light the possibility that ad agency employees see themselves not only as kindred spirits to the independent musicians who made music for their ads, but also as sensitive benefactors, wary of the fine line between corruptive and auspicious promotion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1469540512438156">Taylor, 2007</xref>). This is not because (as Frank cynically suggests of 1960s admen) they fake a kinship so as to appear more hip (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1469540512438156">Frank, 1998</xref>: 113). On the contrary, Taylor’s insights underscore the degree to which their work was not so much hypocritical as paradoxical. It likewise should be a reminder that none are fully represented by their labor; none occupy their jobs without friction; and none can entirely shut off the rest of their existence from 9 to 5 (especially if, as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1469540512438156">McRobbie (2002)</xref> has argued, for many work and leisure are thoroughly intermingled).</p>
<p>Placing these issues into a historical context adds an important dimension to the conversation. Stephens has argued that during the 1960s, ‘“work” was radically redefined’, privileging the expression of pleasure as ‘inherently subversive’, even if that pleasure happened at one’s place of employment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1469540512438156">Stephens, 1998</xref>: 86). Accordingly, this redefinition not only allowed ‘ample space for enterprising hippies to profit from the 1960s movements’ (1998: 86–7), but also provided impetus for the widespread revision of workplace norms in a host of industries as well as the 1970s introduction into both work and leisure culture of what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1469540512438156">Binkley (2007)</xref> has called ‘looseness’. Spanning the late 1960s and early 1970s, the phenomenon of company freaks is a fruitful place in which to witness these transitions taking place, as well as the variety of kinds of work cultural intermediation could entail. Moreover, focusing on the histories of cultural intermediation adds a necessary dimension to inquiries into immaterial and affective labor and the hybrid nature of leisure-oriented work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1469540512438156">McRobbie, 2002</xref>). While these studies shed useful light on the present, their lack of historical focus makes them prone to finding too much novelty in these practices. Following the guidance of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1469540512438156">McFall (2002)</xref> I see company freaks not as the first or the last instance of these transitions, but rather a telling moment in a long tradition of laborers who have found opportunities and contradictions in the developing cultural industries.</p>
<p>To summarize, I am arguing that cultural intermediation is most useful if the category helps to complicate our understandings of the dynamics of commodification and the culture of economic practice, rather than simply confirm our worst suspicions and prove our most vulgar theorizations. When intermediation is seen as carried out by agents who flatly mediate the relationship between culture and commerce or reflect static class positions, it is easy to see those people as blunt instruments of capitalism rather than situated people who make choices about and have opinions regarding the ends of their labor. This last point in part borrows from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1469540512438156">McFall (2002)</xref> who argues that such understandings deny the fact that ‘the ‘cultural’ and the ‘economic’ are entangled dimensions of practice rather than discrete spheres’, (2002: 534), and that ‘culture is not something that intervenes in economic processes, rather it is <italic>constitutive</italic> of them’ (2002: 548). Cultural intermediation does not just introduce culture into the economy, but instead highlights the necessity of their co-production and the totality of their connection. My use of the term is therefore an attempt to apply this insight toward a more productive understanding of the history of rock as a commodity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-1469540512438156"><title>Company freaks and selling (out?) music</title>
<p>As noted above, scholars have often characterized commodification as one of the chief problems of popular music generally and 1960s rock specifically, making it difficult to interpret and be sympathetic to both the pressures and the opportunities the music industry has created as it has grown and commercialized. Nonetheless, even the most pessimistic accounts of the music business of the time report how rock music dramatically reshaped industry practices – the first sign that capitalist appropriation is hardly one way. For instance, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1469540512438156">Goodman’s (1998)</xref> <italic>The Mansion on the Hill,</italic> a trenchant critique of the commercialization of the rock business, is also a meticulous account of the commercial success of rock during and immediately after the 1960s, both in terms of its profitability to labels and its infiltration into the heart of the music business. As he exhibits, this rise was the result of both initiative within the major labels and entrepreneurship beyond it; individuals and industries emerged to depend upon and amplify the growth of rock (such as live venues and concert promotion, radio stations, underground newspapers, and talent agencies) at the same time that the labels themselves were changed by the injection of musicians, producers, and managers who were not acculturated to the business. In many cases, labels already had staff among their ranks who found opportunity within this sea change; these were often the business’s youngest employees, who in some cases staked their careers on rock music. Likewise, Goodman rattles off a litany of forward-thinking label presidents (Jac Holzman, Clive Davis, Ahmet Ertegun), domineering managers (Albert Grossman, David Geffen), and intuitive A&amp;R (artists and repertoire) men (John Hammond) as some of the music history’s most dynamic visionaries.</p>
<p>The present study is not interested in adding the names of particular company freaks to the list of music industry ‘greats’ of the period, though what follows does focus on only a few individuals for reasons I will shortly detail. Goodman’s point is that these figures, as pioneering as they were, were also catalysts of rock’s undoing, powerbrokers who led an industry toward troubling horizons. My argument, however, is neither that company freaks were mercenaries fighting an ignoble fight nor that they should be heralded as its ‘real’ leaders. Instead, it is to recast what kind of battle was in fact going on, to blur or even erase the lines that exist between allies and enemies.</p>
<p>Three company freaks will comprise the bulk of my analysis: (1) Billy James, who worked for Columbia Records from 1961 until 1966, first in New York and later in Los Angeles, before transitioning to Elektra’s LA offices; (2) Jim Fouratt, employed in ‘creative services’ in Columbia’s New York offices from 1968 until the early 1970s; and (3) Danny Fields, publicist for Elektra Records in New York City from 1967 who later moved to Atlantic. I choose James, Fouratt, and Fields not only because they are the company freaks most frequently mentioned within histories of rock music, but also because over the course of my interviews, their names came up more than others among other ‘freaky’ types; this is especially true of James and Fields. In addition to these men, I will more briefly mention the experiences of several other figures: William Yaryan, a publicist who moved between MCA, Atlantic Records, and independent firms between 1970 and 1975 in Los Angeles; Sally Stevens, who worked in promotion in a number of labels during this time period; and Michael Ochs, regional publicity director at Columbia in Los Angeles from 1969 until 1972.</p>
<p>There are a handful of other figures who have been identified as a ‘company freak’ or ‘house hippie’ in writings on the industry of the period. The most notable of these is Richard DiLello, whose book <italic>The Longest Cocktail Party</italic> (1972) chronicles his experience as the house hippie for Apple Records in London, working under famed Beatles publicist Derek Taylor. Though his duties – managing press clippings, taking photographs, interfacing with artists, partaking in nightlife – give him much in common with the company freaks as I will describe them below, focusing on the American cultural and economic context allows me to present a more nuanced examination than if I were to also make claims about the UK. Beyond this geographic delimitation, during the course of my research I encountered a number complications – not just death or inability to locate certain persons for interviews, but also what was initially a surprising amount of debate and confusion about who company freaks were and what they did. There is much overlap, for instance, between company freaks and the rise of independent publicity firms, some of which were started in response to rock and staffed with individuals who chose, for one reason or another, not to work inside major labels. I have purposely focused on a small number of subjects in order to manage the unfixed presence of ‘freaks’ in the record labels of the period. Indeed, if they were unruly figures for record labels of the time, they have proved to be similarly thorny for myself as a historian.</p>
<p>To decipher what I mean, let me begin with an interpretation of the fundamental tension that exists within the title ‘company freak’ (a tension that also exists in the other commonly used term for these jobs, ‘house hippie’). So-called company freaks initially come off as what Hirsch would call ‘contact men,’ whose ‘proliferation’ during this time period is suggestive of ‘the centrality of information on boundary developments’ for culture industries, and the importance of work ‘in the field’ (1972: 133–4). Seen this way, company freaks perform typical duties of the music industry but with flair: walking the walk, talking the talk, and wearing the uniform that allows them to consort with the music’s target audience. Writing at the time, Denisoff explained that a ‘house hippie was usually a writer or producer who could explain the ‘new community’ for the record company and the label to the “street”’ but that some labels ‘employed long hairs as a status symbol or as mere window dressing’ (1975: 125). A brief discussion in the 1973 textbook <italic>You &amp; Media</italic> agrees: ‘the company freak … is decorative, but he has a function’ – to manage the ‘collision of two cultures’ at the heart of his contemporary music industry (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1469540512438156">Clark and Blankenburg, 1973</xref>: 5).</p>
<p>That so much of what a company freak did day-to-day was routine would seem to corroborate the idea that freaks were gussied-up corporate hacks. Writing press releases, crafting ad campaigns, or pitching stories might have been fun work for a twentysomething, but it was hardly revolutionary within the record business; beyond this, it wasn’t as if rock artists were the only ones needing company freaks’ services. Fields expresses this sentiment when he describes himself as a ‘kept hippie’ noting that ‘as much as you can invent your own role, you’re still working for the stable of artists’ (1970: 153, 165). The stress in all of this is on the idea of the ‘company’: that, at bottom, their purpose was to represent company interests.</p>
<p>But the ‘company’ aspect of these positions is only half of the equation – ‘freak’ was also integral, as a foil to and a check upon the ultimate dominance of corporate think. This is what allows Arnold Shaw to boldly proclaim in his <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1469540512438156">1969</xref> book, <italic>The Rock Revolution,</italic> that house hippies (‘hirsute A&amp;R men in search of rock artists’) are fundamental to the ‘overthrow of the older generation’s popular music culture’ (1969: 2). Pushing against strictures that had persisted in record labels for decades, company freaks injected freaky behavior into their work environments, shifting norms around dress, behavior, attitude, respect for authority, and many other arenas. In an interview, Fouratt gave the following example:
<disp-quote>
<p>I just did whatever I wanted to do, and I talked a lot … I would sit at a sales meeting and, I didn’t realize it at first, but nobody said anything until Clive [Davis, President of Columbia Records] said how he felt about something. And Clive would say, ‘Oh, I think this is really great!’ and everyone would say ‘oh, it’s great!’ And I didn’t know that was protocol. And he would always ask me first, and I would just tell him what I thought! (Fouratt, interview with the author, 2011)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Such brazen bucking of corporate etiquette was not necessarily a sign of disrespect – in our conversation, Fouratt was quick to express respect for Davis – but does exemplify how naturally, and extremely, the ‘difference’ company freaks manifested could show through. One of the difficulties of focusing on the ‘freak’ criterion, though, is that it becomes much more difficult to absolutely define. ‘Working on the business side of music recording [there] seemed to be two types’, noted Yaryan, the MCA publicist. ‘Most were interested in money and advancing up the ladder of success. Some were like me and got jobs in the business because they loved music and had a taste for glamour and adventure that rubbing up against fame might provide’ (Yaryan, interview with the author, 2010). The sizeable minority of employees interested in rock for cultural reasons becomes especially visible when regional issues are taken into account. As the musical culture of California – in both the psychedelic communalism of the San Francisco Bay Area and the laid-back swagger of Southern California – became of keen interest to label dons in New York, East Coast bureaucracy came in increasing contact with a cooler West Coast vibe. The melding and mutating of these regional ways of being could result in one coast’s ‘freak’ being simply de riguer on the other. Sally Stevens, a member of the promotions department at Elektra Records who bounced around numerous record labels in the 1960s and 1970s, made this point emphatically, explaining that ‘we were all company freaks. That was the weird thing about those days – nobody was normal’ (Stevens, interview with the author, 2009).</p>
<p>This is puzzling, contradictory terrain – on the one hand, company freaks as token eccentrics and on the other as anyone who simply wasn’t normal – but I have come to find its contradictions instructive. What it elucidates is that company freaks should be thought about as not just bridges <italic>between</italic> cultures oppositionally defined as ‘counter’ and ‘corporate’; rather, they were forgers of a common culture – namely, an environment in which rock music, the capital of major labels, and the individuals who transacted that relationship made sense together. As opposed to being an adulteration of something old, this rock culture was importantly, integrally new, an offspring taking attributes from both parents but resembling neither completely. Company freaks, in all their unconventional ambiguity, were symbols and agents of this (re)birth in and beyond major music labels. This helps to explain how they can be thought of as exceptions and the (new) rule simultaneously – they were very much both.</p>
<p>Thus when Negus suggests that rock ‘facilitated the recruitment into the music of a group of mildly bohemian young people associated with the counter-culture’, (2002b : 120), his view is only partially accurate. Not only does the descriptor ‘mildly bohemian’ dismiss the hard work bohemianism could require, even in its subdued forms; it also undermines the degree to which the job of the company freak was inherently <italic>performative</italic>, involving the active creation of communication and relationships as well as the claiming and re-claiming of institutional and social space. To understand this as ‘mildly bohemian’ is to slight that the work of company freaks was necessarily ad hoc and actively creative in finding outlets for ‘freakish’ expression. Fields’s explanation that a company freak was ‘a role anyhow, not a job, and you invent it as you go along’ (1970: 155) articulates the plasticity – around bohemianness, corporateness, and many other things – that was necessary for success and survival.</p>
<p>The career of Billy James makes this point strongly. Hired by the publicity department at Columbia Records in May of 1961, James initially focused on classical and jazz music but, as an early fan of Bob Dylan, began working for him once the label signed him in the fall of that year. James moved to Los Angeles in 1964 and began taking an interest in the local music scene, eventually coming to work with The Byrds once they signed with the label. His support of the band both within and outside Columbia meant his star would rise along with theirs in the mid-1960s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1469540512438156">Goodman, 1998</xref>: 54). And with this, James earned something of a legendary status. In recalling his first encounter with James, Fields describes him as ‘[t]his charming, barefoot dynamo, running around the office, sitting on the floor, putting his feet up on the walls’ (1970: 154) who would prove to be his inspiration. Capitalizing on this cachet, James was allowed to ‘create a job’ for himself, establishing the practice of ‘artist development’ – a deeper investment and nurturing between labels and the new artists they signed. Though what artist development entailed exactly was unclear, his position was soon modeled at other labels, and the people who held such as jobs were often themselves identified as ‘freaks’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1469540512438156">Denisoff, 1975</xref>: 125; James, interview with the author, 2009).</p>
<p>The amorphous nature of James’s job – extending so far beyond the normal practices of record labels at the time that a new position had to be created – not only suggests that his work was truly extemporaneous, but also underlines the risks Columbia was open to taking in their quest to be successful with rock music. Yet these lengths are not adequately characterized as co-optation per se, which suggests intentionality, manipulation and, above all, an ability to forecast that such strategies would prevail. On the contrary, James’s experience is evidence that such predictions were impossible, because he was making it up as he went along. That said, he has noted that in his role in artist development, he was given ‘freedom, not license’ – a turn of phrase that suggests that the liberties he took also made company executives uneasy (James, interview with the author, 2009). The space within which James could do as he pleased had to be located, pioneered, and constantly defended.</p>
<p>Because the work of freaks was performative and communicative, it was also promotional – following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1469540512438156">Cronin (2004)</xref> I intend this to mean that freaks also had to do the work of explaining their use value to record company executives, musicians, journalists, radio stations, and the like. One instance where this took place was in the use of the term ‘company freak’ itself. Though some I spoke with described it as a joke, or a title others used about them but they never used themselves, others took pride in it. ‘It meant we had the power. It differentiated us from the suits’, noted Yaryan. ‘The 1970s was the high water mark of the underground press and underground FM radio stations operated mostly by hippies and it was presumed they would listen to us. We felt superior’ (Yaryan, interview with the author, 2010). Notoriety could thus be a kind of capital, exercised not only to distinguish one within the label’s corporate culture but also gain authority within it.</p>
<p>Perhaps no company freak understood this balance as well as Danny Fields. Fields is far and away the most frequently recognized figure to have held one of these jobs – and, as such, is its consummate storyteller, frequently identified as having coined the term ‘company freak’ himself. A graduate of University of Pennsylvania who also attended Harvard Law School, Fields was hired by the publicity department for Elektra Records in the late 1960s after stints working for several music-oriented magazines. At the time, Elektra was an established folk label venturing into acquiring more rock artists; Fields has become infamous for signing the MC5 and The Stooges in 1968. ‘Mind you, I was a press agent; I had taken on the liberty of signing bands’ he explained. ‘A lot of people at Elektra despised me because I was changing their company. I was seen as the inventor of this kind of juvenile delinquency’ (Fields, interview with the author, 2008).</p>
<p>Though calling himself a ‘kept hippie’ suggests exploitation, Fields also exercised power that made him a valuable asset to the label. Writing of his position, Fields noted that:
<disp-quote>
<p>The titans supply his salary and expenses, but his heart is with the musicians, which makes schizophrenia a very possible occupational hazard … their artists are on the other side of the generation gap, and the company freak is someone who is supposed to prove the liaison factor between the company and its artists, and also between the company and alternate media. No hip FM DJ, for example, will have anything to do with the promotion sharpies in shiny suits … And yet a record company has to reach these cats because they have a lot of influence on the kids who buy records. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1469540512438156">Fields, 1970</xref>: 153–4)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Keenly aware of his own influence within Elektra as well as its key external constituencies, Fields also enjoyed – even toyed with – company resources. ‘I had expense accounts – I would take 12, 15 people out for dinner. The publicity budgets were seemingly infinite’, he has noted. ‘They would fly me to Denmark for a weekend to see some group I never heard of again. The publicity departments were just so full of giving, like buying favors, which I didn’t object to at all’ (Fields, interview with the author, 2008). While many might interpret the above as the ultimate example of ‘selling out,’ another way to think about it is that Fields was simply taking advantage of the huge amounts of revenue rock was making, playing the record label’s game and even beating them at it.</p>
<p>Ochs expressed another aspect of this when he noted that, in conversations with music journalists, he regularly promoted acts on other labels alongside his own artists. ‘There was a camaraderie among us music junkies’, he explained. ‘It wasn’t like we were company loyalists; we were good music loyalists’ (Ochs, interview with the author, 2009). For Ochs, working for the record label was an instance of ‘good fortune’ that allowed him the chance to work with artists he loved while getting paid to do so, but it in no way made him a lapdog for the company that paid his wage. Given that he had almost no supervision (a common theme among the freaks), Ochs recounted how his interactions with music journalists sometimes directly abused company resources:
<disp-quote>
<p>Writers like Lester Bangs or Ben Edmunds would come in and we’d play. Columbia released so much stuff that I couldn’t even keep up with it – I had stacks of singles that I hadn’t gotten to … And so we used to play jukebox jury. I played the first three seconds of a song and we’d try to guess if it was a hit or not, and if it was a miss as most of them were, we’d just throw them out the window. (Ochs, interview with the author, 2009)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Fouratt also found ways to use company resources to his own ends. An actor, gay rights activist, and member of the New York chapter of the White Panther Party, Fouratt was a ‘cultural radical’ who conceived of his job as ‘working on the inside as a cultural revolutionary’ (Fouratt, interview with the author, 2011). This cultural revolution could take many different forms. For instance, Fouratt told the following story about how he helped to change company policies regarding office décor:
<disp-quote>
<p>I had an office on Sixth Avenue between 52nd and53rd, which was a big deal. And you could not put anything on the walls, and they had a dress code. And I came in dressed in my hippie gear as I would dress anyplace else, and I’d stop by security and they’d have to call upstairs. And at night they would take down everything I had put on the walls, my posters and everything. [Eventually] I went to Clive and said – you know, I was young and arrogant and all of that – and I said, ‘if you want me to work here, you have to let me have my office the way I want to have it.’ And the next day, everything was still up on the walls. And then everyone else was allowed to come in and dress however they wanted to dress and put whatever they wanted on the walls. It was a very big victory within the building. (Fouratt, interview with the author, 2011)</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Fouratt’s support of countercultural interests also extended beyond the offices of Columbia. ‘One of the primary cultural goals we had was to make sure that the underground newspapers that had started up survived’, he noted. When his urging convinced Columbia to place ads in the papers, ‘Elektra and Warner Brothers and all the others did it … it was how the Underground Press Syndicate survived in 1968’ (Fouratt, interview with the author, 2011). Thus, even at moments in which it might seem like the counterculture and corporate interests were at odds, they were interconnected in some very important ways, and embodied in people like Fouratt. ‘As radical politically as I was, I had this other side of me that was very involved in the music culture’, he explained. Though eventually his desire to do more overtly political work won out, especially during his early days at the label, ‘I thought I was putting out a political message or a cultural message’ (Fouratt, interview with the author, 2011).</p>
<p>Though they articulate a certain amount of conflict, the experiences of company freaks also highlight the productive nature of these tensions. Given the ability to help musicians, build a relationship with some of the industry’s most powerful figures, and push the spread of rock music, company freaks were intimately involved in widening the cultural shifts that were necessarily, intimately tied to the commercial culture in which rock would continue to flourish. But they were also involved in changing the companies where they worked – changes that needed to happen if rock was to work as a commercial product. Company freaks were as a result situated actors who participated in bolstering the terrain in which rock and the counterculture could better coexist.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-1469540512438156" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>With the exception of Fields, who went on to become a prominent music executive, most of the subjects interviewed for this article left the music industry by the mid-1970s, for a variety of personal and professional reasons. For that reason, I will refrain from speculating too much on what happened to positions like these within the music industry after that period; suffice to say, I have come across nothing to suggest that the term continued to be used, nor reason to believe that it would have had purchase if it had been. In one sense, company freaks were truly a freak – anomalies of record companies in transition who have been, at best, footnotes in the historical record.</p>
<p>But on many other levels, company freaks were strong predictors of record labels’ future. Artist development, an area James pioneered, has grown to be a key aspect of how a label relates to a musician. The music industry of today is far from the culturally conservative place that it was prior to the mid-1960s. And the idea that a music label, or any cultural industry, would hire young personnel for the purpose of tapping into youth culture is perhaps critiqued by some, but far less noteworthy than it might have been during the period under research – and, in many respects, it is simply good practice. Company freaks, if not catalysts of these shifts, at the very least deserve to be an aspect of their interpretation. That company freaks have been thought about so little, then, is indicative of how difficult it is to move beyond caricatures of the economics of culture during the 1960s.</p>
<p>Insights into historical cultural intermediation therefore can be useful not just in giving more complete pictures of how cultural industries broached new cultural arenas. They can also showcase how cultural intermediation was and continues to be a critical component of what it is we mean when we say culture has been commodified. In the case of rock music, becoming commercial was not as simple as omniscient appropriators descending upon rock’s cultural centers, but was a messier process that involved many kinds of people with a diverse range of experiences and motivations. Company freaks illustrate the way that ‘marketing experts are subject to their own cultural, philosophical concerns’ while ‘counterculturals are inclined to shape their own distinct economic conventions’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1469540512438156">Binkley, 2003</xref>: 246) – and moreover, that ‘marketing experts’ and ‘counterculturals’ can be one in the same. Additionally, as Thornton usefully reminds us, ‘[c]ontrary to the ideologies of both the underground and many subcultural studies, culture industries do not just co-opt and incorporate; they generate ideas and incite culture’ (1996: 157) in part by helping that culture to become a viable business. The tremendous role of the rock music industry in amplifying the power of rock did not come without unintended consequences, but it also produced rewards, both obvious and unlikely.</p>
<p>In the end, company freaks were many things: rebels defying corporate standards; everyday workers seeking opportunity in their early careers; predecessors to the corporate renegades of our own time; music lovers who sympathized and identified with countercultural ideas; and rejecters of the strictures of conventional business, including always kowtowing to the demands of profit. To engage fully with the notion of company freak revises widely held ideas about the ramifications of capitalism during the 1960s, providing instructive, if not necessarily tidy, insights into what it meant – and continues to mean – to labor in the culture industries.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Binkley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Cosmic profit: Countercultural commerce and the problem of trust in American marketing</article-title>. <source>Consumption, Markets and Culture</source> <volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Binkley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Getting Lose: Lifestyle Consumption in the 1970s</source>. <publisher-loc>Durham, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bourdieu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <source>Distinction: A Social Critique of the Judgement of Taste</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Blakenburg</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1973</year>) <source>You &amp; Media</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harper</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Regimes of mediation: Advertising practitioners as cultural intermediaries?</article-title>. <source>Consumption, Markets and Culture</source> <volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>349</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DiLello</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>The Longest Cocktail Party: An Insider’s Diary of The Beatles, Their Million-Dollar Apple Empire, and Its Wild Rise and Fall</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Playboy Books</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denisoff</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>) <source>Solid Gold: The Popular Record Industry</source>. <publisher-loc>New Brunswick, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transaction Books</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Featherstone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Lifestyle and consumer culture</article-title>. <source>Theory, Culture &amp; Society</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>70</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>) <article-title>Who bridges the gap between the record executive and the rock musician? I do</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>The Age of Rock 2: Sights and Sounds of the American Cultural Revolution</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Random House</publisher-name>, pp.<fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>The Conquest of Cool: Business Culture, Counterculture, and the Rise of Hip Consumerism</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frith</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Rock and the politics of memory</article-title>. <source>Social Text</source> <volume>9</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garofalo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>From music publishing to MP3: Music and industry in the 20th century</article-title>. <source>American Music</source> <volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>318</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gibson-Graham</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>The End of Capitalism (As We Knew It): A Feminist Critique of Political Economy</source>. <publisher-loc>Malden, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gitlin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <source>The Sixties: Years of Hope, Days of Rage</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bantam Books</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>The Mansion on the Hill: Dylan, Young, Geffen, Springsteen, and the Head-on Collision of Rock and Commerce</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Vintage</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grossberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983/84</year>) <article-title>The politics of youth culture: Some observations on rock and roll in American culture</article-title>. <source>Social Text</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hebdige</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>) <source>Subculture: The Meaning of Style</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hennion</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>An intermediary between production and consumption: The producer of popular music</article-title>. <source>Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values</source> <volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>400</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hesmondhalgh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Bourdieu, the media, and cultural production</article-title>. <source>Media, Culture, and Society</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hesmondhalgh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>The Cultural Industries</source>, <edition>2nd edn</edition>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>) <article-title>Processing fads and fashions: An organization-set analysis of cultural industry systems</article-title>. <source>The American Journal of Sociology</source> <volume>77</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>639</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1968</year>) <article-title>Scenes: Los Angeles</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Fong-Torres</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>The <italic>Rolling Stone</italic> Rock ‘n’ Roll Reader</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bantam Book</publisher-name>, pp.<fpage>491</fpage>–<lpage>503</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The music industry as workplace: An approach to analysis</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Cultural Work: Understanding the Culture Industries</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, pp.<fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maguire</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Cultural intermediaries and the media</article-title>. <source>Sociology Compass</source> <volume>4</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>405</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McFall</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>What about the old cultural intermediaries? An historical review of advertising producers</article-title>. <source>Cultural Studies</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>532</fpage>–<lpage>52</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McRobbie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Clubs to companies: Notes on the decline of political culture in speeded up creative worlds</article-title>. <source>Cultural Studies</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>516</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Molloy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Larner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Who needs cultural intermediaries indeed? Gendered networks in the designer fashion industry</article-title>. <source>Journal of Cultural Economy</source> <volume>3</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>361</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Negus</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Where the mystical meets the market: Creativity and commerce in the production of popular music</article-title>. <source>The Sociological Review</source> <volume>43</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>316</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Negus</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002a</year>) <article-title>The work of cultural intermediaries and the enduring distance between production and consumption</article-title>. <source>Cultural Studies</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>501</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Negus</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002b</year>) <article-title>Identities and industries: The cultural formation of aesthetic economies</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>du Gay</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pryke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Cultural Economy</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>, pp.<fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nixon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>du Gay</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Who needs cultural intermediaries?</article-title>. <source>Cultural Studies</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>500</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1969</year>) <source>The Rock Revolution</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Crowell-Collier Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Anti-Disciplinary Protest: Sixties Radicalism and Postmodernism</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The changing shape of the culture industry; or, how did electronic music get into television commercials?</article-title>. <source>Television and New Media</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1469540512438156"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Club Cultures: Music, Media, and Subcultural Capital</source>. <publisher-loc>Middletown, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wesleyan University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<bio><p><bold>Devon Powers</bold> is Assistant Professor of Communication, Department of Culture and Communication, Drexel University. Her research focuses on the intermediation and circulation of popular music, from the mid-20th century to the present. With Melissa Aronczyk, she co-edited the book <italic>Blowing Up the Brand: Critical Perspectives on Promotional Culture</italic> (Peter Lang, 2010), which explores the expansion of promotion and branding beyond the realm of business and marketing and into myriad aspects of everyday life. She is completing a monograph about the history of rock music criticism, under contract with University of Massachusetts Press.</p></bio>
</back>
</article>