<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptrn</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TRN</journal-id>
         <journal-title>Transformation: An International Journal of Holistic Mission Studies</journal-title>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">0265-3788</issn>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
         </publisher>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0265378809103383</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0265378809103383</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Articles</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Interfaith Development Efforts as Means to Peace and Witness</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Backues</surname>
                  <given-names>Lindy</given-names>
               </name>
               <aff>Eastern University</aff>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>04</month>
            <year>2009</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>26</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <fpage>67</fpage>
         <lpage>81</lpage>
         <abstract>
            <p>Christian development agencies have been the primary vehicle of choice for holistic involvement and witness. This has played straight into an Enlightenment manner of thinking that compartmentalizes values, limiting the opportunities for explaining the theological and conceptual foundations for development practice and for public witness concerning religious faith. New institutional models appropriate to witness and holistic Christian service need to be considered. An `S4' type organization, explored in practice in Indonesia in an interfaith setting, allows for a more effective sharing of the gospel and robust development work.</p>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd>development</kwd> 
            <kwd>dialogue</kwd> 
            <kwd>institutions</kwd> 
            <kwd>interfaith</kwd> 
            <kwd>peace-making</kwd> 
            <kwd>values</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
         <custom-meta-wrap>
            <custom-meta xlink:type="simple">
               <meta-name>sagemeta-type</meta-name>
               <meta-value>Journal Article</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
            <custom-meta xlink:type="simple">
               <meta-name>search-text</meta-name>
               <meta-value>67
Interfaith
Development Efforts as Means to Peace and Witness
SAGE Publications, Inc.200910.1177/0265378809103383
LindyBackues
Eastern University
Abstract
Christian development agencies
have been the primary vehicle of choice for holistic involvement and witness.
This has played straight into an Enlightenment manner of thinking that compartmentalizes
values, limiting the opportunities for explaining the theological and conceptual
foundations for development practice and for public witness concerning religious
faith. New institutional models appropriate to witness and holistic Christian
service need to be considered. An `S4' type organization, explored in practice
in Indonesia in an interfaith setting, allows for a more effective sharing
of the gospel and robust development work.
development
dialogue
institutions
interfaith
peace-making
values
Keywords
Introduction
Evangelicals have long shied away from interfaith dialogue. In fact, it might
be that one of the historical reasons Evangelicals have been so late in getting
involved in development is the suspicion that such involvement might lead
them away from the gospel by tying them into secularized modes of reasoning
or by diluting the gospel message with alien ideas from other faiths or from
skeptical modernist thought.1 Oddly enough, though, it seems probable that
biblical witness has in fact been limited precisely by this path Evangelicals
have taken.2 An almost exclusive emphasis on the Christian development agency
as the primary vehicle of choice for holistic involvement and witness has
played straight into an Enlightenment manner of thinking, one that partitions
the gospel into divisions and pieces unnat- ural to the message itself. As
we shall see, the Enlightenment, by definition, rules out exchange and dialogue
about values in the public sphere, a position that sig- nificantly restricts
opportunity for public witness concerning religious faith. We shall see that,
to the degree anti-Christian bias exists in the world today (and it clearly
does, justified or not), Christian development organizations end up faced
68
not
only with these biases, but also with a systematic prohibition against explain-
ing theological conceptual foundations for development practice in the first
place. At the end of the day, Christian development organizations ironically
end up co- opted into the Enlightenment's compartmentalization of values.
The gospel ends up either domesticated into Christian ghettos or prohibited
from being discussed within the ambit of so-called `secular' organizations.
Consequently, it is high time new institutional models appropriate to witness
and holistic Christian service were explored. This article attempts to initiate
just such an exploration. As a result, I put forward a particular type of
organization – one I label `S4' – that I believe promises avoidance
of these pitfalls by overcom- ing many of the barriers erected by Enlightenment-style
values. S4 organizations, by emphasizing the importance of sharing the gospel
in an interfaith setting, also allow for more robust development work with
greater opportunities for the establishment of biblical conduits of peace
in this world so fraught with strife, dissention, terror and war. The Enlightenment
Consensus in Disarray: The Cultural Backdrop for Development As Christian
development workers we are confronted with a dilemma, one we no longer can
afford to ignore: What do we do as the global, secular Enlightenment culture
cum consensus crumbles all around us? How do we get on with doing our work,
fulfilling our call, in a terrain which makes so little sense if seen through
the settled conceptual perspective handed down to us by our forbears? In a
word, what should development work undertaken Christianly look like in our
present radically-pluralized yet still contentious world? For instance, it
is no longer tenable to divide our globe into the discrete, packaged categories
of east/west, north/south, developed/developing, secular/religious or Christian/Muslim.
The demographic terrain defies such – with Bradford, England boasting
thousands of Muslim residents of Pakistani descent, Amsterdam awash in North
African and Indonesian citizens, those of Japanese descent consti- tuting
a sizeable and influential population group in Sao Paolo, Brazil, and even
a quarter of Saudi Arabia's population comprised of foreign workers. And,
of course, virtually everyone is aware of the technological interconnect-
edness of our world today. One can simultaneously teleconference with several
parties situated at the four corners of the globe, receive emailed contracts
and return them within a matter of minutes (thereby sealing a deal across
continents), view a Hollywood (or Bollywood) movie in the evening in Kiev – one only just released earlier that afternoon a continent away, and transfer
funds to a vendor of a Chinese computer program who runs his business out
of Beijing – downloading the program and installing it all in the same
movement. In sum, not only have we turned into a `global village' à la Marshall
McLuhan, but trends and information sweep across the face of the world at
such a rate that one notable author has taken to describing our spherical
planet as actually `flat' (Friedman, 2005) – meaning that large-scale
homogenization has smoothed down and blurred cultural and socio-political
not to mention economic differences in a way previously unimaginable. Yet,
this coming together has not brought us together. Wars, terror, misun- derstanding
and division seem at an all-time high. And since very little cannot be instantaneously
broadcast anymore, cartoons published in Copenhagen can prompt riots in Karachi
and policies adopted in the USA are just as likely to cause
69
acts
of terror in Mumbai, Bali or Yemen as in London, Oklahoma City or New York.
It is widely held that this past century – the Enlightenment century
par excellence – has been the bloodiest century in recorded history.3
Part of the problem can be found within the very architecture of Enlightenment
rationality itself. Lesslie Newbigin explores the arbitrary firewall modern
society erects between what might be called the private/value domain and the
public/ fact domain.4 It seems that in modernist thinking, `facts' function
in the public realm whereas `values' are consigned to operate only within
the private. Thus, in the public realm, when one runs into seemingly contradictory
features (say, decid- ing whether something is white or black), it is only
proper to `argue, experiment, carry out tests, and compare results, until
we finally agree on what the facts are; and we expect all reasonable people
to accept them ... ' (Newbigin, 1989: 16) (since nothing can be both black
and white at the same time). However, a process akin to this does not obtain
for the private world of val- ues, a realm where conceptual pluralism of the
deepest sort reigns. Provided one keeps private values private, rational contradiction
and incommensurable views are allowed to be incompatible in the private sphere,
without causing us a bit of cognitive dissonance. This is true since the last
remaining universally embraced value left within the public sphere is an adamant
prohibition against publicly questioning others' values (Newbigin, 1989: 19).5
Obviously, such an arrangement exhibits a deep self-referential problem, since
we end up with a value operating in the public realm as required in order
to restrict additional val- ues from going public – for, even the prohibition
against airing values in public is itself an airing of values in public. Moreover,
keeping those pesky `values' domesticated to the private realm is never as
easy as first assumed since heart- felt values tend to (re-)assert themselves
at the most inconvenient times and in the most unexpected places (such as
on the streets of Paris during riots, or in uncontrolled debates over the
Internet). Further complicating matters – according to Jürgen Habermas – is the fact that such an arrangement actually brooks little space for the
`public sphere' to thrive in a healthy manner outside of control of the state.
Consequently, val- ues no longer are hammered out in public (since a `secular'
value system ends up smuggled in and given preference under the guise of its
neutrality). This configuration permits late global capitalism the opportunity
to exploit com- mercial mass media, thereby shriveling value discourse away
and replacing it with instrumentalist bureaucratic and technological rationalism.
Such a move leaves people with little public role besides competing for the
state's attention, resources and largesse, with nary a chance of shaping the
state and its policies. Civil society simply atrophies.6 Aside from the ill
effects this has had upon public discourse and value delib- eration, and besides
the difficulty it poses for any sincere attempt to publicly bear witness to
the Christian faith, a muddled view of truth of this sort ipso facto throws
all substantive debate concerning development into question. After all, what
is development if it is not an attempt to grapple with and work toward ultimate
images of good? Development, itself, is reduced to a technocrat's exer- cise,
with the value load inevitably assumed muting all discussion as to what this
`good' actually should be. So, the Enlightenment program is in peril – and, with it, all structures and mecha- nisms dependent upon its demarcations,
inclusive of the entities we establish as conduits for our own development
work. We now can see that secular organizations
70
(including
those deemed `development organizations') are not neutral structures; instead,
they induce and institutionalize the privatization and belittling of all public
faith and deep-value dialogue. While it is true that persons of faith can
participate in these, participants must play by the public/private, value/fact
rules, giving a final nod to the governing `secular canopy' in place, complete
with all of its constraints. While one may discuss certain `liberal' values,
such as anti-corruption (honesty, transparency) or democracy (representation
of interests, consultation, openness), the discussion must remain sufficiently
vague so as to avoid tying the points into values carrying any real mandate
for specific change. Such a position obviously runs counter to the very specific
message of the gospel, tied as it is into the specific visitation of God in
Jesus of Nazareth. Somehow we need organizational structures that permit the
broadcast of such a specific narrative, but one that is not so tied to the
value-attenuating rules of Enlightenment strictures. The Viability of Christian
Development Agencies in Today's Interconnected World Probably in part based
upon this outlined dilemma, Christians in development have customarily established
distinctively Christian organizations, ones promising open discussion, consideration
and propagation of the Christian faith position. The hope seems to be that
this will create space for the Christian development worker – space
where the above threats and difficulties seem not to be as acutely felt. Also,
it is thought, testimony and witness to the faith will thereby be made possible.
But, with the appearance of the Christian development agency as institution
of choice in answering this dilemma, other challenges loom large – especially in the milieu of today's world as described earlier. It will help
us to look at these briefly, one by one. In today's global climate, there
is a prevailing anti-Christian bias latent within many alternate faiths and
world view systems (inter alia, Islam, nationalist move- ments, and even secularism,
as described earlier.) We first must recognize that some of this anti- bias
has been of our own making, i.e. the fruit of the way the Christian community
over the years has tied itself to colonialism and inequitable power structures.
Little wonder that persons from other faith traditions have often viewed us
with a jaundiced eye, skeptical of our intentions and our modes of operation.
At the same time, though, it also is true that a bit of this bias often amounts
to simple prejudiced opposition, the sort of hostility Jesus warned his followers
they would face as a matter of course (see Matt. 5:11–12). The gospel
is an upside- down message – one that runs counter to typical worldly
systems. It should no longer surprise us when we run headlong into it. So,
irrespective of the reason, its engendering source or its legitimacy, predis-
posed anti-Christian bias is out there. And, since the world currently is
such a flat, small, global place, gaining entry into the many regions where
the bias obtains is becoming increasingly difficult, to say the least. Nation-states
are closing borders and the breakdown of the old colonialist structures (which
historically helped to bring about the distrust) means that foreigners find
it very difficult to be invited into lands suspicious of their motives. Moreover,
even when gaining entry, establishing credibility with local per- sons often
proves an extremely difficult thing for a Christian foreign national to do – since the Christian structures which serve as our conduits so readily draw
boundaries around us, signing an `us/them' configuration to those we encoun-
ter. In other words, our structures connote – from the beginning – that we are
71
exclusively
different from these persons, with little points of commonality. This inevitably
and consequently alienates them from any invitation to entertain the gospel
message right from the start, since following Jesus ends up defined as a membership
activity in a foreign organization or institution.7 Second (and complicating
matters further), we are confronted with the fact that the boundaries of our
Christian structures seem to buttress and confirm certain overarching ideologies
and religious perspectives that are predisposed against the Christian message,
often not due to history or previous experience, but instead as a part of
internal hard-wiring subsumed under local religious world views, so to speak.
What I am speaking of here are those ideologies and world view systems whose
internal logic runs directly counter to integral portions of the gospel mes-
sage itself.8 By way of example we can look at Islam: as a global faith, it
is decid- edly anti-incarnational as a part of its self-identity – speaking of a god who became human is theologically dismissed a priori. This
being the case, it seems rather self- defeating to begin dialogue based centrally
upon points of theology and religious belief – since we often begin
with the very points our dialogue partners are so in opposition to. And, this
is precisely what we do if we mark our identity through institutional membership,
membership that enshrines theological allegiance as its primary defining characteristic.
Surely, there must be a better way. I believe there is a better way, one whose
contours we shall explore later. Before that exploration, though, it is perhaps
helpful to note in passing that cer- tain specialists in the field of development – persons exhibiting no particular affiliation with Christianity or any other
world religion – are now calling for increased consideration of and
respect for religious perspectives. For instance, Katherine Marshall from
the World Bank, in an address given to the Conference on Religious NGOs and
Development Institutions in Oslo, Norway in April 2005, calls for the World
Bank to be willing and prepared to work with faith-based non-governmental
organizations (NGOs) of a variety of types and foci (Marshall, 2005). It seems
that Marshall – and others like her –9 are beginning to realize
that grassroots development attempts that bypass considerations of religion
and faith allegiance not only put the development organization out of step
with most resi- dents in tradition-based societies (since to sideline religion
in contexts like these is to sideline local world views), it also denies these
same organizations access to conceptual resources often religious in nature – such as a religiously-funded will- ingness to deny self, to sacrifice, and
to commit to works of integrity and loyalty at great personal expense. With
such awareness more and more evident on the part of the World Bank and other
global agencies such as this, it behooves us to find structures best suited
to step into this ever-widening gap. In Search of Models Offering Opportunity
for Collegiality, Empowerment and Witness Realizing and even leveraging off
of the conceptual bankruptcy of the Enlightenment program and its accompanying
institutions, we now may give our attention to fashioning a renewed mindset
with accompanying conduits. These institutions could help us learn to work
together with (willing) persons of other faiths and world views, in a manner
respectful of both their position and ours. These could be structures that
allow partnership, but which also do not compro- mise the need for participants
to give witness to their beliefs as they engage in authentic grass-roots development
empowerment. The sort of mechanisms I envi- sion will not be secular in nature
(since, as we have seen, that modernist form is
72
Figure
1: The S1–S6 Continuum replete with downsides and pitfalls); neither
will it be Christian, since the fencing off that these sorts of structures
requires demarcates too severely to be of use in the climate we face these
days. I have labeled my proposed conduit an `S4' model. Its contours become
more obvious as we explore Figure 1,1 0 reviewing, compar- ing and contrasting
it with the other varieties on offer. The first thing to notice in this grid
is the top row. Listed there are designa- tions borrowed from the late missiologist
Paul Hiebert,11 who noted that in set theory, sets can be categorized as either
bounded or centered in nature.12 A bounded set is a normal in/out grouping – those outside the boundaries of the set are not members of the set. In Figure
1, boundedness would indicate persons claiming membership within the Christian
faith or those outside the Christian faith. In opposition to bounded sets,
membership in a centered set is determined not by the set member 's location
within boundaries, but rather by the member 's relationship to and direction
toward (or away from) the center. Hiebert explains it well: ... A centered
set is created by defining the center or reference point and the relationship
of things to that center. Things related to the center belong to the set,
and those not related to the center do not ... Second, while centered sets
are not created by drawing boundaries, they do have sharp boundaries that
separate things inside the set from those out- side it – between things
related to or moving toward the center and those that are not. Centered sets
are well-formed, just like bounded sets. They are formed by defining the center
and any relationships to it. The bound- ary then emerges automatically. Things
related to the center naturally separate themselves from things that are not
...
73
Third,
there are two variables intrinsic to centered sets. The first is mem- bership.
All members of a set are full members and share fully in its func- tions.
There are not second-class members. The second variable is distance from the
center. Some things are far from the center and others near to it, but all
are moving toward it ... Fourth, centered sets have two types of change inherent
in their structure. The first has to do with entry into or exit from the set.
Things headed away from the center can turn and move toward it ... The second
type of change has to do with movement toward or away from the center. Distant
members can move toward the center, and those near can slide back while still
herded toward it ... (Hiebert, 1994: 123–4, emphasis added) Thus, as
represented in our graph, centered-set membership indicates not so much where
one is positioned in terms of being in or out of Christianity, but instead,
it points to one's direction and movement toward relationship with God through
Jesus Christ. In other words, using our example of development structures,
a bounded set can be illustrated by organizational membership in a Christian
development agency – one is either a member or not, a worker or not,
a Christian or not. Membership in a centered set development organization,
in contrast, would be defined by what the members of the organization were
try- ing to accomplish, what they were trying to do, who they were trying
to please. These organizations would more be constituted by way of their everyday
praxis and ongoing activities – what they were becoming and the long-term
goals they embraced. As shown by our following example, this will result in
organizations focused upon doing a particular style of grass-roots development
work, work that serves as forms of worship to God who wishes for it to be
undertaken. This brief explanation of set theory assists us in understanding
the categories of the grid described in greater detail below. We now may turn
our attention to the different types of structures,1 3 or organizational types
represented in Figure 1 – appraising how each type might assist us
in development work under- taken in today's radically pluralized context.
Advocating an S4 Model S1 represents a classic church group or denomination
attempting to do develop- ment work – utilizing structures intimately
attached to the church and its image. Thus, the language of the church, primary
allegiance to it as institutional home, funding from its coffers, and overt
witness closely tied to its purposes are defin- ing characteristics of this
model. In the American context, organizations such as Church World Service,
Episcopal Relief and Development or the United Methodist General Board of
Global Ministries are examples here. S2 and S3 organizations represent the
likes of World Vision, Habitat for Humanity or the Tear network in the UK,
Australia, New Zealand, the Netherlands, etc. – with the nature of
their identity depending a great deal upon toward which constituency they
attempt to posture themselves. These organizations are S2 as they focus toward
resources and funding obtained from the `church' or the `sending' world, whereas
S3 represents, for instance, when World Vision advertises in Time magazine
(note that, even there, such an organization demarcates itself as an explicitly
Christian organi- zation – thus, its `bounded set' identity). S1–S3,
as bounded-set institutions, gener- ally only employ Christians and they reserve
positions of leadership for Christians.
74
S5 models
launched as such are probably somewhat rare – simply due to the fact
that opportunities for initiating these are hard to come by. Such a model
is illustrated by a group of Christians covenanting together for the purpose
of gain- ing employment at, for instance, a national World Bank office, a
USAID, AusAid or GTZ office, or even at a local water sanitation project in-country.
These folk are still collective, but they undertake this witness communally
in a `secular' context (thus their Christian activities and witness must be
privatized – given the nature of the secular context for this type
of organization, wherein our earlier analysis of the Enlightenment-, modernist-inspired
division of private and public space arises in full force). S6 is where a
Christian takes up employment at any of the S5 sort of organiza- tions described
above, but this time as a solitary individual, not as a part of a col- lective.
Primarily due to this solitary nature, S6 witness – admirable though
it is – struggles with effectiveness.1 4 In fact, due to this, it often
happens that as various S6 individuals became acquainted with each other within
a `secular' organization, they frequently form collectives along the lines
of S5 groupings.1 5 Against such a backdrop, S4 begins to look different.
First, by taking upon itself a `centered-set' witness focus, it calls to work
within its structure anyone who possesses a desire to strive for the betterment
of poor populations, irrespective of the religious vision or grand world view
the person embraces.1 6 In the case of an institution of this sort operating
in an Islamic context, for instance, Muslims and Christians join forces, with
the latter afforded the opportunity to witness to the former – but,
of course, witness could (and probably would) flow in the reverse direction
as well (more on that below). Second, the collective gathering (or koinonia)
structure toward that the believers would be working is either housed within
the `wineskin' or structure of the NGO or is equal to the NGO (thus, it is
still centered-set in nature). This is what is meant by the term `NGO/A-church'.
A defining characteristic of an S4 organization is, as a religious organization
(but not one promoting a specific religion), all individuals involved within
it see `work as worship', though obviously what this worship entails and its
qualities is approached from different perspectives, based upon dialogue (and
this is where witness and evangelism in dialogue openly takes place).1 7 Thus,
from within the framework of an S4 organization, we as Christians are afforded
the opportunity to explain our faith without seeming to wander outside that
which we are expected to do as development practitioners (this witness can
most directly and poignantly be offered to our co-workers, persons holding
to a different religious paradigm but who are attempting work similar in goals).
In addition, by way of this model we can see why the other models might not
prom- ise as much in terms of robust witness, since from within these one
is forced to choose between `bounded-set' and `fuzzy-set' stances – postures which either seal us off into ghettoized, fenced-off cloisters (where
we are watched and censored so as to keep us from trespassing the boundaries)
or which rob us of our distinctive- ness in terms of identity and witness
(by way of privatizing our faith and secular- izing our activities). A Brief
Look at an S4 Example So, can such a model work? In spite of the theoretical
plausibility, is it actually feasible to establish such an organization in
a real place with real people? Based upon my own experience involved in an
S4 organization in Indonesia over a 10-year period of time, I am happy to
report that not only is an S4 institution
75
possible,
it has actually been carried out with a good deal of success, in a manner
giving credibility to its benefits as described here. Our S4 institution was
a NGO that focused upon community empowerment work in various, distinct sectors:
primary health care, microfinance, agricultural extension, local community
advocacy, handicrafts import and export, and after- school educational programs.
The by-laws of our NGO were based upon two pri- mary tenets, ones which undergirded
all of our operations: (1) we committed to focus our attention and programs
upon the marginalized and neglected, and (2) we intentionally viewed our attempts
at empowerment as acts of worship, ones we discursively appraised together
as an intentionally pluralistic community. We explicitly recruited workers
from the two major religious faiths in Indonesia (those Muslim as well as
Christian), inviting all participants to be open and expressive of their faith
position, while at the same time challenging them to learn to purposely listen
to differing opinions and beliefs embraced by those representing other posi-
tions in our community.1 8 As a part of this invitation, we embraced the principle
that all truth was God's truth and, as such, its contours would be obvious
to us as we discussed our different views in community. In short, we challenged
all in our midst to humbly listen to each other, stating our beliefs in clear
and undiluted fashion, trusting that God would lead us into truth as we humbly
sought it out together. As we became more practiced in this process over time,
we got better at it – walls came down and the depths of how we believed
were shared. And, for those of us Christians in the NGO, it became easier
to rely upon the fact that such a position echoed Jesus' words in the Gospel
of John, that as one waits upon the Spirit's guidance, he will lead the believer
into all truth.1 9 As tangible examples of how this played out, I will cite
two representative events – one related to the Muslim 30-day fast month
known as Ramadan, the second linked to an ongoing curriculum designed to cultivate
collective delibera- tion in our NGO concerning our differing religious perspectives
and the ongoing implementation of our programs. One particular year, each
Tuesday over the course of the four weeks of the fast month, we gathered to
explore religious perspectives and, afterward, to break the fast together – an event that was designed primarily by the Muslim workers in our organization.
For the opening discussion, two questions were posed by the moderator (who
was our Human Resources Director): (1) Why do you fast? and (2) How do you
see work as worship? The first week, two representative Muslim co-workers
shared their perspectives related to these questions; the second week, Christian
staff members shared from their perspective, the third week, expatriate staff
offered their perspectives, and the fourth and last week, as Coordinator and
thus senior staff member for the NGO, I shared my own perspective. Obviously,
as we all shared answers to these two questions, considerations of the gospel
often took center stage, as we compared and contrasted these with normal prac-
tices in grassroots development work and with Muslim perspectives pertaining
to these. As Christians, we were able to point to the deeply theological reasons
we were engaged in this work – points that were received thoughtfully
and with serious consideration. We sensed no discomfort or discord, simply
honest interest and a desire to understand each other. This was very different
compared to the customary atmosphere in Indonesia at those times when Muslims
and Christians found themselves discussing differing religious perspectives.
The second, representative case revolved around a discursive training program
that we maintained over the course of our work. Every two weeks – on
a Friday
76
afternoon
after the Muslim weekly prayer event that week – we gathered as an
NGO to talk about various topics related to our work; a different person from
the organization was slated to lead the discussion each time, after being
given oppor- tunity to research the area weeks in advance. Subject matter
such as `Gender Issues and Development', or `The True Nature of Participation',
or `Specious vs. Authentic Pluralism', or various other comparable themes,
constituted the items brought forward for discussion. Inevitably, as each
discussion leader guided us through the time together, various views and perspectives
were explored – ones amply interlaced and even fraught with religious
points of view. Provided the Christians among us could articulate the theological
load and nuance of our per- spectives as they related to the issue at hand,
it gave us the opportunity to fully share the message of the gospel and its
implications. A good many other planned events in addition to these two representative
exam- ples became available to us over the course of our work. And, of course,
as we worked together in such a centered-set style NGO, innumerable spontaneous
and informal occasions for discussion presented themselves to us as we engaged
in our S4 work with our Muslim colleagues. These were opportunities of deep
sharing which would simply have not been possible within a Christian organization
or a secular one. Summarizing the Benefits of S4 Now that prospects for deep
level development work, for peace-making and for witness to the Christian
faith are more readily before us, it seems that the time might be ripe for
us to make concerted efforts toward fashioning bona fide S4 development organizations.
As one looks more closely at the model as we have above, its benefits become
clear, especially as we remember the globally linked, highly secularized,
`flat' world climate we now inhabit: 1 S4 structures allow for legitimate,
integrated identity as development workers as we go about our lives in community.
With this, a holistic and integrated approach to witness and community empowerment
can be maintained, one which need not betray nor disappoint anyone by claiming
to be secular while still carrying out religious activities that, in that
framework, irt dangerously with proselytization. 2 S4 structures
make space for witness and religious identity before co-workers of different
religions as well as before secular on-lookers – without a `cloak and
dagger' approach of posing as one thing (a development worker) but appearing
to be another (a missionary or evangelist). Kingdom-oriented (Christian) development
workers are precisely who they say they are – since they have so woven
their faith perspective into their work that simply going about it, day-to-day,
in the presence of co-workers of other faiths gives testimony to the content
of their beliefs. Holistic evangelization and witness happens as a matter
of course, as they work. Such a posture is full of integrity and thereby reduces
the likelihood the Christian worker will be seen as merely acting to `Christianize'.
3 S4 structures serve as a sort of institutional umbrella – what sociologist
Peter Berger calls a `plausibility structure' – enabling the birth
of small group-style fellowships under their umbrellas. These small groups
can be birthed without extraction of persons from their communities and they
are engendered in the midst of robust social involvement that campaigns toward
justice. 4 S4 structures allow for a larger pool of potential workers for
the development organization – since we need not hire from an exclusively
Christian pool of candidates. No longer are we left trying to choose between
faithful Christians with little development knowledge, skills and potential,
and Christians with development knowledge but who possess little maturity
of character. And since we may speak openly about our theological funding
and its ethical and personal requirements
77
(in
dialogue with all members of the organization), we may be clear what sort
of character qualities we require on the part of potential co-workers. If
it turns out that non-Christians consistently exhibit those qualities, we
hire them, holding them to the standards of our biblically-inspired model.
5 S4 structures are true to the gospel mandate (centered as they are on development
work and, thus, works of kingdom manifestation and poverty alleviation). This
is the case since S4 groupings are conceptually funded by holistic witness – they authentically aim at empowerment of the poor and concerns related to
peace and justice. 6 Related to this point, the internal climate of S4 structures
must be based on mutual respect, dialogue and humble listening. Hubristic
bravado and a will to win should be given no space within S4 organizations.
We must remember that, for the Christian, conversion is a gift of God, prompted
by a movement of the Spirit. As E. Stanley Jones reportedly once said, there
is a great difference between being God's witness and being God's lawyer; we are called to tell God's story, not to argue God's case. 19 Thus, the follower
of Jesus simply learns how to announce God's story as found in Jesus and the
way it intersects with his or her story, leaving the results to God's Spirit.
S4 structures take this caution very seriously, letting God give evidence
of his work in our midst as we, his followers, remain faithful to him in work
and worship, taking opportunity to recite his story in community. There is
much in common here with J. H. Bavinck's concept of elenctics, a term he uses
to refer to the Holy Spirit's action of convicting persons of sin (cf. John
16:8).20 Thus, the Christian has no privileged position in this process – something that opens up space for dialogue and mutual respect. With this,
S4 organizations can be havens of peace, dialogue and harmony, while at the
same time serving as venues of lively discussion and mutual understanding.
Clearly, S4 organizations offer an alternative to the secular as well as to
the Christian development organization models. At first, S4 organizations
will not be readily understood by the majority in our secularized, Enlightenment-steeped
settings – including those from the Church. But, that should not discourage
us, since the benefits they promise – especially when seen in light
of the problems of our present secularized age – certainly outweigh
the consequent confusion they prompt and the explanation they without doubt
require. A final comment needs to be made about the style of development work
best suited to these S4 organizations. Grassroots, empowerment styles of intervention
unquestionably best fit the S4 model described here. This is primarily due
to the fact that the `deep grammar' or `methodological style' of many grass-roots,
par- ticipatory methods seem to mirror the movement that is at the heart of
the gospel message, a movement which shows that when God wished to help the
human race in all of its poverty, he incarnated in our midst – as Eugene
Peterson says in The Message, Jesus `moved into the neighborhood' (John 1:14).
What we are in search of are interventions that mimic the life and trajectory
of Jesus, ones that allow us to have the same mind `that was in Christ Jesus'
(Phil. 2:5) who, `though he was in the form of God, did not regard equality
with God as something to be exploited, but emptied himself, taking the form
of a slave ... ' (Phil. 2:6–7). The sort of development styles that
can (and should) be proffered and pro- moted in S4 organizations are types
which require development practitioners to go about their work humbly, with
simplicity, building rapport over time in local neighborhoods of privation.
Methods similar to Robert Chambers' `Participatory Rural Appraisal' probably
best fit the S4 model –2 1 since, by promoting this sort of style,
Christians and non-Christians alike can work side-by-side attempting to implement
it – and then, talk about it in community afterwards.2 2
78
It
is my contention that if the gospel is true (and I believe it is!), and if
the Holy Spirit truly embodies and empowers his people to do works of the
kingdom (and I believe he does!), then these two facts can combine to cause
Christians to shine before their already sympathetic non-Christian co-workers,
prompting questions related to how such quality and level of work consistently
flow from us over time. These, of course, are questions we surely would like
to entertain – these are elenc- tic moments, born of dialogue and humility.
Best of all, both questions asked as well as answers provided can find their
genesis in the style and type of develop- ment work we as Christians are doing.
S4 structures allow for that type of conflu- ence of message and task, since
they require the work to be undertaken side-by- side with those who share
our aspirations, but who do not yet know our secret. We would like to let
them in on the secret, wouldn't we? With S4 structures, we not only announce
the secret, we get the privilege of dramatizing it before a very sympathetic
audience, day-in and day-out.
Bibliography
Backues, Lindy
(forthcoming) The Incarnation as Motif for Development Practice in
World Mission in a Wesleyan Spirit, edited by Darrell L. Whiteman and Gerald H. Anderson. Nashville, TN: Providence House .
Bavinck, Johan Herman
(1960) An Introduction to the Science of Missions.
Philadelphia, PA: The Presbyterian and
Reformed Publishing Company.
Bauman, Zygmunt
(2001) Modernity and the Holocaust. Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press.
Berger, Peter
(1979) The Heretical Imperative: Contemporary Possibilities
of Religious Affirmation. London: Collins.
Chambers, Robert
(1983) Rural Development Putting the Last First.
Harlow: Addison Wesley Longman.
Chambers, Robert
(1994a) `The Origins and Practice of Participatory Rural
Appraisal', World Development 22(7): 953-69.
Chambers, Robert
(1994b) `Participatory Rural Appraisal (PRA): Analysis
of Experience', World Development 22(9): 1253-68.
Chambers, Robert
(1994c) `Participatory Rural Appraisal (PRA): Challenges,
Potentials and Paradigm', World Development 22(10): 1437-54.
Chambers, Robert
(1997) Whose Reality Counts? Putting the First Last.
London: Intermediate Technology Publications .
Clouser, Roy A.
(1991) The Myth of Religious Neutrality: An Essay on the
Hidden Role of Religious Belief in Theories. South Bend,
IN: University of Notre Dame Press.
Daneel, Marthinus L.
(2005) `Liberative Ecumenism at the African Grassroots' , in Marthinus L. Daneel, Charles Van Engen and Hendrik
Vroom (eds) Fullness of Life For All: Challenges for Mission
in Early 21st Century, pp. 295-327. Amsterdam: Rodopi.
Friedman, Thomas L.
(2005) The World Is Flat: A Brief History of the Twenty-First
Century. New York: Farrar, Straus
and Giroux.
Habermas, Jürgen
(1989) The Structural Transformation of the Public Sphere,
trans. Thomas Burger assisted by Frederick Lawrence. Cambridge : Polity Press.
Hiebert, Paul G.
(1978) `Conversion, Culture and Cognitive Categories' , Gospel in Context 4: 24-9.
Hiebert, Paul G.
(1979) `Sets and Structures: A Study of Church Patterns' , in David J. Hesselgrave (ed.)
New Horizons in World Missions, pp. 217-27. Grand Rapids,
MI : Baker Book House.
Hiebert, Paul G. ( 1985) Anthropological Insights for Missionaries. Grand Rapids, MI: Baker Book House.
Hiebert, Paul G.
(1994) Anthropological Reflections on Missiological Issues . Grand Rapids, MI: Baker Book
House .
Holenstein, Anne-Marie
(2005) Role and Significance of Religion and Spirituality
in Development Co-operation: A Reflection and Working Paper. Bern: Swiss Agency for Development and Co-operation,
March.
79
Kirk, J. Andrew
(2000) What Is Mission? Theological Explorations.
Minneapolis, MN: Fortress Press.
Marsden, George M.
(1982) Fundamentalism and American Culture: The Shaping
of Twentieth-Century Evangelicalism, 1870-1925. New York : Oxford University Press.
Marsden, George M.
(1991) Understanding Fundamentalism and Evangelicalism . rand Rapids, MI: Wm. B. Eerdmans
Publishing Company.
Marshall, Katherine
(2005) Faith and Development: Rethinking Development Debates . Washington, DC: World Bank.
Myers, Bryant L.
(1999) Walking with the Poor: Principles and Practices
of Transformational Development. Maryknoll, NY:
Orbis Books.
Newbigin, Lesslie
(1986) Foolishness to the Greeks: The Gospel and Western
Culture. London: SPCK.
Newbigin, Lesslie
(1989) The Gospel in a Pluralist Society. Grand Rapids, MI: Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Company .
Noll, Mark A.
(1995) The Scandal of the Evangelical Mind. Grand Rapids, MI: Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Company .
Polanyi, Michael
(1958) Personal Knowledge: Towards a Postcritical Philosophy . London: Routledge &amp; Kegan
Paul.
Travis, John
(1998) `Must all Muslims leave Islam to follow Jesus?' , Evangelical Missions Quarterly 34(4): 411-15.
Travis, John
(2000) `Messianic Muslim Followers of Isa: A Closer Look
at C5 Believers and Congregations', International Journal
of Frontier Missions 17(1): 53-9.
Travis, John
and Travis, Anna
(2005) `Appropriate Approaches in Muslim Contexts',
in Charles H. Kraft (ed.) Appropriate
Christianity, pp. 397-414. Pasadena, CA: William
Carey Library.
Volf, Miroslav
(1996) Exclusion and Embrace: A Theological Exploration
of Identity, Otherness, and Reconciliation. Nashville,
TN: Abingdon Press.
Wolterstorff, Nicholas
(1984) Reason Within the Bounds of Religion. Grand Rapids, MI: Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Company .
Notes
1 The fundamentalist-modernist
controversy in the US is one source of this suspicion (see Marsden, 1982,
1991).
2 Noll (1995) describes
the overall intellectual abdication of Evangelicals in the US during the
course of the 20th century, resulting in a surrendering of the public sphere
in the process to classical theological liberalism as well as to an overall
secularist world view.
3 Sociologist Zygmunt Bauman
(2001) makes the case that precisely the self-assured Enlightenment world
of modernity made possible the Holocaust, by enabling the normal trappings
of modernity and its emphasis on processing, production, control and a resulting
dehumanizing mindset.
4 See Newbigin (1986, 1989).
Much of Newbigin's intellectual funding for these points comes by way of
philosopher Michael Polanyi. See especially Polanyi's (1958). For a similar
exploration of these sorts of epistemological issues, see Wolterstorff (1984)
and Clouser (1991).
5 Sociologist Peter Berger
(1979) puts forward a similar thesis.
6 For a deeper look into
this process, see Habermas (1989).
7 In language reminiscent
of Miroslav Volf, we will regretfully arise before them as signs, not of
embrace, but of exclusion; see Volf (1996).
8 Before we frame this
as a problem for non-Christian faith systems alone, we should admit that
the same can often be said about a wide variety of more fundamentalist Christian
positions. However, exploring the nature of that problem here would take
us away from our central topic.
9 See Holenstein (2005).
10 I must admit familiarity
with a similar sort of matrix, the C1—C6 Continuum, which has been
utilized to classify and categorize church planting styles in reference to
unreached, majority religion people groups (primarily, but not exclusively, 80those
Islamic in nature). While the taxonomy presented here is similar (in that
there are also six points on our continuum as well), the reader will notice
that our `S1—S6 Continuum' points to a completely different phenomenon.
For a look at the C1—C6 Continuum, see Travis (1998, 2000; Travis and
Travis, 2005).
11 See Paul G. Hiebert (1978,
1979, 1985, 1994).
12 Though they are a third
possibility, fuzzy sets are not as heuristically helpful for our purposes
here. This is the case since they are not strictly binary — delineated
as `in' or `out'. On the contrary, membership within these `sets' is less
easily determined, since they are based upon vaguely defined limits with
no clear boundaries.
13 `S' stands for `structure'
here.
14 This definition of `effectivness'
is a purely sociological one, and I use this perspective to challenge the
readers to think in new ways. It is, of course, the case that a holistic
view of `effectiveness' would take into account the nature of each individual's
calling and how God uses that person in ways that are beyond our understanding
and capacity to measure in those terms.
15 One should note that these
latter two types of organizations are `fuzzy-set' in nature, since by definition
a collective witness is not allowed in the structures and organizations containing
them.
16 It must be recognized
that S4 organizations do not exclude persons embracing secularized world views.
The only requirement — the same requirement holding for all participants — is that the secular individual may not demand the privileged conceptual position
of neutrality that has historically been his or her privilege in the conventional
secularist paradigm. In the S4 model, a secular world view must be treated
just like all other grand-scale world views (whether overtly religious or
non-religious in nature); persons embracing `secularism' take part in the
community of dialogue with respect for others' perspectives precisely as
must all participants.
17. This sort of an organization
would need to embrace a theology of religions that is less filled with fear
and more open to alternative religious and conceptual contributions deriving
from other religions — without falling prey to a universalistic watering
down of the core of the gospel message. In other words, in a centered set
organization, the center would need to hold: that center being Jesus. For
conceptual assistance in deriving a biblically-based theology of witness in
the midst of theological pluralism, see Kirk (2000). For a type of case study
of S4-related work similar to that I describe here, see Daneel (2005).
18 Not only did this cross-perspective
dialogue bridge divides between Christianity and Islam, it also served the
same function for a variety of intra-faith discussions. For instance, we
enthusiastically welcomed participants from the controversial Ahmadiyya movement
as part of our fold; historically, Ahmadiyya has often been regarded by the
wider Islamic community as wayward concerning certain articles of the worldwide
Islamic faith. Nonetheless, it was our experience that Muslims in our group
from more `orthodox' streams of Islam, over time, learned how to listen to
and respect those from within Ahmadiyya, making space for them as coworkers
focused on assisting the poor.
19 We hear the following
from Jesus in John 16:12—15: `I still have many things to say to you,
but you cannot bear them now. When the Spirit of truth comes, he will guide
you into all the truth; for he will not speak on his own, but will speak
whatever he hears, and he will declare to you the things that are to come.
He will glorify me, because he will take what is mine and declare it to you.
All that the Father has is mine. For this reason I said that he will take
what is mine and declare it to you'.
20 In the process of telling
God's story, we must learn to communicate the manner in which our story fits
into that overarching, grand narrative story. That `story telling' is the
essence of the evangelistic task.
21 Cf. Bavinck (1960).
`The term “elenctic” is derived from the Greek verb elengchein
. In Homer the verb has the meaning of `to bring to shame'. It is connected
with the word elengchos that signifies shame. In later Attic Greek
the significance of the 81term underwent a certain change so that the
emphasis fell more upon the conviction of guilt, the demonstration of guilt.
It is this latter significance that it has in the New Testament. Its meaning
is entirely ethical and religious' (Bavnick, 1960: 221). Bavinck (1960: 229)
later goes on to describe the mechanics of elenctics in the following way:
` ... We must emphasize that the subject of elenctics is in the deepest sense
the Holy Spirit. He alone can call to repentance and we are only means in
his hand. This truth is also of tremendous importance with respect to the
basis of elenctics. It is the Holy Spirit himself who creates a basis. He
awakens in man that deeply hidden awareness of guilt. He convinces man of
sin, even where previously no consciousness of sin was apparently present.
The Holy Spirit uses the word of the preacher and touches the heart of the
hearer, making it accessible to the word. If elenctics were only a human
activity, the situation would be nearly hopeless. But it is much more, infinitely
more. Now this certain knowledge that the Holy Spirit is the true author,
ought not to give us any excuse to shirk our duty or to take our work any
less seriously. On the contrary, the Holy Spirit demands of us a true and
complete surrender to the task he has assigned to us, and it is only after
we have so yielded that he will use us as his instruments. With anything less,
we can accomplish nothing. But, this knowledge gives us the comfort that
in the last instance the results do not depend upon our weak powers, but
that it is the Holy Spirit who would make us powerful in Christ'.
22 For insight into `Participatory
Rural Appraisal', see Robert Chambers (1983, 1994a,b,c, 1997). For an intentionally
Christian look at development practices `incarnational' in type, see Myers
(1999).
23 For a more complete
consideration of the development style referred to here, see Backues (forthcoming).</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-wrap>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <notes>
         <p>
            <list list-type="order">
               <list-item>
                  <p>1 The fundamentalist-modernist controversy in the US is one source of this suspicion (see Marsden, 1982, 1991).</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>2 Noll (1995) describes the overall intellectual abdication of Evangelicals in the US during the course of the 20th century, resulting in a surrendering of the public sphere in the process to classical theological liberalism as well as to an overall secularist world view.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>3 Sociologist Zygmunt Bauman (2001) makes the case that precisely the self-assured Enlightenment world of modernity made possible the Holocaust, by enabling the normal trappings of modernity and its emphasis on processing, production, control and a resulting dehumanizing mindset.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>4 See Newbigin (1986, 1989). Much of Newbigin's intellectual funding for these points comes by way of philosopher Michael Polanyi. See especially Polanyi's (1958). For a similar exploration of these sorts of epistemological issues, see Wolterstorff (1984) and Clouser (1991).</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>5 Sociologist Peter Berger (1979) puts forward a similar thesis.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>6 For a deeper look into this process, see Habermas (1989).</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>7 In language reminiscent of Miroslav Volf, we will regretfully arise before them as signs, not of embrace, but of exclusion; see Volf (1996).</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>8 Before we frame this as a problem for non-Christian faith systems alone, we should admit that the same can often be said about a wide variety of more fundamentalist Christian positions. However, exploring the nature of that problem here would take us away from our central topic.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>9 See Holenstein (2005).</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>10 I must admit familiarity with a similar sort of matrix, the C1—C6 Continuum, which has been utilized to classify and categorize church planting styles in reference to unreached, majority religion people groups (primarily, but not exclusively, those Islamic in nature). While the taxonomy presented here is similar (in that there are also six points on our continuum as well), the reader will notice that our `S1—S6 Continuum' points to a completely different phenomenon. For a look at the C1—C6 Continuum, see Travis (1998, 2000; Travis and Travis, 2005).</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>11 See Paul G. Hiebert (1978, 1979, 1985, 1994).</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>12 Though they are a third possibility, fuzzy sets are not as heuristically helpful for our purposes here. This is the case since they are not strictly binary — delineated as `in' or `out'. On the contrary, membership within these `sets' is less easily determined, since they are based upon vaguely defined limits with no clear boundaries.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>13 `S' stands for `structure' here.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>14 This definition of `effectivness' is a purely sociological one, and I use this perspective to challenge the readers to think in new ways. It is, of course, the case that a holistic view of `effectiveness' would take into account the nature of each individual's calling and how God uses that person in ways that are beyond our understanding and capacity to measure in those terms.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>15 One should note that these latter two types of organizations are `fuzzy-set' in nature, since by definition a collective witness is not allowed in the structures and organizations containing them.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>16 It must be recognized that S4 organizations do not exclude persons embracing secularized world views. The only requirement — the same requirement holding for all participants — is that the secular individual may not demand the privileged conceptual position of neutrality that has historically been his or her privilege in the conventional secularist paradigm. In the S4 model, a secular world view must be treated just like all other grand-scale world views (whether overtly religious or non-religious in nature); persons embracing `secularism' take part in the community of dialogue with respect for others' perspectives precisely as must all participants.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>17. This sort of an organization would need to embrace a theology of religions that is less filled with fear and more open to alternative religious and conceptual contributions deriving from other religions — without falling prey to a universalistic watering down of the core of the gospel message. In other words, in a centered set organization, the center would need to hold: that center being Jesus. For conceptual assistance in deriving a biblically-based theology of witness in the midst of theological pluralism, see Kirk (2000). For a type of case study of S4-related work similar to that I describe here, see Daneel (2005).</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>18 Not only did this cross-perspective dialogue bridge divides between Christianity and Islam, it also served the same function for a variety of intra-faith discussions. For instance, we enthusiastically welcomed participants from the controversial Ahmadiyya movement as part of our fold; historically, Ahmadiyya has often been regarded by the wider Islamic community as wayward concerning certain articles of the worldwide Islamic faith. Nonetheless, it was our experience that Muslims in our group from more `orthodox' streams of Islam, over time, learned how to listen to and respect those from within Ahmadiyya, making space for them as coworkers focused on assisting the poor.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>19 We hear the following from Jesus in John 16:12—15: `I still have many things to say to you, but you cannot bear them now. When the Spirit of truth comes, he will guide you into all the truth; for he will not speak on his own, but will speak whatever he hears, and he will declare to you the things that are to come. He will glorify me, because he will take what is mine and declare it to you. All that the Father has is mine. For this reason I said that he will take what is mine and declare it to you'.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>20 In the process of telling God's story, we must learn to communicate the manner in which our story fits into that overarching, grand narrative story. That `story telling' is the essence of the evangelistic task.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>21 Cf. Bavinck (1960). `The term “elenctic” is derived from the Greek verb <italic>elengchein</italic> . In Homer the verb has the meaning of `to bring to shame'. It is connected with the word <italic>elengchos</italic> that signifies shame. In later Attic Greek the significance of the term underwent a certain change so that the emphasis fell more upon the conviction of guilt, the demonstration of guilt. It is this latter significance that it has in the New Testament. Its meaning is entirely ethical and religious' (Bavnick, 1960: 221). Bavinck (1960: 229) later goes on to describe the mechanics of elenctics in the following way: ` ... We must emphasize that the subject of elenctics is in the deepest sense the Holy Spirit. He alone can call to repentance and we are only means in his hand. This truth is also of tremendous importance with respect to the basis of elenctics. It is the Holy Spirit himself who creates a basis. He awakens in man that deeply hidden awareness of guilt. He convinces man of sin, even where previously no consciousness of sin was apparently present. The Holy Spirit uses the word of the preacher and touches the heart of the hearer, making it accessible to the word. If elenctics were only a human activity, the situation would be nearly hopeless. But it is much more, infinitely more. Now this certain knowledge that the Holy Spirit is the true author, ought not to give us any excuse to shirk our duty or to take our work any less seriously. On the contrary, the Holy Spirit demands of us a true and complete surrender to the task he has assigned to us, and it is only after we have so yielded that he will use us as his instruments. With anything less, we can accomplish nothing. But, this knowledge gives us the comfort that in the last instance the results do not depend upon our weak powers, but that it is the Holy Spirit who would make us powerful in Christ'.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>22 For insight into `Participatory Rural Appraisal', see Robert Chambers (1983, 1994a,b,c, 1997). For an intentionally Christian look at development practices `incarnational' in type, see Myers (1999).</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <p>23 For a more complete consideration of the development style referred to here, see Backues (forthcoming).</p>
               </list-item>
            </list>
         </p>
      </notes>
      <ref-list>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Backues, Lindy</surname>
               </name> (forthcoming) <source>The Incarnation as Motif for Development Practice in World Mission in a Wesleyan Spirit</source>, edited by <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Darrell L. Whiteman</surname>
               </name> and <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gerald H. Anderson.</surname>
               </name> 
               <publisher-loc>Nashville, TN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Providence House</publisher-name> .</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Bavinck, Johan Herman</surname>
               </name> (<year>1960</year>) <source>An Introduction to the Science of Missions</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Presbyterian and Reformed Publishing Company</publisher-name>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Bauman, Zygmunt</surname>
               </name> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Modernity and the Holocaust</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Berger, Peter</surname>
               </name> (<year>1979</year>) <source>The Heretical Imperative: Contemporary Possibilities of Religious Affirmation</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Collins</publisher-name>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Chambers, Robert</surname>
               </name> (<year>1983</year>) <source>Rural Development Putting the Last</source> First. <publisher-loc>Harlow</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Addison Wesley Longman</publisher-name>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Chambers, Robert</surname>
               </name> (<year>1994</year>a) <article-title>`The Origins and Practice of Participatory Rural Appraisal'</article-title>, <source>World Development</source> 
               <volume>22</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>953</fpage>-<lpage>69</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Chambers, Robert</surname>
               </name> (<year>1994</year>b) <article-title>`Participatory Rural Appraisal (PRA): Analysis of Experience'</article-title>, <source>World Development</source> 
               <volume>22</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>1253</fpage>-<lpage>68</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Chambers, Robert</surname>
               </name> (<year>1994</year>c) <article-title>`Participatory Rural Appraisal (PRA): Challenges, Potentials and Paradigm'</article-title>, <source>World Development</source> 
               <volume>22</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>1437</fpage>-<lpage>54</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Chambers, Robert</surname>
               </name> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Whose Reality Counts? Putting the First Last</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Intermediate Technology Publications</publisher-name> .</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Clouser, Roy A.</surname>
               </name> (<year>1991</year>) <source>The Myth of Religious Neutrality: An Essay on the Hidden Role of Religious Belief in Theories</source>. <publisher-loc>South Bend, IN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Notre Dame Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Daneel, Marthinus L.</surname>
               </name> (<year>2005</year>) <source>`Liberative Ecumenism at the African Grassroots'</source> , in <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Marthinus L. Daneel</surname>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Charles Van Engen</surname>
               </name> and <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hendrik Vroom</surname>
               </name> (eds) <source>Fullness of Life For All: Challenges for Mission in Early 21st Century</source>, pp. <fpage>295</fpage>-<lpage>327</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rodopi</publisher-name>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Friedman, Thomas L.</surname>
               </name> (<year>2005</year>) <source>The World Is Flat: A Brief History of the Twenty-First Century</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Farrar, Straus and Giroux</publisher-name>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Habermas, Jürgen</surname>
               </name> (<year>1989</year>) <source>The Structural Transformation of the Public Sphere, trans. Thomas Burger assisted by Frederick Lawrence</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc> : <publisher-name>Polity Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hiebert, Paul G.</surname>
               </name> (<year>1978</year>) <article-title>`Conversion, Culture and Cognitive Categories'</article-title> , <source>Gospel in Context</source> 
               <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>24</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hiebert, Paul G.</surname>
               </name> (<year>1979</year>) <source>`Sets and Structures: A Study of Church Patterns'</source> , in <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>David J. Hesselgrave</surname>
               </name> (ed.) <source>New Horizons in World Missions</source>, pp. <fpage>217</fpage>-<lpage>27</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Grand Rapids, MI</publisher-loc> : <publisher-name>Baker Book House</publisher-name>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Hiebert, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Paul G.</surname>
               </name> ( <year>1985</year>) <source>Anthropological Insights for Missionaries</source>. <publisher-loc>Grand Rapids, MI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Baker Book House</publisher-name>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hiebert, Paul G.</surname>
               </name> (<year>1994</year>) <source>Anthropological Reflections on Missiological Issues</source> . <publisher-loc>Grand Rapids, MI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Baker Book House</publisher-name> .</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Holenstein, Anne-Marie</surname>
               </name> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Role and Significance of Religion and Spirituality in Development Co-operation: A Reflection and Working Paper</source>. <publisher-loc>Bern</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Swiss Agency for Development and Co-operation, March</publisher-name>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kirk, J. Andrew</surname>
               </name> (<year>2000</year>) <source>What Is Mission? Theological Explorations</source>. <publisher-loc>Minneapolis, MN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Fortress Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Marsden, George M.</surname>
               </name> (<year>1982</year>) <source>Fundamentalism and American Culture: The Shaping of Twentieth-Century Evangelicalism, 1870-1925</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc> : <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Marsden, George M.</surname>
               </name> (<year>1991</year>) <source>Understanding Fundamentalism and Evangelicalism</source> . <publisher-loc>rand Rapids, MI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Company</publisher-name>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Marshall, Katherine</surname>
               </name> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Faith and Development: Rethinking Development Debates</source> . <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Bank</publisher-name>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Myers, Bryant L.</surname>
               </name> (<year>1999</year>) <source>Walking with the Poor: Principles and Practices of Transformational Development</source>. <publisher-loc>Maryknoll, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Orbis Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Newbigin, Lesslie</surname>
               </name> (<year>1986</year>) <source>Foolishness to the Greeks: The Gospel and Western Culture</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SPCK</publisher-name>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Newbigin, Lesslie</surname>
               </name> (<year>1989</year>) <source>The Gospel in a Pluralist Society</source>. <publisher-loc>Grand Rapids, MI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Company</publisher-name> .</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Noll, Mark A.</surname>
               </name> (<year>1995</year>) <source>The Scandal of the Evangelical Mind</source>. <publisher-loc>Grand Rapids, MI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Company</publisher-name> .</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Polanyi, Michael</surname>
               </name> (<year>1958</year>) <source>Personal Knowledge: Towards a Postcritical Philosophy</source> . <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul</publisher-name>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Travis, John</surname>
               </name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>`Must all Muslims leave Islam to follow Jesus?'</article-title> , <source>Evangelical Missions Quarterly</source> 
               <volume>34</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>411</fpage>-<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Travis, John</surname>
               </name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>`Messianic Muslim Followers of Isa: A Closer Look at C5 Believers and Congregations'</article-title>, <source>International Journal of Frontier Missions</source> 
               <volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>53</fpage>-<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Travis, John</surname>
               </name> and <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Travis, Anna</surname>
               </name> (<year>2005</year>) <source>`Appropriate Approaches in Muslim Contexts'</source>, in <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Charles H. Kraft</surname>
               </name> (ed.) <source>Appropriate Christianity</source>, pp. <fpage>397</fpage>-<lpage>414</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Pasadena, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>William Carey Library</publisher-name>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Volf, Miroslav</surname>
               </name> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Exclusion and Embrace: A Theological Exploration of Identity, Otherness, and Reconciliation</source>. <publisher-loc>Nashville, TN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Abingdon Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
         </ref>
         <ref>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Wolterstorff, Nicholas</surname>
               </name> (<year>1984</year>) <source>Reason Within the Bounds of Religion</source>. <publisher-loc>Grand Rapids, MI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Company</publisher-name> .</citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>