<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">NLF</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spnlf</journal-id>
<journal-title>New Labor Forum</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1095-7960</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1557-2978</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1095796012471307</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1095796012471307</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>Under the Radar</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>Ben</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1095796012471307">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1095796012471307"><label>1</label>City University of New York, New York, NY</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1095796012471307">Ben Becker, <email>becker.ben@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>22</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>7</fpage>
<lpage>9</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2013, The Murphy Institute, City University of New York</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Joseph S. Murphy Institute, CUNY</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<custom-meta-wrap>
<custom-meta>
<meta-name>cover-date</meta-name>
<meta-value>January/February 2013</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-wrap>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<boxed-text id="boxed-text1-1095796012471307">
<p><disp-quote>
<p><italic>“We would have killed many [U.S. soldiers] already . . . but our commanders are cowards and don’t let us.”</italic></p>
<attrib>—A twenty-year-old Afghan soldier talking to the <italic>New York Times</italic> about U.S. troops in the country</attrib>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>(<italic>Source</italic>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/09/26/world/asia/in-afghanistan-us-advisers-train-allies-with-caution.html">www.nytimes.com/2012/09/26/world/asia/in-afghanistan-us-advisers-train-allies-with-caution.html</ext-link>)</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p><italic>“If I hear anybody say it was because Romney wasn’t conservative enough I’m going to go nuts. We’re not losing 95 percent of African-Americans and two-thirds of Hispanics and voters under 30 because we’re not being hard-ass enough.”</italic></p>
<attrib>—Republican Senator Lindsey Graham (South Carolina)</attrib>
</disp-quote></p>
</boxed-text>
<boxed-text id="boxed-text2-1095796012471307">
<p><bold>2/3</bold></p>
<p>—The proportion of Chicago parents who supported the recent teachers’ strike, according to a poll conducted by a right-wing subsidiary of the Illinois Manufacturing Association.</p>
<p>(<italic>Source</italic>: a We Ask America poll, cited at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ctunet.com/blognew-poll-shows-that-that-majority-of-the-public-supports-the-strike">www.ctunet.com/blognew-poll-shows-that-that-majority-of-the-public-supports-the-strike</ext-link>)</p>
<p><bold>13 percent</bold></p>
<p>—The amount by which the net worth of the richest 400 Americans grew from 2011 to 2012, totaling $1.7 trillion—one-eighth of the entire economy.</p>
<p>(<italic>Source</italic>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bottomline.nbcnews.com/_news/2012/09/19/13963593-richest-400-americans-net-worth-jumps-13-percent-to-17-trillion?lite">http://bottomline.nbcnews.com/_news/2012/09/19/13963593-richest-400-americans-net-worth-jumps-13-percent-to-17-trillion?lite</ext-link>)</p>
</boxed-text>
<sec id="section1-1095796012471307">
<title>Women’s Rights Protests Target Both RNC and DNC</title>
<p>While the Republican and Democratic Conventions both tried to reach women voters, largely ignored were the simultaneous women’s rights marches held in eight cities around the country. Fed up with both major parties, a new organization, WORD (Women Organized to Resist and Defend), initiated the Day of Action, declaring that “The Republican candidates . . . have been competing to see who can spout the most anti-woman rhetoric,” and adding that Obama too “has compromised with the anti-choice forces on many occasions.”</p>
<p>The protests drew hundreds in various cities, generally reflecting a younger and more diverse constituency than the more established women’s organizations. The SlutWalk marches in 2011 also took place outside of these groups, suggesting the emergence of a new generation of feminist organization.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1095796012471307">
<title>“No Justice, No Pizza”</title>
<p>A largely immigrant workforce in Milwaukee, Wisconsin, struck all summer against the factory of Palermo, a company that makes frozen pizza. Facing low wages, unsafe working conditions, and arbitrary firings, 80 percent signed a petition for union representation. Refusing to recognize the union, days later, Palermo fired eighty-nine workers supposedly on account of their immigration status. Immigration and Customs Enforcement denied the company’s claims that it had set a deadline to verify its employees’ status, and in response to the strike called off their audit entirely. The workers called for an ongoing boycott of Palermo products and solidarity at Costco, which is the pizza company’s primary distributor.</p>
<p>Hundreds of miles away in New York City, when immigrant workers at a small Hot &amp; Crusty voted for an independent union, the owner stopped paying rent, figuring that the place would close and he could reopen it under a different company name. Occupy activists organized twenty-four-hour picket lines and took several arrests while occupying the pizzeria to prevent its closure. Finally, the company relented, reopened the store, recognized the union, and gave it a hiring hall. This unqualified win showed the very best of what the “occupy” idea offers and its wide applicability.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1095796012471307">
<title>Syracuse Bus Hub Becomes Battleground over Gentrification, Free Speech, and Disability Rights</title>
<p>A newly opened bus hub in Syracuse, New York, billed as an effort to revitalize the city’s downtown, instead drew together a coalition of organizations to protest the ribbon-cutting ceremony. Disabled in Action of Greater Syracuse organized the protest because of the city’s failure to deliver on promised design features to make the facility broadly accessible. Antigentrification organizations protested the lack of community input and noted the city’s intent to upgrade the downtown area at the expense of poor and working-class communities. Civil liberties organizations and antiwar activists, reading the fine print of the development plan, were likewise outraged by the new regulations that will require permits for literature distribution in the hub. Protesters chanted, “Make it right! Make it right!” down Syracuse’s main thoroughfare despite police orders to disperse or risk arrest.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1095796012471307">
<title>Corporations Collect and Keep Their Employees’ Taxes</title>
<p>Nineteen state legislatures have allowed more than 2,700 companies to receive tax credits equal to the amount their employees contribute in state income taxes. This subsidy, aimed at retaining the companies in state, essentially means that the companies are collecting and keeping their workers’ taxes. None of the states require notifying the workers. Many Fortune 500 companies benefit from the subsidy, including General Electric, Goldman Sachs, Procter &amp; Gamble, Chrysler, Ford, General Motors, and AMC Theatres. This tax credit and others are detailed in David Cay Johnston’s <italic>The Fine Print: How Big Companies Use “Plain English” to Rob You Blind</italic>.</p>
<graphic id="img1-1095796012471307" position="anchor" xlink:href="10.1177_1095796012471307-img1.tif"/>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1095796012471307">
<title>OWS Raids and Lawsuits</title>
<p>In the summer of 2012, SWAT (special weapons and tactics) teams raided the apartments of activists with Occupy and the Red Spark Collective in Seattle and Olympia, Washington, and Portland, Oregon. The New York Police Department barged into the homes of several Occupy activists days before the large May Day march. In Los Angeles, the offices of ANSWER (Act Now to Stop War and End Racism) were broken into and ransacked in an operation that had all the trappings of a political raid rather than a common burglary.</p>
<p>There were also several cases of police infiltrating Occupy activists. Five Cleveland activists were arrested on terrorism charges, for allegedly plotting to destroy a bridge—although they claim undercover agents hatched the plot. Three were arrested in Chicago prior to the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) summit in a nearly identical case. Occupy protesters in Houston are facing felony charges because, in chaining themselves together, they utilized a pipe—which later turned out to be supplied by an undercover officer.</p>
<p>In a victory for the other side, U.S. District Judge Jed Rakoff ruled that a civil suit could proceed against NYPD officers who arrested more than 700 Occupy Wall Street marchers on the Brooklyn Bridge in October 2011. After reviewing a video of the incident, he ruled that they were not properly warned by officers, and that police exerted “some degree of control over the marchers, defining their route and directing them, at times, to follow certain rules.” City attorneys had argued that the arresting officers were entitled to “qualified immunity,” a notion the judge rejected.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1095796012471307">
<title>Walmart Workers Do the Impossible</title>
<p>Last fall, sixty-three Walmart workers in the Los Angeles metropolitan area walked off the job to call attention once again to the poor wages and working conditions for which the corporation is well known. It was the largest such job action in the history of Walmart in the United States, where none of its stores are unionized.</p>
<p>Emboldened by the Los Angeles action, workers walked off the job at Walmart stores in Dallas, Texas; the Bay Area and Sacramento, California; Seattle; Miami; Washington, D.C.; and Chicago. The number of strikers in these follow-up actions was minimal—only eighty-eight workers in twenty-eight stores—and they did not seriously disrupt business. But they showed that it is possible for workers to publicly defy the corporate Goliath.</p>
<p>These coordinated actions were the first fruit of OUR Walmart, a nonunion worker association tied closely to the United Food and Commercial Workers. Even this elementary form of organization, joined by only a tiny fraction of Walmart employees, appears to have increased the capacity and confidence of workers to take action on the job. Under U.S. labor law, nonunion workers have the right to collective action over workplace issues, although in practice, it comes with additional risks.</p>
<p>Risks aside, nonunion laborers at one of Walmart’s subcontracted distribution centers in Illinois claimed victory after a twenty-one-day strike. It, too, was organized through the model of a workers’ center, Warehouse Workers for Justice, which was established by the United Electrical Workers.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<title>Author Biography</title>
<p><bold>Ben Becker</bold> is a Ph.D. candidate in U.S. history at the City University of New York’s Graduate Center.</p>
</bio>
</back>
</article>