<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CTR</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spctr</journal-id><journal-title>Clothing and Textiles Research Journal</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0887-302X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1940-2473</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0887302X12472724</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0887302X12472724</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Challenges and Solutions of Sustainable Apparel Product Development</article-title><subtitle>A Case Study of Eileen Fisher</subtitle></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Curwen</surname><given-names>Lisa G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0887302X12472724">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0887302X12472724"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Juyeon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0887302X12472724">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>Ajoy K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0887302X12472724">2</xref></contrib><bio><title>Author Biographies</title><p><bold>Lisa G. Curwen</bold> recently graduated from the department of Design and Merchandising at Colorado State University with a Master's Degree following a twenty-five year career as a textile designer and apparel product developer. Her interests include bridging sustainability research and industry practice.</p><p><bold>Juyeon Park</bold>, PhD, is an assistant professor in the department of design and merchandising at Colorado State University. Her scholarly interests include design activism and product development for human well-being.</p><p><bold>Ajoy K. Sarkar</bold>, PhD, is an associate professor at the Fashion Institute of Technology in New York. His areas of research are sustainable textiles and protective clothing.</p></bio></contrib-group><aff id="aff1-0887302X12472724"><label>1</label>Colorado State University, Fort Collins, CO, USA</aff><aff id="aff2-0887302X12472724"><label>2</label>Fashion Institute of Technology, State University of New York, New York, NY, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-0887302X12472724">Lisa G. Curwen, Colorado State University, 2970 Clinton St., Denver, CO 80238, USA. Email: <email>lgcurwen@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>1</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="other">ITAA</copyright-holder></permissions><abstract><p>The three-fold purpose of this study is to document current challenges the apparel industry experiences in developing sustainable apparel, discover product development strategies for fulfilling sustainable business goals, and determine the principles guiding successful interaction between designers and the upstream supply chain.  This study adopted a case study method to identify and communicate practical challenges and solutions of Eileen Fisher, a women's apparel manufacturer. Data were collected from thirteen in-depth interviews conducted with members of the case company and its suppliers, with secondary data analysis from the case company's website and archival records. The study identified five challenges the case company encountered with respect to maintaining product value, quality, and aesthetics, meeting needs of suppliers, and coping with higher material and labor costs. Five solutions were put into place supporting sustainability objectives, and which highlight the practice of innovation in design, optimizing timing and resources, gathering and diffusing information, relationship management, and making trade-offs for cost and value. Five principles, which guided the design team and its interaction with upstream suppliers, were identified and modeled. The implication for other apparel companies in overcoming challenges of sustainable product development is that it begins with a clear mission, strong company mandate, and like-minded supply partners. The authors believe that, in beginning to fill an area of limited research, examination of the connections between design process and the supply chain is imperative for advancing sustainable practices in the apparel and textile industry.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>apparel design</kwd><kwd>design process</kwd><kwd>supply chain</kwd><kwd>green products</kwd><kwd>product</kwd><kwd>development</kwd><kwd>social responsibility</kwd><kwd>sustainable design</kwd><kwd>sustainability</kwd><kwd>eco-fashion</kwd><kwd>textiles</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="section1-0887302X12472724"><title>Introduction</title><p>The textile supply chain is of a highly complex nature requiring extensive international, national, and local supply chain networks that must respond to the frequent changes in product lines and styles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0887302X12472724">Forman, 2004</xref>). In addition, conventional fiber production, dyeing and processing, garment assembly, transportation, and use and maintenance of the garment create enormous streams of waste (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0887302X12472724">Bhamra, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0887302X12472724">Chen &amp; Burns, 2006</xref>). As apparel companies undertake the mission of sustainable design (i.e., systems that support human well-being and are compatible with sustaining natural environmental systems) they are focusing on the planning stage of the supply chain—the design phase—because that is where most decisions are made that potentially impact the entire life cycle of the product (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0887302X12472724">Bhamra &amp; Lofthouse, 2007</xref>).</p><p>This research focuses on the design phase of an apparel firm’s sustainable sweater program. The particular purposes of this case study are to document challenges the firm experiences, discover design, and product development strategies that are implemented in fulfilling its sustainable design business goals, and determine the principles behind the successful interaction between the design team and its upstream supply chain. The upstream supply chain consists of a firm’s raw materials suppliers while the downstream supply chain is its distribution channel. As such, the following research inquiries are posed: (1) what are the design and product development challenges encountered in the creation of a sustainable product line; (2) what solutions are implemented to support sustainability objectives; and (3) how are relationships between the case company and its upstream supply chain affected in the process? In support of the stated research inquiries, and to establish a frame of reference, how the case company defines sustainability and what its sustainable design objectives are also investigated.</p></sec><sec id="section2-0887302X12472724"><title>Justification/Significance of Study</title><p>Ample research exists on reducing the environmental impacts of textile and apparel production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0887302X12472724">Allwood, Laursen, Russell, &amp; Malvido de Rodriguez, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0887302X12472724">Bevilacqua, Ciarapica, Giacchette, &amp; Marchetti, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0887302X12472724">Chen &amp; Burns, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0887302X12472724">Muthu, Li, Hu, &amp; Mok, 2012</xref>). In addition, studies on textile and apparel sustainability have been conducted from the point of view of effective supply chain management (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0887302X12472724">Cao, Zhang, To, &amp; Ng, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0887302X12472724">Chi, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0887302X12472724">Forman, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0887302X12472724">Kogg, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0887302X12472724">Morana &amp; Seuring, 2011</xref>). Practices for teaching sustainable apparel design, in the context of university level educational courses, have been reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0887302X12472724">Cao, Frey, Farr, &amp; Gam, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0887302X12472724">Gam &amp; Banning, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0887302X12472724">Ha-Brookshire &amp; Norum, 2011</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0887302X12472724">Armstrong and LeHew (2011</xref>) called for a new paradigm beyond that which created our current industrial world in order to provide solutions to today’s ecological problems and position the apparel industry for the future. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0887302X12472724">Niinimaki and Hassi (2011</xref>) surveyed consumers’ perspectives on environmental issues in the textile and apparel industry and determined how likely they were to engage in the environmentally friendly design strategies that emerged, such as slow fashion, customized clothing, and co-creation, to mention a few. The business report from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0887302X12472724">Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (2011</xref>) recapped progress on environmental performance, consumption trends, supply chain, and so forth in the U.K. textile sector. Finally, in a case study on Gap, Inc., sustainable practices achieved by supply chain collaboration and organizational restructuring were reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0887302X12472724">Worley, Feyerherm, &amp; Knudsen, 2010</xref>).</p><p>As reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0887302X12472724">Easton (2007</xref>), sustainably designed soft goods cannot be successfully developed without a better and more comprehensive understanding of the supply chain; however, apparel industry studies on integrating sustainability with the product development process and the supply chain are few. Although a model called <italic>cradle to cradle for apparel design</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0887302X12472724">Gam, Cao, Farr, &amp; Heine, 2008</xref>) introduces an apparel design and production process that emphasizes sustainability, it lacks clarity on tools for successful supply chain interactions. Case studies on Patagonia’s switch to organic cotton (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0887302X12472724">Chouinard &amp; Brown, 1997</xref>) and Nike’s sustainable <italic>Considered Boot</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0887302X12472724">Jacques, Agnogino, &amp; Guimaraes, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0887302X12472724">White, Stewart, Howes, &amp; Adams, 2008</xref>) have been instructive in addressing the subject of sustainability; however, additional scholarly research on industry practices of sustainable apparel product development is needed to help explicate a more comprehensive picture. This study is significant because it provides solutions to specific issues in the design phase that designers, given a mandate for sustainability, are confronting.</p><sec id="section3-0887302X12472724"><title>Product Development Considerations</title><p>The design stages of the product development process have a direct influence on the final product as this is where the most critical decisions are made, including cost, appearance, materials selection, innovation, performance, sustainability, and quality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0887302X12472724">Bhamra &amp; Lofthouse, 2007</xref>). The designer must evaluate the needs of all stakeholders to determine how to proceed with a design concept and make choices according to the risks and benefits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0887302X12472724">Howarth &amp; Hadfield, 2006</xref>). A sustainable product development process of a closed-loop nature requires modifications from the traditional linear process that does not consider sustainability. Design choices are made about product components to be disassembled and reused as well as materials that can be processed into new products (i.e., recycled). Review of themes reported in other design industries follow, as they potentially apply to the apparel product design process.</p><p>Integrative product design, a philosophy that originated in the engineering field, underscores the importance of multidisciplinary teams and cross-functional organizations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0887302X12472724">Mentzer et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0887302X12472724">White et al., 2008</xref>). The thinking is that a single functional group, such as a design team, is not equipped to successfully identify and launch viable sustainability options on its own (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0887302X12472724">White et al., 2008</xref>). It is reported that sustainable design requires an integrative approach using the expertise of a wide variety of organizational actors who cooperate to develop a product, with internal alignment between designers, merchandisers, business strategists, production teams, marketing staff, end of life managers, and corporate responsibility managers to align sustainable options with customer value (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0887302X12472724">Hong, Kwon, &amp; Roh, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0887302X12472724">White et al., 2008</xref>).</p><p>The values held by an organization are an important factor for sustainable practices since they underlie the ethos of the organization and enable designers to take action (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0887302X12472724">Hong et al., 2009</xref>). Effective sustainable product development is reported to be a result of a firm’s strategic commitment and orientation toward sustainability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0887302X12472724">Rossi, Charon, Wing, &amp; Ewell, 2006</xref>). Furthermore, systems-based thinking is required for implementing a sustainable design process; that is, the parts of the system must be understood as they relate to each other, but the system must be approached as a whole (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0887302X12472724">Hong et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p>Assessment tools have been integral to sustainable product design by providing an internal report card for designers. Life cycle analysis (LCA) is the method most often used for pinpointing potential improvements in the process by assessing environmental impacts associated with all stages of a product’s life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0887302X12472724">Seuring &amp; Muller, 2008</xref>). LCA has been used by apparel and footwear companies such as Patagonia and Nike by assessing the primary materials of their garments through tracking energy consumption, CO<sub>2</sub> emissions, waste generation, and water use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0887302X12472724">Nike, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0887302X12472724">Patagonia, 2011</xref>). Herman Miller, with the help of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0887302X12472724">McDonough and Braungart (2002</xref>), developed design for the environment, a tool which evaluates how well the product meets the cradle-to-cradle ideal of being made from 100% biological and/or technical nutrients and answers questions regarding materials content, recyclability, and disassembly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0887302X12472724">Rossi et al., 2006</xref>). The Eco-index is another system used by companies to rate products for internal review. The tool’s success is based on how much is known about materials’ supply chains (Oakes, 2011).</p><p>All materials used in the production of a product determine its environmental impact (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0887302X12472724">Huang, Liu, Zhang, &amp; Sutherland, 2009</xref>). Approximately 80% of clothing’s impact is determined at the design stage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0887302X12472724">European Commission, 2011</xref>), making material choices crucial when sustainability is being considered. Materials for clothing include fibers and trims (i.e., buttons, zippers, etc.) which have been cultivated, manufactured, processed, dyed, and finished. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0887302X12472724">Chen and Burns (2006</xref>) analyzed the life cycle of a full range of textiles for environmental impacts and concluded that virtually all negatively impact the environment. Researchers purport limiting and simplifying the number and types of materials for more sustainable design (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0887302X12472724">MacPherson, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0887302X12472724">McDonough &amp; Braungart, 2002</xref>). In fact, using fewer materials has been said to foster creativity and resourcefulness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0887302X12472724">MacPherson, 2004</xref>). Consideration of garment and textile care during the design process can drastically alter the environmental impact of apparel maintenance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0887302X12472724">Allwood et al., 2008</xref>), since the most significant environmental impacts arise from use and maintenance rather than manufacture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0887302X12472724">Bhamra, 2007</xref>). Trade-offs based on customer value, sustainability metrics, and cost have also become part of the design process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0887302X12472724">Huang et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0887302X12472724">Waage, 2007</xref>).</p><p>Cultivating strong supply chain relationships is important for developing sustainable products (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0887302X12472724">Rossi et al., 2006</xref>). For example, the length and strength of the relationship between a focal company and its suppliers was found to determine the leverage it has (Levenson, 2008). Petersen, Handfield, and Ragatz’s (2005) findings on integrating suppliers into new product development support how critical supplier selection is; collaborators’ capabilities must be considered, as well as the compatibility of business cultures between firms.</p><p>Knowledge sharing was reported to enhance competitive advantage, and trust positively impacted knowledge sharing among competitive and cooperative firms in green supply chains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0887302X12472724">Cheng, Yeh, &amp; Tu, 2008</xref>). Furthermore, early supplier involvement enabled knowledge sharing, resulting in successful products (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0887302X12472724">Petersen, Handfield, &amp; Ragatz, 2005</xref>). Overcoming the information sharing challenges within the supply chain of replacing toxic materials with the invention of safe ones was reported in various case studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0887302X12472724">McDonough, Braungart, Anastos, &amp; Zimmerman, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0887302X12472724">Rossi et al., 2006</xref>). In addition, solving sustainability problems by implementing strategies such as information sharing and integrative product development have also been documented (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0887302X12472724">Kogg, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0887302X12472724">McDonough et al., 2003</xref>). Furthermore, it is reported that supply chain transparency is believed to create an environment that leads to greater accountability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0887302X12472724">Doorey, 2011</xref>).</p><p>Product development research on successful process, organizational, and technical practices from various industries was reviewed. Of particular interest were the considerations of an organization’s values, integrative product design, assessments, material choices, innovation, supply chain relationships, and information sharing. Research from other industries was included for context and to help understand the concerns apparel product developers face.</p></sec><sec id="section4-0887302X12472724"><title>Profile and History of the Case Company</title><p>The case company of this study is a brand name women’s fashion apparel firm named Eileen Fisher (EF). Founded in 1984, EF supplies women’s fashion apparel to department stores, specialty stores, and its own freestanding stores throughout the United States and around the world. The company is headquartered in New York, employs 875 people, and as of 2010, reported sales of $300 million. EF maintains a commitment to being socially conscious and engages in initiatives and grant programs focused on individual well-being, human rights in the workplace, environmental stewardship, support of women and girls, and partnerships with the community.</p><p>As early as the 1990s, following the sweatshop scandals that revealed Kathy Lee Gifford and Nike apparel goods were made under poor and exploitative working conditions, EF made a commitment to improve the human rights conditions of its upstream supply chain partners. The company began to require its factories to apply international workplace standards to their facilities, certifying that basic rights of workers have been protected. Subsequently, in 2006, the company made an equal commitment to environmental sustainability which was initiated through a groundswell of interest in environmental stewardship by EF’s employees as well as by the strong personal commitment of the company’s owner. EF’s mission statement was updated to reflect the new strategy, and a formal environmental initiative was launched which coincided with inception of the Peru project, a sustainable initiative and focus of this study.</p><p>The product line of EF’s Peru project is comprised of fully fashioned knit sweaters. The sweaters are made of 100% long staple organic cotton, which is grown, spun, and knit in Peru by suppliers that work within a fair trade model. Fair trade enables workers to receive a living wage, promotes social investments in the workers’ communities by the employers, and ensures the work environment is safe and healthy (Kocken, 2006). EF’s sustainability leader described the Peru project as “a nice marriage between the two [environmental and social components]; it is a local supply chain totally, from fiber all the way to the finished garment, and [the product] is organic and it’s dyed in a responsible way” (Alicia, personal communication, July 7, 2011). In order to keep the participants anonymous in this article, individuals and suppliers were arbitrarily renamed by the researchers.</p><p>The Peru project was the result of EF deciding to engage with a supplier called <italic>Design Inheritance</italic> (DI), a socially responsible small business that specializes in making apparel from environmentally friendly fibers and dyes and provides sustainable work to artisan cooperatives at fair trade wages. DI contracts work to Knit Peru (KP), a Peruvian apparel cooperative which provides training and work to women who make environmentally friendly products and use natural Peruvian fibers such as long staple cotton, merino wool, silk, and alpaca. KP workers knit products at home-based facilities in remote areas, as well as in a central manufacturing facility. EF’s desire to use sumptuous yarns that are environmentally friendly accorded with the availability of Peruvian organic cotton yarns, which are known for their high quality. In addition, its social-minded tradition of empowering women fit with the work model of the suppliers in the chain. EF, therefore, saw that making sweaters that were sustainably designed and produced within the Peruvian supply chain was an opportunity to differentiate its product and tell a compelling supply chain story that reflected the company’s own mission.</p><p>With supply chain members on board to fulfill EF’s strategic initiative for a sustainably designed sweater program, what followed was a series of challenges for the design department. The cottage industry sweaters from Peru had to blend in with the rest of the company’s high-quality products that were being made in China. Although the sustainable aspect of the product was important, first and foremost the product had to stand on its own aesthetic merits. As the design process facilitator explained, “Our customer responds to beautiful product; if it’s sustainable, that’s a bonus” (Lauren, personal communication, June 17, 2011). This case study explains how EF succeeded in overcoming problems with its product and processes though the efforts of the company’s design and product development departments as well as with its upstream supply chain partners.</p></sec></sec><sec id="section5-0887302X12472724" sec-type="methods"><title>Method</title><p>A case study approach was adopted in order to gain an in-depth understanding of the case company’s situation, which is not easily investigated using other techniques such as surveys and enabling data collection from multiple sources of evidence to triangulate the data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0887302X12472724">Yin, 2008</xref>). Data sources included in-depth interviews, direct observation, and archival documents. A qualitative method of inquiry was adopted which derived from a reflective and grounded process of data generation and analysis. Rich descriptions answering “How?” or “Why?” questions about a contemporary set of events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0887302X12472724">Yin, 2008</xref>) were drawn from 13 participants; they included 11 employees of the case company and 2 members of two different supply chain partners. A pilot interview was deemed appropriate to select a company whose approach to sustainability came from the product development perspective.</p><sec id="section6-0887302X12472724"><title>Sample Selection and Instrument Development</title><p>Initial interviews took place to determine eligibility and willingness to participate in the study. The researchers contacted three soft goods manufacturers that were referred by personal contacts and who engaged in eco-conscious practices. One was a small private textile converter and garment maker, another was a publicly traded mass retailer that produced private label apparel and soft goods, and the third was a large, international designer apparel brand. Case company criteria was based on fulfilling the research inquiries and required the potential case company to develop textiles and apparel through a global supply chain, to be involved in sustainable design practices, and to share experiences of problems and solutions encountered. An exploratory interview of approximately 45 min with a key contact from each company was conducted to gain information about the companies’ suitability for the study (i.e., orientation toward sustainability) and willingness to participate. Of the three potential case companies, two declined participation in the main study: the private textile converter terminated its business of eco-fabrics and the mass retailer’s sustainable practices focused on operations and logistics rather than design. The remaining company fulfilled all criteria and was interested in participation. Pilot and main study interviews were conducted by the same interviewer in order to maintain the validity of data. The interviewer informed each participant about the voluntary nature of the study and addressed any questions or concerns the participants from the case company had about study participation.</p><p>Participating individuals for the main study, conducted in 2011, were recruited through purposeful sampling methods within the case company and among two of the case company’s suppliers, one in Peru and the other in China. Fourteen potential participants representing a cross section of employees who engage in the sustainable design and product development process were identified through collaboration between the researchers and the case company’s key contact. Of the 14 who were invited for interviews with the researchers, 13 agreed (for the participant profile, refer to <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0887302X12472724">Table 1</xref>). Twenty-five open-ended questions regarding challenges encountered, tools implemented, and how relationships were affected, were asked of the participants; each interview took 30–60 min. All questions were purposefully composed to guide the conversation and allow for follow-up if necessary. The questions were designed to discover the stated research aims and included inquiries on problems encountered with sustainable programs, tools, and processes implemented to support them, relevance of relationships with suppliers, and definition of sustainability. To accommodate the interviewee’s schedule, the researchers collected data via telephone interview with the exception of one, which was performed in person, by request, during the interviewer’s visit to the case company. One researcher made a field visit to the case company where she gathered background information about the company, met the key contact and the participants, and conducted one interview in person. The same researcher collected data in the form of notes, photographs, and direct observations of the case company headquarters, its separate sales showroom, and several of its retail stores. Third party archival documents about the case company and its suppliers were also used as information sources.</p><table-wrap id="table1-0887302X12472724" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Participant Profile.</p></caption><graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0887302X12472724" xlink:href="10.1177_0887302X12472724-table1.tif"/><table><thead><tr><th>Name</th><th>Job Title</th><th>Years at Company</th><th>Years in Sustainability</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Alicia</td><td>Sustainability director</td><td>5</td><td>10</td></tr><tr><td>Beverly</td><td>Fabric developer</td><td>n/a</td><td>n/a</td></tr><tr><td>Bonnie</td><td>Account manager</td><td>4</td><td>n/a</td></tr><tr><td>Carly</td><td>Vendor/agent</td><td>18</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>Debra</td><td>VP manufacturing</td><td>19</td><td>17</td></tr><tr><td>Joy</td><td>Director social consciousness</td><td>18</td><td>14</td></tr><tr><td>Judy</td><td>VP product development</td><td>9</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>Lauren</td><td>Design process facilitator</td><td>6</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Melissa</td><td>Designer</td><td>18</td><td>12</td></tr><tr><td>Miriam</td><td>Designer</td><td>3½</td><td>3½</td></tr><tr><td>Pam</td><td>Recycle operation manager</td><td>n/a</td><td>n/a</td></tr><tr><td>Rick</td><td>Vendor/agent</td><td>15</td><td>15</td></tr><tr><td>Tanya</td><td>Retail director</td><td>10</td><td>3</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The following protocol was executed to insure validity: (1) interviews were audiotaped with the participant’s permission and transcribed verbatim; (2) verbatim transcriptions of interviews were entered into the NVivo software program, which assisted the researchers in the organization and analysis of content; (3) transcriptions were coded through the use of “nodes” reflecting thematic content; (4) nodes reflected questions asked, as well as new themes that emerged from the data; (5) nodes were organized according to research question; (6) an iterative approach was taken for coding and recoding, for the sake of accuracy; (7) memos were taken and relationships and patterns were noted; and (8) summaries, memos, examples, charts, diagrams were recorded for evidence.</p></sec><sec id="section7-0887302X12472724"><title>Data Analysis and Validation</title><p>Data were coded and manipulated using the NVivo software program in order to find themes and subthemes related to each research question. A process of constant comparison was used to refine themes, discover relationships, and identify broad patterns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19a-0887302X12472724">Glaser &amp; Strauss, 1967</xref>). Validity and reliability of the research findings were supported through various practices as recommended by standard case study methodology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0887302X12472724">Yin, 2008</xref>). Construct validity was demonstrated through (1) the convergence of patterns from multiple sources of data to provide triangulation; (2) the chain of evidence from questions to results; (3) the key contact’s confirmation of the initial report; and (4) the participants’ review of results of the study (there were no concerns or comments). The researchers consistently adhered to the protocol created for the study, and all data were maintained in a research database, thus supporting the procedural repeatability (i.e., reliability) of the study.</p></sec><sec id="section8-0887302X12472724"><title>Identifying the Problem</title><p>To provide a context for EF’s sustainable design initiatives, it was necessary to understand how the concept of sustainability was understood by those interviewed. The data revealed that the term <italic>sustainability</italic> was used to describe the environmental part the company plays in its larger role of social responsibility. Participants noted that environmental issues are linked to social and economic ones under the umbrella of social consciousness.</p><p>EF, having a longer history in human rights practices than in environmental ones, considered both crucial to being socially responsible. The sustainability leader stated, “I think in general, in the company, we see sustainability defined in many ways [social, environmental, and economic], but to the outside world, it’s an environmental issue” (Alicia, personal communication, July 7, 2011). Therefore, sustainability was referred to as mostly an ecological issue to be addressed from the standpoint of materials and their environmental impact. Furthermore, the importance of tracing the upstream supply chain and developing relationships with its members was underscored, given that environmental issues are an objective. The fabric leader (Beverly, personal communication, July 25, 2011) stated:</p><disp-quote><p>We are looking a little deeper into in the supply chain trying to understand more, and streamline and be able to control it more, so we can be more directive to the vendors—you know, use this dye source, use this fiber source.</p></disp-quote><p>EF’s stated goal, as communicated on the products’ hangtags, and which could potentially differentiate EF for a competitive advantage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0887302X12472724">Porter, 1985</xref>), is for 20% of its product line to have ecologically sustainable components. Thus, the Peru project fit the company’s environmental and social objectives with its use of certified organic cotton material and fair trade labor.</p><sec id="section9-0887302X12472724"><title>Identified Challenges for Sustainable Apparel Product Development</title><p>Interview questions elicited stories and examples from the various participants’ points of view. Participants described their experiences of developing the Peru sweater program including the successes, failures, and obstacles encountered.</p><p>Creating an aesthetically beautiful and salable product, while maintaining DI’s local Peruvian supply chain, presented challenges to EF’s design team. There were limits to the yarn choices available in Peru; the spinning of yarn was not as sophisticated as in Italy where EF purchased yarns that were sent to Chinese factories for knitting. An account manager described the product, when the Peru Project began, as “very heavy and basic, and didn’t have perceived value” (Bonnie, personal communication, August 19, 2011). A further limitation revolved around the capabilities of the machinery used by the Peruvian knitters. The V.P. of product development described them as “somewhat rustic and not refined enough” compared to the capabilities of sophisticated knitting machines used in Chinese factories (Judy, personal communication, June 27, 2011). The first challenge to overcome was that the sweaters lacked perceived value.</p><p>The second challenge was that styles were dropping from the line due to their late arrival. EF designers were finding that getting samples was taking longer than their process could support. There was a point in EF’s design process where the team reviewed all the prototype samples in order to finalize which styles got placed in the line. The products from Peru, however, were not arriving in time for this juncture. As a result, those styles would fall out of contention for placement in the line because the design team would rather select, as a designer explained, “something we have, and that we see, and that we know is going to work,” rather than rely on something that was not there to see (Melissa, personal communication, June 17, 2011). EF designers found that even shipping between Peru and New York took longer than what the design process was geared up for. EF leaders made allowances for the lateness in the beginning but recognized it had to change if they were to have a successful program of sweaters.</p><p>The high quality of construction and the accurate sizing that EF products were known for were not apparent in initial Peru project garments, therefore failing the EF aesthetic and quality standards. The V.P. of product development said, “There have been some challenges with [KP] getting the aesthetic and getting it right. When I say aesthetic, it is really about a finesse and execution that we are looking for … at a certain high quality level” (Judy, personal communication, June 27, 2011). The artfulness of product execution is imperative for EF. “Although we are very interested in sustainability, we are also very demanding in terms of quality of our product,” declared the V.P. of manufacturing (Debra, personal communication, July 7, 2011). Because all EF products were held to the same quality standards, whether they came from an artisan community or sophisticated factories, this proved to be a formidable obstacle and third challenge faced by EF.</p><p>At the beginning of the Peru project, as explained by the sales manager, a new style was created which was well received by the sales force; 20,000 units were booked for the season, a dramatic increase over the few thousand units previously contracted. KP scaled up for the increase in production by purchasing new equipment and training more knitters. Due to lackluster product sales and the seasonality of the cotton yarn fiber, EF did not buy as much product the next season and orders returned to previous levels of a few thousand units. The suppliers were left with unused machines and what appeared to be a shaky investment. The owner of DI lamented to EF’s team leaders that KP’s artisans were left in the predicament of having built up their businesses to accommodate EF’s capacity needs only to see the orders drop off and leave them in a lurch. Therefore, unused machine capacity was jeopardizing suppliers’ livelihoods, which provided an additional challenge for EF.</p><p>EF faced a fifth challenge when ordinary markups threatened sales. The cost of organic cotton runs considerably higher than conventional cotton but the fiber itself demonstrates no appreciable difference in value as perceived by the customer, explained the design process facilitator. A higher material cost typically requires a higher selling price. Coupled with the product’s basic make and mediocre quality, the higher price negatively impacted sales. The design team recognized that it needed to find a way to offer salable garments, despite higher priced organic cotton yarns, so the Peru project could compete successfully in the marketplace.</p></sec><sec id="section10-0887302X12472724"><title>Solutions to Identified Challenges</title><p>As explained above, the sustainability project had multiple problems and possibilities for failure. Thus, the design team identified five solutions to overcome the five challenges. In these solutions, the team members (1) exercised creativity and innovation in design to increase the product’s perceived value; (2) optimized timing and resources to overcome styles dropping from the line due to their late arrival; (3) engaged hands-on and upstream to improve product’s aesthetics and quality; (4) managed relationships responsibly and for the long term to help suppliers maintain machine capacity, thus protecting their livelihoods; and (5) made trade-offs based on cost and value to reduce typical markups which threatened sales. Challenges encountered with the Peru project, their root causes, countermeasures taken, solutions, and resulting effects are elucidated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0887302X12472724">Table 2</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="table2-0887302X12472724" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Analysis of Peru Project Challenges Encountered by Eileen Fisher Design Team.</p></caption><graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0887302X12472724" xlink:href="10.1177_0887302X12472724-table2.tif"/><table><thead><tr><th>Challenge</th><th>Root Cause</th><th>Countermeasure</th><th>Solution</th><th>Effect</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Sweaters lacked perceived value</p></list-item></list></td><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Limited yarn selection and machine capabilities</p></list-item></list></td><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Developed more creative designs</p></list-item><list-item><p>Developed new yarns and new ways to use existing yarns</p></list-item></list></td><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Exercised creativity and innovation in design</p></list-item></list></td><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Sweaters are more salable</p></list-item><list-item><p>Win–win for EF and supply partners</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Styles dropped from line due to late arrival</p></list-item></list></td><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Suppliers needed more time to submit samples</p></list-item></list></td><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Adjusted design process time line by giving two additional weeks to suppliers</p></list-item><list-item><p>Reduced breadth of samples requested</p></list-item></list></td><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Optimized timing and resources</p></list-item></list></td><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Timely arrival of samples to be adopted into the line</p></list-item><list-item><p>Supplier’s and EF’s business grows</p></list-item><list-item><p>New timing calendar puts a temporary strain on the designer</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Product failed aesthetic and quality standards</p></list-item></list></td><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Suppliers lacked the required craftsmanship and understanding of EF’s standards</p></list-item></list></td><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Designers made seasonal trips to Peru to tutor artisans</p></list-item></list></td><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Engaged hands-on “upstream”</p></list-item></list></td><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Quality is improved</p></list-item><list-item><p>Relationships are strengthened</p></list-item><list-item><p>Seasonal tutoring trips are eventually unnecessary</p></list-item><list-item><p>Product is more salable</p></list-item><list-item><p>Vendor becomes more desirable to other customers</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Unused machine capacity jeopardized suppliers’ livelihoods</p></list-item></list></td><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>High variability of order quantities from season to season, typical of fashion business</p></list-item></list></td><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Submitted orders to supplier for steady but conservative quantities.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Developed new products for alternate seasons to keep suppliers in year-round production</p></list-item></list></td><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Managed relationships responsibly and for the long term</p></list-item></list></td><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Producers have steady workload and can anticipate business accordingly</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Prices with typical markups not competitive and threatened sales</p></list-item></list></td><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Higher cost for organic cotton and fair trade; uncontrollable commodity pricing</p></list-item></list></td><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>EF absorbed some of the margin and found the savings elsewhere in company</p></list-item></list></td><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Made trade-offs balancing company values and cost</p></list-item></list></td><td><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Prices are competitive for better sales</p></list-item><list-item><p>EF is positioned in the long term for market share</p></list-item><list-item><p>EF relies on alternate business to make up margins</p></list-item></list></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn1-0887302X12472724"><p><italic>Note</italic>. EF = Eileen Fisher.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Designers exercised their creativity and innovation in design by substituting, limiting, and streamlining materials and processes. The Peru project sweaters were comprised, initially, of just two sizes of organic cotton yarn, because that was all that was grown, spun, and dyed locally. The basic yarn was a liability at first; however, as per the sweater designer, its limitations prompted creativity in garment stitches and shapes. The fabric team, as a matter of course, worked to replace conventional materials with refashioned eco-friendly versions having a suitable supply chain. In addition, reviews were put in place, such as tagging design boards with an “e” logo to indicate what products had an ecological component, to assess what portion of each new line addressed company sustainability goals.</p><p>Second, designers worked to optimize timing and resources. Early order placements for organic cotton were required for product developers to hedge against the variable nature of commodity supply and demand. In addition, a designer noted, “It’s integral to the design process to commit early enough to both the materials and to the design, so that we can ship by sea instead of by air.” In addition to adjusting their calendars, the design process facilitator (Lauren, personal communication, June 17, 2011) reduced the breadth of samples requested in order to limit waste of both materials and of manpower:</p><disp-quote><p>What we realized was that the timeline that worked great for our Asian suppliers was not supporting what the people in Peru needed to be successful … So we back everything up … to make sure they have time that they need to get the protos to us on time.</p></disp-quote><p>Designers found it necessary to go “upstream” and “hands-on” to solve problems with aesthetics and quality. It was noteworthy that designers took the lead, rather than quality control experts or the agent. In doing so, they discovered the critical value of direct experience with the artisans for the purpose of fitting, finishing, and ironing out problems with garments. The agent and supply chain manager for the contractor DI was asked to suspend his typical role of intermediary in order to create space for direct relationships and knowledge sharing between the artisans and the design team. The sweater designer declared, “I think I am more comfortable and understand what Peru’s limitations are and wouldn’t push them to a place they can’t understand, or know what I am talking about, or be able to achieve” (Miriam, personal communication, July 26, 2011). She explored different finishes that they could achieve to make the garments look less rustic and devised new draping constructions for added interest. Hands-on tutoring elevated product quality and achieved EF’s expected aesthetic level. The design process and timing were adjusted for routine travel to Peru at the juncture between prototypes and samples until such trips were no longer needed. The sweater designer emphasized, “I feel the face to face time just put us all on the same page” (Miriam, personal communication, July 26, 2011).</p><p>The design team determined it must stabilize order quantities—the original cause of KP’s overproduction—which were followed by unstable working conditions for the knitters, so it submitted smaller but steadier orders. Designers also developed new products for alternate seasons to keep suppliers in year-round production. The sustainability leader described the lesson they learned about stability a small entrepreneur needs from a bigger company, “You can’t do that up and down thing like we do in the fashion industry. They need a steady workload. It doesn’t have to be big; it just has to be steady because they’re supporting people” (Alicia, personal communication, July 7, 2011). In addition, EF honored the artisan’s timeframes instead of forcing theirs on them. Artisans are based from 3 to 6 hr away from the central city and are mothers whose kids are going to and from school, so the production had to be on their time frame. “For a while it was like, ‘you’ve got to speed it up!’ But the beauty of working with a community like that is that you want to allow them their lives,” said the director of social consciousness (Joy, personal communication, June 6, 2011). The combination of respect, commitment, and guidance toward supply partners was key to EF’s fourth solution to manage supplier relationships responsibly and for the long term.</p><p>The design process priority included fulfilling the design vision first. “The design has to be compelling for the customer to buy it” (Melissa, personal communication, June 17, 2011); but it also followed a parallel track to embed sustainability into its core business practices. Data revealed that “people want to be more sustainable but they feel they have to have the go-ahead from the company, because of the economics of it” (Joy, personal communication, June 6, 2011). With organic cotton costing about 25% more than conventional cotton, and fair trade labor costing more, EF’s clear mission and mandate for sustainability empowered employees to make choices:</p><disp-quote><p>We have organic cotton in a lot of our tops; it’s about 75% … and the way we have been able to manage that is to absorb some of the margin and make it more affordable for our customers. If we really passed the entire cost onto our customers, we wouldn’t sell any of it. That’s the truth. (Joy, personal communication, June 6, 2011)</p></disp-quote><p>Trade-offs balancing company values and cost were, therefore, made by the design team as the solution to the higher costs incurred for following principles to which they were committed.</p></sec><sec id="section11-0887302X12472724"><title>Principles for Effective Sustainable Design</title><p>EF’s strong mandate was a by-product of the grassroots endeavors of the firm’s members, some of whom were very passionate about sustainability. However, it is ultimately the mission of the company that enables change to happen. “An individual holding a torch in a company is not sustainable. If you want to light a fire, you have to hand the torch from the individual to the company; the company has to hold the torch” (Melissa, personal communication, June 17, 2011). The necessity of a <italic>strong company mandate</italic> is the first principle.</p><p>Second, participants imparted that developing sustainable designs with suppliers requires shared values within and across organizations. They acknowledged that EF assessed the general value system of its suppliers, agents, third party companies, and employees before enlisting them. In addition, EF aspires to do business with those engaged in socially responsible practices; this imperative for a <italic>core values match</italic> was also expressed by of the owner of DI (Rick, personal communication, July 12, 2011):</p><disp-quote><p>We have a certain amount of capacity and we’re looking for the right partners … One of the reasons that we have chosen to work with Eileen Fisher is because there is a core values match … Their company sees the value of what we are doing in our company, so that’s the common denominator.</p></disp-quote><p>To <italic>gather and diffuse information</italic> is a third principle EF practiced. For example, the sustainability leader enlisted a third party to perform life cycle assessments on the main fibers in the line. Based on by the LCA data, EF devised an internal ranking schedule for fiber types as well as dyeing and finishing processes. The cumulative score informs designers on the sustainability of each product so they can determine how to best meet environmental objectives. EF also advocated supply chain transparency by posting a list of all vendors on the website in order to inform consumers and hold suppliers accountable. Low impact care instructions were promoted to the consumer with “hand wash and line dry” labels to counter the detrimental effects of laundering and dry cleaning and to get people on board to support sustainable practices.</p><p>The fourth principle of practicing <italic>cross-functional organization</italic> grew out of EF’s collaborative culture and how it was already operating, but formally organized and codified it. More than 40 cross-functional teams were ongoing, and teams arose and dissolved depending on the needs of the company, supporting the research suggesting that sustainable design requires an integrative approach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0887302X12472724">Hong et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0887302X12472724">White et al., 2008</xref>). Data revealed the important role of the eco-team, an oversight group who acted as advocates for sustainable design initiatives. Cross-functional in nature, the team was made up of individuals from the areas of social responsibility, sales, manufacturing, design process, fabric, and design. The eco-team spawned eco-product and eco-business subteams. Eco-team members were members of other teams such as the core concept team, leadership forum, process team, facilitating leader team, and creative forum. EF’s leadership system supported the cross-pollination of information between departments, facilitating sustainable practices in the company as well as in the design process.</p><p>Participants accorded that local sourcing and a small supply chain were unique and key factors for the success of the Peru program’s success, highlighting a fifth principle: the <italic>significance of the supply chain</italic>. Cotton crops are grown on certified organic farms right in the area where suppliers are knitting and spinning the yarn. “It’s very unusual, especially in yarn [sourcing]. It’s hard to find that kind of small supply chain anywhere else really” (Miriam, personal communication, July 26, 2011). The V.P. of manufacturing believes the Peru supply chain comes very close to meeting EF’s vision of sustainability. “It is probably the most closed, clean loop that we actually have” (Debra, personal communication, July 7, 2011).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="section12-0887302X12472724"><title>Conclusions and Discussion</title><p>This study has shown that, despite the advantage of employing a local Peruvian supply chain for its eco-friendly attributes, EF faced and surmounted a number of challenges for a viable program of sustainable sweaters. The solutions exercised had manifold effects, which are outlined in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0887302X12472724">Table 2</xref>. Samples had a timely arrival for adoption into the line, despite putting a temporary strain on the sweater designer each season; the producers assumed a steady workload and could anticipate business accordingly; product quality improved, supply chain relationships were strengthened, and the product became more salable through improved quality and more competitive pricing. Furthermore, EF possessed a sustainable sweater marketing story that may serve to position the company for competitive advantage in the long term.</p><p>Research questions have been answered as follows: (1) maintaining product value, quality, and aesthetics, meeting needs of suppliers, and coping with higher material and labor costs are the design and product development challenges encountered in the creation of EF’s sustainable product line; (2) creative thinking, flexibility, and knowledge sharing, both in EF and with its suppliers, support sustainability objectives; and (3) as a result, relationships between the case company and its upstream supply chain are strengthened for the long term.</p><p>All of the solutions and principles which emerged from this research concur with those reviewed in the Product Development Considerations section of this article, such as integrative product design, the importance of an organization’s values, focus on materials, and the necessity of design innovation. The combination of solutions and principles from EF’s Peru project scenario is organized in a conceptual process map in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0887302X12472724">Figure 1</xref>. The company mandate is the underpinning to overcoming problems affecting successful sustainable outcomes. While other companies may have abandoned the Peru project due to the challenges with quality and price, EF persevered because the program embodied those values in which the company and its employees believed. Next, EF defined its priorities for products by their aesthetic and sustainable merits, as well as the supply chain arrangement. Knowledge sharing followed with the gathering and diffusing of ideas among colleagues, suppliers, and other stakeholders; and matching core values between EF and its supply chain partners. EF reorganized to create the cross-functional eco-team and restructured supply chain communication. Finally, skillful attention was paid to design components such as materials, timing, and sourcing, and to relationship components, such as respect for, commitment to, and guidance of its suppliers. “Define,” “Adapt,” and “Relate” are overarching stages of the process for sustainable outcomes.</p><fig id="fig1-0887302X12472724" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Sustainable design process map of Eileen Fisher’s Peru project: interactions of design team and upstream supply chain (<italic>illustrated by the researcher</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0887302X12472724-fig1.tif"/></fig><p>EF’s sustainable design strategy was not radical; it considered the existing systems and processes in the textile and apparel industry and worked within those parameters. While EF nurtured its internal organizational structure, the design team zeroed on areas in the upstream supply chain where it could make the most difference in eliminating environmental impacts of its product. EF approached the journey as one of continuous improvement to slowly shift industry practices toward becoming more ecological. Implications of this study for EF are to keep organizational structure fluid; to redefine priorities according to the particular sustainability objective or initiative; and to explore new ways of knowledge sharing to develop and test additional sustainability models. Whether or not the same sustainable model of organic + fair trade is a viable one for new programs remains to be seen. The implications for other apparel companies are that surmounting challenges of sustainable product development starts with a clear mission, strong company mandate, and like-minded supply chain partners.</p><sec id="section13-0887302X12472724"><title>For Future Study</title><p>The richness of this study is that a case study of one apparel company enabled the researchers to evaluate the interworkings of a complete design team and some of its suppliers in the development of a sustainable product. In the context of the entire textile and apparel supply network, EF’s Peru supply chain may be unique; however, this company provides a reference to the challenges of disruptive change within the design process. As previously discussed, the review of literature and the observations of the case company indicate useful practices for nurturing sustainable new product development through design process and supply chain focus. To shed additional light on the subject, researchers should consider conducting cross-case studies of various apparel companies’ sustainable design and supply chain dynamics in order to reveal and compare similar and/or different strategies throughout the upstream and downstream supply chain. In addition, only one of the present case company’s sustainable initiatives was reported on in this article. Conducting further research on the other initiatives undertaken by the case company may offer a more comprehensive picture of how sustainable design practices in a single company compare and contrast. The authors believe that, in beginning to fill an area of limited research, examination of the connections between design process and supply chain focus is imperative for advancing sustainable practices in the apparel and textile industry.</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn1-0887302X12472724"><label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label><p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2-0887302X12472724"><label>Funding</label><p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allwood</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laursen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malvido de Rodriguez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>An approach to scenario analysis of the sustainability of an industrial sector applied to clothing and textiles in the UK</article-title>. <source>Journal of Cleaner production</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>1234</fpage>–<lpage>1246</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>LeHew</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Sustainable apparel product development: In search of a new dominant social paradigm for the field using sustainable approaches</article-title>. <source>Fashion Practice</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>29</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.2752/175693811X12925927157018</comment></citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bevilacqua</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciarapica</surname><given-names>F. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giacchette</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchetti</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>A carbon footprint analysis in the textile supply chain</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Sustainable Engineering</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhamra</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Building ecodesign throughout the supply chain: A new imperative for the textile &amp; clothing industry</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Miraftab </surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horrocks</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (Eds.), <source>Ecotextiles: The way forward for sustainable development</source> (pp. <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>49</lpage>). Cambridge: <publisher-name>Woodhead Publishing Limited</publisher-name>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhamra</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lofthouse</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Design for sustainability: A practical approach</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (Ed.). <publisher-loc>Hampshire (pp. 37-38), England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Gower</publisher-name>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farr</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gam</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>An environmental sustainability course for design and merchandising student</article-title>. <source>Journal of Family &amp; Consumer Sciences</source>, <volume>98</volume>, <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>To</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>How are supply chains coordinated: An empirical observation in textile-apparel buisiness</article-title>. <source>Journal of Fashion Marketing and Management</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>384</fpage>–<lpage>396</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Environmental analysis of textile products</article-title>. <source>Clothing and Textiles Research Journal</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>248</fpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Trust and knowledge sharing in green supply chains</article-title>. <source>Supply Chain Management: An International Journal</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>283</fpage>–<lpage>295</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Building a sustainable supply chain: An analysis of corporate social respponsibility (CSR) practices in the Chinese textile and apparel industry</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Textile Institute</source>, <volume>102</volume>, <fpage>837</fpage>–<lpage>848</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chouinard</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Going organic: Converting Patagonia’s cotton product line</article-title>. <source>Journal of Industrial Ecology</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>129</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="web"><collab collab-type="author">Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs</collab>. (<year>2011</year>). <source>Sustainable clothing road map progress report</source>. <publisher-loc>London, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>. <comment>Retrieved from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/publications/2011/06/02/pb13461-clothing-roadmap/">http://www.defra.gov.uk/publications/2011/06/02/pb13461-clothing-roadmap/</ext-link></citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doorey</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The transparent supply chain: From resistance to implementation at Nike and Levi-Strauss</article-title>. <source>Journal of Business Ethics</source>, <volume>103</volume>, <fpage>587</fpage>–<lpage>603</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1007/s10551-011-0882-1</comment></citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Easton</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Supply chain partnerships for sustainable textile production</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Miraftab</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (Ed.), <source>Ecotextiles: The way forward for sustainable development</source> (pp. <fpage>50</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, England</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Woodhead Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="web"><collab collab-type="author">European Commission</collab>. (<year>2011</year>). <source>Ecodesign your future</source>. <comment>Retrieved January 30, 2012, from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ec.europa.eu/enterprise/policies/sustainable-business/ecodesign/files/brochure_ecodesign_en.pdf">http://ec.europa.eu/enterprise/policies/sustainable-business/ecodesign/files/brochure_ecodesign_en.pdf</ext-link></citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Organising environmental supply chain management: Experience from a sector with frequent product shifts and complex product chains: The case of the Danish textile sector</article-title>. <source>Greener Management International</source>, <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gam</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farr</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heine</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>C2CAD: A sustainable apparel design and production model</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Clothing Science and Technology</source>, <volume>21</volume>, <fpage>166</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gam</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Banning</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Adressing sustainable aparel design challenges with problem based learning</article-title>. <source>Clothing and Textiles Research Journal</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>202</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1177/0887302X11414874</comment></citation></ref><ref id="bibr19a-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1967</year>). <source>The discovery of Grounded Theory: Strategies for Qualitative Research</source>. <publisher-loc>Hawthorne, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Aldine Publishing Company</publisher-name>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ha-Brookshire</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Norum</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Cotton and sustainability: Impacting student learning through sustainable Cotton summit</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Sustainability in Higher Education</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>369</fpage>–<lpage>380</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1108/14676371111168287</comment></citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>H.-B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Implementation of strategic green orientation in supply chain: An empirical study of manufacturing firms</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Innovation Management</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>512</fpage>–<lpage>532</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howarth</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadfield</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>A sustainable product design model</article-title>. <source>Materials and Design</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>1128</fpage>–<lpage>1133</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Materials selection for environmentally conscious design via a proposed life cycle environmental performance index</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Advanced Manufacturing Technology</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>1073</fpage>–<lpage>1082</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacques</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agnogino</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guimaraes</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Sustainable product development initiatives in the footwear industry based on the cradle to cradle concept</source>. <comment>15th Design for Manufacturing and the Lifecycle Conference</comment>. <publisher-loc>Montreal, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ASME</publisher-name>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kocken</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006, February</year>). <source>EFTA: Joining fair trade forces</source>. <comment>Retrieved December 13, 2011, from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.european-fair-trade-association.org/efta/Doc/What.pdf">http://www.european-fair-trade-association.org/efta/Doc/What.pdf</ext-link></citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kogg</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Greening a Cotton-textile supply chain: A case study of the transition toward organic production without a powerful focal company</article-title>. <source>Greener Management International</source>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levenson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008, November 24</year>). <article-title>Citizen Nike</article-title>. <source>Fortune</source>, <volume>158</volume>, <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>170</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacPherson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Redefining the approach, widening the lens</source>. <comment>National Education Conference Papers</comment>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Industrial Designers Society of America</publisher-name>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McDonough</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Braungart</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Cradle to cradle: Remaking the way we make things</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>North Point Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McDonough</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Braungart</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anastos</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Applying the principles of green engineering to cradle to cradle design</article-title>. <source>Environmental Science &amp; Technology</source>, <fpage>434A</fpage>–<lpage>441A</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mentzer</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>DeWitt</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keebler</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nix</surname><given-names>N. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zacahria</surname><given-names>Z. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Defining supply chain management</article-title>. <source>Journal of Business Logistics</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr31-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morana</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seuring</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>A three level framework for closed-loop supply chain management: Linking society, chain and actor level</article-title>. <source>Sustainability</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>678</fpage>–<lpage>691</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.3390/su3040678</comment></citation></ref><ref id="bibr32-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muthu</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mok</surname><given-names>P. Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Quantification of environmental impact and ecological sustainability for textile fibres</article-title>. <source>Ecological Indicators</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>66</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr33-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niinimaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Emerging design strategies in sustainable production and consumption of textiles and clothing</article-title>. <source>Journal Of Cleaner Production</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>1876</fpage>–<lpage>1833</lpage>. <comment>doi:10.1016/j.jclepro.2011.04.020</comment></citation></ref><ref id="bibr34-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="web"><collab collab-type="author">Nike</collab>. (<year>2010</year>). <source>Nike considered designs</source>. <comment>Retrieved January 24, 2012, from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nikebiz.com/responsibility/Pages/CalculatorPage.aspx">http://www.nikebiz.com/responsibility/Pages/CalculatorPage.aspx</ext-link></citation></ref><ref id="bibr35-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oakes</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011, July 7</year>). <source>How the eco-index is leading apparel to a green future</source>. <comment>Retrieved January 21, 2012, from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.greenbiz.com/blog/2011/07/06/eco-index?page=0%2C0">http://www.greenbiz.com/blog/2011/07/06/eco-index?page=0%2C0</ext-link></citation></ref><ref id="bibr36-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="web"><collab collab-type="author">Patagonia</collab>. (<year>2011</year>). <source>The footprint chronicles tool</source>. <comment>Retrieved March 11, 2011, from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.patagonia.com/us/footprint/index.jsp">http://www.patagonia.com/us/footprint/index.jsp</ext-link></citation></ref><ref id="bibr37-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Handfield</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ragatz</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Supplier integration into new product development: Coordination product, process and supply chain design</article-title>. <source>Journal of Operations Management</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>371</fpage>–<lpage>388</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr38-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <source>Competitive advantage: Creating and sustaining superior performance</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Free Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr39-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Charon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ewell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Design for the next generation: Incorporating cradle-to-cradle design into Herman Miller products</article-title>. <source>Journal of Industrial Ecology</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr40-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seuring</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>From a literature review to a conceptual framework for sustainable supply chain management</article-title>. <source>Journal of Cleaner Production</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>1699</fpage>–<lpage>1710</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr41-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waage</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Re-considering product design: A practical “road-map” for integration of sustainability issues</article-title>. <source>Journal of Cleaner Production</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>638</fpage>–<lpage>649</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr42-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Howes</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Allied for sustainable design: An a-b-c-d approach to making better products</source>. <publisher-name>Retrieved from http://www.bsr.org/reports/BSR_Sustainable_Design_Report_0508.pdf</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="bibr43-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Worley</surname><given-names>C. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feyerherm</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knudsen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Building a collaboration capability for sustainability: How Gap, Inc. is creating and leveraging a strategic asset</article-title>. <source>Organizational Dynamics</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>334</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bibr44-0887302X12472724"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Case study research: Design and methods</source> (<edition>4th ed</edition>.). <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>