<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JIV</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjiv</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Interpers Violence</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Interpersonal Violence</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0886-2605</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-6518</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0886260512448850</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0886260512448850</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Across Racial/Ethnic Boundaries</article-title>
<subtitle>Investigating Intimate Violence Within a National Sample</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Carbone-Lopez</surname><given-names>Kristin</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0886260512448850">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0886260512448850"><label>1</label>University of Missouri—St. Louis, Saint Louis, MO, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0886260512448850">Kristin Carbone-Lopez, Department of Criminology and Criminal Justice, University of Missouri, St. Louis, One University Boulevard, 324 Lucas Hall, Saint Louis, MO 63121, USA Email: <email>carbonelopezk@umsl.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>28</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>3</fpage>
<lpage>24</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The number of interracial relationships in the United States continues to increase. The fact is, though, that race remains a significant influence in the lives of individuals and in their relationships. Although there is evidence that relationships that cross racial/ethnic boundaries may be at greater risk for conflict and dissolution, there have been few investigations as to whether such relationships are at greater risk for violence. Using data from the National Violence Against Women Survey, I find that there are differences in risk of intimate violence depending on the racial/ethnic dyad of the couple. Ethnic monoracial relationships demonstrate the greatest risk for physical and nonphysical forms of violence, controlling for structural factors, whereas women in interracial relationships report higher rates of nonphysical violence, as compared with women in White monoracial relationships. Implications for theory and practice are discussed.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>race/ethnicity</kwd>
<kwd>interracial relationships</kwd>
<kwd>domestic violence</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0886260512448850" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Efforts over the past three decades have yielded considerable knowledge about victimization, particularly violence against women by intimate partners. National data sources indicate. By now, scholars have amassed considerable knowledge on the victimization experiences of women, including violence by intimate partners. National data sources indicate that a sizeable proportion of women experience some form of violence within an intimate relationship in the United States (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0886260512448850">Straus &amp; Gelles, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0886260512448850">Tjaden &amp; Thoennes, 2000</xref>). And whereas intimate violence can occur across all racial, ethnic, and social class groups, there is increasing evidence that women of color and women living in poverty may be at greater risk of violence by intimate partners (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0886260512448850">Benson, Fox, DeMaris, &amp; Van Wyck, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0886260512448850">Lauritsen &amp; Schaum, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0886260512448850">Rennison &amp; Welchans, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0886260512448850">Tjaden &amp; Thoennes, 2000</xref>). Further attention to the role of race/ethnicity and other structural factors in victimization risk, however, is warranted.</p>
<p>In particular, the population structure of the United States is shifting and—with it—the composition and dynamics of intimate relationships. Although relationships between persons of different racial and ethnic backgrounds were historically legally prohibited (and often punished greatly), interracial or interethnic relationships are becoming somewhat more common. In fact, based on 2000 Census data, approximately 7% of the 61.5 million married and cohabiting couples were interracial (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0886260512448850">Rosenfeld &amp; Kim, 2005</xref>), an increase from previous years. These numerical increases do not necessarily indicate total social acceptance of such relationships. Moreover, there is emerging evidence that some individuals in interracial relationships face additional stressors and that interracial relationships overall may be at greater risk of dissolution and divorce as compared with intraracial marriages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0886260512448850">Bramlett &amp; Mosher, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0886260512448850">Bratter &amp; King, 2008</xref>). Whether interracial relationships are at greater risk of intimate <italic>violence</italic>, however, remains relatively unclear.</p>
<p>Using data from the National Violence Against Women Survey (NVAWS), I examine whether the prevalence and nature of intimate violence differs among interracial versus intraracial couples in the United States. In particular, I ask whether there are significant prevalence differences when comparing interracial, monoracial White, and ethnic minority monoracial relationships. Second, because prior research notes the importance of examining various forms of intimate partner violence (IPV), including physical and sexual violence, emotional abuse, and stalking (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0886260512448850">Johnson, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0886260512448850">Kaukinen, 2004</xref>), I investigate whether there are there significant differences in the <italic>forms</italic> of intimate violence experienced by each group.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0886260512448850">
<title>Intimate Partner Violence and Race/Ethnicity</title>
<p>Domestic violence scholars have long argued that relationship or intimate violence occurs across all racial, ethnic, and socioeconomic lines. At the same time, though, there is evidence that women of color and impoverished women may be at somewhat greater risks of victimization compared with White women or women with greater financial resources (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0886260512448850">Benson et al., 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0886260512448850">Lauritsen &amp; Schaum, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0886260512448850">Rennison &amp; Welchans, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0886260512448850">Tjaden &amp; Thoennes, 2000</xref>). Moreover, ethnic minority monoracial couples appear to also have higher rates of intimate violence compared with monoracial White couples. Within broad population-based and community samples, Black, Hispanic, and American Indian couples report rates of violence that are higher than White couples (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0886260512448850">Bachman, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0886260512448850">Neff, Holamon, &amp; Schluter, 1995</xref>; Sorenson, Upchurch, &amp; Shen, 1995; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0886260512448850">Straus, Gelles &amp; Steinmetz, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0886260512448850">Straus &amp; Smith, 1990</xref>) and they also are at greater risk for recurring violence during the relationship (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0886260512448850">Caetano, Field, Ramisetty-Mikler, &amp; McGrath, 2005</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0886260512448850">1</xref></sup> Furthermore, the rates of more serious physical violence appear to be higher within ethnic minority couples (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0886260512448850">Straus et al., 1980</xref>).</p>
<p>To explain the increased risk of violence among ethnic minorities in the United States, scholars initially suggested that higher prevalence rates of violence among certain groups result from their greater acceptance of the use of violence as a means to settle conflicts. Disadvantaged communities and groups, in particular, may develop norms that emphasize masculine (i.e., tough) reputation, independence, and ultimately the willingness to use violence against others, even intimate partners (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0886260512448850">Messerschmidt, 1993</xref>). These community norms surrounding violence also have implications for the likelihood that other members of the community will witness or intervene in situations of violence against women (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0886260512448850">Browning, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>Yet focusing on cultural differences excludes the important role of structural conditions. The social structural theory proposes instead that it is not the cultural characteristics or norms of a group that are related to violence, but rather the structural conditions that members of the group face, such as poverty, low educational attainment, high unemployment, and discrimination based on race/ethnicity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0886260512448850">Benson et al, 2003</xref>). These factors may then mediate the relationship between race/ethnicity and violence; restricted access to economic resources and individual opportunities because of race/ethnicity may increase stress and consequently contribute to increased risk of intimate violence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0886260512448850">Gelles &amp; Straus, 1988</xref>). Indeed, there is some evidence that once other factors including socioeconomic indicators, alcohol use, and family history of violence are taken into account, the differences in rates of physical violence between White and Hispanic couples, but not between Black and White couples, disappear (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0886260512448850">Caetano, Cunradi, Clark &amp; Schafer, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0886260512448850">Kantor, Jasinski, &amp; Aldarando, 1994</xref>). Consequently, there exist quite complicated (and even contradictory) relationships between race, ethnicity, and intimate violence in the United States (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0886260512448850">West, 2005</xref>). And it is clear that factors outside of the race/ethnicity of members of intimate relationships are relevant as well.</p>
<p>Interracial couples, like all couples, “function in and are affected by the larger societal composition” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0886260512448850">Potter, 2006</xref>, p. 116). Each member of the couple has his/her own lived experiences of race, class, and gender within the “often inescapable rules of race relations in this country” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0886260512448850">Childs, 2005</xref>, p. 19) and these experiences may affect intimate relationships. In relationships that bridge racial and ethnic divides, the marginalization and domination experienced by the minority partner may extend into the relationship. Racism, accusations of it, or suspicions of it, may surface even in the most committed relationships; indeed, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0886260512448850">Rosenblatt and colleagues (1995)</xref> found that, within their sample, racially loaded statements were occasionally used in anger or even in a sarcastic manner by interracial couples during conflicts. Whether racially charged conflict translates into greater risk for physical or other forms of abuse, however, is unclear. There is some evidence that rates of <italic>lethal</italic> violence are somewhat higher within interracial marriages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0886260512448850">Mercy &amp; Saltzman, 1989</xref>), but there has been little systematic exploration of potential differences in rates and patterns of nonlethal violence, including both physical and emotional abuse, in interracial—as compared to monoracial—relationships. The unique legal and social histories and contemporary experiences of interracial couples, however, suggest that they experience continued structural and social challenges. As a result, we might expect such relationships to be at somewhat greater risk of interpersonal stress and, consequently, violence.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0886260512448850">
<title>Interracial Relationships: Conflict and Functioning</title>
<p>Interracial marriage and cohabitation rates have increased in the United States more than fivefold since the 1970s when interracial marriages comprised less than 1% of all marriages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0886260512448850">Lee &amp; Edmonston, 2005</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0886260512448850">2</xref></sup> However, such relationships are still far from typical. And despite these increases, and the repeal of laws that legally prohibit these relationships,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0886260512448850">3</xref></sup> interracial relationships in this country continue to face social disapproval and even discrimination. Although two decades ago there was a great deal of animus regarding interracial marriage and dating, the majority of Americans today agree that people of different races should be able to date and marry one another (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0886260512448850">Ludwig, 2004</xref>). Yet, despite this level of endorsement, race and ethnicity continue to have a powerful effect on experiences—both individual and relational—in the United States. Individuals involved in interracial relationships, although not prevented by law, may face disapproval and even ostracism from acquaintances, friends, and family members. They may also be less likely to publicly announce their relationship, even to the point of hiding it from their family and friends (Wang, Kao &amp; Joyner, 2004). And marginalization and disapproval may take their toll, not only on the individuals involved in interracial relationships, but also on the relationships themselves; there is evidence, for example, that interracial relationships may be at greater risk of dissolution or divorce (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0886260512448850">Bramlett &amp; Mosher, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0886260512448850">Bratter &amp; King, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>Higher rates of dissolution may signal that interracial relationships suffer from reduced commitment, greater conflict between partners, or increased pressure from the outside to end the relationship. Indeed, some studies have noted that members of interracial relationships report lower levels of relationship satisfaction compared with those involved in monoracial relationships (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0886260512448850">Forry, Leslie, &amp; Letiecq, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0886260512448850">Hohmann-Marriott &amp; Amato, 2008</xref>; but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0886260512448850">Troy, Lewis-Smith, &amp; Laurenceau 2006</xref>). Moreover, there is evidence that persons involved in interracial couples may face obstacles and challenges to their relationships not encountered by persons within monoracial relationships including family opposition, mistreatment in commercial settings, and even obscene phone calls, hate mail, and vandalized property (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0886260512448850">Rosenblatt et al., 1995</xref>). Such relationships may also be complicated by language barriers and differences in expectations regarding love, sex, and childrearing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0886260512448850">Usita &amp; Poulsen, 2003</xref>).</p>
<p>Other factors may also account for some of the observed gap in relationship quality between interracial and monoracial couples including complex relationship histories, relationship heterogamy and low socioeconomic status (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0886260512448850">Hohmann-Marriott &amp; Amato, 2008</xref>). Interracial couples report prior marriages and cohabitations, living with stepchildren, and parental divorce at greater rates than monoracial couples. Members of interracial relationships are also more likely to differ in age, education level, and religion compared with those in monoracial relationships. These differences can lead to status inconsistencies where either the male (traditional status arrangement) or female partner (status reversal) has a greater level of perceived (or actual) power within the relationship based on their educational, financial, and occupational resources or race/ethnicity. Such inconsistencies may increase the risk of men using both physical violence and emotional abuse toward their partners (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0886260512448850">Coleman &amp; Straus, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0886260512448850">Kaukinen, 2004</xref>). And, given the racialized socioeconomic structure of the United States, interracial couples, on average, may have fewer resources available to them than couples in which both partners are White. These unique stressors, coupled with the lack of social support, may put interracial relationships at greater risk for conflict and even violence.</p>
<p>Until recently, there have been few empirical investigations of this issue. In one important recent example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0886260512448850">Fusco (2010)</xref> examined all cases of intimate violence reported to police within a large suburban county over a one-year period. She found a number of important racial dyad differences in couple history, incident characteristics, and likelihood of arrest. Specifically, interracial couples were more likely to have a prior history of IPV calls to police and to engage in “mutual” assault, and their violence was more likely to result in injury and perpetrator arrest, compared with white and ethnic minority monoracial couples. Although these findings provide important insight into the nature and prevalence of violence within interracial couples, they are limited by a reliance on incidents known to law enforcement. Therefore, it is impossible to determine whether rates of violence truly differ among interracial couples or whether their IPV experiences are more likely to come to the attention of law enforcement. Perhaps more importantly, limiting an analysis to only IPV incidents known to police overemphasizes the importance of physical violence, yet scholars generally note that IPV includes many other components such as emotional or controlling behavior as well as threats of violence, sexual violence, and stalking.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0886260512448850">
<title>Present Research</title>
<p>In the present work, I begin to explore the prevalence and nature of violence within interracial couples in the United States. In particular, the focus here is whether rates of violence differ across race/ethnic group; in other words, are interracial relationships at greater risk of intimate violence, as compared with White or ethnic minority monoracial relationships? Second, I question whether the nature of intimate violence differs depending on the race/ethnic composition of the relationship. More specifically, I am interested in whether interracial relationships at greater risk for <italic>both</italic> physical and emotional forms of IPV or if one type is more prevalent among interracial relationships. Answers to such questions can provide additional information on how race/ethnicity and race relations in the United States shape the experience and interpretation of violence and provide important clues for practitioners.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0886260512448850" sec-type="methods">
<title>Data and Method</title>
<p>To address these research objectives, I use the NVAWS. The survey was cosponsored by the National Institute of Justice (NIJ), the National Center for Injury Prevention and Control (NCIPC), and the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). The sample was drawn as a national, random-digit dialing (RDD) sample of telephone households in the United States and subsequently stratified by U.S. Census region. The “most-recent-birthday method” was used to select the designated respondent in households with multiple eligible respondents. The final sample included 8,000 women and 8,005 men of 18 years and older, representing an overall participation rate of 72% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0886260512448850">Tjaden &amp; Thoennes, 2000</xref>, p. 4). Only women are included in the present analysis.</p>
<p>A unique feature of the survey is that it gathered respondents’ lifetime experiences of physical and sexual assault (including victimization that occurred in childhood), emotional abuse and controlling behavior by intimate partners, and physical, sexual, and stalking violence in adulthood. In eliciting this information, respondents were first asked a series of behavior-specific screening questions regarding acts of violence (e.g., “has anyone ever pushed, grabbed or shoved you?”). Respondents were then asked a series of more detailed questions pertaining to the incident, including their relationship to the attacker. If the perpetrator was a spouse or cohabiting partner, respondents were asked to identify whether it was a current or former partner. In the present analyses, I focus only on the respondent’s <italic>current</italic> (marital or cohabiting) relationship.</p>
<p>Information on violence within the current relationship is coupled with additional information from the respondent on their current spouse or cohabiting partner. Respondents were asked to provide demographic information, including race, age, and educational attainment, only for their current partner. The analyses are restricted to women involved in a cohabiting or marital relationship at the time the survey was administered and who responded to the questions asked about their current partner. In addition, the sample is restricted to respondents who identified their (and their partner’s) race and/or ethnicity, yielding a total sample size of 5,200 women.</p>
<sec id="section6-0886260512448850">
<title>Dependent Variables</title>
<p>As the primary focus is on experiences of intimate violence, several dependent variables are used in these analyses which provide information on various forms of IPV. These include minor physical violence, severe physical violence, sexual assault, stalking, threats of violence, and nonphysical emotional abuse and control behaviors. Using items derived from the modified Conflict Tactics Scale (CTS) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0886260512448850">Straus, 1990</xref>), respondents indicated whether they had experienced a number of violent acts as an adult. These questions measure specific behaviors allowing researchers to determine whether women have been the victim of certain physical acts, regardless of whether women describe their experience as “abuse.” Research using the CTS often differentiates between “minor” and “severe” violence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0886260512448850">Feld &amp; Straus, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0886260512448850">Kalmuss &amp; Straus, 1982</xref>) and these categorizations are also used in the following analyses. <italic>Minor physical violence</italic> includes women’s reports of experiences of victimization by partners including pushing, grabbing, or shoving; pulling hair; of having something thrown at them that could hurt; or slapping or hitting. <italic>Severe physical violence</italic> includes experiences of: kicking or biting; choking or attempted drowning; having been hit with an object; beating up; threats made with a gun, knife or other weapon; or the use of any weapon on them. Measures were created to indicate each type of violence, minor or severe, perpetrated by the respondent’s current spouse or partner. Each of these two physical violence variables is dichotomous, where “1” indicates at least one previous experience of that type of physical violence within the current relationship.</p>
<p><italic>Sexual assault</italic> is also included as an indicator of violence within an intimate relationship. Respondents were asked whether a man or boy ever made or tried to make them have sex, including oral and anal sex, or sexually assaulted them by using force or threats. The measure used here includes only sexual assaults experienced in adulthood and perpetrated by respondents’ current partners. To measure <italic>stalking</italic> within the intimate relationship, respondents were asked whether they had experienced any of the following: Sending her unsolicited letters or written correspondence, following or spying on her, making unsolicited phone calls to her, standing outside her home, school, or workplace, showing up at places she was even though he had no business being there, leaving unwanted items for her to find, trying to communicate with her in other ways against her will, and vandalizing her property or destroying something she loved. In line with previous research, a respondent was coded as having experienced intimate stalking if she reported that (a) the behavior had occurred on more than one occasion; (b) the perpetrator was a current spouse or partner; and (c) she was either “very frightened by these behaviors or believed that she, or someone close to her, would be seriously harmed or killed during the harassment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0886260512448850">Tjaden &amp; Thoennes, 2000</xref>). Following questions about each of these physical forms of violence, respondents were also asked whether anyone had ever “threatened to harm or kill” them, aside from any incidents that had already been mentioned. <italic>Threats by a current partner or spouse</italic> are included in the analyses as well as a form of intimate violence. Each of these measures, sexual violence, stalking, and threats of violence are dichotomous such that a value of “1” indicates that particular form of violence by a current intimate partner.</p>
<p>Although one goal of the present analyses is to examine the possibility that diverse forms of violence occur differentially within interracial and monoracial intimate relationships, I also examine an indicator of <italic>any</italic> physical violence within the current relationship. Women who reported any form of physical violence, stalking, sexual assault, or threats of violence are thus included in this measure; a value of “1” indicates <italic>any</italic> form of physical violence by a current intimate partner.</p>
<p>Information was also included within the data on whether a woman had experienced any of a number of nonphysical controlling or emotionally abusive behaviors by a current partner. Often these behaviors are referred to as psychological or emotional abuse and are separated here into two dichotomous indicators of nonphysical behaviors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0886260512448850">Carbone-Lopez, Rennison, &amp; Macmillan, 2012</xref>). The first, called <italic>verbal aggression</italic> includes partners who (a) have a hard time seeing things from respondents’ point of view (b) try to provoke arguments (c) call the respondent names in front of others (d) make the respondent feel inadequate or (e) shout or swear at the respondent. The second measure of controlling behavior, <italic>coercive control</italic> (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0886260512448850">Stark, 2007</xref>), includes partners who (a) are jealous or possessive (b) try to limit respondents’ contact with family or friends (c) insist on knowing who respondents are with at all times (d) prevent respondents from having access to family income or (e) prevent the respondent from working outside of the home.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0886260512448850">
<title>Covariates</title>
<p>In these analyses, I am interested primarily in the possibility of differences in violence experiences depending on whether an intimate relationship crosses racial/ethnic boundaries. Thus, I compare three groups: White, non-Hispanic monoracial couples, ethnic minority monoracial couples, and interracial couples. The first group, which is the largest, is comprised of respondents who report that they and their current partner are <italic>White, non-Hispanic</italic> (<italic>n</italic> = 4,227). <italic>Ethnic minority monoracial</italic> couples include respondents and partners who are of the same race or ethnicity, but are non-White including couples where both individuals are Black, non-Hispanic (<italic>n</italic> = 291), those in which both individuals are Hispanic (<italic>n</italic> = 213), both are Asian or Pacific Islanders (<italic>n</italic> = 49), both are American Indian or Alaskan Natives (<italic>n</italic> = 8), and those in which both individuals identify as “mixed” race or ethnicity (<italic>n</italic> = 19). Altogether, 580 respondents (representing 11% of the sample) are involved in ethnic minority monoracial relationships. Finally, <italic>interracial</italic> couples include respondents and partners who fall into different racial/ethnic categories (<italic>n</italic> = 393).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0886260512448850">4</xref></sup> For example, a couple in which the woman was White and her current partner was Hispanic would be categorized as an interracial couple. This group constitutes 8% of the sample.</p>
<p>In addition to the racial/ethnic dyads, in the analyses I control for a number of other relevant factors for intimate violence. The first of these is <italic>respondent age</italic>, which is inversely related to risk of IPV (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0886260512448850">Rennison &amp; Welchans, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0886260512448850">Tjaden &amp; Thoennes, 2000</xref>). Age is included as a continuous measure and ranges from 18 to 97 years. Second, a common theme in existing literature is that there is a correlation between childhood victimization (both physical and sexual) and later experiences of violence. Women in the NVAWS were asked about physical violence they may have experienced as a child before the age of 18. Using the same modified CTS, they were asked to identify whether a parent or guardian had ever: thrown something that could hurt them, pushed, grabbed, or shoved them, pulled their hair, slapped or hit them, kicked or bit them, choked or attempted to drown them, hit them with an object, beat them up, or threatened them with or used a gun, knife, or other weapon against them. Using this information, a variable measuring childhood physical victimization is also included; “1” indicates any experience of physical violence by a parent or guardian in childhood.</p>
<p>The NVAWS also includes information on sexual victimization in childhood and adolescence. As noted, NVAWS respondents were asked whether they had experienced sexual assault at any time during their lifetime, including attempted and completed acts of forced sexual intercourse, as well as other forms of sexual assault such as someone inserting objects into their anus or vagina. If respondents indicated any experience of sexual assault, they were asked the age at which it occurred. If there were multiple assaults by a single perpetrator, they were also asked the age of the first and the most recent sexual assault. Using this information, a dichotomous indicator identifies women who had experienced <italic>childhood sexual assault</italic>, by any perpetrator, prior to the age of 18.</p>
<p>Other relationship dynamics are also related to the risk of intimate violence and are included here as control variables. To capture relative status differences between partners, which may be related to intimate violence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0886260512448850">Anderson, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0886260512448850">Kaukinen, 2004</xref>), I also include measures of the difference in educational attainment between respondents and their current partners. The original variables in the data ranged from “1” (<italic>no schooling</italic>) to “7” (<italic>postgraduate degree</italic>). I subtracted respondent education from partner education and this difference was then transformed into three dichotomous indicators: <italic>respondent higher educational attainment, partner higher educational attainment</italic>, and <italic>equal educational attainment</italic>. Finally, I also controlled for <italic>private health insurance</italic>, a variable indicating whether the respondent had private or employer-contributing health insurance, as compared to government-funded or no health insurance. Risk for intimate violence is greater among couples who are economically distressed (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0886260512448850">Benson et al., 2003</xref>); rather than use household income which has a large proportion of missing values, I use private health insurance as a proxy measure to capture relative wealth or economic status.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0886260512448850">5</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0886260512448850" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0886260512448850">Table 1</xref> presents descriptive characteristics of the entire sample as well as for each racial/ethnic relationship dyad. Moreover, the table also includes information on whether there are significant demographic or victimization differences across groups. Women in ethnic minority monoracial and interracial relationships are significantly younger than White women in relationships with White men. The partners of women in ethnic minority monoracial relationships are also younger than the partners of White women. Women in ethnic minority monoracial and interracial couples were also less likely to be married to their current partner. Finally, women in ethnic minority monoracial and interracial relationships were less likely to have private health insurance.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0886260512448850" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Descriptive Statistics by Race-Ethnic Dyad, National Violence Against Women Survey (1995-96)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0886260512448850" xlink:href="10.1177_0886260512448850-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Total Sample<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">White Monoracial<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Ethnic Monoracial<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Interracial/ Ethnic<hr/></th>
<th/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="center">%/Mean (<italic>SD</italic>)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="center">%/Mean (<italic>SD</italic>)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="center">%/Mean (<italic>SD</italic>)</th>
<th/>
<th align="center"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="center">%/Mean (<italic>SD</italic>)</th>
<th/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="10">Demographic characteristics</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Respondent age</td>
<td>5,125</td>
<td>43.61 (14.03)</td>
<td>4,171</td>
<td>44.53 (14.04)</td>
<td>568</td>
<td>39.64 (13.13)</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0886260512448850">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>386</td>
<td>39.56 (13.43)</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0886260512448850">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Partner age</td>
<td>5,107</td>
<td>46.15 (14.57)</td>
<td>4,161</td>
<td>47.03 (14.61)</td>
<td>562</td>
<td>42.30 (13.80)</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0886260512448850">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>384</td>
<td>42.15 (13.61)</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0886260512448850">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Married</td>
<td>5,198</td>
<td>90.2</td>
<td>4,225</td>
<td>91.8</td>
<td>580</td>
<td>84.5</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0886260512448850">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>393</td>
<td>81.4</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0886260512448850">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Respondent higher education</td>
<td>5,135</td>
<td>28.2</td>
<td>4,185</td>
<td>27.8</td>
<td>560</td>
<td>31.8</td>
<td/>
<td>390</td>
<td>27.4</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Partner higher education</td>
<td>5,135</td>
<td>26.4</td>
<td>4,185</td>
<td>26.6</td>
<td>560</td>
<td>24.1</td>
<td/>
<td>390</td>
<td>27.7</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Respondent and partner equal education</td>
<td>5,135</td>
<td>45.4</td>
<td>4,185</td>
<td>45.6</td>
<td>560</td>
<td>44.1</td>
<td/>
<td>390</td>
<td>44.9</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Private medical insurance</td>
<td>5,153</td>
<td>74.8</td>
<td>4,195</td>
<td>77.1</td>
<td>571</td>
<td>60.9</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0886260512448850">a</xref>, <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0886260512448850">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>387</td>
<td>69.8</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0886260512448850">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="10">Victimization histories</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Childhood physical violence</td>
<td>5,103</td>
<td>22.8</td>
<td>4,148</td>
<td>22.7</td>
<td>571</td>
<td>19.6</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0886260512448850">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>384</td>
<td>28.6</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0886260512448850">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Childhood sexual violence</td>
<td>5,167</td>
<td>8.9</td>
<td>4,200</td>
<td>8.7</td>
<td>577</td>
<td>7.5</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0886260512448850">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>390</td>
<td>13.6</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0886260512448850">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Violence within intimate relationship</td>
<td>5,005</td>
<td>5.1</td>
<td>4,065</td>
<td>4.5</td>
<td>558</td>
<td>8.1</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0886260512448850">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>382</td>
<td>7.1</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Minor physical violence</td>
<td>5,156</td>
<td>4.8</td>
<td>4,188</td>
<td>4.3</td>
<td>577</td>
<td>7.3</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0886260512448850">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>391</td>
<td>6.6</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Severe physical violence</td>
<td>5,156</td>
<td>1.7</td>
<td>4,191</td>
<td>1.5</td>
<td>574</td>
<td>2.8</td>
<td/>
<td>391</td>
<td>2.8</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Threats of violence</td>
<td>5,190</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>4,220</td>
<td>0.1</td>
<td>577</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td/>
<td>393</td>
<td>0.5</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Rape/sexual assault</td>
<td>5,137</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>4,176</td>
<td>0.1</td>
<td>573</td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td/>
<td>388</td>
<td>0.3</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Stalking</td>
<td>5,137</td>
<td>0.2</td>
<td>4,172</td>
<td>0.1</td>
<td>575</td>
<td>0.5</td>
<td/>
<td>390</td>
<td>0</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Verbal aggression</td>
<td>5,112</td>
<td>30.6</td>
<td>4,169</td>
<td>29.3</td>
<td>563</td>
<td>35.4</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0886260512448850">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>380</td>
<td>37.6</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0886260512448850">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Coercive control</td>
<td>5,137</td>
<td>17.2</td>
<td>4,179</td>
<td>14.1</td>
<td>569</td>
<td>31.8</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0886260512448850">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>389</td>
<td>28.8</td>
<td><sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0886260512448850">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>5,200</td>
<td/>
<td>4,227</td>
<td/>
<td>580</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>393</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0886260512448850">
<p>Note: Significant differences determined using one-way ANOVA with Bonferroni post hoc correction.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn2-0886260512448850">
<label>a</label>
<p>Significantly different from White mono-racial at <italic>p</italic> &lt;.05.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0886260512448850">
<label>b</label>
<p>Significantly different from interracial at <italic>p</italic> &lt;.05.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>In terms of violence histories, women in ethnic minority monoracial relationships report fewer experiences of childhood physical or sexual abuse compared with women in White monoracial or interracial relationships. In contrast, they are significantly more likely than White women involved with White men to report minor or any physical violence by an intimate partner. Interestingly, there were no differences in physical IPV when comparing White women in monoracial relationships with women in interracial couples. Nonphysical violence (both verbal aggression and coercive control) was more prevalent among women in ethnic minority monoracial and interracial relationships.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0886260512448850">6</xref></sup></p>
<p>Although the findings thus far suggest that there may be some differences in IPV experiences across racial/ethnic relationship dyads, it is also important to ascertain whether these differences hold after controlling for other relevant correlates of intimate violence. Thus, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0886260512448850">Table 2</xref> provides logistic regression results for overall (any) IPV, minor and severe physical intimate violence.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0886260512448850">7</xref></sup> After controlling for relevant correlates of IPV, interracial relationships were at no greater risk of any physical violence compared with White monoracial relationships. However, ethnic minority monoracial relationships were significantly more likely to involve physical violence (any or minor) compared with relationships composed of White women and White men. Beyond the race/ethnic relationship dyad effects, child physical and sexual abuse had quite large and positive effects on the likelihood that women would experience physical violence within a current relationship and these effects held regardless of the racial/ethnic composition of the relationship. Age had an inverse relationship with risk of severe physical violence, whereas the greater educational attainment of women relative to their partners translated into an increased risk of any physical IPV. Private medical insurance served as a protective factor against the likelihood of any form of physical violence, all else constant.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0886260512448850" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Logistic Regression Models Predicting Physical IPV, NVAWS (1995-96)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0886260512448850" xlink:href="10.1177_0886260512448850-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Any Physical Violence<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">“Minor” Physical Violence<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">“Severe” Physical Violence<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center"><italic>b</italic> (<italic>SE</italic>)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
<th align="center">exp(<italic>B</italic>)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>b</italic> (<italic>SE</italic>)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
<th align="center">exp(<italic>B</italic>)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>b</italic> (<italic>SE</italic>)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
<th align="center">exp(<italic>B</italic>)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="10">Covariates</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Interracial relationship<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0886260512448850">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.331 (0.224)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.315 (0.228)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.359 (0.352)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Ethnic mono-racial relationship<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0886260512448850">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.589 (0.186)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0886260512448850">**</xref></td>
<td>1.803</td>
<td>0.546 (0.191)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0886260512448850">**</xref></td>
<td>1.727</td>
<td>0.539 (0.296)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Respondent higher education<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0886260512448850">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.363 (0.178)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0886260512448850">*</xref></td>
<td>1.437</td>
<td>0.319 (0.180)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.495 (0.303)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Respondent and partner equal education<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0886260512448850">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>−0.012 (0.175)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.012 (0.176)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.160 (0.300)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Respondent age</td>
<td>−0.010 (0.005)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−0.009 (0.005)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−0.021 (0.009)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0886260512448850">*</xref></td>
<td>0.979</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Private medical insurance</td>
<td>−0.336 (0.148)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0886260512448850">*</xref></td>
<td>0.715</td>
<td>−0.318 (0.149)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0886260512448850">*</xref></td>
<td>0.728</td>
<td>−0.517 (0.233)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0886260512448850">*</xref></td>
<td>0.596</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Child physical victimization</td>
<td>1.323 (0.137)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0886260512448850">***</xref></td>
<td>3.754</td>
<td>1.387 (0.138)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0886260512448850">***</xref></td>
<td>4.002</td>
<td>1.032 (0.224)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0886260512448850">***</xref></td>
<td>2.808</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Child sexual victimization</td>
<td>0.577 (0.177)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0886260512448850">**</xref></td>
<td>1.781</td>
<td>0.481 (0.182)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0886260512448850">**</xref></td>
<td>1.618</td>
<td>0.816 (0.264)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0886260512448850">**</xref></td>
<td>2.261</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Constant</td>
<td>−3.020 (0.317)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0886260512448850">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>−3.131 (0.322)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0886260512448850">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>−3.610 (0.510)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0886260512448850">***</xref></td>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0886260512448850">
<label>a</label>
<p>Reference category is White mono-racial relationship.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-0886260512448850">
<label>b</label>
<p>Reference category is partner higher education.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn6-0886260512448850">
<label>***</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt;.001. **<italic>p</italic> &lt;.01. *<italic>p</italic> &lt;.05.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>Turning to <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0886260512448850">Table 3</xref>, which presents logistic regression coefficients for experiences of verbal aggression and coercive control by an intimate partner, we can see that the racial/ethnic relationship dyad is quite important. Both ethnic minority monoracial and interracial relationships are at significantly greater risk of these forms of emotional, nonphysical forms of IPV, compared with White monoracial relationships and controlling for other IPV correlates. As with physical violence, childhood experiences of physical and sexual violence increase, and age decreases, the risk of verbal aggression and coercive control. Greater educational attainment for women, relative to their partner, is related to an increase in the risk of the partner’s use of emotional forms of abuse; additionally, women’s equal education relative to partners also translates into increased risk for coercive control. Finally, private medical insurance corresponds to a decrease in the risk of both forms of emotional abuse.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0886260512448850" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Logistic Regression Models Predicting Nonphysical IPV, NVAWS (1995-96)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0886260512448850" xlink:href="10.1177_0886260512448850-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Verbal Aggression<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="3">Coercive Control<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center"><italic>b</italic> (<italic>SE</italic>)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
<th align="center">exp(<italic>B</italic>)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>b</italic> (<italic>SE</italic>)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
<th align="center">exp(<italic>B</italic>)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="7">Covariates</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Interracial relationship<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-0886260512448850">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.260 (0.119)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0886260512448850">*</xref></td>
<td>1.297</td>
<td>0.781 (0.129)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0886260512448850">***</xref></td>
<td>2.183</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Ethnic mono-racial relationship<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn7-0886260512448850">a</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.217 (0.103)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0886260512448850">*</xref></td>
<td>1.243</td>
<td>1.008 (0.110)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0886260512448850">***</xref></td>
<td>2.740</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Respondent higher education<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0886260512448850">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.200 (0.087)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0886260512448850">*</xref></td>
<td>1.221</td>
<td>0.266 (0.110)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0886260512448850">*</xref></td>
<td>1.304</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Respondent and partner equal education<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn8-0886260512448850">b</xref></sup></td>
<td>0.031 (0.080)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>0.211 (0.102)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0886260512448850">*</xref></td>
<td>1.234</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Respondent age</td>
<td>−0.007 (0.002)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0886260512448850">**</xref></td>
<td>0.993</td>
<td>−0.015 (0.003)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0886260512448850">***</xref></td>
<td>0.985</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Private medical insurance</td>
<td>−0.360 (0.074)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0886260512448850">***</xref></td>
<td>0.698</td>
<td>−0.564 (0.087)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0886260512448850">***</xref></td>
<td>0.569</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Child physical victimization</td>
<td>0.687 (0.073)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0886260512448850">***</xref></td>
<td>1.987</td>
<td>0.720 (0.087)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0886260512448850">***</xref></td>
<td>2.055</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Child sexual victimization</td>
<td>0.648 (0.106)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0886260512448850">***</xref></td>
<td>1.911</td>
<td>0.666 (0.118)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0886260512448850">***</xref></td>
<td>1.946</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Constant</td>
<td>−0.634 (0.150)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0886260512448850">***</xref></td>
<td/>
<td>−1.230 (0.182)</td>
<td><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0886260512448850">***</xref></td>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn7-0886260512448850">
<label>a</label>
<p>Reference category is White mono-racial relationship.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn8-0886260512448850">
<label>b</label>
<p>Reference category is partner higher education.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn9-0886260512448850">
<label>***</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt;.001. **<italic>p</italic> &lt;.01. *<italic>p</italic> &lt;.05.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0886260512448850" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Despite increasing acceptance and rates of interracial couples in the United States, the research on functioning within such relationships, as compared to intraracial relationships, has been relatively sparse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0886260512448850">Troy et al., 2006</xref>). In particular, there have been few studies to specifically examine the prevalence and nature of violence within interracial relationships (but see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0886260512448850">Fusco, 2010</xref>). Using data from a nationally representative survey, I investigated whether interracial relationships are, in fact, at greater risk of intimate violence compared to intraracial relationships. Results from these analyses correspond in some ways with prior research as well as the expectation that relationships crossing racial/ethnic boundaries might be at greater risk for certain types of intimate violence. Yet, these findings also diverge from these expectations in important ways.</p>
<p>In the bivariate analyses, physical intimate violence and emotional abuse were higher among ethnic minority monoracial and—to some extent—interracial couples, compared with White monoracial couples. The differences in physical violence between interracial couples and White monoracial couples, however, disappeared when other factors were introduced into the multivariate models. To put it differently, interracial relationships appear to entail no greater risk for the expression of physical violence than relationships in which both partners are White. This is contrary to the expectation that the higher stress levels that may be related to being in an interracial relationship (those that arise from within the relationship as well as those from external sources) might lead to increased conflict and ultimately to violence. The same is not true, however, for ethnic minority monoracial relationships; they have greater risks of physical violence compared with White monoracial relationships, all else constant. Although previous research (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0886260512448850">Caetano et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0886260512448850">Kantor et al., 1994</xref>) suggested that some of the differences between White couples and Black or Hispanic couples may disappear when accounting for relevant socioeconomic and other factors, this is not the case in the present analyses. One possible explanation for this is related to relying on proxy indicators of socioeconomic status. I return to this limitation below.</p>
<p>At the same time, interracial relationships—as well as ethnic minority monoracial relationships—were at greater risk of nonphysical forms of intimate violence. Both verbal aggression and control tactics were more prevalent within such relationships. Particularly in the case of ethnic minority monoracial relationships or interracial couples composed of White women and men of color, some men may rely on nonviolent, emotional abuse to (re)assert their authority in the relationship. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0886260512448850">Kaukinen (2004)</xref> found similar patterns among status reversal couples (women having a higher status than men) and suggested that emotionally abusive behaviors may serve as an alternative way in which to construct a masculine image for those men who are otherwise limited in their ability to do so through a traditional breadwinner role. In addition, within the sample described here, not only were women in ethnic minority monoracial and interracial relationships less likely to have private health insurance, but also their relationships were less likely to involve marriage. These unique stressors—reduced access to resources, marginalization because of race/ethnicity, and somewhat less committed relationships—may contribute to increased conflict, yet not necessarily violence, within the relationship.</p>
<p>As is the case with all research, there are a number of limitations that deserve mention. The data used for these analyses were collected more than a decade ago. The sociohistorical context in which the data were collected may limit the conclusions that can be drawn regarding interracial relationships. Less than 10% of the women in the sample were, in fact, involved in a current intimate relationship that crossed racial/ethnic boundaries. The small numbers of such relationships, coupled with the relative rarity of intimate violence within national samples, precluded additional analyses. In particular, one aspect to explore in future research is whether, in interracial relationships, it is the woman or her partner who is a person of color and how this affects various risks for violence. As suggested above, White women coupled with men of color may be at greater risk of certain forms of IPV because of their status relative to that of their partner and his attempts to define his male role. In interracial relationships composed of White men with women of color, we might also expect to see higher risks of intimate violence, but for different reasons. In these relationships, because of their race, men hold a higher status relative to their partner, which may put the woman at greater risk for violence, particularly physical violence.</p>
<p>Second, only <italic>current</italic> relationships were considered here; no racial/ethnic information was collected for women’s former partners and consequently they could not be examined. Yet, previous research has noted that the majority of intimate violence that women recall within national samples is perpetrated by former partners (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0886260512448850">Carbone-Lopez et al., 2012</xref>). Not including dissolved relationships, or even less committed relationships like dating relationships, may affect the results. Given that interracial relationships are at greater risk of dissolution, this may mean that we are underestimating violence within these relationships by only examining those relationships that are ongoing. Clearly this is an important area for future research.</p>
<p>Finally, as noted above, the measures available in the NVAWS, particularly those related to economic resources, are somewhat limited. For example, because of missing information on individual and household income, proxy measures for socioeconomic status and relative status between partners were used in the present analyses. Including valid indicators of income, wealth, job prestige and neighborhood composition may be useful in future research to try and untangle the complicated relationships between social status, race/ethnicity, and intimate violence. In addition, although prior evidence suggests that interracial relationships may experience somewhat greater levels of stress (because of resource shortage or otherwise) or alienation from society because of their relationships, unfortunately there are not suitable measures of either within the data. Such information would be useful in determining the extent to which stress and/or alienation mediate the relationship between involvement in interracial relationships and IPV. Future research—particularly qualitative research—should also continue to focus on the way in which power differentials in relationships (based not only on gender, but also on race/ethnicity, immigration status, disability, etc.) create conflict and ultimately contribute to the risk of violence.</p>
<p>Notwithstanding the limitations, these results have both theoretical and practical importance. Defying the myth that interracial relationships necessarily are more troubled and therefore more violent prompts us to continue to investigate how relationships, regardless of race/ethnicity, work and what other factors contribute to risk of intimate violence. At the same time, there will continue to be tremendous social pressure against relationships that cross racial/ethnic boundaries, at least until such relationships constitute the majority. Therefore, practitioners who work with clients involved in interracial relationships should continually seek and incorporate culturally specific models for addressing violence. Prevention efforts should also be attuned to culturally and ethnically specific models for reducing dating and intimate violence, while simultaneously recognizing the often substantial <italic>within-group</italic> differences among racial and ethnic minorities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0886260512448850">Donnelly, Cook, van Ausdale, &amp; Foley, 2005</xref>). The fact is, however, that race and ethnicity remain significant organizing factors in the United States and, as such, affect individuals and their relationships. Working continually to increase social tolerance of relationships that cross racial/ethnic boundaries can serve to strengthen the external support available to couples and to ensure that all women, regardless of race/ethnicity, have access to the resources needed to escape violence.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The author would like to thank Janet Lauritsen, Jody Miller, and Andrea Nichols for their helpful comments on a previous draft. In addition, the author is grateful to the reviewers for their suggestions.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0886260512448850">
<label>1.</label>
<p>It is important to note that different sampling strategies produce different results in terms of whether ethnic minority couples are at greater risk of intimate violence compared with White couples. For example, research using shelter populations generally finds no racial differences in intimate violence among Black, Latina, and White women (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0886260512448850">Gondolf, Fisher &amp; McFerron, 1988</xref>). In contrast, as noted, large population-based samples (such as the National Family Violence Survey and others) as well as some community samples indicate that Black, Hispanic, and American Indian women report higher rates of violence by intimate partners than White women.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0886260512448850">
<label>2.</label>
<p>It is important to note that patterns of interracial relationships differ by racial/ethnic group. For example, marriage between Hispanics and non-Hispanics has traditionally been somewhat more common, and it continues to increase. In fact, interracial relationships most often pair a White person with a non-White spouse; intermarriage between two persons of color is relatively infrequent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0886260512448850">Lee &amp; Edmonston, 2005</xref>) though more recent Census data suggest that these patterns may be changing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0886260512448850">Qian &amp; Lichter, 2007</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0886260512448850">
<label>3.</label>
<p>Laws prohibiting marital and sexual relationships between Whites and ethnic and racial minorities existed for more than a century in the United States. Though a few states repealed their antimiscegenation laws early on, it was not until the 1950s and 1960s that the laws faced serious challenge in courts. In a landmark case (Loving vs. Virginia), in 1967, the Supreme Court ruled that such laws violated individual civil rights and many states quickly followed suit, repealing their laws. The bans against interracial marriages in some states continued, however, though most were not enforceable. In 2000, Alabama became the last state to repeal its state law against marriage between Whites and those considered non-White.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0886260512448850">
<label>4.</label>
<p>Of these interracial relationships, approximately 38% (<italic>n</italic> = 151) involved White women who were in relationships with men of color, 47% (<italic>n</italic> = 185) involved women of color who were in intimate relationships with White men, and 15% (<italic>n</italic> = 57) involved men and women who were non-White but of differing racial/ethnic backgrounds.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0886260512448850">
<label>5.</label>
<p>Preliminary regression analysis suggested that household income and race were very strong predictors of private medical insurance, supporting the contention that it serves as a useful proxy for wealth.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0886260512448850">
<label>6.</label>
<p>On further examination, there are some significant differences in the prevalence of individual forms of emotional abuse and control behavior. Compared with women in White monoracial couples, women in ethnic minority monoracial and interracial relationships were more likely to report that their partners were “jealous or possessive,” try to “provoke arguments” or “limit contact” with friends and family, insist on knowing their location at all times, and prevent them from having access to family income. Women in interracial relationships reported more often than women in White monoracial relationships that their partners had a “hard time seeing things” from their point of view. Compared with White women coupled with White men, women in ethnic minority monoracial relationships were more likely to indicate that their partner makes them feel “inadequate” or “shouts or swears” at them. Finally, women in ethnic minority monoracial relationships more often indicated that their partner did not allow them to work outside of the house compared to women in White monoracial or interracial relationships.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-0886260512448850">
<label>7.</label>
<p>The prevalence of sexual assault, stalking and threats in current intimate relationships was too low to allow for estimation of the logistic regression models. However, as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0886260512448850">Table 1</xref>, there were no differences by racial/ethnic relationship dyad in the likelihood of these types of IPV.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Bio</title>
<p><bold>Kristin Carbone-Lopez</bold> is assistant professor in the Department of Criminology and Criminal Justice at the University of Missouri—St. Louis. Her research focuses on gender and the connections between crime and victimization across the life course with a particular emphasis on violence against women. Recent publications appear in <italic>Criminology, Journal of Research in Crime and Delinquency, and Youth Violence &amp; Juvenile Justice</italic>.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Gender, status and domestic violence: An integration of feminist and family violence approaches</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marriage and Family</source>, <volume>59</volume>, <fpage>655</fpage>-<lpage>669</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bachman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <source>Death and violence on the reservation: Homicide, family violence, and suicide in American Indian populations</source>. <publisher-loc>Westport, CT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Autumn House</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DeMaris</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Wyk</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Neighborhood disadvantage, individual economic distress and violence against women in intimate relationships</article-title>. <source>Journal of Quantitative Criminology</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>207</fpage>-<lpage>235</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bramlett</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mosher</surname><given-names>W. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Cohabitation, marriage, divorce, and remarriage in the United States. National Center for Health Statistics</article-title>. <source>Vital Health Statistics</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>22</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bratter</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>“But will it last?”: Marital instability among interracial and same-race couples</article-title>. <source>Family Relations</source>, <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>160</fpage>-<lpage>171</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Browning</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The span of collective efficacy: Extending social disorganization theory to partner violence</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marriage and Family</source>, <volume>64</volume>, <fpage>833</fpage>-<lpage>850</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Caetano</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cunradi</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schafer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Intimate partner violence and drinking patterns among White, Black, and Hispanic couples in the U.S</article-title>. <source>Journal of Substance Abuse</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>123</fpage>-<lpage>138</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Caetano</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ramisetty-Mikler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The 5-year course of intimate partner violence among White, Black, and Hispanic couples in the United States</article-title>. <source>Journal of Interpersonal Violence</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>1039</fpage>-<lpage>1057</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carbone-Lopez</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rennison</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Macmillan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The transcendence of violence across relationships: New methods for understanding men’s and women’s experiences of intimate partner violence across the life course</article-title>. <source>Journal of Quantitative Criminology</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>319</fpage>-<lpage>346</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Childs</surname><given-names>E. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>Navigating interracial borders: Black-White couples and their social worlds</source>. <publisher-loc>New Brunswick, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rutgers University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Straus</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Marital power, conflict, and violence in a nationally representative sample of American couples</article-title>. <source>Violence and Victims</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>141</fpage>-<lpage>157</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van Ausdale</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>White privilege, color blindness, and services to battered women</article-title>. <source>Violence Against Women</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>6</fpage>-<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feld</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Straus</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Escalation and desistance of wife assault in marriage</article-title>. <source>Criminology</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>141</fpage>-<lpage>161</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Forry</surname><given-names>N. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Letiecq</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Marital quality in interracial relationships: The role of sex role ideology and perceived fairness</article-title>. <source>Journal of Family Issues</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>1538</fpage>-<lpage>1552</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fusco</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Intimate partner violence in interracial couples: A comparison to White and ethnic minority monoracial couples</article-title>. <source>Journal of Interpersonal Violence</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>1785</fpage>-<lpage>1800</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gelles</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Straus</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <source>Intimate violence</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Simon and Schuster</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gondolf</surname><given-names>E. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McFerron</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Racial differences among shelter residents: A comparison of Anglo, Black, and Hispanic battered</article-title>. <source>Journal of Family Violence</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>39</fpage>-<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hohmann-Marriott</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Amato</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Relationship quality in interethnic marriages and cohabitations</article-title>. <source>Social Forces</source>, <volume>87</volume>, <fpage>825</fpage>-<lpage>855</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Patriarchal terrorism and common couple violence: Two forms of violence against women</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marriage and Family</source>, <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>283</fpage>-<lpage>294</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kalmuss</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Straus</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>Wife’s marital dependency and wife abuse</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marriage and the Family</source>, <volume>44</volume>, <fpage>277</fpage>-<lpage>286</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kantor</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jasinski</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aldarondo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Sociocultural status and incidence of marital violence in Hispanic families</article-title>. <source>Violence and Victims</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>207</fpage>-<lpage>222</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaukinen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Compatability, physical violence, and emotional abuse in intimate relationships</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marriage and Family</source>, <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>452</fpage>-<lpage>471</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lauritsen</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schaum</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The social ecology of violence against women</article-title>. <source>Criminology</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>323</fpage>-<lpage>357</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edmonston</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <source>New marriages, new families: U.S. racial and Hispanic intermarriage. Vol. 60</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Population Reference Bureau</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Acceptance of interracial marriage at record high</article-title>. <source>Gallop News</source>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gallup.com/poll/11836/acceptance-interracial-marriage-record-high.aspx">http://www.gallup.com/poll/11836/acceptance-interracial-marriage-record-high.aspx</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mercy</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saltzman</surname><given-names>Linda E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Fatal violence among spouses in the United States, 1976-85</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Public Health</source>, <volume>79</volume>, <fpage>595</fpage>-<lpage>599</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Messerschmidt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>Masculinities and crime: Critique and reconceptualization of a theory</source>. <publisher-loc>Lanham, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rowman &amp; Littlefield</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Neff</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holamon</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schluter</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Spousal violence among Anglos, Blacks, and Mexican Americans: The role of demographic variables, psychosocial predictors, and alcohol consumption</article-title>. <source>Journal of Family Violence</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>An argument for Black Feminist criminology: Understanding African American women’s experiences with intimate partner abuse using an integrated approach</article-title>. <source>Feminist Criminology</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>16</fpage>-<lpage>124</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lichter</surname><given-names>D. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Social boundaries and marital assimilation: Interpreting trends in racial and ethnic intermarriage</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source>, <volume>72</volume>, <fpage>68</fpage>-<lpage>94</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rennison</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Welchans</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>Intimate partner violence</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>USGPO. NCJ 178247</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rosenblatt</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karis</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source>Multiracial couples: Black and White voices</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rosenfeld</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The independence of young adults and the rise of interracial and same-sex unions</article-title>. <source>American Sociological Review</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>541</fpage>-<lpage>562</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sorenson</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Upchurch</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shun</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Violence and injury in marital arguments: Risk patterns and gender differences</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Public Health</source>, <volume>86</volume>, <fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Coercive control: How men entrap women in personal life</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Straus</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>The new conflict tactics scale and its critics: An evaluation and new data on validity and reliability</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Straus</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gelles</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Physical violence in American families: Risk factors and adaptations to violence in 8,145 families</source> (pp. <fpage>49</fpage>-<lpage>73</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New Brunswick, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transaction</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Straus</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gelles</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>How violent are American families? Estimates from the National Family Violence Resurvey and other studies</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Straus</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gelles</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Physical violence in American families: Risk factors and adaptations to violence in 8,145 families</source> (pp. <fpage>95</fpage>-<lpage>108</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New Brunswick, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transaction</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Straus</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gelles</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steinmetz</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <source>Behind closed doors: Violence in the American family</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Doubleday/Anchor</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Straus</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Violence in Hispanic families in the United States: Incidence rates and structural interpretations</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Straus</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gelles</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Physical violence in American families: Risk factors and adaptations to violence in 8,145 families</source> (pp. <fpage>341</fpage>-<lpage>363</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New Brunswick, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transactions</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tjaden</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thoennes</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>Full report of the prevalence, incidence, and consequences of violence against women</source>. <publisher-name>U.S. Department of Justice</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Troy</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewis-Smith</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laurenceau</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Interracial and intraracial romantic relationships: The search for differences in satisfaction, conflict, and attachment style</article-title>. <source>Journal of Social and Personal Relationships</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>65</fpage>-<lpage>80</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Usita</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Poulsen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Interracial relationships in Hawaii: Issues, benefits and therapeutic interventions</article-title>. <source>Journal of Couple and Relationship Therapy</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>73</fpage>-<lpage>83</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Joyner</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Stability of interracial and intraracial romantic relationships among adolescents</article-title>. <source>Social Science Research</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>435</fpage>-<lpage>453</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0886260512448850">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>West</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Domestic violence in ethnically and racially diverse families: The “political gag order” has been lifted</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Sokoloff</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Domestic violence at the margins: Readings on race, class, gender and culture</source> (pp. <fpage>157</fpage>-<lpage>173</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Piscataway, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rutgers University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref></ref-list>
</back>
</article>