<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TRJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptrj</journal-id>
<journal-title>Textile Research Journal</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0040-5175</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1746-7748</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0040517512460296</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0040517512460296</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Effect of fiber count and knit structure on intra- and inter-yarn transport of liquid water</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Birrfelder</surname><given-names>Pascale</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0040517512460296">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0040517512460296">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Dorrestijn</surname><given-names>Marko</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0040517512460296">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0040517512460296">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>René M</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0040517512460296">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0040517512460296"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0040517512460296"><label>1</label>Empa – Swiss Federal Laboratories for Materials Science and Technology, Laboratory for Protection and Physiology, Switzerland</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0040517512460296"><label>2</label>Institute of Human Movement Sciences and Sport, ETH Zurich, Switzerland</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0040517512460296"><label>3</label>Institute of Process Engineering, ETH Zurich, Switzerland</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0040517512460296">Rene M Rossi, Empa – Swiss Federal Laboratories for Materials Science and Technology, Laboratory for Protection and Physiology, Lerchenfeldstr. 5, 9014 St. Gallen, Switzerland. Email: <email>rene.rossi@empa.ch</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>83</volume>
<issue>14</issue>
<fpage>1477</fpage>
<lpage>1488</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The moisture transport in fabrics determines its cooling effect and therefore the wearing comfort during sudorific activities. When liquid sweat is present, the moisture absorption by a fabric is characterized by the in-plane and transplanar wicking. We investigated the effect of fabric structure and fiber count on wicking by X-ray projection images using four different polyester knit structures (rib, eyelet, interlock and modified interlock, all hydrophilic), as well as five rib knits with different fiber counts per yarn (24–192, all quasi-hydrophobic with water contact angles 89 ± 1). Experiments were conducted with two-layer samples of the same fabric exposed to different external pressures. The liquid was transported in recognizable waterfronts, which can be interpreted as distinct intra-yarn and inter-yarn in-plane wicking fronts. For layer-to-layer wicking in hydrophilic samples, pressure-dependent time delays were observed; the delays correlated negatively with the relative void area at the interface, and were shortest for the rib knits. For the quasi-hydrophobic samples, however, the liquid wicked up to the upper layer without time delays, which was due to the liquid being pressed into the fabric, that is, due to the supply-driven flow. We distinguish this from the supply-limited flow, which is driven by capillary forces. The presented results have implications for the design of clothing systems for sudorific activities.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>in-plane wicking</kwd>
<kwd>fiber counts</kwd>
<kwd>knits</kwd>
<kwd>polyester</kwd>
<kwd>transplanar wicking</kwd>
<kwd>X-ray projections</kwd>
<kwd>intra-yarn capillaries</kwd>
<kwd>inter-yarn structure</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>In recent years, the demand for wear comfort of functional clothing has continually gained in importance and therefore the interest in wicking through fibrous materials has been increased.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0040517512460296">1</xref></sup> During exercise, the clothing layer(s) next to the skin is being wetted by the accumulation of liquid water (sweat) on the skin.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0040517512460296">2</xref></sup> In the textile, moisture is transported either as water vapor or by direct uptake of excess liquid from the skin. The body evaporative cooling is more efficient the closer to the skin it occurs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0040517512460296">3</xref></sup> In contrast, outward liquid water transport (transplanar wicking) can be advantageous, since it reduces the after-cooling effect when the body is at rest. Skin wetness is an important factor for the overall comfort and, therefore, inner layers that pass the moisture to the next layer are more comfortable to wear than a wet layer.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0040517512460296">2</xref></sup> In order to optimize the wearer’s textile comfort, transplanar as well as in-plane wicking properties are important contributors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0040517512460296">3</xref></sup> Several relevant parameters, such as geometrical properties of the pores formed by the fibers (intra-yarn) and yarns (inter-yarn), the surface properties of the fibers (hydrophobicity) and the fiber moisture absorption capacity (hygroscopy) have an influence on wicking in porous fabrics.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0040517512460296">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0040517512460296">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>The effect of moisture transport through fibrous materials has frequently been studied using different methods. The in-plane water transport has already been investigated visually<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0040517512460296">6</xref></sup> and by electrical conductivity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0040517512460296">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0040517512460296">8</xref></sup> Several studies have gravimetrically analyzed the transplanar water transport of single-<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0040517512460296">9</xref></sup> and multilayer fabrics,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0040517512460296">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0040517512460296">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0040517512460296"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0040517512460296"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0040517512460296"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0040517512460296">14</xref></sup> as well as measurements on sweating manikins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0040517512460296">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0040517512460296">16</xref></sup> and on sweating cylinder systems.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0040517512460296">17</xref></sup> Sarkar et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0040517512460296">18</xref></sup> used a so-called transplanar water transport tester to measure the initial water absorption of the fabric. However, none of these methods show how liquid spreads three-dimensionally within each layer; for resolving the water distribution, several advanced experimental techniques are available, such as Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0040517512460296">19</xref></sup> Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectroscopy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0040517512460296">20</xref></sup> and the fast but costly Neutron Radiography.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0040517512460296">21</xref></sup> Furthermore, X-ray attenuation techniques have been used to quantitatively investigate the moisture distribution in porous fabrics and are an established tool.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0040517512460296">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0040517512460296">22</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0040517512460296"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0040517512460296">24</xref></sup> The visualization of the water transport inside fabric is mainly relevant for fabrics containing denier gradients or other asymmetrical capillary transport properties. Rossi et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0040517512460296">3</xref></sup> and Zhuang et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0040517512460296">25</xref></sup> showed that the transplanar water transport increases with rising external pressure due to a greater number of contact points between the fabric layers. In-plane wicking also rose with higher pressure.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0040517512460296">3</xref></sup> Obtaining the full three-dimensional (3D) images required in X-ray studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0040517512460296">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0040517512460296">24</xref></sup> was time consuming, as recording a typical high-resolution 3D image takes of the order of 10 minutes. However, the high flow velocity of water through some fibrous materials demanded reduced scan times, in order to be able to analyze both intra- and inter-yarn water transport. Therefore, in the present work, we developed a new method to obtain fast high-resolution projections (under 5 seconds) in order to analyze the in-plane and transplanar wicking behavior of fabrics with different inter- and intra-yarn capillary structures in near real time when exposed to three different pressure levels.</p>
<sec id="sec1-0040517512460296" sec-type="methods|materials"><title>Method and materials</title>
<sec id="sec2-0040517512460296"><title>X-ray projection images</title>
<p>The setup was similar to our previous study.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0040517512460296">3</xref></sup> The µCT 80 tomograph (Scanco Medical AG, Switzerland) applied an anode voltage of 70 kV and had a resolution of 37 µm (pixel size). For each measurement sequence, two layers of the same fabric (diameter 65 mm) were stacked wrinkle-free with the ‘skin’ side downwards in a cylindrical sample holder, and held by an impermeable piston. A variable pressure was applied to the piston by an adjustable screw. Liquid water was delivered through a nozzle at the center of the lower sample surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0040517512460296">Figure 1</xref>).
<fig id="fig1-0040517512460296" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Measurement setup with the sample holder and the water supply.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512460296-fig1.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>The sample holder was placed in the µCT such that the central X-rays were parallel to the wales of the knits. Measurements were conducted in a conditioned room (20 ± 1℃, 65 ± 5% relative humidity outside the scanner; 23℃, 55% inside the scanner). All samples were stored outside the scanner for at least 24 hours before the measurements. Sample holders were stored inside the scanner. After placing samples into the scanner, they were conditioned for 15 minutes prior to measurements. Radiographic projections were recorded at a rate of one image per 4.5 s, for 910 s. The first two projections recorded the dry sample for the subsequent data analysis. Water was supplied at a constant rate of 0.45 ml/min (sweating phase).</p>
<p>The pressure used to compress the fabric sample was varied in correspondence with three typical pressure levels (0.2, 2 and 5 kPa) found in worn clothing.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0040517512460296">26</xref></sup></p>
<p>Each projection image was 3D-reconstructed using a Matlab R2011a script written in-house. It is an iterative algorithm that contains the geometry of the computerized tomography (CT) scanner and assumes that lateral wicking proceeds axisymetrically. Anisotropy in the textile can break the symmetry, leading to overestimated water content near the front of the water distribution; this was observed for several samples, but the effect on the calculated capillary transport constants was negligible.</p>
<p>The in-plane water distribution was plotted in relation to the sample radius versus time by calculating the mean water concentration over the sample thickness. The transplanar water distribution was graphically represented versus time by radially averaging the concentration values. The water concentration is defined as the relative volumetric water content, that is, ml/cm<sup>3</sup> or vol%. As previously shown by several studies,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0040517512460296">27</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0040517512460296"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0040517512460296">29</xref></sup> the liquid wicks proportionally to the square root of the time <italic>t</italic> (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-0040517512460296">Equation (1)</xref>):
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0040517512460296"><label>(1)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math1-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-0040517512460296" xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512460296-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>s</italic> describes the covered distance and <italic>k<sub>s</sub></italic> a capillary transport constant. We determined the linear dependencies (<italic>k<sub>s</sub></italic>) by fitting <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-0040517512460296">Equation (1)</xref> to the time-resolved wicking fronts. The wicking fronts were defined as the leading edges of the water transport; the fastest, foremost front was arbitrarily defined at a water concentration of 10 vol%. Diffusion and condensation of water vapor is assumed to be negligible compared to the transport of liquid water, since the liquid, textile and sample holder were thermally equilibrated prior to radiography measurements.</p>
<p>All statistical analyses were conducted using SPSS 19.0 software (Chicago, IL, USA). The effects of fabric samples and applied pressure levels were analyzed by analysis of variance (ANOVA). Post hoc comparisons were performed according to Bonferroni’s method.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0040517512460296">30</xref></sup> The level of significance was set at 0.05. Values are presented as mean ± standard deviation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-0040517512460296"><title>Capillary constant and water contact angle</title>
<p>Besides <italic>k<sub>s</sub></italic>, we define a capillary constant <italic>c</italic> that is purely geometry based. These capillary constants and water contact angles were measured with a tensiometer (K100 MK2, Krüss GmbH). The sorption method was applied, modeling the knit structures as an array of round capillaries. The samples, hanging on a sensitive scale, were dipped at one end into a test liquid and the gained mass (<italic>m</italic>) by capillary penetration was recorded over time (<italic>t</italic>). The relation between gained mass, liquid properties and capillary constant (<italic>c</italic>) is given in the modified Washburn equation:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0040517512460296"><label>(2a)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math2-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>cos</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula2-0040517512460296" xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512460296-eq2.tif"/></disp-formula>

<disp-formula id="disp-formula3-0040517512460296"><label>(2b)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math3-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>≡</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>64</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula3-0040517512460296" xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512460296-eq3.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>n<sub>c</sub></italic> is the number of capillaries, 
<inline-formula id="ilm1-0040517512460296"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math1-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
 the capillary diameter and <italic>ρ</italic>, <italic>σ<sub>l</sub></italic> and <italic>η</italic> are the density, surface tension and viscosity of the liquid, respectively. In a first step, the capillary constant <italic>c</italic> was determined using <italic>n</italic>-hexane as the test liquid, which features a contact angle of nearly 0° such that cos(θ) equals 1.</p>
<p>Water contact angles of the knit structures were determined in a second step by placing the known capillary constant into <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-0040517512460296">Equation (2a)</xref> and measuring the liquid penetration with water as the test liquid. The relevant properties of hexane and water are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0040517512460296">Table 1</xref>.
<table-wrap id="table1-0040517512460296" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Properties of the test liquids at 25℃</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0040517512460296" xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512460296-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Liquid</th>
<th>ρ [kg/m<sup>3</sup>]</th>
<th>σ<italic><sub>l</sub></italic> [mN/m]</th>
<th>η [mPa s]</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td><italic>n</italic>-hexane</td>
<td>655</td>
<td>18.2</td>
<td>0.296</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>water</td>
<td>998</td>
<td>72.8</td>
<td>1.002</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>Only hydrophilic samples can be characterized with the capillary penetration method. No liquid penetrates through the knit structures if the contact angle is higher than 90°.</p>
<p>The measured dependency of the capillary constant on the fiber count was compared to the theory, in order to verify the expected wicking behavior. Similarly to the Washburn theory, we assume a constant yarn diameter and a circular capillary cross-section; also, assuming a homogeneous distribution of fibers over the yarn’s cross-section, the space filled by capillaries is equal to the intra-yarn void space. Then the capillary diameter is
<disp-formula id="disp-formula4-0040517512460296"><label>(3)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math4-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>fc</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula4-0040517512460296" xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512460296-eq4.tif"/></disp-formula>
where 
<inline-formula id="ilm2-0040517512460296"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math2-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>fc</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
 is the yarn’s fiber count, <italic>A<sub>y</sub></italic> is the yarn cross-section and 
<inline-formula id="ilm3-0040517512460296"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math3-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
 is the porosity of the yarn. The total number of capillaries is
<disp-formula id="disp-formula5-0040517512460296"><label>(4)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math5-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>TWf</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>fc</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula5-0040517512460296" xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512460296-eq5.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>T</italic>, <italic>W</italic> are the thickness and width of the textile sample, respectively, and <italic>f<sub>y</sub></italic> is the “fill factor” of the yarns versus the total volume. Substitution of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula4-0040517512460296">Equations (3)</xref> and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula5-0040517512460296">4</xref>) into <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula3-0040517512460296">Equation (2b)</xref> gives
<disp-formula id="disp-formula6-0040517512460296"><label>(5)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math6-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>TWf</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>fc</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula6-0040517512460296" xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512460296-eq6.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>This relationship was used to fit the <italic>c</italic> versus 
<inline-formula id="ilm4-0040517512460296"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math4-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>fc</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
 data with <italic>f<sub>y</sub></italic> as a fit parameter. The values 
<inline-formula id="ilm5-0040517512460296"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math5-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>50</mml:mn><mml:mo>±</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>05</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
 and 
<inline-formula id="ilm6-0040517512460296"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math6-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>025</mml:mn><mml:mo>±</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>002</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>mm</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
 were calculated from fiber and yarn diameters obtained from optical micrographs, and 
<inline-formula id="ilm7-0040517512460296"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math7-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>20</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>mm</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
.</p>
<p>In order to obtain a capillary transport constant <italic>k<sub>s</sub></italic><sub>,</sub><italic><sub>T</sub></italic> from <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-0040517512460296">Equation (2a)</xref>, we write the water mass <italic>m</italic> in terms of the covered distance <italic>s<sub>T</sub></italic> in the tensiometer:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula7-0040517512460296"><label>(6)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math7-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>TWs</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula7-0040517512460296" xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512460296-eq7.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>T</italic>, <italic>W</italic> are the thickness and width of the textile strip, respectively, and 
<inline-formula id="ilm8-0040517512460296"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math8-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
 is the porosity of the textile. Substituting into <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula2-0040517512460296">Equation (2a)</xref>, and taking the square root on both sides, gives
<disp-formula id="disp-formula8-0040517512460296"><label>(7)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math8-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mo>√</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>cos</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi> </mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>η</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>≡</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula8-0040517512460296" xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512460296-eq8.tif"/></disp-formula>
for direct comparison with <italic>k<sub>s</sub></italic> data.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0040517512460296" sec-type="materials"><title>Materials</title>
<p>The fabrics used in this study were made of polyester fibers (100%). We selected four different knit structures and five rib knits with different fiber counts per yarn (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0040517512460296">Table 2</xref>) in order to vary the capillary structure. The yarn titers were 78 and 76 dtex for the knit structures and fiber count series, respectively. In order to keep the yarn titer constant for varying fiber counts, the fiber titer was varied. The rib qualities were 1 × 1 knits. The eyelet structure was single pique.
<table-wrap id="table2-0040517512460296" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Properties of the investigated fabrics</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0040517512460296" xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512460296-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Code</th>
<th>Construction</th>
<th>Fiber count</th>
<th>Thickness (mm) at 0.2 kPa</th>
<th>Thickness (mm) at 5 kPa</th>
<th>Textile porosity (%)</th>
<th>Contact angle (°)</th>
</tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>R-68</td>
<td>Rib</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>1.06</td>
<td>0.84</td>
<td>86</td>
<td>66 ± 4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>I-68</td>
<td>Interlock</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>1.08</td>
<td>0.91</td>
<td>87</td>
<td>79 ± 3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Im-68</td>
<td>Interlock mod.</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>1.31</td>
<td>1.09</td>
<td>88</td>
<td>66 ± 4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>E-68</td>
<td>Eyelet</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>1.51</td>
<td>1.26</td>
<td>89</td>
<td>65 ± 1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>R-192</td>
<td>Rib</td>
<td>192</td>
<td>0.92</td>
<td>0.70</td>
<td>89</td>
<td>88.3 ± 0.5<sup>a</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>R-128</td>
<td>Rib</td>
<td>128</td>
<td>0.98</td>
<td>0.73</td>
<td>87</td>
<td>89.1 ± 0.1<sup>a</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>R-96</td>
<td>Rib</td>
<td>96</td>
<td>1.12</td>
<td>0.88</td>
<td>84</td>
<td>89.7 ± 0.1<sup>a</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>R-32</td>
<td>Rib</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>1.28</td>
<td>1.04</td>
<td>86</td>
<td>89.92 ± 0.05<sup>a</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>R-24</td>
<td>Rib</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>1.31</td>
<td>1.09</td>
<td>88</td>
<td>89.7 ± 0.2<sup>a</sup></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0040517512460296"><label>a</label>
<p>Standard deviation based on three measurements.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>We named the samples according to their structure and yarn count, R-68 meaning a rib structure with 68 filaments in the yarn. The samples with different fiber counts (R-24–R-192) were found to be quasi-hydrophobic (contact angles nearly 90°), whereas the fabrics with different knit structures were hydrophilic and revealed values within the range of 66–80°. The difference in average contact angle between the fiber count variations and the knit variations is due to the fact that they were produced in different batches. Textile porosities were calculated from the sample thicknesses measured at 0.2 kPa, the sample weights and the density of polyester (1.38 kg m<sup>−3</sup>). Sample thicknesses were measured with an F16502 Universal Micrometer (FRANK-PTI, Germany).</p>
<p>The fabrics were not treated with any finishing. Before the experiments they were washed once at 40℃ according to EN ISO 6330:2000 procedure 5A/40°.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0040517512460296" sec-type="results"><title>Results and discussion</title>
<sec id="sec6-0040517512460296"><title>Capillary constant versus fiber count</title>
<p>For the fiber count variations, the capillary constants found through tensiometry were compared to the theory. Using the yarn fill factor <italic>f<sub>y</sub></italic> as a fit parameter, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula6-0040517512460296">Equation (5)</xref> was fitted to the data. For 
<inline-formula id="ilm9-0040517512460296"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math9-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>68</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
, the data were in good agreement with the theory, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0040517512460296">Figure 2</xref>.
<fig id="fig2-0040517512460296" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Capillary constants <italic>c</italic> (represented as 
<inline-formula id="ilm10-0040517512460296"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math10-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
) for the different fiber counts. The linear curve is the fitted trend line.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512460296-fig2.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>Using this fit to predict a trend for the in-plane wicking rate versus fiber count, however, is not straightforward. In order to obtain (in-plane) capillary transport constants 
<inline-formula id="ilm11-0040517512460296"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math11-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
 from the geometry-based <italic>c</italic> values using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula8-0040517512460296">Equation (7)</xref>, other textile parameters need to be taken into account as well. Nonetheless, if these are assumed to be constant, 
<inline-formula id="ilm12-0040517512460296"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math12-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>∝</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mroot><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>fc</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mroot></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
, that is, a relatively weak dependency exists. Furthermore, <italic>k<sub>s</sub></italic> was found to increase linearly with 
<inline-formula id="ilm13-0040517512460296"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math13-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0040517512460296">Figure 3(c)</xref>), although also weakly. Therefore, since the wicking rate is proportional to <italic>k<sub>s</sub></italic>, a slight negative correlation is expected between in-plane wicking and fiber count.
<fig id="fig3-0040517512460296" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>In-plane capillary transport constants for the knit variations (a) and three of the fiber count variations (b) at three applied pressure levels. For 0.2 kPa, the transport constants are plotted versus those obtained from tensiometry (c); the linear fit is 
<inline-formula id="ilm14-0040517512460296"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math14-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
, which excluded the data point for E-68. Error bars are based on three measurements. *Statistically significant difference (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512460296-fig3.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-0040517512460296"><title>In-plane wicking effect</title>
<p>In-plane water spreading is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0040517512460296">Figure 4</xref><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0040517512460296"/>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0040517512460296">6</xref> by representative examples of the different knit structures and the fiber count samples. The graphs present the water concentration (vol%) versus time (horizontal axis) and radial position (vertical axis). The top axis indicates the supplied water volume (in ml).
<fig id="fig4-0040517512460296" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>In-plane water transport in the knit structures eyelet (sample E-68): (a) interlock (I-68); (b) and the quasi-hydrophobic rib (R-68); (c) at low pressure (0.2 kPa). A, B and C describe three distinct waterfronts. Radial position: 0 mm means the center of the sample (position of the sweating nozzle) and 32 mm the outer edge. Colors represent the water concentration (vol%; color online only).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512460296-fig4.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>The visual color analysis in the graphs shows that liquid water is proceeding in multiple waterfronts in the knit structure samples. As the wicking velocity is theoretically different for distinct capillary sizes, multiple waterfronts should be seen due to different capillary forces in the inter- and intra-yarn structures. Indeed, all samples exhibited three waterfronts (labeled A, B, and C), or four waterfronts.</p>
<sec id="sec8-0040517512460296"><title>Influence of knit structure</title>
<p>The first wicking front A starts right at the beginning of the measurement and is shown at a concentration of 10–20 vol% (dark blue front in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0040517512460296">Figure 4(a)–(c)</xref>). This waterfront must be due to an intra-yarn water transport (as opposed to inter-yarn), because capillary forces are larger inside the yarns (according to the Lukas–Washburn equation<sup>31</sup>). Due to the relatively low water concentration at the beginning, it will first fill the smaller intra-yarn voids. Analogously, the second recognizable front B (light blue front in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0040517512460296">Figure 4(a) and (b)</xref>) describes the start of water transport to the second, upper layer, as can be seen by comparison with <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0040517512460296">Figure 7(a) and (b)</xref>. Since fronts A and B are the first fronts in each layer, and their concentrations are comparable, front B expectedly represents intra-yarn transport as well. At a water concentration of 60–80 vol% (yellow-red front, 20–60 vol% above the total of fronts A and B), we observe a third front C, which must be the inter-yarn wicking front (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0040517512460296">Figure 4(a)–(c)</xref>). In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0040517512460296">Figure 4(b)</xref>, a slight differentiation within front C can be observed, between the yellow front (60 vol%) and the red front (60 vol%), which indicates distinct inter-yarn wicking in both layers. Interestingly, the intra-yarn front A progressed similarly for the different knit structure samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0040517512460296">Figure 4(a)–(c)</xref>) compared to the inter-yarn fronts C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0040517512460296">Figure 4(a)–(c)</xref>). Since the fiber counts were equal, and the knit structures differed, this seems to confirm that the first front corresponded to intra-yarn wicking. The “stripe artifacts” seen in the figures were caused by increased water concentrations between the wales of the textiles; they are most pronounced for the rib knits.
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0040517512460296"><title>Influence of fiber count</title>
<p>The in-plane water distribution in dependency of the fiber count also shows several wicking fronts. At a concentration of 10–20 vol% the liquid spreads as first front A (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0040517512460296">Figure 5(a) and (b)</xref>) through the small intra-yarn voids to the outer edge of the lower sample layer. The water absorption of the quasi-hydrophobic fiber count samples was much slower compared to the knit structure samples, which caused an accumulation around the water nozzle (concentration of nearly 100% (dark red) from the beginning of the measurement in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0040517512460296">Figure 5(a) and (b)</xref>). As a result of this accumulation, the liquid was pressed in the transplanar direction, through the large inter-yarn loops into the upper layer, as the liquid spreads along the path of least resistance. Although this forced flow was initially dominant, a subsequent differentiation can be seen between three waterfronts; this is in agreement with tensiometry data, which revealed some capillary-driven flow for these quasi-hydrophobic samples. Because the three fronts occurred at similar water concentrations as for the knit structure samples, we assume that the nature of waterfronts A–C corresponds to those seen for the knit variations. The samples R-24 and R-32 did not show the spreading of the intra-yarn wicking fronts A and B, as they coincided with the inter-yarn fronts at all times (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0040517512460296">Figure 5(c)</xref>). In other words, forced flow remained dominant for these samples. Apparently, high fiber counts were required to induce significant capillary-driven flow. Interestingly, this is in contrast with our prediction above that there would be slight negative correlation between wicking rate and fiber count; the prediction is based on the model for 
<inline-formula id="ilm15-0040517512460296"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math15-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
 and it is assumed that all other variables remain constant.
<fig id="fig5-0040517512460296" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>In-plane water transport in the fiber count samples R-192 (a), R-96 (b) and R-24 (c) at low pressure (0.2 kPa). A, B and C describe three distinct waterfronts. (Color online only.)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512460296-fig5.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-0040517512460296"><title>Influence of pressure</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0040517512460296">Figure 6</xref> shows the pressure-induced changes of radial liquid displacement represented by I-68 as a representative example for the knit structure samples. The inter-yarn wicking fronts (C) and the intra-yarn fronts of the lower layer (A) and the upper layer (B) were observed to move closer with increasing pressure, which is conceivably due to compression of the interlayer gap and inter-yarn space. Above a certain pressure level, the liquid water accumulated around the water nozzle, as can be seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0040517512460296">Figure 6(c)</xref> for sample I-68. Interestingly, sample R-68 showed such an accumulation already at 2 kPa. The accumulation may be caused by the reduction of the intra- and inter-yarn void space, such that the in-plane wicking rate became slower than the rate of the supplied water, as was also found by Zhuang et al.<sup>25</sup> Indeed, the intra-yarn fronts (A and B) became slower for increasing pressure. Samples Im-68 and E-68 showed no such water accumulation for any pressure, which may be explained by the fact that these samples are thicker than for samples I-68 and R-68. Thicker samples expectedly offer more void space in the transplanar direction, thus offering a higher volumetric capillary flow rate for the same waterfront velocity; consequently, higher pressures are required for the capillary flow to fall below the supplied flow. For the fiber count samples, the intra-sample variation in wicking behavior was too high to reveal any statistically significant pressure dependencies.
<fig id="fig6-0040517512460296" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Water distribution in I-68 at the applied pressure levels 0.2 kPa (a), 2 kPa (b) and 5 kPa (c).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512460296-fig6.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig7-0040517512460296" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Transplanar water transport in E-68 (a), I-68 (b) and the quasi-hydrophobic R-96 (c) at low pressure (0.2 kPa). The zero of the “vertical position” axis coincides with the skin-textile interface. α and β describe two distinct waterfronts. (Color online only.)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512460296-fig7.tif"/>
</fig>
</p>
<p>Thus, by increasing the applied pressure onto the fabric, we crossed from a regime of “supply-limited flow”, where the wicking rate was limited by the supplied water flow, into a regime of “supply-driven” flow, where the excess supply leads to an accumulation around the point of water injection.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-0040517512460296"><title>In-plane capillary transport constants</title>
<p>Capillary transport constants <italic>k<sub>s</sub></italic> were determined for the first wicking front A (intra-yarn) of all samples by fitting <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-0040517512460296">Equation (1)</xref> to the fronts. For each type of knit, three samples were measured. Error bars show the variation amongst the three samples rather than the uncertainty of individual curve fits. None of the differences in in-plane wicking rate within the two groups knit variations and fiber count variations were statistically significant. However, the mean in-plane wicking rate was on average 25% faster for E-68 and Im-68 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0040517512460296">Figure 3(a)</xref>) compared to sample R-192 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0040517512460296">Figure 3(b)</xref>) for low pressure (0.2 kPa), which is statistically significant. Statistical significances may be improved by applying wicking models that are more advanced than the classical Washburn model; in particular, waterfronts A show non-Washburn behavior at high pressure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0040517512460296">Figure 6(c)</xref>) and at low fiber count (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0040517512460296">Figure 5(c)</xref>). Furthermore, the fiber count variations appear to exhibit slower wicking with decreasing fiber counts per yarn at low pressure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0040517512460296">Figure 3(b)</xref>). The in-plane capillary transport constants of the samples with the lowest count of fibers (R-24 and R-32) could not be exactly determined, as the intra-yarn wicking front coincided with the inter-yarn front at all times.</p>
<p>In addition, in-plane wicking was pressure dependent for some samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0040517512460296">Figure 3</xref>). Some of the knit variations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0040517512460296">Figure 3(a)</xref>; Im-68, E-68), as well as the rib knits R-192 and R-128 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0040517512460296">Figure 3(b)</xref>), tended to wick slower at higher pressure levels. However, for all other samples, no clear pressure dependency could be observed. This contrasts with our previous findings on sock materials (Rossi et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0040517512460296">3</xref></sup>), where the capillary transport constants increased with pressure (from 0.4 to 81 kPa), but in this previous study, the thickness of the sock samples was about 2–3 times higher than in this present study. The present results may be explained by the findings of Zhuang et al.,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0040517512460296">25</xref></sup> who found that water transport decreases above a (material-dependent) critical pressure due to the lack of void space in the fabric. Which of the two regimes applies conceivably depends on parameters such as textile porosity, geometry of the “capillaries”, surface free energies of the liquid and fibers and fiber texture.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0040517512460296">Figure 3(c)</xref> shows <italic>k<sub>s</sub></italic> as a function of the 
<inline-formula id="ilm16-0040517512460296"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math16-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
 data obtained from tensiometry. The curve is seen to deviate significantly from 
<inline-formula id="ilm17-0040517512460296"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math17-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
. Firstly, the slope is only 0.3, which may be an indication of “supply-limited flow” towards higher-<italic>k</italic> (hydrophilic) samples. Supply-limited flow occurs when the supplied water flow is less than the maximum wicking rate. Secondly, the trend line does not pass through the origin, which may be due to the effect of gravity in the tensiometer and/or compression of the textiles in the CT scanner. The eyelet samples (E-68) deviated from the trend: in the tensiometer, these samples exhibited stepwise wicking (thus lowering 
<inline-formula id="ilm18-0040517512460296"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math18-0040517512460296"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
), which appeared to be due to slow filling of the eyelets under the influence of gravity.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-0040517512460296"><title>Transplanar wicking effect</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0040517512460296">Figure 7</xref> shows the vertical water transport of E-68 and I-68 as representative samples for the knit structures and R-96 as a typical example of the fiber count variations. The graphs represent the water concentrations (vol%) versus time (horizontal axis) sample thickness (vertical axis). The whole thickness of the fabric sample is divided into two segments representing the two single fabric layers.</p>
<sec id="sec13-0040517512460296"><title>Influence of structure</title>
<p>As for the in-plane wicking, the transplanar liquid water transport considered in the different knit structures also spread in wicking fronts. At a water concentration of 10 vol% in the lower fabric layer, the small intra-yarn capillaries were already filled (as was shown in the in-plane wicking analysis) and transported the liquid transplanar as the first wicking front (blue front (α) in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0040517512460296">Figure 7(a) and (b)</xref>). Subsequently, the inter-yarn transport followed in a next wicking front at 50–70 vol% (yellow-red front (β) in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0040517512460296">Figure 7(a) and (b)</xref>).</p>
<p>Time delays were observed between the intra- (α) and inter-yarn (β) waterfronts in the knit structure samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0040517512460296">Figure 7(a) and (b)</xref>). Interestingly, sample E-68 showed longer delays (on average 3.7 min time differences) than the other knit variations (R-68: 2.5 min; I-68: 1.7 min; Im-68: 1.9 min). The reason for this may be that the eyelets have inter-yarn capillaries of relatively large diameter, which filled up relatively slowly.</p>
<p>Time differences were also seen in layer-to-layer wicking between the different samples, particularly for the first waterfront. The time required for the liquid to wick to the next layer to obtain a critical threshold concentration was significantly longer in I-68 and Im-68 compared to E-68 and R-68. The latter two fabrics feature a higher interfacial void area at the face side, which was determined by picture analysis from optical micrographs. Thus, a smaller interlayer contact area exists (percentages in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0040517512460296">Figure 8(a)</xref>); from this one might expect longer delays in layer-to-layer wicking, but the opposite was observed. It appears that a critical threshold concentration has to be reached before the upper layer is wetted, in correspondence with the findings of Adler and Walsh;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0040517512460296">12</xref></sup> then, in the case of supply-limited flow, smaller textile areas are filled faster in the transplanar direction, thus reaching critical concentrations more rapidly.
<fig id="fig8-0040517512460296" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>(a) Onset of layer-to-layer wicking considered in the knit variations at low pressure (0.2 kPa). Percentage interfacial void areas are shown in brackets. Error bars are based on three measurements. (b) Influence of pressure on the time delays averaged over all four structures.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512460296-fig8.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>The influence of pressure is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0040517512460296">Figure 8(b)</xref>. The shorter delays for higher pressures are expectedly caused by an increase in the interlayer contact area (or number of contact points).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec14-0040517512460296"><title>Influence of fiber count</title>
<p>The water distribution in the fiber count samples showed that the liquid wicked to the upper layer without layer-to-layer time differences at around 30–50 vol% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0040517512460296">Figure 7(c)</xref>). This concentration threshold is somewhat higher than the previously observed intra-yarn wicking concentrations. Therefore, some of the liquid must have been transported through the inter-yarn voids in this case. As discussed in the <italic>In-plane wicking effect</italic> section, the water was squeezed into the capillaries due to the accumulation around the water nozzle. Consequently, transplanar wicking was reinforced. In this case the interlayer gap is not a limiting factor for layer-to-layer wicking. As soon as the liquid reached the top of the lower layer, wicking took place without reaching a detectable critical threshold concentration. This suggests that inter-yarn wicking may be a prerequisite for fast layer-to-layer wicking.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec15-0040517512460296"><title>Influence of pressure</title>
<p>Applying higher pressure on the knit structure samples led to an earlier onset of the layer-to-layer wicking, as shown by the representative knit sample I-68 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0040517512460296">Figure 9</xref>). Conceivably, this is mostly due to the decreasing interlayer gap. Therefore, a higher contact area exists and the liquid spreads faster to the upper layer, which is in agreement with the findings of previous works.<sup>3,25</sup> On the other hand, the quasi-hydrophobic fiber count samples showed no significant changes in transplanar wicking with increasing pressure. However, the scan time of 4.5 s per projection image limits a more detailed analysis of wicking behavior to explain this observation.
<fig id="fig9-0040517512460296" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Transplanar wicking behavior of I-68 at pressure levels 0.2 kPa (a), 2 kPa (b) and 5 kPa (c).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512460296-fig9.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec16-0040517512460296"><title>Transplanar capillary transport constants</title>
<p>The transplanar capillary transport constants <italic>k<sub>s</sub></italic> were determined from the first wicking front (10 vol%) in the outer layer. By considering all three applied pressure levels, samples E-68 and Im-68 tended to wick the fastest (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0040517512460296">Figure 10(a)</xref>). However, the only two significant between-sample differences were found in sample E-68 compared to I-68 and R-68 at 2 kPa. Higher pressure applied to the knit variations led to some trends of decreasing transplanar wicking rates in the outer layer. These pressure-dependent differences were only statistically significant for sample R-68 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0040517512460296">Figure 10(a)</xref>), showing the biggest decrease between 0.2 and 2 kPa.
<fig id="fig10-0040517512460296" position="float"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p>Transplanar capillary transport constants of the knit structure samples at three applied pressure levels (a) and the fiber count samples (b). For the knit structures, only the outer of the two textile layers was considered because of the delays in layer-to-layer wicking. Error bars are based on three measurements.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0040517512460296-fig10.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>For the quasi-hydrophobic fiber count samples, the capillary transport constants tended to increase with decreasing fiber count (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0040517512460296">Figure 10(b)</xref>), probably due to larger intra-yarn space. This result supports our hypothesis that the liquid was pressed in the transplanar direction into the capillaries due to the hydrophobicity. In this case the larger void spaces were filled first as the liquid spread along the path of least resistance. This led us to define two flow regimes: supply-driven flow, where the supplied flow exceeds the wicking rate, and supply-limited flow, where the supplied flow curbs the capillary-driven flow.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec17-0040517512460296" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The in-plane and transplanar wicking effects of polyester fabrics with different structures and fiber counts were analyzed by X-ray projection measurements, which allowed the study of the transient wicking behavior almost in real time.</p>
<p>For most fabrics, two or more waterfronts were observed that were explained by differences in intra- and inter-yarn capillary transport. The first front at a water concentration of 10 vol% appeared to be associated with intra-yarn wicking, whereas the front at a concentration of 50–70 vol% seemed to represent inter-yarn transport.</p>
<p>In the quasi-hydrophobic fiber count variations, in-plane wicking was slower than in the more hydrophilic knit structure samples. Consequently, the supplied amount of water could not be transported laterally fast enough by the intra-yarn capillaries and, thus, an accumulation around the water nozzle was observed. Hence, in these samples, the liquid wicked up to the upper layer without layer-to-layer time differences. The transplanar wicking rate decreased with more fibers per yarn.</p>
<p>In the hydrophilic knit structure variations, time differences in the onset for layer-to-layer wicking correlated with their interfacial void area; the shortest time delays were seen for the (hydrophilic) rib knit (70 s @ 0.2 kPa), which had the largest void area. By applying higher pressure, these times were shortened due to the higher interlayer contact area. Pressure increases also led to shorter time differences between intra- and inter-yarn wicking. Furthermore, by varying the pressure, a transition was observed from a “supply-limited flow” regime to a “supply-driven flow” regime, depending on whether the supplied flow rate was less or more than the maximum capillary-driven flow.</p>
<p>Wicking rates obtained from the radiography data were compared to tensiometry data. The respective capillary transport constants correlated linearly, but not proportionally. This was due to the influence of gravity in the tensiometer, and because in the CT setup, pressures were applied and flow rates were constant (in order to provide a more realistic simulation of sweat uptake by garments). The capillary transport constant from tensiometry was found to be inversely proportional to the fiber count.</p>
<p>In general, intra-yarn transport was found to be responsible for the fastest in-plane water spreading (hydrophilic yarns), while inter-yarn transport was responsible for the fastest layer-to-layer wicking (hydrophobic yarns). From the results, we infer that a hydrophobic inner layer of low fiber count may be ideal for transporting excess liquid away from the skin (supply-driven flow). Also, we expect that if a second hydrophilic knit were worn over it, excess liquid would collect there and distribute laterally (supply-limited flow), thus keeping the skin relatively dry.</p>
<p>Of the hydrophilic knit qualities, rib and eyelet types appear to be desirable for fast layer-to-layer wicking, whereas interlock-type knits performed better in an in-plane comparison. Higher fiber counts correlated with higher in-plane wicking rates but with slower transplanar water transfer. We foresee that the combination of different knits, contact angles and fiber counts in consecutive clothing layers can lead to significant improvements in wear comfort.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>We gratefully thank Rolf Stämpfli and Simon Annaheim for helpful discussions.</p></ack>
<sec id="sec18-0040517512460296"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list><title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0040517512460296"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patnaik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rengasamy</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kothari</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Wetting and wicking in fibrous materials</article-title>. <source>Textil Prog</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>105</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0040517512460296"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crow</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Osczevski</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The interaction of water with fabrics</article-title>. <source>Textil Res J</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>280</fpage>–<lpage>288</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0040517512460296"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stämpfli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Psikuta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Transplanar and in-plane wicking effects in sock materials under pressure</article-title>. <source>Textil Res J</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>1549</fpage>–<lpage>1558</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0040517512460296"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kissa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Wetting and wicking</article-title>. <source>Textil Res J</source> <year>1996</year>; <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>660</fpage>–<lpage>668</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0040517512460296"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Liquid transport in fabric structures</article-title>. <source>Textil Res J</source> <year>1995</year>; <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>299</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0040517512460296"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harnett</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A survey and comparison of laboratory test methods for measuring wicking</article-title>. <source>Textil Res J</source> <year>1984</year>; <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>471</fpage>–<lpage>478</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0040517512460296"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Langenhove</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiekens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Textiles and the transport of moisture</article-title>. <source>Textil Asia</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0040517512460296"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Moisture management tester: a method to characterize fabric liquid moisture management properties</article-title>. <source>Textil Res J</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0040517512460296"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comfort properties of heat-resistant protective workwear in varying conditions of physical activity and environment</article-title>. <source>Textil Res J</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>523</fpage>–<lpage>530</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0040517512460296"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyomkin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Spontaneous transplanar uptake of liquids by fabrics</article-title>. <source>Textil Res J</source> <year>1984</year>; <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>706</fpage>–<lpage>712</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0040517512460296"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of multilayer clothing system array on water vapor transfer in condensation in cold weather clothing ensemble</article-title>. <source>Textil Res J</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>197</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0040517512460296"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanisms of transient moisture transport between fabrics</article-title>. <source>Textil Res J</source> <year>1984</year>; <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>334</fpage>–<lpage>343</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0040517512460296"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>May</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Water vapor transfer and condensation effects in multilayer textile combinations</article-title>. <source>Textil Res J</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0040517512460296"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spencer-Smith</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The physical basis of clothing comfort, Part 4: the passage of heat and water through damp clothing assemblies</article-title>. <source>Clothing Res J</source> <year>1977</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>116</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0040517512460296"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Havenith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Apparent latent heat of evaporation from clothing: attenuation and "heat pipe" effects</article-title>. <source>J Appl Physiol</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0040517512460296"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Meinander</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dry and wet heat transfer through clothing dependent on the clothing properties under cold conditions</article-title>. <source>Int J Occup Saf Ergon</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0040517512460296"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keiser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Moisture transport and absorption in multilayer protective clothing fabrics</article-title>. <source>Textil Res J</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>604</fpage>–<lpage>613</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0040517512460296"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Transplanar water transport tester for fabrics</article-title>. <source>Meas Sci Technol</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1465</fpage>–<lpage>1471</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0040517512460296"><label>19</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leisen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckham</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Quantitative magnetic resonance imaging of fluid distribution and movement in textiles</article-title>. <source>Textil Res J</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>1033</fpage>–<lpage>1045</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0040517512460296"><label>20</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bencsik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Adriaensen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Quantitative NMR monitoring of liquid ingress into repellent heterogeneous layered fabrics</article-title>. <source>J Magn Reson</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>193</volume>: <fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0040517512460296"><label>21</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reifler</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Frei</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The method of neutron imaging as a tool for the study of the dynamics of water movement in wet aramid-based ballistic body armour panels</article-title>. <source>Meas Sci Technol</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1925</fpage>–<lpage>1934</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0040517512460296"><label>22</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keiser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyss</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of steam formation and migration in firefighters' protective clothing using X-ray radiography</article-title>. <source>Int J Occup Saf Ergon</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>229</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0040517512460296"><label>23</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roels</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmeliet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of moisture flow in porous materials using microfocus X-ray radiography</article-title>. <source>Int J Heat Mass Tran</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>4762</fpage>–<lpage>4772</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0040517512460296"><label>24</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brühwiler</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Laib</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>X-ray tomography measurements of the moisture distribution in multilayered clothing systems</article-title>. <source>Textil Res J</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>18</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0040517512460296"><label>25</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Harlock</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Brook</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Transfer wicking mechanisms of knitted fabrics used as undergarments for outdoor activities</article-title>. <source>Textil Res J</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>727</fpage>–<lpage>734</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0040517512460296"><label>26</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Numerical simulation of 3D dynamic garment pressure</article-title>. <source>Textil Res J</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>72</volume>: <fpage>245</fpage>–<lpage>245</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0040517512460296"><label>27</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hollies</surname><given-names>NRS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaessinger</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogaty</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Water transport mechanisms in textile materials Part I: the role of yarn roughness in capillary-type penetration</article-title>. <source>Textil Res J</source> <year>1956</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>829</fpage>–<lpage>835</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0040517512460296"><label>28</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hollies</surname><given-names>NRS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaessinger</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Water transport mechanisms in textile materials Part II: capillary-type penetration in yarns and fabrics</article-title>. <source>Textil Res J</source> <year>1957</year>; <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>8</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0040517512460296"><label>29</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minor</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wulkow</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The migration of liquid in textile assemblies, Part II</article-title>. <source>Textil Res J</source> <year>1959</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>931</fpage>–<lpage>939</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0040517512460296"><label>30</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Design and analysis of experiments</source> <year>2009</year>. <edition>7th edn</edition>. <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken, NJ</publisher-loc>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0040517512460296"><label>31</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Washburn</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The dynamics of capillary flow</article-title>. <source>Phys Rev</source> <year>1921</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>283</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>