<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="letter" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ANP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spanp</journal-id>
<journal-title>Australian &amp; New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0004-8674</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1440-1614</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0004867412460104</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0004867412460104</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Correspondence</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Letters</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Levosulpiride-induced rabbit syndrome</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>Shobit</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Goyal</surname><given-names>Nishant</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>Vinod Kumar</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0004867412460104">Department of Psychiatry, Central Institute of Psychiatry, Ranchi, India</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0004867412460104">Nishant Goyal, Central Institute of Psychiatry, A 201 Koyla Vihar, Kanke Road, Ranchi, 834008, India. Email: <email>psynishant@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>47</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>288</fpage>
<lpage>289</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">The Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>To the Editor</p>
<p>Rabbit syndrome (RS) is a rare movement disorder characterized by involuntary, rhythmic, fast, and fine movements of the oral and masticatory muscles along the vertical axis of the mouth. The involuntary movements associated with RS appear after a long period (in most cases months or years) of antipsychotic treatment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0004867412460104">Catena et al., 2007</xref>). The prevalence of RS ranges from 2.3–4.4% in patients treated with typical antipsychotics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0004867412460104">Schwartz and Hocherman, 2004</xref>). Catena Dell’Osso and colleagues found 11 cases of RS associated with atypical antipsychotics. Most of them were linked to risperidone and a few were associated with clozapine, olanzapine, quetiapine, and aripiprazole (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0004867412460104">Catena Dell’Osso et al., 2007</xref>). It has been postulated that the underlying mechanism of RS is the supersensitivity of dopamine receptors, possibly due to an underlying predisposition with attention on the basal ganglia, in particular the substantia nigra pars reticulata, which is also implicated in oral dyskinesia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0004867412460104">Praharaj et al., 2008</xref>). We report a case of RS associated with the use of levosulpiride.</p>
<p>The index-case patient, a 22-year-old single female, with unremarkable family, past and personal history, presented with complaints of delayed motor and language milestones and difficult temperament since early childhood. There was a history of gradual onset of abusive behaviour, anger outbursts, increased activity, increased energy, and impaired biological functions, with an episodic course for 6 years. The patient had short stature and kyphoscoliosis on physical examination. The mental status examination revealed increased expressive gestures, overproductive and loud speech, irritable affect, and delusion of grandeur.</p>
<p>The patient was diagnosed with bipolar affective disorder, currently manic with psychotic symptoms and was treated on an outpatient basis with carbamazepine (600 mg/day<sup>-1</sup>) and risperidone (3 mg/day<sup>-1</sup>). She developed akathisia, tremors, and rigidity over a period of 2 weeks. Subsequently, the antipsychotic was changed to levosulpiride (100 mg/day<sup>-1</sup>). After 2 months, on follow-up, the patient reported the development of oral involuntary movements. The movements were fine, rhythmic, and rapid, along the vertical axis and without lingual involvement. A diagnosis of RS was made and levosulpiride was reduced to 50 mg/day and benzhexol was added. The patient’s RS diminished significantly within next 4 weeks and further improvement was noted at the next follow-up.</p>
<p>RS is believed to be a rare condition affecting only a small fraction of the psychiatric population using antipsychotics. Atypical antipsychotics differ from typical antipsychotics in their effectiveness in psychosis and their side effect profile. Though RS generally appears late, in our case it appeared after 2 months of levosulpiride usage. Our case agrees with the fact that RS develops more commonly in females, though ours was an early-onset case (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0004867412460104">Wu and Su, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>To our knowledge, there are no reports of levosulpiride-induced RS. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0004867412460104">Shin et al. (2009)</xref> studied the clinical characteristics of patients with levosulpiride-induced movement disorder and found parkinsonism to be the most common side effect, followed by tardive dyskinesia, and isolated tremor. No case of RS was reported. Levosulpiride is a specific inhibitor of the dopamine D<sub>2</sub> receptors, particularly as it binds specifically and stereoselectively to presynaptic D<sub>2</sub> receptors which have sodium-dependent functions. Therefore, the supersensitivity of dopamine receptors could be the underlying mechanism of RS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0004867412460104">Praharaj et al., 2008</xref>), though this mechanism may be too simplistic, and the actual pathophysiology may vary between individuals. Different antipsychotic drugs were used before levosulpiride, and the fact that the extrapyramidal symptoms (EPS) emerged shows the importance of individual factors (vulnerability) in RS in our case. Vulnerability for drug-induced EPS, the earlier onset of RS (i.e. 2 months), and the rapid improvement which occurred with the reduction in levosulpiride dosage (and the addition of benzhexol) implicates the role of a low-dose mechanistic blockade of dopamine receptors in the genesis of RS. A similar mechanism has been reported in the genesis of resting orolingual tremors with levosulpiride (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0004867412460104">Kim et al., 2009</xref>), but future neurophysiological research of the basal ganglia holds the key to better understanding and improved treatment of this syndrome.</p>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of interest</label>
<p>The authors report no conflicts of interest. The authors alone are responsible for the content and writing of the paper.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0004867412460104">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Catena</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fagiolini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Consoli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The rabbit syndrome: state of the art</article-title>. <source>Current Clinical Pharmacology</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>212</fpage>–<lpage>216</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0004867412460104">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Catena Dell’Osso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fagiolini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ducci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Newer antipsychotics and the rabbit syndrome</article-title>. <source>Clinical Practice and Epidemiology in Mental Health</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>6</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0004867412460104">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Levosulpiride-induced resting orolingual tremor</article-title>. <source>Movement Disorders</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>1700</fpage>–<lpage>1701</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0004867412460104">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Praharaj</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jana</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Olanzapine-induced rabbit syndrome</article-title>. <source>Southern Medical Journal</source> <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>1069</fpage>–<lpage>1070</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0004867412460104">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hocherman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Antipsychotic-induced rabbit syndrome: epidemiology, management and pathophysiology</article-title>. <source>CNS Drugs</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0004867412460104">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Levosulpiride-induced movement disorders</article-title>. <source>Movement Disorders</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>2249</fpage>–<lpage>2253</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0004867412460104">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Quetiapine-induced rabbit syndrome in a patient with bipolar disorder</article-title>. <source>Progress in Neuro-Psychopharmacology &amp; Biological Psychiatry</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>2002</fpage>–<lpage>2003</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>