<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review" xml:lang="EN">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">FAP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spfap</journal-id>
<journal-title>Feminism &amp; Psychology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0959-3535</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7161</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0959353512472480</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0959353512472480</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Martha E Thompson and Michael Armato, <italic>Investigating Gender: Developing a Feminist Sociological Imagination</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>George</surname><given-names>Meghan</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>23</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>272</fpage>
<lpage>274</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0959353512472480"><title>Martha E Thompson and Michael Armato, <italic>Investigating Gender: Developing a Feminist Sociological Imagination</italic>, Polity Press: Cambridge, 2012, 350 pp., ISBN: 978-0-7456-5185-9</title>
<sec id="sec2-0959353512472480"><title><bold>Reviewed by</bold>: Meghan George, <italic>Ryerson University, Canada</italic></title>
<p>We take for granted that segregation by sex exists in many areas of our society. In doing so we perpetuate this segregation and our definitions of gender become even more exclusive. This is the point made in the introduction to <italic>Investigating Gender: Developing a Feminist Sociological Imagination</italic> by Martha Thompson and Michael Armato, professors of sociology and women’s studies at Northeastern Illinois University. To prove their case, Thompson and Armato point to our use of signs separating men’s and women’s restrooms. If the feminist movement has been successful in fighting for gender equality, why do we insist that women not be allowed to use the men’s restroom, and vice versa? And why, for that matter, is it acceptable to use a silhouette of an individual in a dress to depict a woman? Is this not reminiscent, they argue, of a time when African Americans and Caucasians were forbidden to share restroom facilities? By abiding by the rules and traditions set out by society, we appear to be undermining feminism and buying into the supposed differences between the sexes. Though their example may be a bit jarring at first, it seems that the intent of the authors is to open the reader’s eyes to the subtle ways in which each and every one of us is affected by sex, gender and feminism.</p>
<p>Following in the spirit of the introduction, the remainder of the book encourages the reader to look closely at potential injustices in society and analyze their own experiences of inequality, a process they term ‘developing one’s feminist sociological imagination’. Thompson and Armato share their own examples at the beginning of each of the book’s 10 chapters to illustrate how subtle inequality can sometimes be. For instance, in the opening of the chapter on families, Thompson shares the story of her marital agreement to share responsibilities (i.e. home, child care and work) with her partner despite the fact that women were expected to play a larger domestic role at that time. She also describes the resistance she faced when she informed people she was keeping her maiden name. These vignettes were useful tools, not only to introduce each new topic, but also to guide the reader in how to pull personal experience into their analysis of gender, and how to recognize inequality in seemingly innocuous or socially accepted situations.</p>
<p>Chapter topics included a discussion on bodies, families, education, work, health, media, politics and interpersonal violence. Not only do these topics cover the basics of how being male or female impacts one’s experience and behavior with regards to each broad institution, they also provide examples of past research that resulted in the knowledge we now have on gender equality and helped establish what was still to be done in the field. The chapters easily flow from small intimate institutions such as families, to larger institutions such as government and politics. Despite covering so much ground, Thompson and Armato keep the chapters simple enough to make the book an easy read – a helpful quality in a textbook.</p>
<p>One aspect of the text that stood out was its use of data from international examples. While the majority of the work cited focuses on North American issues of gender and feminism, the authors are sensitive to the fact that these issues do not uniformly reflect the experience of women worldwide. In each chapter, the topic of discussion is examined in four representative countries: Kenya, Sweden, Mexico and China. These countries represent a spectrum of socioeconomics and cultural models, and in comparing the North American experience to each of these countries, Thompson and Armato are able to show how the same institutions and situations can produce a variety of experiences based on cultural context. The opportunity to explore these issues in an international framework was enlightening. It provided the reader with material not often available in North American feminist research journals, and showed the diversity of the gendered experience around the world. This was a refreshing teaching technique.</p>
<p>As well as providing international examples, in true textbook fashion each chapter comes with a set of discussion questions and learning activities designed to help readers in their own research and investigations. The questions are centered around the topic outlined in the chapter, and while some seemed rather more ambitious than others (for instance, the chapter on bodies suggests readers interview someone affected by the treatment of intersex individuals, such as physicians or counsellors, then write a report about their findings), they certainly brought attention to the application of the material within the chapter.</p>
<p>An important point made by the authors (which, by the end of the book, actually became a bit repetitive) was that studying gender alone limited one’s understanding of the complex intersection between gender and so many other variables. For instance, gender may impact how an individual is treated or behaves, but race and class also play their part. A white woman may experience discrimination very differently from that of a Latina, just as an upper class woman may have different opportunities than a working class woman. So while the reader ‘investigates gender’, they must be aware that gender is not the only factor influencing a person’s life experience. The authors are very conscious of this fact and they make efforts to provide both general gender-specific research as well as specific examples of how different variables intersect with the topic.</p>
<p>The final chapter of <italic>Investigating Gender</italic> summarizes the main themes of the book and the focus of each chapter. It also looks forward to future research and social applications of feminist studies. The authors acknowledge the need for more awareness of the topics discussed in the book and they express their hope that the book has not only inspired academic analysis of feminist research, but also an everyday awareness of the topic.</p>
<p><italic>Investigating Gender</italic> is a feminist teaching and resource guide, written from a feminist sociological perspective. As a student of psychology, I was concerned when I started reading the book that my lack of sociological background would hinder my reading experience. Perhaps I missed some of the nuances only those attuned to a sociological perspective would pick up on, but I believe that the book served its purpose in inspiring my feminist sociological imagination. The margins of every chapter in my copy are covered in notes about examples I’ve personally witnessed, my outrage over learning certain facts and statistics, and my thoughts on how to work towards social justice. The message of this book is therefore clear: Regardless of your academic background, feminism is a vital field of research around the world that must look to other intersecting factors in order to bring about social change.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
</article>