<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RSH</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sprsh</journal-id>
<journal-title>Perspectives in Public Health</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1757-9139</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1757-9147</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1757913911399364</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1757913911399364</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Peer Review</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Development of a practical toolkit using participatory action research to address health inequalities through NGOs in the UK: Challenges and lessons learned</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Chirewa</surname><given-names>Blessing</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1757913911399364">Brunel University, Graduate School, Centre for Public Health Research, Uxbridge, Middlesex, UK Email: <email>blessing.chirewa@brunel.ac.uk</email></aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>132</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>228</fpage>
<lpage>234</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© Royal Society for Public Health 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Royal Society for Public Health</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This study aimed to develop a practical toolkit to support non-government organizations (NGOs) in tackling health inequalities in the UK and to highlight the challenges and lessons learned. A mixed qualitative methodology within an action research framework was conducted. Semi-structured questionnaires, focus group interviews and discussions with an expert reference group aimed to identify the important themes and produce the toolkit content. A practical guide of information materials for NGOs working on addressing health inequalities was subsequently developed and successfully piloted. The experience of using participatory action research revealed a number of lessons and challenges. The key challenges were lack of training and experience in conducting action research, costs and insufficient resources, slow and time-consuming process, lack of commitment from marginalized groups, and differences in emphasis of goals and vision among participants. The main lessons learned were importance of effective leadership and project management skills, importance of integrating researchers and the researched as equal partners, creation and nurturing of trust, importance of evaluating and piloting processes, importance of engaging with marginalized groups, and use of evidence base in decision making. The lessons and challenges enumerating herein are of value to researchers aiming to implement participatory action research in developing checklists, tools, practical guidance and frameworks, and they offer important areas to consider before starting such projects. In addition, this offers an insight into how the dynamics of participatory action research methodology evolved in the development of the toolkit. Future research and initiatives in this area should focus on ways to improve the toolkit and make it more relevant to a wider community, and methods for evaluating the impact of the toolkit on practice.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>toolkit</kwd>
<kwd>health inequalities</kwd>
<kwd>NGOs</kwd>
<kwd>action research</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1757913911399364" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Inequalities in health are a major public health concern in all developed countries.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1757913911399364">1</xref></sup> Consequently, reducing inequalities in health has become a key priority for the UK government.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1757913911399364">2</xref></sup> One of the goals of the 1999 public health White Paper <italic>Saving Lives: Our Healthier Nation</italic> was to ‘improve the health of the worst off in society and narrow the gap’. In order to narrow the gap between the rich and the worst off, there is growing recognition among governments and international organizations that the involvement of all stakeholders is needed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1757913911399364">3</xref></sup> The UK government’s Cross Cutting Review (CCR) identified that non-government organizations (NGOs)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1757913911399364">i</xref></sup> may be able to deliver services more effectively to certain groups because their structures enable them to operate in environments where statutory bodies find it impossible. Furthermore, NGOs are seen to have the ability to tap into disadvantaged groups and engage with them.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1757913911399364">4</xref></sup> One of the NGOs’ strengths is their ability to understand local context and use of bottom-up approaches to alleviate poverty and reduce health inequalities.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1757913911399364">5</xref></sup> However, what is often lacking among the NGOs and their partners is a good ‘route map’ for tackling health inequalities. Recognizing this need, the NGO Forum<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1757913911399364">ii</xref></sup> commissioned an action research project with the aim of developing a toolkit<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1757913911399364">iii</xref></sup> that could be used to inform future projects. In this article we describe the process of developing a toolkit for NGOs to support them in tackling health inequalities and to draw some practical lessons from the process of using participatory action research (PAR) methodology. The lessons and challenges enumerating herein will offer an insight into how the dynamics of PAR methodology evolved in the development of the toolkit. Furthermore, for individuals and organizations interested in developing toolkits in future and other projects, it will offer important areas to consider before starting such projects and suggestions on overcoming any challenges that may arise.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1757913911399364">
<title>The Need for a Toolkit to Support NGOs</title>
<p>A number of barriers limiting the involvement of NGOs in tackling health inequalities have been identified.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1757913911399364">4</xref></sup> They include lack of time and a skill gap in the process of acquiring and appraising literature, along with a question mark over the ability of poorly funded NGOs to ensure that the best available evidence about good practice is incorporated into their work.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1757913911399364">6</xref></sup> Most research currently used to influence patterns of practice and guidelines have been carried out in highly selected populations, usually assembled in highly specialized research or teaching facilities.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1757913911399364">7</xref></sup> The conclusions or guidelines produced from most of these studies may or may not apply to individuals who are seen in the average community setting.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1757913911399364">7</xref></sup> Given the complexity of these processes, it is not surprising that several strategies designed to move research evidence into practice show little effect.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1757913911399364">6</xref></sup> A toolkit was therefore developed in this study to complement and support NGOs, particularly those who work predominantly when other support is not available (for instance, when there is no access to resources such as computers, internet services or research literature, or communication tools such as telephones). As the toolkit is readily available to whoever needs it, it was felt to be particularly appropriate in overcoming the time constraints involved with searching for evidence on how best to manage projects.</p>
<p>While a toolkit provides useful resources and materials, it does not provide the last word; and it can never be absolutely comprehensive in addressing a broad subject such as health inequalities. It only provides a framework for service improvement and development of good practice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1757913911399364">8</xref></sup> More often, health practitioners who are opponents of toolkits might argue that they are a waste of money, gathering dust on the shelves once you place them in the office. To counter this argument, we would point out that there is a mismatch between what a toolkit is designed to do and what practitioners require. It is a question of matching tools to tasks.</p>
<p>The development of the toolkit was considered to be about disseminating best available evidence about particular projects and lessons that could be drawn from them. It was about giving people a set of steps that they would go through, thus avoiding leaping into a poor intervention before thinking it through, thereby increasing their chances of success. This would enable NGOs to benchmark their programmes, provide a better understanding of the problems, and share experiences and information to improve practices. While inequalities in health have many dimensions, including those linked to age, physical disabilities or learning difficulties, this study outlines a strategy that is not specific to particular health inequalities but is a general overview of some practical guidelines.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1757913911399364" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="section4-1757913911399364">
<title>Study design</title>
<p>In order to develop the toolkit, the project used mixed qualitative methods within a PAR framework. The initial preparatory phase (step 1) involved literature search, and the designing of research questions and questionnaires (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1757913911399364">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1757913911399364" position="float">
<label>Figure 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Stages in the development of the toolkit</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1757913911399364-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The PAR approach was chosen because it was considered highly appropriate for the development and evaluation of new health tools;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1757913911399364">9</xref></sup> it also enabled empowerment and project ownership among the participants. More significantly, it enabled the development of the whole process to be grounded in the views of the NGOs and their partners.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1757913911399364">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>The research participants were drawn from the NGO forum affiliates (<italic>n</italic> = 30), NHS primary care trusts (PCTs) (<italic>n</italic> = 2) and an expert group (academics) (<italic>N</italic> = 4) with an interest in health inequalities and the third sector.</p>
<p>In action research, participants can be actors in the research process as well as sources of data, and it is important to specify their level of involvement.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1757913911399364">10</xref></sup> Key stakeholders were involved in a consultative role only; they did not have any input into data analysis. Expert groups were involved in a co-learning role.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1757913911399364">
<title>Sampling</title>
<p>Sampling was purposive, with the aim of collecting a diverse sample of key stakeholders from different groups of the NGO forum (in terms of size and activities carried out) and to recruit participants who had particular experiences and roles that were pertinent to the study objectives. We applied purposive sampling methods to seek groups or settings and individuals where the processes being studied were most likely to occur.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1757913911399364">11</xref></sup> Initially a snowballing technique was used, beginning with the people known to the research team, followed by selection criteria based on ethnicity, region, and the size of the community and the NGO.</p>
<p>Snowballing was considered to be a suitable sampling method because some of the NGOs we worked with were very small, with no offices and in some cases with only one full-time member of staff, and therefore difficult to locate.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1757913911399364">
<title>Key stages</title>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1757913911399364">Figure 1</xref> shows the key stages in the toolkit development and the methods employed in each step.</p>
<sec id="section8-1757913911399364">
<title>Step 1: Developing a framework for toolkit design</title>
<p>We conducted an in-depth thematic literature review. The search was restricted to 1999–2009 to ensure that identified publications were recent, diverse and relevant. Wide-ranging literature searches were undertaken using databases of published literature (such as MEDLINE, CINAHL, Science Direct, Scopus, <italic>British Medical Journal</italic> (<italic>BMJ</italic>), Pubmed), internet search engines such as Google and specific relevant websites searches (e.g. the National Electronic Library for Health). These searches identified unpublished reports and published literature that could be used to identify potential evidence-based interventions for addressing health inequalities through NGOs. The literature review enabled the designing of research questions and questionnaires. The questionnaires developed were piloted for sense and clarity among fellow researchers and two NGOs members (selected for their proximity to the research team); minor alterations were made as a result.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1757913911399364">
<title>Step 2: Data collection</title>
<p>The questionnaires were emailed to participants to find out the following: what the health inequalities were; what works and what doesn’t when addressing health inequalities; what a toolkit is; suggestions on toolkit content; and the role of NGOs in addressing health inequalities. The main limitation of emailing questionnaires was that marginalized NGOs without access to the internet were technically excluded from the study; therefore we sent postal questionnaires to these NGOs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1757913911399364">
<title>Step 3: Evaluation of questionnaire responses</title>
<p>The questionnaire responses were analysed using qualitative software Atlas-ti version 8.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1757913911399364">
<title>Step 4: Interviews</title>
<p>Face-to-face and telephone interviews were conducted with those participants who could not complete the questionnaires. All interviews were audiotaped (with the consent of the participants) and subsequently transcribed. All participants were sent their own transcripts for correction or comment. The transcripts were then analysed using qualitative software Atlas-ti version 8. Data analysis involved using a constant comparative method, in which transcripts were repeatedly reviewed to find emerging themes, which was consistent with the general inductive approach.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1757913911399364">12</xref></sup> Frequent discussions on coding and themes were held among the research team; differences were resolved and a consensus on each of the transcripts was reached.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1757913911399364">
<title>Step 5: Design and development of the toolkit</title>
<p>A framework for the development of the toolkit was developed from the themes that emerged in step 4. Having agreed which domains would be included within the draft toolkit, stakeholders were further consulted on its content.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1757913911399364">
<title>Step 6: Piloting of the toolkit</title>
<p>The purpose of this step was to check that the participants and stakeholders understood the processes and the toolkit content. In addition, acceptability of the format was checked and clarity of the key themes in the toolkit was ascertained. Piloting of the toolkit involved the following activities:</p>
<list id="list1-1757913911399364" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>An informal invitation was sent to several NGOs to participate in the pilot process.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>A draft toolkit was emailed to a sample of 15 NGOs, diverse in size, type and location. A feedback form was attached to the email, which invited participants to rate the degree to which they agreed with a series of statements about the toolkit’s form and content and its potential usefulness to their organization.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Two focus group discussions (n = 12) were carried out and the interviews were audiotaped and transcribed. The transcripts were analysed using qualitative computer software Atlas-ti version 8.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1757913911399364">
<title>Step 7: Evaluation</title>
<p>This involved the analysis of feedback comments from the piloting of the draft toolkit.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1757913911399364">
<title>Step 8: Final product</title>
<p>The research team made final changes based on the stakeholders’ review comments; there were many formatting issues, as well as issues arising from the size of the completed toolkit. Once these were resolved, the final copy was ready for production.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1757913911399364">
<title>Ethics statement</title>
<p>Ethics approval was sought and granted from the Brunel University research ethics committee.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-1757913911399364" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The primary outcome of this study was the development of a toolkit for NGOs, which was published in October 2009. For the scope of this paper, it is not feasible to do more than give an overview of the toolkit contents.</p>
<p>The toolkit consists of a set of resources for the NGOs to use when addressing health inequalities. It adopted an easy-to-use format, with titles in everyday language to avoid jargon and misunderstanding. The first chapters give an introduction to health inequalities and NGOs, and the rationale for the development of the toolkit. Subsequent chapters present the following: a definition of health inequalities and inequities; an overview of health inequalities in England; a needs assessment guide; a framework for implementing change; and an evaluation guide. The final chapter lists sources of funding and practical examples of ‘successful’ and ‘unsuccessful’ projects.</p>
<p>The web form of the toolkit can be accessed at the following address: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ngoforum.org.uk/Inequality%20Guide%2026.10.09.pdf">http://www.ngoforum.org.uk/Inequality%20Guide%2026.10.09.pdf</ext-link></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-1757913911399364" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The hard-to-reach and marginalized groups shoulder the heaviest burdens in health inequalities.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1757913911399364">13</xref></sup> PAR holds great promise for producing more useful and culturally appropriate interventions and for providing a model to empower the groups to become partners in the elimination of health inequalities. In this study, PAR methodology provided a useful source of evidence for linking research to action for NGOs, and in doing so, ensured relevancy, acceptance and ownership of the resulting toolkit.</p>
<p>Despite differences in the make-up of the NGOs who participated in the project, each expressed genuine commitment to using the toolkit and engaging with the communities. There appeared to be some relationship between the level of buy-in and the size of the NGO; the smaller NGOs demonstrated a stronger identity with the toolkit.</p>
<p>While the toolkit is intended for use by NGOs, it may also be a useful resource for anyone working on tackling health inequalities when resources are not readily available.</p>
<sec id="section19-1757913911399364">
<title>Challenges faced in developing the toolkit</title>
<p>Our exploration of PAR in this study revealed a number of challenges. Some we had predicted but others we had not, yet all were viewed as part of our learning and integral to the process of developing a practical toolkit and effecting change through the use of PAR methodology. These challenges are important lessons for future use of PAR and are outlined below.</p>
<sec id="section20-1757913911399364">
<title>Different emphasis on goals, values, priorities and perspectives</title>
<p>The process of collecting evidence was not free from difficulty. Representatives from one of the groups we spoke with stated that while they would envisage clear benefits to being engaged in the development of the toolkit, they would not commit time to the process of identifying evidence or uncovering existing evidence. As an example, the research team received an email from one organization that read; “we have looked around and cannot identify anyone to complete your questionnaire or to grant you a telephone interview at this moment in time.” Others groups contacted by the research team did not have computers or administrative support or paid staff and were not willing to participate in the study. Groups such as these display all the hallmarks that conform to the label hard-to-reach or hard-to-engage. They tend to be underfunded, over reliant on the goodwill of volunteers and are often forced to exit the market due to financial and organizational pressures. There were other groups who declined to be involved as they saw no benefit in supplying evidence when the final document would not be presented in their native language, for instance Hindi. Challenges also arose because members of the partnerships have for, example, different values, beliefs and cultures.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1757913911399364">14</xref></sup> Importantly, these various differences do not suggest a ‘right’ or ‘wrong’ way that partnerships should operate; rather they suggest the need to consider and accommodate diverse perspectives.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-1757913911399364">
<title>Lack of commitment</title>
<p>It was problematic to get some members of the NGO forum to commit to participating in the study; others were dismissive without engaging and some would not respond to an email. The full contribution of all members of the NGO forum was not clear, which could lead to an underestimated projection of resources required for future PAR inquiries. Full participation by the NGOs is therefore imperative to ensure their influence in the project.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1757913911399364">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1757913911399364">15</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-1757913911399364">
<title>Lack of training and experience in conducting PAR</title>
<p>The principal researcher and the NGO forum members involved in the research had limited training and experience in conducting PAR. Although there is a large and growing literature on how to carry out PAR,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1757913911399364">16</xref></sup> no direct training was received and there were few opportunities to strengthen their skills in this area. However, the involvement of experienced researchers in an advisory capacity was beneficial to the research process as they creatively helped to manage the principal researcher’s time and that of stakeholders. Achieving a balance between the research needs and the NGO forum members’ interests was a challenge. Therefore, ensuring that all partners are satisfied requires vigilant, ongoing attention and dialogue.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1757913911399364">17</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-1757913911399364">
<title>Slow and time-consuming process</title>
<p>PAR is characterized by a series of trials and errors through the iterative processes of identifying problems and generating solutions to bring about change.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1757913911399364">18</xref></sup> It was common during the project for participants to view early efforts as completely or partially unsuccessful. We often had to return to the drawing board in order to accomplish our initial goals. Unlike conventional research projects in which timelines for participant recruitment, data collection, data analysis and reporting of results can be tentatively outlined, PAR can be entirely unpredictable. This was a source of frustration to participants and the research team alike.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section24-1757913911399364">
<title>Costs and insufficient resources</title>
<p>There are numerous costs for both the researched (NGO forum/community) and the research partners (research team) involved in PAR efforts, but insufficient resources to overcome them.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1757913911399364">14</xref></sup> Smaller NGO forum members faced financial costs from involvement, such as lack of adequate reimbursement for their time spent in participating, as well as opportunity costs for time taken away from other job responsibilities. Implementing PAR is therefore costly; it requires investment of time and resources in development and maintenance that is seldom fully funded. The researcher must be committed and able to obtain flexible funding and be prepared to make personal financial contributions.</p>
<p>The challenges observed in this study, such as time, funding issues, tenure guidelines and the readiness of NGO forum members to undertake research, further support the findings of previous studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1757913911399364">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1757913911399364">19</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1757913911399364"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1757913911399364">21</xref></sup> This work therefore adds to the understanding of these issues and emphasizes the need to think of specific strategies for success in project management.</p>
<p>The challenges outlined above are reflections of the large task the NGOs face, which is to effect long-term change on the health of hard-to-reach groups. Despite the magnitude of these challenges, NGOs are well placed to act as a vehicle towards this immense task of addressing health inequalities.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section25-1757913911399364">
<title>Lessons learned</title>
<p>Building on these challenges, several overarching lessons were learned during the process of developing the toolkit.</p>
<sec id="section26-1757913911399364">
<title>Lesson 1</title>
<p>During the development of the toolkit, some NGOs found out that just undertaking a structured process in project design was useful and important as it prompted them to think differently. Following a structured process enabled them to learn earlier in the development cycle rather than at a later stage where it might have been difficult to make amends. Conducting a literature search in the development of the toolkit framework enabled the use of evidence-based resources.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section27-1757913911399364">
<title>Lesson 2</title>
<p>Evaluating and piloting the toolkit were found to be valuable processes as this enabled engagement and further participation of the stakeholders. Through the processes of engagement and participation, unfavourable outcomes were eliminated.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section28-1757913911399364">
<title>Lesson 3</title>
<p>The creation and nurturing of trust was found out to be a basic element of a successful and mutually beneficial community–academic relationship. It became apparent during the study that working with the hard-to-reach groups was about trust and sustained initiatives, not a one-time event.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section29-1757913911399364">
<title>Lesson 4</title>
<p>Working with marginalized groups involved identifying and developing project leaders from their members, which was a strategy to empower them and obtain their buy-in. We found out that the process of team building between the researched and the researchers was not automatic. It was important to spend a good deal of time developing a shared understanding of NGO programmes, their mission and values. From the beginning, we made it clear that we would work with and carefully listen to their leaders/managers with the aim of developing a consensus about the purposes, methods and targeted outcomes of the toolkit.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section30-1757913911399364">
<title>Lesson 5</title>
<p>Leadership, project support from managers and project ownership by the community were recognized to be of great importance. Perceived acceptability and feasibility of the project in the local setting were acknowledged by the NGO stakeholders as important factors in determining whether a specific intervention was selected for implementation or adoption.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section31-1757913911399364">
<title>Lesson 6</title>
<p>Most successful projects were a result of a good match between what the evidence base suggested would be an appropriate type of intervention and what was seen as the most feasible option locally. Sensitivity to local settings was recognized as being crucial if projects were to be adopted and successfully implemented.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section32-1757913911399364">
<title>Lesson 7</title>
<p>Sufficient time, availability of resources and benefits are required for all partners to ensure active and meaningful participation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section33-1757913911399364">
<title>Lesson 8</title>
<p>Integration of the researchers and the researched as equal partners in every phase of the project was found to be a valued and important outcome in the relationship. This enabled every voice to be listened to, thus enabling full participation and a sense of belongingness that enhanced the consensus-building strategy. From the beginning of the project, the strategy was to clarify terms of partnership, employ NGO forum members’ knowledge and expertise whenever possible, and promote NGO forum members’ capacity on an ongoing basis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section34-1757913911399364">
<title>Lesson 9</title>
<p>Recognizing, respecting and embracing the different cultures of the stakeholders and partner NGOs is imperative for successful PAR efforts. Addressing diversity can foster inclusiveness and active participation of members. It was therefore important to reach out to as many NGO forum members as possible, with an emphasis being placed on the very small NGO organizations in order to mirror the various subgroups working with the hard-to-reach, marginalized communities that have historically been ‘invisible’.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section35-1757913911399364">
<title>Strength and limitations</title>
<p>The strength of the present study lies in its use of qualitative data to gather rich and detailed information about the experiences of key NGO stakeholders in tackling health inequalities. The use of semi-structured interviews allowed participants to convey their experiences in their own words, thereby improving the relevance, ownership and acceptability of the toolkit. The research was carried out in the very contexts that we as the researchers sought to benefit.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1757913911399364">22</xref></sup> Thus, the methodology allowed targeted groups such as the hard-to-reach and stakeholders to define their concerns and develop and implement solutions to local problems, using local-level resources, and take an active role in the research process.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section36-1757913911399364">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>The study had a number of limitations, including reliance on a small group of key stakeholders as a source of evidence. This was a convenient purposive sample that was homogenous and not randomly selected. This non-random selection may have influenced the content of the toolkit through self-selection bias. There was a lack of ethnic diversity in the participating stakeholders. In addition, the piloting process was limited by the project timelines; PAR requires adequate time to allow change to happen without participants feeling that it is imposed. Finally, the toolkit did not undergo a quality assurance test by agencies outside of the NGO forum due to lack of time.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section37-1757913911399364" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Difficult challenges such as costs, time, lack of resources and commitment may confront researchers engaging in PAR, yet this approach can greatly enrich the quality of research. By taking into account the lessons learned, PAR can be used to address genuine community issues and to ensure the use of methods and approaches that are culturally sensitive and that improve the validity and reliability of research findings. However, it is neither possible nor appropriate to use PAR in all research studies, but other research approaches may benefit from the challenges experienced and lessons learned from this research project. Future research and initiatives in this area should focus on ways to improve the toolkit, making it more relevant to a wider community, and on methods for evaluating the impact of the toolkit on practice.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<app-group>
<app id="app1-1757913911399364">
<title>Appendix</title>
<sec id="section38-1757913911399364">
<title>A1. Questionnaire: Health inequalities – Learning resource</title>
<list id="list2-1757913911399364" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>(i) How would you describe health inequalities?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(ii) Are you currently carrying out any work to address health inequalities? <bold>Yes/No</bold>. If <bold>yes</bold>, could you please give details</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(iii) Have you seen something that really works well in addressing health inequalities; i.e. a project/intervention/or a method recently? <bold>Yes/No</bold>. If <bold>yes</bold>, please give details (please list as many as you can)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(iv) Why did it work so well? Resources/people involved/location/other</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(v) Have you seen a project/intervention that really failed to work recently? <bold>Yes/No</bold>. If <bold>yes</bold>, please give details.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(vi) Why do you think it failed?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(vii) Where would you recommend finding good sources of information to help similar organizations like yours to address inequalities in health? Do you have any organizations or websites that you refer to regularly? <bold>Yes/No</bold>. If <bold>yes</bold>, please give details.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(viii) What would you advise if someone were to set up something similar to your project from the start?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(ix) What role do you think NGO/the Third Sector have in addressing health inequalities?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(x) What is your opinion about a practical toolkit to support the NGOs/Third Sector in tackling health inequalities?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(xi) Do you have any existing toolkits/similar resources in your organization that can be useful for people working on addressing health inequalities? <bold>Yes/No</bold>. If <bold>yes</bold>, please give details.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(xii) What would you like to see (i.e. content) in a toolkit? And what would be useful to you?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(xiii) What are your <bold>THREE TOP PRACTICAL TIPS</bold> to help others doing similar work to yourself?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(xiv) Do you need more/better ways to share information about what works and what does not work in addressing health inequalities? <bold>Yes/No</bold>. If <bold>yes</bold>, please give details of your expectations.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section39-1757913911399364">
<title>A2. Feedback form</title>
<sec id="section40-1757913911399364">
<title>Practical guide – Feedback form</title>
<list id="list3-1757913911399364" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>(i) How would you rate the value of the practical guide? <bold>Please circle a number</bold></p>
<p> Not at all valuable 1 2 3 4 5 extremely valuable</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(ii) Did you find the practical guide user friendly and adaptable to your current settings?</p>
<p> Agree Neutral Disagree</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(iii) Was the practical guide of manageable size?</p>
<p> Agree Neutral Disagree</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(iv) Was the guide written in a clear, simple language?</p>
<p> Agree Neutral Disagree</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(v) Did you find the practical guide relevant to your community setting?</p>
<p> Agree Neutral Disagree</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(vi) Did you think the title of the practical guide was appropriate?</p>
<p> Agree Neutral Disagree</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(vii) Did you think the content of the practical guide was inclusive?</p>
<p> Agree Neutral Disagree</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(viii) Did you think the practical guide was appropriate for your organization?</p>
<p> Agree Neutral Disagree</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(ix) In what context did you use the practical guide (e.g. planning a new project)?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(x) How would the practical guide be improved?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(xi) Any comments or recommendations for the future?</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</sec>
</app>
</app-group>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1757913911399364">
<label>i</label>
<p>The diversity of NGOs strains any simple definition. In wider usage, the term NGO is applied to any organization that is (i) self-governing and independent from government, (ii) not explicitly created for profit, and (iii) has meaningful voluntary content. The acronym NGO is used increasingly to cover ‘non-profits’, ‘charitable organizations’, the ‘third sector’, ‘voluntary organizations’, ‘communit-based organizations’ or ‘community-sector organizations’.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1757913911399364">3</xref></sup></p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1757913911399364">
<label>ii</label>
<p>The NGO forum was established as a consequence of the 1999 white paper <italic>Saving Lives: Our Healthier Nation</italic> in order to assist dialogue and engagement with NGOs in developing cross-government policy and practice relevant to health inequalities and wider public health. The NGO forum helps shape the direction of health inequalities policy and an understanding of the communities they serve, through advocacy and leadership.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1757913911399364">
<label>iii</label>
<p>A toolkit can be described as a ‘hands-on practical guide or checklist’. According to Conole and Oliver,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1757913911399364">23</xref></sup> they represent a mid-point between facilitated, uncritical development of resources and a deep argument with fundamental issues and theories.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1757913911399364">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>House of Commons</collab>. <source>Health Inequalities Third Report of Session 2008–9. Volume 1. Report No HC 286-1</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Health Committee of the House of Commons</publisher-name>, <year>2009</year></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1757913911399364">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>Department of Health</collab>. <source>Tackling Health Inequalities: Status Report on the Programme for Action</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department of Health</publisher-name>, <year>2005</year></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1757913911399364">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zafar Ullah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hyder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Government–NGO collaboration: The case of tuberculosis control in Bangladesh</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health Policy and Planning</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>155</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1757913911399364">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Popple</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Redmond</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Community development and the voluntary sector in the new millennium: The implications of the Third Way in the UK</article-title>. <source>Community Development Journal</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>400</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1757913911399364">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="gov">
<collab>Department for Communities and Local Government</collab>. <source>Third Sector Strategy for Communities and Local Government</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department for Communities and Local Government</publisher-name>, <year>2007</year>. <comment>Available at &lt;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/communities/pdf/324564.pdf">http://www.communities.gov.uk/documents/communities/pdf/324564.pdf</ext-link>&gt;</comment> <access-date>Last accessed 04/03/11</access-date></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1757913911399364">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bakewell</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sabbah</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>NGOs in Development: Evidence and the Policy Process</source>. <publisher-loc>INTRAC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The International NGO Training and Research Centre</publisher-name>, <year>2004</year></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1757913911399364">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rosser</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Bringing important research evidence into practice: Canadian developments</article-title>. <source>Journal of Family Practice</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>i38</fpage>–<lpage>i45</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1757913911399364">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ryton</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Little</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gilsenan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Step to it: A toolkit for evidence-based practice</article-title>. <source>Journal of Practice Development in Health Care</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>220</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1757913911399364">
<label>9</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hampshire</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>What is action research and can it promote change in primary care?</article-title> <source>Journal of Evaluation Clinical Practice</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>343</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1757913911399364">
<label>10</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Waterman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tillen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dickson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Koning</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Action research: A systematic review and guidance for assessment</article-title>. <source>Health Technology Assessment</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>5</volume>(<issue>23</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1757913911399364">
<label>11</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Doing Qualitative Research</source>. <edition>2nd Edn</edition>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage Publications</publisher-name>, <year>2005</year></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1757913911399364">
<label>12</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A general inductive approach for qualitative data analysis</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Auckland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>School of Population Health, University of Auckland</publisher-name>, <year>2004</year>. <comment>Available at &lt;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.health.auckland.ac.nz/hrmas.resources/qualdatanlysis.html">http://www.health.auckland.ac.nz/hrmas.resources/qualdatanlysis.html</ext-link>&gt;</comment> <access-date>Last accessed 04/03/11</access-date></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1757913911399364">
<label>13</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Flanagan</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>‘Reaching the hard to reach’ – Lessons learned from the voluntary and community sector. A qualitative study</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health Services Research</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>10</volume>(<issue>92</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1757913911399364">
<label>14</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Minkler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Ethical challenges for the ‘outside’ researcher in community-based participatory research</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health Education and Behaviour</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>684</fpage>–<lpage>701</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1757913911399364">
<label>15</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mercer</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Can public health researchers and agencies reconcile the push from the funding bodies and the pull from communities?</article-title> <source>American Journal of Public Health</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>91</volume>: <fpage>1926</fpage>–<lpage>1929</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1757913911399364">
<label>16</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Minkler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wallerstein</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Introduction to Community-Based Participatory Research for Health</source>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>, <year>2003</year></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1757913911399364">
<label>17</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lantz</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Viruell-Fuentes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Israel</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Softley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guzman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Can communities and academia work together on public health research? Evaluating results from a community-based participatory research partnership in Detroit</article-title>. <source>Journal of Urban Health: Bulletin of the New York Academy of Medicine</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>507</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1757913911399364">
<label>18</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berge</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mendenhall</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>William</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Using community-based participatory research (CBPR) to target health disparities in families</article-title>. <source>Journal of Family Relations</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>475</fpage>–<lpage>488</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1757913911399364">
<label>19</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nyden</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Academic incentives for faculty participation in community-based research</article-title>. <source>Journal of General Internal Medicine</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>576</fpage>–<lpage>585</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1757913911399364">
<label>20</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burhansstipanov</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Christopher</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schumacher</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Lessons learned from community-based participatory research in Indian Country</article-title>. <source>Cancer Control</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>12</volume>(<supplement>suppl 2</supplement>): <fpage>70</fpage>–<lpage>76</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1757913911399364">
<label>21</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Garwick</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Auger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Participatory action research: The Indian stories family project</article-title>. <source>Nursing Outlook</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>266</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1757913911399364">
<label>22</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Coghlan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Action research from the inside: Issues and challenges in doing action research in your own hospital</article-title>. <source>Journal of Advanced Nursing</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>674</fpage>–<lpage>682</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1757913911399364">
<label>23</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Conole</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Embedding theory into learning technology practice with toolkits</article-title>. <source>Journal of Interactive Media in Education</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>28</lpage></citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>