<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JFM</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjfm</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Feline Medicine and Surgery</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1098-612X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1532-2750</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1098612X12463010</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1098612X12463010</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Reports</subject></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Suspected muscarinic mushroom intoxication in a cat</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Herreria-Bustillo</surname><given-names>Vicente J</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1098612X12463010">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Saiz-Alvarez</surname><given-names>Rocio</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1098612X12463010">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Jasani</surname><given-names>Shailen</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1098612X12463010">2</xref>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1098612X12463010"><label>1</label>Vets Now Referrals Swindon, Swindon, UK</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1098612X12463010"><label>2</label>Vets Now Limited, Dunfermline, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1098612X12463010">Vicente J Herreria-Bustillo LV, Vets Now Referrals Swindon, Unit 10, Berkshire House, County Park, Shrivenham Road, Swindon, SN1 2NR, UK Email: <email>vincent.vet@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>160</fpage>
<lpage>162</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© ISFM and AAFP 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">International Society of Feline Medicine and American Association of Feline Practitioners</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>A 3-year-old domestic shorthair cat was witnessed ingesting mushrooms and developed signs of muscarine intoxication. After stabilisation and treatment with atropine the cat recovered well and was discharged from hospital in 2 days. This report describes the features and successful management of this unusual toxicosis in cats.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1098612X12463010" sec-type="case reports">
<title>Case Report</title>
<p>A 3-year-old, male neutered, domestic shorthair cat presented to the emergency service for an acute episode of dyspnoea, cyanosis, open-mouth breathing and drooling. In less than 30 mins following the witnessed ingestion of mushrooms, the cat had started drooling, and then vomited mushrooms and passed diarrhoea. This was followed minutes later by the onset of respiratory distress. No other significant history was reported. On examination of the major body systems (primary survey) significant abnormalities detected were moderate-to-severe bradycardia [heart rate (HR) 100 beats per min], poor quality pulses, tachypnoea [respiratory rate (RR) 92 breaths per min] with open-mouth breathing, bilateral pulmonary crackles, depressed mentation and severe bilateral miosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1098612X12463010">Figure 1</xref>). An emergency database was obtained consisting of manual packed cell volume (PCV), plasma total solids (TS), venous blood gases and electrolytes, and plasma biochemistry profile. The following significant findings were detected: PCV 59%, TS 10.2 g/l, glucose 14.5 mmol/l [reference interval (RI) 3.5–7.5 mmol/l], urea 15.5 mmol/l (RI 2.8–11 mmol/l) and creatinine 167 μmol/l (RI 0–190 µmol/l). Venous blood gases, electrolytes and liver transaminases (alanine aminotransferase and alkaline phosphatase) were within RIs. These findings were considered consistent with haemoconcentration and pre-renal azotaemia, most likely secondary to hypersalivation and gastrointestinal fluid loss. The mild hyperglycaemia was presumed to be ‘stress’-induced. Given the severity of the cat’s dyspnoea and associated crackles, empirical furosemide (Dimazon; Intervet) at a dose of 3 mg/kg was administered intramuscularly and the cat was then placed in an oxygen cage with close monitoring. After a few minutes breathing had improved sufficiently for a more comprehensive physical examination (secondary survey) to be completed on which no other significant abnormalities were detected. The history of mushroom ingestion and the associated clinical findings were considered suggestive of muscarinic intoxication. Atropine (Hameln Pharmaceuticals) was therefore given by intramuscular injection at a dose of 0.04 mg/kg, to which a positive response was witnessed within 30 mins. Repeated major systems examination revealed a HR of 200 beats per min, a RR of 40 breaths per min with mild residual crackles and improved mentation. Intravenous fluid therapy was started with Hartmann’s solution at 6 ml/kg/h. Some gastrointestinal decontamination had occurred via vomiting and it was not considered rational to attempt activated charcoal administration given the unpredictability of the cat’s clinical status going forward. The cat improved gradually without any further medication and was discharged 2 days following initial presentation.</p>
<fig id="fig1-1098612X12463010" position="float">
<label>Figure 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Cat showing severe miosis</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1098612X12463010-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Mushroom toxicity is uncommon in cats. The Veterinary Poisons Information Service in the UK has received 867 canine and only 57 feline enquiries relating to potential mushroom exposure over the last 10 years.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1098612X12463010">1</xref></sup> Similarly, the Animal Poison Control Center in the USA receives, on average, six feline reports annually.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1098612X12463010">2</xref></sup> The most common mushrooms involved in muscarine poisoning include the genera <italic>Inocybe</italic> and <italic>Clitocybe</italic>, although the genera <italic>Mycena, Boletus, Entoloma</italic> and <italic>Omphalotus</italic> can have significant muscarine levels.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1098612X12463010">2</xref></sup> Unfortunately, it was not possible to accurately identify the mushrooms ingested in this case. Correct morphological identification of mushrooms can be challenging and, if in doubt, it is recommended that a mycologist is consulted for complete identification using the fungal spores; samples should be stored wrapped in paper rather than plastic bags or containers, as the latter can result in sample deterioration due to high humidity. Muscarine is a muscarinic receptor agonist that produces postganglionic parasympathomimetic effects.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1098612X12463010">2</xref></sup> Signs of intoxication can occur rapidly (within 5–30 mins) and mostly within 2 h of ingestion, and may include one or more components of salivation, lacrimation, urination and diarrhoea (SLUD).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1098612X12463010">3</xref></sup> Other common clinical signs include bradycardia, hypotension, shock, dyspnoea and wheezing due to bronchoconstriction and increased respiratory secretions, abdominal pain, miosis, visual disturbance and rhinorrhoea. As a result, another, more comprehensive, acronym used is DUMBBELS (diarrhoea, urination, miosis, bronchorrhoea, bronchoconstriction, emesis, lacrimation, salivation).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1098612X12463010">3</xref></sup> The cat described in this case was presented with most of these signs, showing diarrhoea, emesis, salivation, miosis, and signs of bronchorrhoea and bronchoconstriction. The rapid onset of signs following witnessed mushroom ingestion also suggests muscarinic intoxication. Other possible aetiologies to consider in the differential diagnosis are exposures to organophosphates and carbamates.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1098612X12463010">2</xref></sup> These pesticides act by inhibiting acetylcholinesterase causing parasympathomimetic effects similar to muscarine intoxication; however, they also stimulate nicotinic receptors and cross the blood–brain barrier producing nicotinic signs, such as muscle tremors and seizures.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1098612X12463010">2</xref></sup> The recommended therapy for muscarine intoxication includes gastrointestinal decontamination, antidotal atropine administration, oxygen supplementation and supportive measures, such as fluid therapy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1098612X12463010">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1098612X12463010">3</xref></sup> Atropine competes with muscarine at the level of the receptors. Literature guidelines for atropine therapy vary considerably with respect to the dose and route of administration.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1098612X12463010">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1098612X12463010"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1098612X12463010">4</xref></sup> Doses reported for its use in muscarine intoxication vary between 0.04 mg/kg and 2 mg/kg.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1098612X12463010">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1098612X12463010">3</xref></sup> The dose used in this case was therefore the lowest recommended dose, but a satisfactory response was seen within 30 mins, which is similar to other published reports in small animals.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1098612X12463010">2</xref></sup> Most publications recommend giving part of the dose intravenously and part either subcutaneously or intramusculary.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1098612X12463010">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1098612X12463010"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1098612X12463010">4</xref></sup> In this case we decided to administer the full dose intramuscularly to avoid excessive handling in a dyspnoeic patient and the effect was satisfactory. A recommended clinical end-point to guide atropine therapy is the drying up of oral and respiratory secretions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1098612X12463010">3</xref></sup> It is recommended not to use the resolution of miosis for this purpose because by the time the pupils return to normal size most patients are likely to have received too much atropine.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1098612X12463010">3</xref></sup> Potential adverse effects of excessive atropinisation include tachycardia, hyperthermia, behavioural changes and gastrointestinal stasis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1098612X12463010">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1098612X12463010">4</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1098612X12463010">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>This report describes the features and successful management of suspected muscarinic mushroom intoxication in a cat, and shows that this unusual toxicosis can be managed successfully in this species. To our knowledge this is the first published report of suspected muscarinic mushroom intoxication in cats. The cat described in this case responded well to appropriate therapy and did not show any long-term effects, which is similar to other published reports in dogs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1098612X12463010">2</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors for the preparation of this case report.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Conflict of interest</label>
<p>The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest. This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p><bold>Accepted:</bold> 10 September 2012</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1098612X12463010">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="other"><collab>Veterinary Poisons Information Service</collab>. <article-title>Number of enquiries involving fungi in dogs and cats reported to the VPIS 2002–2011</article-title>. Unpublished report. <month>June</month> <year>2012</year>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>VPIS</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1098612X12463010">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Puschner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wegenast</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Mushroom poisoning cases in dogs and cats: diagnosis and treatment of hepatotoxic, neurotoxic, gastroenterotoxic, nephrotoxic, and muscarinic mushrooms</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin Small Anim</source> <year>2012</year>; <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>375</fpage>–<lpage>387</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1098612X12463010">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schonwald</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Mushrooms</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Dart</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed). <source>Medical toxicology</source>. <edition>3rd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lippincott Williams and Wilkins</publisher-name>, <year>2004</year>, pp <fpage>1719</fpage>–<lpage>1735</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1098612X12463010">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Plumb</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Plumb’s veterinary drug handbook</article-title>. <edition>7th ed</edition>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vin.com/doc/?id=4693777">http://www.vin.com/doc/?id=4693777</ext-link> (<year>2008</year>, <access-date>accessed 3 July 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref></ref-list>
</back>
</article>