<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JAH</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjah</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Aging Health</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Aging and Health</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0898-2643</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-6887</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0898264311421960</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0898264311421960</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Social Participation and Maintaining Recommended Waist Circumference</article-title>
<subtitle>Prospective Evidence From the English Longitudinal Study of Aging</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Kouvonen</surname><given-names>Anne</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0898264311421960">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Swift</surname><given-names>Judy Anne</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0898264311421960">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Stafford</surname><given-names>Mai</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0898264311421960">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>Tom</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0898264311421960">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Vahtera</surname><given-names>Jussi</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0898264311421960">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5-0898264311421960">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Väänänen</surname><given-names>Ari</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5-0898264311421960">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Heponiemi</surname><given-names>Tarja</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6-0898264311421960">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>De Vogli</surname><given-names>Roberto</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7-0898264311421960">7</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8-0898264311421960">8</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>Amanda</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0898264311421960">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kivimäki</surname><given-names>Mika</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5-0898264311421960">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8-0898264311421960">8</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9-0898264311421960">9</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0898264311421960"><label>1</label>Warsaw School of Social Sciences and Humanities, Wroclaw, Poland</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0898264311421960"><label>2</label>University of Nottingham, Nottingham, UK</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0898264311421960"><label>3</label>MRC Unit for Lifelong Health and Ageing, London, UK</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0898264311421960"><label>4</label>University of Turku and Turku University Hospital, Turku, Finland</aff>
<aff id="aff5-0898264311421960"><label>5</label>Finnish Institute of Occupational Health, Helsinki, Finland</aff>
<aff id="aff6-0898264311421960"><label>6</label>National Institute for Health and Welfare, Helsinki, Finland</aff>
<aff id="aff7-0898264311421960"><label>7</label>University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff8-0898264311421960"><label>8</label>University College London, London, UK</aff>
<aff id="aff9-0898264311421960"><label>9</label>University of Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0898264311421960">Anne Kouvonen, Warsaw School of Social Sciences and Humanities, Wroclaw Faculty, ul. Grunwaldzka 98, 50-357 Wroclaw, Poland Email: <email>anne.kouvonen@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>24</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>250</fpage>
<lpage>268</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© SAGE Publications 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p><bold>Objectives:</bold> To investigate whether older adults participating in social activities are more likely to maintain or achieve recommended waist circumference (WC) levels. <bold>Method:</bold> A total of 4,280 older adults who participated in Wave 2 (baseline) and Wave 4 (follow-up) of the English Longitudinal Study of Ageing. WC was measured by a nurse in both study waves. <bold>Results:</bold> Participation in education, arts, music groups, evening classes, and in charitable associations was associated with maintaining recommended WC only in those men whose WC was in the recommended range at baseline. Participation in social activities was not associated with achieving recommended WC in women or men with initially large waist. <bold>Discussion:</bold> Participation in cultural and charitable activities may help in maintaining a recommended level of WC in older men with WC originally in the recommended range.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>waist circumference</kwd>
<kwd>social participation</kwd>
<kwd>older adults</kwd>
<kwd>obesity</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0898264311421960" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Obesity levels have risen in all age groups in industrialised countries, but the prevalence of obesity is particularly high in older adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0898264311421960">Witham &amp; Avenell, 2010</xref>). According to the National Heart Forum, for example, the proportion of people who are obese is rising in the United Kingdom whereas the proportion of normal weight individuals in the United Kingdom is falling, and the percentage of those who are overweight remains relatively steady (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0898264311421960">Brown, Byatt, Marsh, &amp; McPherson, 2010</xref>). Much of the data on obesity is based on body mass index (BMI) but when considering obesity especially in older people, waist circumference (WC), a measure of abdominal obesity, may also be relevant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0898264311421960">Visscher et al., 2001</xref>). WC may have a role in physical health outcomes that is partially independent of BMI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0898264311421960">Testa et al., 2010</xref>), and a large waist is a strong anthropometric predictor of vascular events and diabetes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0898264311421960">Haslam, Sattar, &amp; Lean, 2006</xref>). In 2008, 44% of English women and 34% of men had a high-risk WC and the prevalence increased with age in both sexes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0898264311421960">NHS Information Centre, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>Although much of the research on the determinants of obesity has focused on behavioral (e.g., dietary patterns, physical activity) and biological factors (e.g., metabolic rate; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0898264311421960">Du, &amp; Feskens, 2010</xref>), more recently, aspects of the social environment that may shape these obesity-related behaviors and biology have gained attention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0898264311421960">Ali &amp; Lindström, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0898264311421960">Jenkins &amp; Fultz, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0898264311421960">Kamiya, Whelan, Timonen, &amp; Kenny, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0898264311421960">Poortinga, 2006</xref>). One hypothesis is that social participation, that is, taking part in social networks, groups and associations, and cultural and other social and civic activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0898264311421960">Kamiya et al., 2010</xref>), may help in maintaining a healthy weight by favourably influencing behavioural choices, coping resources, and even the functioning of biological regulatory systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0898264311421960">Everson-Rose &amp; Lewis, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0898264311421960">Gruenewald, Seeman, Ryff, Karlamangla, &amp; Singer, 2006</xref>). Although social participation has been suggested to decrease as people age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0898264311421960">Baum et al., 2000</xref>), participation in socially productive activities is likely to be most salient in later life when people are less involved with the activities of paid employment and child rearing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0898264311421960">McMunn, Nazroo, Wahrendorf, Breeze, &amp; Zaninotto, 2009</xref>). Therefore, it can be hypothesized that social participation is particularly beneficial in terms of maintaining healthy WC in cohorts of older adults.</p>
<p>Previous research has shown that regular participation in social and productive activities may be beneficial to older people’s health (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0898264311421960">Lennartsson &amp; Silverstein, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0898264311421960">Mendes de Leon, Glass, &amp; Berkman, 2003</xref>), but few studies have specifically examined effects of social participation on healthy body weight and the existing evidence is inconsistent including both positive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0898264311421960">Ali &amp; Lindström, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0898264311421960">Jenkins &amp; Fultz, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0898264311421960">Kamiya et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0898264311421960">Veenstra et al., 2005</xref>) and null findings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0898264311421960">Greiner, Li, Kawachi, Hunt, &amp; Ahluwalia, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0898264311421960">Moore, Daniel, Paquet, Dubé, &amp; Gauvin, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0898264311421960">Poortinga, 2006</xref>). Furthermore, in one study, greater social participation was associated with higher BMI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0898264311421960">Zettel-Watson &amp; Britton, 2008</xref>). Several factors related to study design and measurement may have contributed to these mixed findings. First, previous evidence comes mainly from cross-sectional studies but longitudinal research is needed to establish the temporal order between social participation and body weight. It would also be important to control for underlying chronic illnesses that may lead to weight loss or low body weight, and decreased participation in social activities. Second, many of the previous studies used self-reported height and weight, rather than clinical anthropometric measurements. In fact, with the exception of the study by Moore and colleagues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0898264311421960">Moore et al., 2009</xref>), previous studies have not assessed WC despite it being a useful indicator of fat mass especially in older age groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0898264311421960">Testa et al., 2010</xref>). Third, earlier studies have not differentiated between those with recommended WC at baseline and those with large WC. It has been shown that obesity spreads through social networks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0898264311421960">Christakis &amp; Fowler, 2007</xref>), and the effect of social participation may, therefore, depend on the prevailing health-related norms of the group the person is interacting with; these norms can be either health promoting or detrimental (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0898264311421960">Kawachi &amp; Berkman, 2001</xref>). It is possible that people with high levels of WC are more often members of groups consisting mainly of overweight people whereas the reverse could be true for those with WC within the recommended range.</p>
<p>To overcome these limitations, the present study used longitudinal data from the English Longitudinal Study of Ageing (ELSA) to examine the association between different types of social participation at baseline and maintaining or achieving recommended WC levels at follow-up in community-dwelling older adults.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0898264311421960" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section3-0898264311421960">
<title>Design and Participants</title>
<p>The ELSA is a panel study of people living in England aged 50+ years. The ELSA sample was drawn from households who participated in the Health Survey for England (HSE; an annual, nationally representative cross-sectional household survey) in 1998, 1999, or 2001 and who were born before March, 1952. Individuals were classified as core ELSA sample members at Wave 1 if they were included in the HSE and were aged 50 on April 1, 2002 when the first Wave of ELSA took place. ELSA participants are followed up every 2 years. Wave 2 (2004-2005) was the first wave that included a nurse visit and this was repeated in Wave 4 (2008-2009). Only participants with an interview in person were eligible for a nurse visit. Those who dropped out from Wave 1 to Wave 2 were more likely to be of lower SES, to have a longstanding limiting illness, and more likely to be non-White than the respondents to Wave 2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0898264311421960">Scholes, Taylor, Cheshire, Cox, &amp; Lessof, 2008</xref>). More detail on sampling and response rates for the ELSA are given elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0898264311421960">Banks et al., 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>The present analysis focused on data collected in Waves 2 (baseline) and 4 (2008-2009; follow-up). A total of 7,666 sample members took part in Wave 2, when WC was first measured. The 2,671 participants with missing data on WC at follow-up (i.e., at Wave 4) because they had died, dropped out, or did not have a recorded WC measurement at Wave 4, were excluded from the analysis. We additionally excluded 715 participants who had incomplete data in terms of social participation and/or covariates, leaving a total of 4,280 participants in the final analytic sample (2,373 women and 1,907 men). Compared to the included population, participants in the total baseline population (Wave 2 nurse data) were slightly older (mean age 64.9 in the final analytic sample vs. 66.7 in the baseline population) and had a lower mean WC (101.1 vs. 98.2 in men and 90.5 vs. 87.8 for women).</p>
<p>All participants provided informed consent separately for the interview and nurse’s visit. Data were accessed through the Economic and Social Data Service. Ethical approval for the ELSA study was obtained from the London Multicentre Research and Ethics Committee.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0898264311421960">
<title>Social Participation</title>
<p>Social participation was measured by asking respondents to indicate whether they were members of any type of organizations, clubs, or societies. The types of the listed activities included the following: (a) political party, trade union, or environmental group; (b) tenants’ or residents’ group or Neighbourhood Watch; (c) church or other religious group; (d) charitable association; (e) education, arts or music group, or evening class; (f) social club; and (g) sports group, gym, or exercise class; (h) other. Because of the diverse nature of the eighth category and because of the strong relationship between leisure-time physical activity and body weight, in the present analysis, only participation in the first six categories of activities was examined.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0898264311421960">
<title>Waist Circumference</title>
<p>WC, measured during the nurse visit at baseline and follow-up, was defined as the midpoint between the lower rib and the upper margin of the iliac crest. Two measurements were taken using a tape with an insertion buckle at one end. Circumference was recorded to the nearest even millimeter and if the two measurements differed by &gt;3 cm, then a third was taken. The mean values of the two valid measurements (the two that were the closest to each other, if there were three measurements) used in the analysis ranged between 61.3 and 171.6 cm at Wave 2. Cut-off points for recommended WC specific to older adults were employed; ≤ 97cm for men and ≤ 88 cm for women (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0898264311421960">Heim et al., 2010</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0898264311421960">
<title>Covariates</title>
<p>Several factors which have been associated with obesity or body weight (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0898264311421960">Kaplan, Huguet, Newsom, McFarland, &amp; Lindsay, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0898264311421960">Kimokoti et al., 2010</xref>) were included in the analyses. Covariates were measured at Wave 2. Data on sex, age, ethnicity (White vs. non-White), marital status, and socioeconomic status of the participants were obtained in the interview. Marital status was dichotomized into being married or living with a partner versus being single, separated, divorced, or widowed. Socioeconomic status (SES) was classified according to household wealth quintiles. Total nonpension household wealth was defined as the sum of financial worth, physical worth (such as business wealth, land, or jewelry), and housing wealth after deducting debts; it represents a better measure of the long-term economic status of older people than income (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0898264311421960">Demakakos, Nazroo, Breeze, &amp; Marmot, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>Participants were asked if they had ever smoked. Individuals who responded in the affirmative were asked whether or not they smoked at present. Participants who responded “yes” to both questions were classified as current smokers. This measure has been validated against saliva cotinine levels in the Health Survey for England (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0898264311421960">Erens &amp; Primatesta, 2001</xref>). The measure of physical activity was adapted from measures developed for the Whitehall II Study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0898264311421960">Singh-Manoux, Hillsdon, Brunner, &amp; Marmot, 2005</xref>). Participants were asked how often they took part in vigorous, moderate, or mild physical activity. Examples of each type of activity were provided. Participants were categorized as having high physical activity, moderate physical activity, low physical activity, or being sedentary.</p>
<p>Participants were asked if they had one or more illnesses, disabilities, or infirmities that had affected or could affect them for a prolonged period. Those who replied in the affirmative were asked if this condition limited their activities. Participants who replied “yes” to the second question were classified as suffering from a limiting long-standing illness.</p>
<p>The eight-item shortened version of the Centre for Epidemiologic Study Depression Scale (CES-D) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0898264311421960">Radloff, 1977</xref>) with <italic>yes/no</italic> response options was used to estimate the prevalence of depressive symptoms. In line with previous studies, those who reported four or more symptoms were classified as having depression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0898264311421960">Hamer, Molloy, de Oliveira, &amp; Demakakos, 2009</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0898264311421960">
<title>Statistical Analysis</title>
<p>Sex-stratified age-adjusted ANOVA models were applied to assess differences in means of WC at Wave 2 (baseline) by covariates. In prospective design, logistic regression was applied to determine whether social participation at baseline predicted maintaining or achieving WC in the recommended range at follow-up. Sex-stratified models adjusted for age, ethnicity, marital status, baseline WC, total wealth, longstanding limiting illness, depressive symptoms, smoking status, and physical activity.</p>
<p>The associations were analysed separately for those participants who were initially (at Wave 2) in the recommended WC category and for those who were initially in the larger waist category. In this way, the analyses investigated both maintaining recommended WC and achieving recommended WC.</p>
<p>As WC at Wave 4 was relatively skewed (skew = .544; <italic>SE</italic> = 0.056 and kurtosis = 1.244; <italic>SE</italic> = 112 for men; and skew = .494; <italic>SE</italic> = 0.05 and kurtosis = .382; <italic>SE</italic> = 0.100 for women, respectively), it was not considered to be appropriate for analysis as a continuous variable. Instead, we performed additional analyses using WC deciles. WC at Wave 2 and WC at Wave 4 were first divided into deciles (separately for women and men) and the Wave 2 WC deciles were then subtracted from the Wave 4 WC deciles to assess change in WC. Again, the analyses were stratified by Wave 2 WC groups (i.e., those with a recommended level of WC versus those with a high WC).</p>
<p>All analyses were carried out using PASW Statistics 18 (SPSS Inc, Chicago, Illinois).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0898264311421960" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The mean age of the 4,280 participants (2,373 women) at baseline was 64.9 years (<italic>SD</italic> = 8.67; range 52 to 90+). <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0898264311421960">Table 1</xref> shows baseline characteristics of the participants and the age-adjusted means of WC at baseline by sex. The mean WC was above the recommended range in both men and women; 101.1 cm (<italic>SD</italic> = 10.7; range 68.6 to 143.7) in men and 90.5 cm (<italic>SD</italic> = 12.3; range 61.3 to 47.8) in women. Lower SES (measured as total wealth), having a limiting longstanding illness, reporting depressive symptoms and low physical activity were associated with a higher WC (all <italic>p</italic> values ≤ .05). The most common types of social participation among men were attending social clubs (23.6% of the participants) and tenants’ groups or Neighbourhood Watch (23.6%). Among women, the most common types of social participation were church or other religious group (27.5%) and charitable associations (21.3%). In men there were no significant differences in age-adjusted means of baseline WC between different types of participation. In women, participation in other types of organizations than charitable associations and social clubs was associated with a slightly lower age-adjusted mean WC at baseline.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0898264311421960" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Characteristics of Included Participants and Age-Adjusted Means of Waist Circumference (WC) by Study Variables at Baseline (Wave 2)</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0898264311421960" xlink:href="10.1177_0898264311421960-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Men</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Women</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center"><italic>n</italic> (%)</th>
<th align="center">Mean WC (<italic>SE</italic>)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>n</italic> (%)</th>
<th align="center">Mean WC (<italic>SE</italic>)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>All</td>
<td>1,907 (44.6)</td>
<td>101.1 (0.3)</td>
<td>2,373 (55.4)</td>
<td>90.5 (0.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Ethnicity</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> White</td>
<td>1,881 (98.6)</td>
<td>101.1 (0.3)</td>
<td>2,350 (99.0)</td>
<td>90.5 (0.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Non-White</td>
<td>26 (1.4)</td>
<td>102.4 (2.1)</td>
<td>23 (1.0)</td>
<td>90.4 (2.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> = .6</td>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> = .9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Marital status</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Married or cohabiting</td>
<td>1,569 (82.2)</td>
<td>101.3 (0.3)</td>
<td>1,505 (63.4)</td>
<td>90.2 (0.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>338 (17.8)</td>
<td>100.3 (0.6)</td>
<td>868 (36.6)</td>
<td>90.9 (0.4)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> = .1</td>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> = .2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Household wealth</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Q1 (Lowest quintile)</td>
<td>219 (11.5)</td>
<td>103.4 (0.7)</td>
<td>371 (15.6)</td>
<td>94.1 (0.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Q2</td>
<td>317 (16.6)</td>
<td>102.6 (0.6)</td>
<td>432 (18.2)</td>
<td>91.8 (0.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Q3</td>
<td>382 (20.0)</td>
<td>101.3 (0.6)</td>
<td>475 (20.0)</td>
<td>91.1 (0.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Q4</td>
<td>476 (25.0)</td>
<td>100.4 (0.5)</td>
<td>547 (23.1)</td>
<td>89.6 (0.5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Q5 (Highest quintile)</td>
<td>513 (26.9)</td>
<td>99.8 (0.5)</td>
<td>548 (23.1)</td>
<td>87.4 (0.5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> &lt; .001</td>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> &lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Limiting longstanding illness</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No</td>
<td>1,396 (73.2)</td>
<td>100.2 (0.3)</td>
<td>1,605 (67.6)</td>
<td>88.8 (0.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yes</td>
<td>511 (26.8)</td>
<td>103.6 (0.5)</td>
<td>768 (32.4)</td>
<td>93.9 (0.4)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> &lt; .001</td>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> &lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Depressive symptoms</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No</td>
<td>1,743 (91.4)</td>
<td>100.9 (0.3)</td>
<td>2,018 (85.0)</td>
<td>90.2 (0.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yes</td>
<td>164 (8.6)</td>
<td>103.6 (0.9)</td>
<td>355 (15.0)</td>
<td>91.7 (0.7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> = .002</td>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> = .013</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Smoking status</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No</td>
<td>1,659 (87.0)</td>
<td>101.2 (0.3)</td>
<td>2,089 (88.0)</td>
<td>90.4 (0.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Current</td>
<td>248 (13.0)</td>
<td>101.0 (0.7)</td>
<td>284 (12.0)</td>
<td>90.9 (0.7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> = .8</td>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> = .6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Physical activity level</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> High</td>
<td>510 (26.7)</td>
<td>98.8 (0.5)</td>
<td>452 (19.1)</td>
<td>87.2 (0.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Moderate</td>
<td>1,069 (56.1)</td>
<td>101.2 (0.3)</td>
<td>1,301 (54.8)</td>
<td>89.7 (0.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Low</td>
<td>293 (15.4)</td>
<td>104.5 (0.6)</td>
<td>573 (24.1)</td>
<td>94.3 (0.5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Sedentary</td>
<td>35 (1.8)</td>
<td>106.8 (1.8)</td>
<td>47 (2.0)</td>
<td>96.5 (1.8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> &lt; .001</td>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> &lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Membership in organizations</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"> Political party, trade union or environmental group</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>   No</td>
<td>1,558 (81.7)</td>
<td>101.2 (0.3)</td>
<td>2,067 (87.1)</td>
<td>90.7 (0.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>   Yes</td>
<td>349 (18.3)</td>
<td>100.8 (0.6)</td>
<td>306 (12.9)</td>
<td>88.9 (0.7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> = .6</td>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> = .015</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"> Tenants’ or residents’ group or Neighbourhood Watch</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>   No</td>
<td>1,456 (76.4)</td>
<td>101.3 (0.3)</td>
<td>1,874 (79.0)</td>
<td>90.9 (0.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>   Yes</td>
<td>451 (23.6)</td>
<td>100.7 (0.5)</td>
<td>499 (21.0)</td>
<td>89.0 (0.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> = .3</td>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> = .003</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"> Church or other religious group</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>   No</td>
<td>1,566 (82.1)</td>
<td>101.1 (0.3)</td>
<td>1,720 (72.5)</td>
<td>90.8 (0.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>   Yes</td>
<td>341 (17.9)</td>
<td>101.3 (0.6)</td>
<td>653 (27.5)</td>
<td>89.6 (0.5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> = .7</td>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> = .04</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"> Charitable association</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>   No</td>
<td>1,546 (81.1)</td>
<td>101.3 (0.3)</td>
<td>1,867 (78.7)</td>
<td>90.7 (0.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>   Yes</td>
<td>361 (18.9)</td>
<td>100.3 (0.6)</td>
<td>506 (21.3)</td>
<td>89.6 (0.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> = .1</td>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> = .07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"> Education, arts or music group, or evening class</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>   No</td>
<td>1,684 (88.3)</td>
<td>101.3 (0.3)</td>
<td>1,930 (81.3)</td>
<td>91.0 (0.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>   Yes</td>
<td>223 (11.7)</td>
<td>100.1 (0.7)</td>
<td>443 (18.7)</td>
<td>88.2 (0.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> = .1</td>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> &lt; .001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"> Social club</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>   No</td>
<td>1,456 (76.4)</td>
<td>101.0 (0.3)</td>
<td>1,920 (80.9)</td>
<td>90.4 (0.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>   Yes</td>
<td>451 (23.6)</td>
<td>101.7 (0.5)</td>
<td>453 (19.1)</td>
<td>91.0 (0.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> = .3</td>
<td/>
<td><italic>p</italic> = .4</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0898264311421960">
<p><italic>Note</italic>. Only participants with no missing data in any of the variables were included. <italic>SE</italic>, standard error. <italic>p</italic> values from ANOVA models.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0898264311421960">Table 2</xref> displays the results from logistic regression analyses of the associations between social participation at baseline and the maintaining recommended WC at follow-up. After adjustment for age, ethnicity, marital status, baseline WC, total household wealth, long-term limiting illness, depression, smoking, and physical activity, participation in education, arts or music groups, or evening classes (odds ratio = 2.48, 95% confidence interval = [1.35, 4.57]), and in charitable associations (odds ratio = 1.95, 95% confidence interval = [1.19, 3.21]) were associated with an increased likelihood of maintaining recommended WC in those men whose WC was initially in the recommended range. In contrast, in those with initially large WC, social participation was not associated with achieving recommended levels of WC at follow-up. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0898264311421960">Table 2</xref> also shows that there were no prospective associations between social participation and maintaining WC in the recommended range in women.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0898264311421960" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Associations Between Social Participation at Baseline (Wave 2) and Maintaining or Achieving Recommended Waist Circumference<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0898264311421960">a</xref></sup> (WC) at Follow-Up (Wave 4)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0898264311421960">b</xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0898264311421960" xlink:href="10.1177_0898264311421960-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Men</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Women</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Those with WC ≤ 97cm at Wave 2</th>
<th align="center">Those with WC &gt; 97cm at Wave 2</th>
<th align="center">Those with WC ≤ 88cm at Wave 2</th>
<th align="center">Those with WC &gt; 88cm at Wave 2</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">OR [95% CI]</th>
<th align="center">OR [95% CI]</th>
<th align="center">OR [95% CI]</th>
<th align="center">OR [95% CI]</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">(<italic>n</italic> = 686)</th>
<th align="center">(<italic>n</italic> = 1,221)</th>
<th align="center">(<italic>n</italic> = 1,059)</th>
<th align="center">(<italic>n</italic> = 1,314)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="5">Type of participation</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Political party, trade union or environmental group</td>
<td>1.20 [0.79, 1.96]</td>
<td>0.56 [0.29, 1.09]</td>
<td>1.23 [0.75, 2.03]</td>
<td>0.54 [0.26, 1.12]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Tenants’ or residents’ group or Neighbourhood Watch</td>
<td>1.41 [0.90, 2.21]</td>
<td>0.87 [0.49, 1.44]</td>
<td>1.00 [0.98, 1.02]</td>
<td>1.08 [0.67, 1.76]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Church or other religious group</td>
<td>1.59 [0.94, 2.67]</td>
<td>1.17 [0.68, 2.01]</td>
<td>1.01 [0.69, 1.46]</td>
<td>1.35 [0.87, 2.11]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Charitable association</td>
<td>1.95 [1.19, 3.21]</td>
<td>0.68 [0.36, 1.26]</td>
<td>0.71 [0.48, 1.04]</td>
<td>1.02 [0.62, 1.69]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Education, arts or music group or evening class</td>
<td>2.48 [1.35, 4.57]</td>
<td>0.91 [0.45, 1.85]</td>
<td>0.90 [0.60, 1.36]</td>
<td>0.99 [0.52, 1.57]</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Social club</td>
<td>0.93 [0.60, 1.47]</td>
<td>1.03 [0.60, 1.75]</td>
<td>1.00 [0.66, 1.53]</td>
<td>0.95 [0.57, 1.57]</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0898264311421960">
<p><italic>Note.</italic> Estimates are odds ratios (95% CI).</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0898264311421960">
<label>a.</label>
<p>WC ≤ 97cm for men and WC ≤ 88cm for women.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-0898264311421960">
<label>b.</label>
<p>Adjusted for age, ethnicity, marital status, baseline WC, total wealth, limiting longstanding illness, depressive symptoms, smoking, and physical activity.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0898264311421960">Table 3</xref> presents the results from linear regression analyses using change in WC deciles as an outcome. The results were very similar to those obtained with a binary measurement of WC as an outcome. After adjustment for age, ethnicity, marital status, total household wealth, long-term limiting illness, depression, smoking, and physical activity, participation in education, arts or music groups, or evening classes (β = –.103, <italic>p</italic> = .008), in charitable associations (β = –.091, <italic>p</italic> = .02), and in tenants’ or residents’ groups or Neighbourhood Watch (β = –.088, <italic>p</italic> = .02) were all negatively associated with a WC increase during the follow-up in those men whose WC was initially in the recommended range. There were no associations between social participation and WC increase in women or in those men with initially large WC.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0898264311421960" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Associations Between Social Participation at Baseline (Wave 2) and the Difference Between Waist Circumference (WC) at Baseline and at Follow-Up (Wave 4)<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0898264311421960">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-0898264311421960">b</xref></sup>; Analysis Stratified by Baseline WC</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0898264311421960" xlink:href="10.1177_0898264311421960-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Men</th>
<th align="center" colspan="4">Women</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Those with WC ≤ 97cm at Wave 2 (<italic>n</italic> = 686)</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Those with WC &gt; 97cm at Wave 2 (<italic>n</italic> = 1,221)</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Those with WC ≤ 88cm at Wave 2 (<italic>n</italic> = 1,059)</th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Those with WC &gt; 88cm at Wave 2 (<italic>n</italic> = 1,314)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">β</th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
<th align="center">β</th>
<th align="center"><italic>P</italic></th>
<th align="center">β</th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
<th align="center">β</th>
<th align="center"><italic>p</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="9">Type of participation</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Political party, trade union or environmental group</td>
<td>−.018</td>
<td>.6</td>
<td>.003</td>
<td>.9</td>
<td>.009</td>
<td>.8</td>
<td>.053</td>
<td>.06</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Tenants’ or residents’ group or Neighbourhood Watch</td>
<td>−.088</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>−.027</td>
<td>.4</td>
<td>.031</td>
<td>.3</td>
<td>.030</td>
<td>.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Church or other religious group</td>
<td>−.064</td>
<td>.1</td>
<td>.020</td>
<td>.5</td>
<td>−.043</td>
<td>.2</td>
<td>−.014</td>
<td>.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Charitable association</td>
<td>−.091</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>.047</td>
<td>.2</td>
<td>.060</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>.042</td>
<td>.1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Education, arts or music group or evening class</td>
<td>−.103</td>
<td>.008</td>
<td>.020</td>
<td>.5</td>
<td>.047</td>
<td>.1</td>
<td>.030</td>
<td>.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Social club</td>
<td>.035</td>
<td>.4</td>
<td>−.009</td>
<td>.8</td>
<td>−.011</td>
<td>.7</td>
<td>−.002</td>
<td>.9</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn5-0898264311421960">
<label>a.</label>
<p>WC deciles at baseline subtracted from WC deciles at follow-up.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn6-0898264311421960">
<label>b.</label>
<p>Adjusted for age, ethnicity, marital status, total wealth, limiting longstanding illness, depressive symptoms, smoking, and physical activity.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0898264311421960" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In this prospective 4-year follow-up study of people aged 52+ years, social participation in education, arts or music groups, or evening classes, and in charitable associations was associated with maintaining recommended WC only among men who were at recommended WC levels at baseline. In contrast, social participation was not associated with achieving a recommended WC at follow-up among those men who initially had a large waist. For women, there was no clear evidence to suggest that social participation is associated with maintaining or achieving recommended WC.</p>
<p>There are several plausible pathways by which social participation can exert their influence on WC. First, social participation may alleviate stress and affect WC through physiologic pathways including hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis response, immune system function, and allostatic load (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0898264311421960">Berkman, Glass, Brissette, &amp; Seeman, 2000</xref>). It has been further proposed, for example, that cultural stimulation, which can derive from participation in arts and cultural associations, may have specific effects on physical and mental health, possibly via psychoneuroimmunological mechanisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0898264311421960">Johansson, Konlaan, &amp; Bygren, 2001</xref>). Indeed, earlier research has shown that attendance at certain kinds of cultural events (e.g., visiting the cinema, concerts, museums, or art exhibitions) is associated with better health and longevity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0898264311421960">Konlaan, Bygren, &amp; Johansson, 2000</xref>).</p>
<p>Second, social participation may also improve psychological well-being (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0898264311421960">Kiely &amp; Flacker, 2003</xref>). Meaningful social roles in society can promote a sense of self-efficacy and self-esteem, and enhance social support; these factors have been linked to important health outcomes in later life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0898264311421960">Glass, Mendes de Leon, Marottoli, &amp; Berkman, 1999</xref>). Social participation can define and reinforce meaningful social roles which in turn, may provide a sense of value, attachment and belonging (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0898264311421960">Berkman et al., 2000</xref>). In contrast, low participation may indicate loneliness and social isolation, which have both been linked to depression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0898264311421960">Cacioppo, Hawkley, &amp; Thisted, 2010</xref>) and adverse health behaviors, such as low physical activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0898264311421960">Hawkley, Thisted, &amp; Cacioppo, 2009</xref>). However, in the present study an adjustment for physical activity had little effect on estimates, suggesting that the association between social participation and recommended WC in men whose WC levels were initially in the recommended range may primarily be explained by other mechanisms.</p>
<p>Third, social participation may promote more rapid diffusion of health information, increase access to local services and amenities, and promote maintenance of healthy behavioral norms where they exist (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0898264311421960">Kawachi &amp; Berkman, 2001</xref>), such as norms of healthy eating and physical activity. It is possible that healthy behavioral norms commonly prevail in charitable associations, and in education, arts or music groups, and evening classes. This may be connected to the fact that people from higher educational background and from higher SES groups more commonly participate in these types of activities.</p>
<p>In this study, there was no prospective association between social participation and maintaining recommended WC in women. However, it has been suggested that women have higher participation in informal social activities such as visiting/visited by family and friends (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0898264311421960">Baum et al., 2000</xref>). It is possible that in terms of maintaining healthy weight, these informal networks which were not examined in this study, are more important for women.</p>
<sec id="section10-0898264311421960">
<title>Strengths and Limitations</title>
<p>The nationally representative nature of the ELSA study and its rigorous design strengthen the present study. The large data allowed sufficient statistical power to examine associations separately for men and women and to make comparisons between those with WC initially in the recommended range and those with initially large WC. Moreover, unlike earlier studies which have often measured only self-reported height and weight, this study used objectively measured WC as an outcome. In addition, the study differentiates between different forms of participation to assess the specific influence of each form on maintaining or achieving recommended WC levels. In terms of health promotion, this may provide greater precision in thinking about how best to intervene on social participation to influence obesity rates.</p>
<p>However, the present results should be considered in light of several limitations; some of which are unavoidable in all long-term prospective studies on health in older adults and some of which are more specific to the present study. First, even though the sample is otherwise nationally representative, with regards to the ethnic composition, the ELSA population is very homogeneous. There are two main reasons why this could be so. First, ethnic minorities in England tend to be younger, reflecting the timing of and the age at past migration. In addition, people who do not speak English were excluded from the HSE sample and, as a result, are virtually absent from ELSA.</p>
<p>Second, a number of individuals died between the two study Waves or were lost to follow-up. The issue of selective survival and selective attrition is common in longitudinal studies in older adults and may lead to the under or overestimation of the true association. However, any differences between the baseline population and the final analytic sample were small, suggesting that selective retention is an unlikely source of major bias in the present study.</p>
<p>Third, the current measure of social participation was relatively crude as it only assessed whether the participant was a member of a particular type of organization or not. Therefore, the frequency, intensity, and level of participation in each type of activity are not known. Moreover, only the types of organizations the participants were members of but not the actual number of organizations was measured. For example, it is possible that some participants were members of several different charitable associations or educational groups and this was not reflected in the measure.</p>
<p>Fourth, the measured social activities vary in the extent to which they are more social or physical in nature. Many of the activities that were assessed also potentially involve some physical activity; it is thus possible that physical activity component partially accounts for the association between social participation and WC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0898264311421960">Verkleij, Scheele, &amp; van der Wouden, 2009</xref>). However, the association between participation in charitable associations, and education, arts or music groups, or evening classes, and recommended WC in men remained robust after adjustment for physical activity although the possibility of measurement error remains when using self-reported physical activity measures.</p>
<p>Fifth, the analyses were controlled for the possible confounding and mediating effects of baseline WC, health behaviors, depression, longstanding limiting illness, and sociodemographic variables; however, unmeasured factors such as diet or genetic differences might have influenced the results. Furthermore, any study of the association between social participation and weight management is also complicated by the possibility of reciprocal causation, that is, a large WC may also reduce social participation. Obesity often carries a stigma that negatively affects social, emotional, and psychological functioning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0898264311421960">Puhl &amp; Heuer, 2010</xref>). There is some evidence that this obesity stigma and negative self-concepts related to physical appearance may work as a leisure constraint (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0898264311421960">Lewis &amp; Van Puymhroeck, 2008</xref>). In addition, morbidly obese individuals can be limited in their physical capability to participate in activities. In particular, obesity has been found to be a risk factor for reporting homebound status among community-dwelling older persons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0898264311421960">Jensen et al., 2006</xref>). Reverse causality cannot be fully discounted. However, taking into account baseline WC provides evidence that the results are not fully explained by reverse causality.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0898264311421960">
<title>Implications</title>
<p>In the United Kingdom, the age group with the highest proportion of overweight or obese people is the group aged 55 to 74 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0898264311421960">Brown et al., 2010</xref>). In general, participants most readily recruited to traditional exercise interventions tend to be highly motivated, healthier, and from higher SES groups, and adherence to standard exercise programs quickly drops off (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0898264311421960">Fried et al., 2004</xref>). The model of individual-level intervention focusing on advocating healthy diet and exercise has had limited success (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0898264311421960">Hill, Wyatt, Reed, Peters, 2003</xref>). New methods are needed to reach older adults—especially those who might not otherwise engage in health-promotion programs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0898264311421960">Fried et al., 2004</xref>). The present results suggest that aspects of social participation may be a potential additional component to be integrated in interventions designed to prevent weight gain in older men with WC in the recommended range. However, the results should be interpreted with caution as the role of social participation for weight loss and among women is unclear and not proven yet and the observed associations may not be causal in nature. Moreover, it is important to keep in mind that social participation works in the wider context of health-related circumstances, such as income inequality, which are not easily amenable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0898264311421960">Pickett, Kelly, Brunner, Lobstein, &amp; Wilkinson, 2005</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p>The data were made available through the UK Data Archive. ELSA was developed by a team of researchers based at University College of London, the National Centre for Social Research and the Institute for Fiscal Studies. The data were collected by the National Centre for Social Research. The developers and funders of ELSA and the Archive do not bear any responsibility for the analyses or interpretations presented here.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>The authors disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: The funding for ELSA is provided by the National Institute of Aging in the United States, and a consortium of UK Government departments coordinated by the Office for National Statistics. AK and TC were supported by a grant from the Economic and Social Research Council (ESRC; RES-000-22-3489). TC is supported by grants from the Health and Safety Executive (HSE), UK; Sheffield Hallam University, UK; Yorkshire &amp; Humberside SHA, UK, Babcock International Group plc., and the European Agency for Health and Safety at Work. RDV is partially supported by the Economic and Social Research Council (ESRC). JV and MK are supported by the Academy of Finland (projects 124322, 124271, and 132944). MK is also supported by the EU New OSH ERA Research Programme, the BUPA Foundation, UK, and the National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute (R01 HL036310-20A2) and the National Institute on Aging, NIH, USA (R01AG034454). AV is supported by the Finnish Work Environment Fund (project 109395) and the Academy of Finland (project 128089). TH is supported by the Finnish Work Environment Fund (project 107154) and the Academy of Finland (project 128002). AG is supported by the National Institute of Health Research Service Delivery Organisation Programme, UK, and Babcock International Group plc. The researchers are all independent of the funders.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lindström</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Socioeconomic, psychosocial, behavioural, and psychological determinants of BMI among young women: differing patterns for underweight and overweight/obesity</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Public Health</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>325</fpage>-<lpage>331</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lessof</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nazroo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stafford</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Steptoe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.). (<year>2010</year>). <source>Financial circumstances, health and well-being of the older population in England: The 2008 English Longitudinal Study of Ageing (Wave 4)</source>. <publisher-name>Institute for Fiscal Studies</publisher-name>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ifs.org.uk/elsa/report10/elsa_w4-1.pdf">http://www.ifs.org.uk/elsa/report10/elsa_w4-1.pdf</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baum</surname><given-names>F. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Modra</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Epidemiology of participation: an Australian community study</article-title>. <source>Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health</source>, <volume>54</volume>, <fpage>414</fpage>-<lpage>423</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berkman</surname><given-names>L. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brissette</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seeman</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>From social integration to health: Durkheim in the new millennium</article-title>. <source>Social Science &amp; Medicine</source>, <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>843</fpage>-<lpage>857</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Byatt</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McPherson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>A prediction of obesity trends for adults and their associated diseases. Analysis from the Health Survey for England 1993-2007</source>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nhfshare.heartforum.org.uk/RMAssets/NHFreports/NHF_adultobese_short_170210.pdf">http://nhfshare.heartforum.org.uk/RMAssets/NHFreports/NHF_adultobese_short_170210.pdf</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cacioppo</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hawkley</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thisted</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Perceived social isolation makes me sad: 5-year cross-lagged analyses of loneliness and depressive symptomatology in the Chicago Health, Aging, and Social Relations Study</article-title>. <source>Psychology and Aging</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>453</fpage>-<lpage>463</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Christakis</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The spread of obesity in a large social network over 32 years</article-title>. <source>New England Journal of Medicine</source>, <volume>357</volume>, <fpage>370</fpage>-<lpage>379</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Demakakos</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nazroo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Breeze</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marmot</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Socioeconomic status and health: The role of subjective social status</article-title>. <source>Social Science &amp; Medicine</source>, <volume>67</volume>, <fpage>330</fpage>-<lpage>340</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feskens</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Dietary determinants of obesity</article-title>. <source>Acta Cardiologica</source>, <volume>65</volume>, <fpage>377</fpage>-<lpage>386</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Erens</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Primatesta</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Health Survey for England 2000: Cardiovascular disease</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stationery Office</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Everson-Rose</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>T. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Psychosocial factors and cardiovascular diseases</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Public Health</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>469</fpage>-<lpage>500</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fried</surname><given-names>L. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frick</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Zeger</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>A social model for health promotion for an aging population: initial evidence on the experience corps model</article-title>. <source>Journal of Urban Health</source>, <volume>81</volume>, <fpage>64</fpage>-<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mendes de Leon</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marottoli</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berkman</surname><given-names>L. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Population based study of social and productive activities as predictors of survival among elderly Americans</article-title>. <source>British Medical Journal</source>, <volume>319</volume>, <fpage>478</fpage>-<lpage>483</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Greiner</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kawachi</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahluwalia</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The relationships of social participation and community ratings to health and health behaviors in areas with high and low population density</article-title>. <source>Social Science &amp; Medicine</source>, <volume>59</volume>, <fpage>2303</fpage>-<lpage>2312</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gruenewald</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seeman</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ryff</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Karlamangla</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Combinations of biomarkers predictive of later life mortality</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences USA</source>, <volume>103</volume>, <fpage>14158</fpage>-<lpage>14163</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Molloy</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Demakakos</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Leisure time physical activity, risk of depressive symptoms, and inflammatory mediators: The English Longitudinal Study of Ageing</article-title>. <source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>1050</fpage>-<lpage>1055</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haslam</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sattar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lean</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>ABC of obesity. Obesity—time to wake up</article-title>. <source>British Medical Journal</source>, <volume>333</volume>, <fpage>640</fpage>-<lpage>642</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hawkley</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thisted</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cacioppo</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Loneliness predicts reduced physical activity: Cross-sectional &amp; longitudinal analyses</article-title>. <source>Health Psychology</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>354</fpage>-<lpage>363</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heim</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Snijder</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heymans</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deeg</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seidell</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Exploring cut-off values for large waist circumference in older adults: A new methodological approach</article-title>. <source>Journal of Nutrition, Health &amp; Aging</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>272</fpage>-<lpage>277</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>J. O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wyatt</surname><given-names>H. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>G. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Obesity and the environment: Where do we go from here?</article-title> <source>Science</source>, <volume>299</volume>, <fpage>853</fpage>-<lpage>855</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fultz</surname><given-names>N. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The relationship of older adults’ activities and body mass index</article-title>. <source>Journal of Aging and Health</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>217</fpage>-<lpage>234</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Callahan</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Still</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dupont</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Obesity is a risk factor for reporting homebound status among community-dwelling older persons</article-title>. <source>Obesity (Silver Spring)</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>509</fpage>-<lpage>517</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Konlaan</surname><given-names>B. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bygren</surname><given-names>L. O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Sustaining habits of attending cultural events and maintenance of health: A longitudinal study</article-title>. <source>Health Promotion International</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>229</fpage>-<lpage>234</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kamiya</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Timonen</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kenny</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The differential impact of subjective and objective aspects of social engagement on cardiovascular risk factors</article-title>. <source>BMC Geriatrics</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>81</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huguet</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newsom</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McFarland</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lindsay</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Prevalence and correlates of overweight and obesity among older adults: Findings from the Canadian National Population Health Survey</article-title>. <source>Journals of Gerontology Series A: Biological Sciences and Medical Sciences</source>, <volume>58</volume>, <fpage>1018</fpage>-<lpage>1030</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kawachi</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berkman</surname><given-names>L. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Social ties and mental health</article-title>. <source>Journal of Urban Health</source>, <volume>78</volume>, <fpage>458</fpage>-<lpage>467</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kiely</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Flacker</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The protective effect of social engagement on 1-year mortality in a long-stay nursing home population</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Epidemiology</source>, <volume>56</volume>, <fpage>472</fpage>-<lpage>478</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kimokoti</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Newby</surname><given-names>P. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gona</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jasuja</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pencina</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Millen</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Diet quality, physical activity, smoking status, and weight fluctuation are associated with weight change in women and men</article-title>. <source>Journal of Nutrition</source>, <volume>140</volume>, <fpage>1287</fpage>-<lpage>1293</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Konlaan</surname><given-names>B. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bygren</surname><given-names>L. O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Visiting the cinema, concerts, museums or art exhibitions as determinant of survival: a Swedish fourteen-year cohort follow-up</article-title>. <source>Scandinavian Journal of Public Health</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>174</fpage>-<lpage>178</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lennartsson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Silverstein</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Does engagement with life enhance survival of elderly people in Sweden? The role of social and leisure activities</article-title>. <source>Journal of Gerontology: Psychological Sciences and Social Sciences</source>, <volume>56</volume>, <fpage>S335</fpage>-<lpage>S342</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Puymhroeck</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Obesity-stigma as a multifaceted constraint to leisure</article-title>. <source>Journal of Leisure Research</source>, <volume>40</volume>, <fpage>574</fpage>-<lpage>588</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McMunn</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nazroo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wahrendorf</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Breeze</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zaninotto</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Participation in socially-productive activities, reciprocity and wellbeing in later life: Baseline results in England</article-title>. <source>Ageing &amp; Society 2009</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>765</fpage>-<lpage>782</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mendes de Leon</surname><given-names>C. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berkman</surname><given-names>L. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Social engagement and disability in a community population of older adults: The New Haven EPESE</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Epidemiology</source>, <volume>157</volume>, <fpage>633</fpage>-<lpage>642</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paquet</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dubé</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gauvin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Association of individual network social capital with abdominal adiposity, overweight and obesity</article-title>. <source>Journal of Public Health (Oxford)</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>-<lpage>183</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>The NHS Information Centre</collab>. (<year>2008</year>). <source>Health Survey for England 2008. Physical activity and fitness. Summary of key findings</source>. <comment>Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ic.nhs.uk/webfiles/publications/HSE/HSE08/HSE_08_Summary_of_key_findings.pdf">http://www.ic.nhs.uk/webfiles/publications/HSE/HSE08/HSE_08_Summary_of_key_findings.pdf</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pickett</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lobstein</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Wider income gaps, wider waistbands? An ecological study of obesity and income inequality</article-title>. <source>Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health</source>, <volume>59</volume>, <fpage>670</fpage>-<lpage>674</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Poortinga</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Perceptions of the environment, physical activity, and obesity</article-title>. <source>Social Science &amp; Medicine</source>, <volume>63</volume>, <fpage>2835</fpage>-<lpage>2846</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Puhl</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heuer</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Obesity stigma: Important considerations for public health</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Public Health</source>, <volume>100</volume>, <fpage>1019</fpage>-<lpage>1028</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Radloff</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>). <article-title>The CES-D scale: A self-report depression scale for research in the general population</article-title>. <source>Applied Psychological Measurement</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>385</fpage>-<lpage>401</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Scholes</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheshire</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lessof</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Retirement, health and relationships of the older population in England: The 2004 English Longitudinal Study of Ageing Technical Report</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Centre for Social Research</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Singh-Manoux</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hillsdon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marmot</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Effects of physical activity on cognitive functioning in middle age: Evidence from the Whitehall II prospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Public Health</source>, <volume>95</volume>, <fpage>2252</fpage>-<lpage>2258</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Testa</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cacciatore</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Galizia</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Della-Morte</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mazzella</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Langellotto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Abete</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Waist circumference but not body mass index predicts long-term mortality in elderly subjects with chronic heart failure</article-title>. <source>Journal of American Geriatrics Society</source>, <volume>58</volume>, <fpage>1433</fpage>-<lpage>1440</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Veenstra</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Luginaah</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wakefield</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Birch</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eyles</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Who you know, where you live: social capital, neighbourhood and health</article-title>. <source>Social Science &amp; Medicine</source>, <volume>60</volume>, <fpage>2799</fpage>-<lpage>2818</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Verkleij</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scheele</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van der Wouden</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Late-life social activity</article-title>. <source>Archives of Internal Medicine</source>, <volume>169</volume>, <fpage>1931</fpage>-<lpage>1932</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Visscher</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seidell</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Molarius</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van der Kuip</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hofman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Witteman</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>A comparison of body mass index, waist-hip ratio and waist circumference as predictors of all-cause mortality among the elderly: The Rotterdam Study</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Obesity Related Metabolic Disorders</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>1730</fpage>-<lpage>1735</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Witham</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Avenell</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Interventions to achieve long-term weight loss in obese older people: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Age and Ageing</source>, <volume>39</volume>, <fpage>176</fpage>-<lpage>184</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0898264311421960">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zettel-Watson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Britton</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The impact of obesity on the social participation of older adults</article-title>. <source>Journal of General Psychology</source>, <volume>135</volume>, <fpage>409</fpage>-<lpage>423</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>