<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JCM</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjcm</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Composite Materials</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9983</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1530-793X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0021998312443394</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0021998312443394</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Sonication effect on the mechanical properties of MWCNTs reinforced natural rubber</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Tarawneh</surname><given-names>Mou'ad A</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0021998312443394">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0021998312443394"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>Sahrim Hj</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0021998312443394">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>EhNoum</surname><given-names>SeYong</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0021998312443394">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>Kin-tak</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0021998312443394">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0021998312443394"><label>1</label>School of Applied Physics, Faculty of Science and Technology, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia, Selangor, Malaysia</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0021998312443394"><label>2</label>Department of Mechanical Engineering, The Hong Kong Polytechnic University, Kowloon, Hong Kong SAR China</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0021998312443394">Mou'ad A Tarawneh, School of Applied Physics, Faculty of Science and Technology, Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia, 43600 Bangi, Selangor, Malaysia. Email: <email>moaath20042002@yahoo.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>47</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>579</fpage>
<lpage>585</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This study investigated the sonication effect on the mechanical properties of thermoplastic natural rubber (TPNR) nanocomposites reinforced by multi-walled carbon nanotubes (MWCNTs). The TPNR nanocomposites were prepared using the melt blending method from polypropylene, natural rubber and liquid natural rubber as a compatibilizer, respectively, with 1% of MWCNTs. The results showed that a good dispersion on nanotubes was achieved by sonication. An optimal sonication time of 1 h was found to produce nanocomposites with maximum tensile and impact strength. The Young’s modulus, tensile strength, elongation at break and impact strength increased by almost 11%, 21%, 43% and 50%, respectively as compared with a pristine TPNR sample. The effect of sonication was also confirmed by dynamic mechanical analysis, it showed that the storage modulus <italic>E</italic>′, loss modulus <italic>E</italic>″ and glass transition temperature (<italic>T</italic><sub>g</sub>) also increased for all MWCNTs reinforced samples. Scanning electron micrographs confirm the effect of good dispersion of MWCNTs and their interfacial bonding in TPNR after sonication.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Carbon nanotubes</kwd>
<kwd>thermoplastic natural rubber</kwd>
<kwd>mechanical properties</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0021998312443394" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Thermoplastic elastomers (TPEs) based on natural rubber and thermoplastic blends are termed as thermoplastic natural rubber (TPNR) blends. There are two types of TPNR, namely thermoplastic polyolefin (TPO) and thermoplastic vulcanizate (TPV).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021998312443394">1</xref></sup> TPNR can be used in a wide range of applications including cable insulation, footwear, packaging industries, etc. Its excellent weather-resistance properties, low density, and relatively low cost make it ideal for use in different types of engineering components (such as sight shields, interior trim, cable insulation and packaging industry). In general, fillers are required for achieving the stiffness of TPNR compounds. Adding small amount of nanofiller into TPNR can improve its stiffness, ductility and tensile strength, Young’s modulus, impact strength and elongation at break.</p>
<p>Since the discovery of carbon nanotubes (CNTs), polymers mixed with CNTs have been studied widely due to their extraordinary electrical and mechanical properties which make them potentially used for a wide range of applications.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0021998312443394">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0021998312443394"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0021998312443394">4</xref></sup> Therefore, CNTs are used as inclusions in various matrices to improve electrical, mechanical or thermal properties. CNTs in single-walled (SWCNT) or multi-walled (MWCNT) type have been appreciated to be used as next generation reinforcements for polymer composites. MWCNTs have been proven to be very effective fillers especially in tailored polymeric materials, which are suited to prescribed applications at very low loadings. This is because neat MWCNTs exhibit excellent mechanical (theoretically as high as 1 TPa tensile modulus), thermal, and electrical properties.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0021998312443394">5</xref></sup> One of the advantages of MWCNTs used as a filler is their high aspect ratio, as high as 1000, which can induce better adhesion with polymeric matrix, which is an important factor for effective enhancement of the nanocomposite’s properties.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0021998312443394">6</xref></sup> This enables percolation of the fillers at very low concentrations and makes them attractive for use in a broad spectrum of applications, especially as reinforcing fibers in nanocomposites. However, the potential of using CNTs as polymer composites has not yet been realized mainly because of the difficulties in solubility and processability. Several fundamental processing challenges must be overcome to enable the applicable composites by CNTs. The dispersion property becomes more important when CNTs are blended into polymer. However, due to their large total surface area, CNTs tend to remain as entangled agglomerates and, thus, a homogeneously dispersed state within a polymer is not easily carried out.</p>
<p>Mechanical property tests, chemical treatments and the ultrasonication method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0021998312443394">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0021998312443394"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0021998312443394"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0021998312443394">10</xref></sup> have been used to disperse CNTs in polymer. However, despite the considerable number of studies concerning the preparation and properties of CNT/Polymer nanocomposites, the effect of ultrasonication time on dispersion is not very well understood. In addition, no report has been published regarding the processing of CNT/TPNR nanocomposites using continuous ultrasonic vibration.</p>
<p>In this work, MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposites were prepared with an ultrasonic vibration bath; ultrasonic vibration or sonication produces high shear to promote good dispersion of MWCNTs in TPNR. The effect of different times of sonication treatment on the mechanical properties of TPNR nanocomposites is reported in this article.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0021998312443394"><title>Experiment set up</title>
<sec id="sec3-0021998312443394" sec-type="materials"><title>Materials</title>
<p>The MWCNTs used in this work were manufactured by the CVD process and supplied by the Chinese Academy of Science (CAS). The specification of the MWCNTs are as follows: purity &gt;95%, length 10–30 µm, diameter &lt;8 nm, bulk density 0.27 g/cm<sup>3</sup>. Polypropylene, with the density of 0.905 g/cm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0021998312443394">3</xref></sup>, was supplied by Propilinas (M) Sdn. Bhd. Natural rubber was obtained from Guthrie (M) Sdn. Bhd and liquid natural rubber (LNR) was produced by photochemical degradation technique in laboratory.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0021998312443394"><title>Composite preparation</title>
<p>The indirect technique (IDT) was used to prepare the MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposites. This involved mixing of MWCNTs with LNR and then treating by ultrasonic bath (70 W, 42 kHz + 1–6%) for different time durations (1 h, 3 h and 5 h). The TPNR nanocomposites were prepared by melt blending in the ratio of 10, 20 and 70 wt% of LNR then NR and PP respectively, with 1 wt% MWCNTs. The LNR was used as compatiblizer. The mixing of the nanocomposites was done in the internal mixer (Haake Rheomix OS) at temperature of 180°C with a rotor speed of 80 rpm and 11 min mixing time.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0021998312443394"><title>Characterization</title>
<p>Tensile property tests were conducted for all samples by using Testometric universal testing machine (M350-10CT) with a 5 kN load cell according to the ASTM 412 standard. At least five samples were tested for each composition, and the average value was reported.</p>
<p>The Izod impact test was carried out by using Ray Ran Pendulum Impact System according to ASTM D 256-90 b. The velocity and weight of the hammer were 3.45 m/s and 0.898 kg, respectively. The sample dimension was 63 × 12 × 3 mm<sup>3</sup>.</p>
<p>The dynamic mechanical properties of the composites were measured by using the TA DMA-2980 with a sample with dimensions of 30 × 12.5 × 3 mm<sup>3</sup>. DMA thermograms were obtained at frequency of 1 Hz in a nitrogen atmosphere, at temperatures from −100°C to 150°C at scan rate of 5°C/min.</p>
<p>The morphology of the MWCNTs and the composite were examined by scanning electron microscope (SEM, Philips XL 30) with acceleration voltage of 100 kV. An ultrathin section was prepared by Leica ultracut E with cryo FC4E attachment at −100°C.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0021998312443394" sec-type="results"><title>Results and discussion</title>
<sec id="sec7-0021998312443394"><title>Tensile properties</title>
<p>The tensile strength and Young’s modulus of MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposites treated by sonication are presented in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0021998312443394">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0021998312443394">2</xref>. The employment of sonication has led to the improvement in tensile properties of the MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposites. The maximum strength of MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposites was achieved at 1 h of sonication treatment. The tensile strength and Young’s modulus increased up to 21% and 11%, respectively. The present of MWCNTs enhanced the mechanical properties of TPNR. The MWCNTs also exhibited strong interface between the nanotubes and the polymer matrix which is required to transfer the load from the matrix to the MWCNTs effectively.
<fig id="fig1-0021998312443394" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Tensile strength of MWCNT/TPNR nanocomposites at different sonication time. MWCNTs: multi-walled carbon nanotubes; TPNR: thermoplastic natural rubber.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312443394-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig2-0021998312443394" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Young’s modulus of MWCNT/TPNR nanocomposite at different sonication times. MWCNTs: multi-walled carbon nanotubes; TPNR: thermoplastic natural rubber.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312443394-fig2.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0021998312443394">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0021998312443394">2</xref> show that the tensile strength decreases by continuously increasing the sonication time over 1 h. This decrease was caused by the agglomeration of the MWCNTs which resulted in the delimitation of the MWCNTs and decreased the degree of intercalation. The agglomeration of the MWCNTs in the matrix will increase the stress concentrations, and areas of the matrix without the MWCNTs, which will degrade the mechanical properties of the composite.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0021998312443394">11</xref></sup></p>
<p>The nanoscale filler is believed to become a nucleating agent that will contribute more uniformity to the spherulite growth.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0021998312443394">12</xref></sup> However, it is noted from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0021998312443394">Figure 3</xref> that after 1 h the treated composites shows a lower elongation at break compared to the TPNR. As discussed earlier, the applied treatment of more than 1 h causes the MWCNTs to start forming agglomerations that become larger and larger inside the matrix. Therefore, the elongation at break decreased due to the increasing of the clusters size of the MWCNTs, which are effective as a nucleating agent (degree of crystallinity decreased). This directly affects the mechanical properties of the composites.
<fig id="fig3-0021998312443394" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Elongation at break of MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposites at different sonication times. MWCNTs: multi-walled carbon nanotubes; TPNR: thermoplastic natural rubber.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312443394-fig3.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-0021998312443394"><title>Impact strength</title>
<p>The impact strength of MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposites is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0021998312443394">Figure 4</xref>. It was found that the impact strength of MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposites improved with sonication treatment. The result also shows that the maximal strength was obtained for a sample sonicated for 1 h. Better dispersion of MWCNTs in the matrix generates a significant toughening effect on the MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposites. In addition, when the load is transferred to the physical network between the matrix and the filler, the debonding of the chain (disentanglement) segments from the filler surface facilitates the relaxation of the matrix entanglement structure, leading to higher impact toughness.
<fig id="fig4-0021998312443394" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Impact strength of MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposites at different sonication times. MWCNTs: multi-walled carbon nanotubes; TPNR: thermoplastic natural rubber.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312443394-fig4.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>For the MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposite sonicated for 1 h, it can be seen that its tensile strength and impact properties were higher than those of a pristine sample. Therefore, an optimum sonicating time must be achieved in order to obtain the maximum dispersion ability. The size of the agglomerated MWCNTs was reduced when the optimum sonicating time was reached; the surface area for the interaction between MWCNTs and TPNR increased and thus, provided the maximum reinforcement.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0021998312443394"><title>Dynamic mechanical analysis</title>
<p>Dynamic mechanical analysis (DMA) is a useful technique and very sensitive for the investigation of macromolecular chain conformations and movements during the exposure of polymers to a variation in temperatures. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0021998312443394">Figure 5</xref> shows the storage modulus of neat TPNR and its nanocomposites treated at different sonication time, as a function of temperature. The storage modulus of neat TPNR and its nanocomposites decreased with increasing temperature, as expected. However, the most characteristic difference is that the storage modulus of MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposites tends to increase by increasing the amount of the MWCNTs. This indicates the effectiveness of the sonication treatment effect. The maximum values of storage modulus were obtained of the samples sonicated for 1 h and 3 h.
<fig id="fig5-0021998312443394" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Storage modulus of TPNR and MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposites treated at different sonication times (US: Sonicated samples). MWCNTs: multi-walled carbon nanotubes; TPNR: thermoplastic natural rubber.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312443394-fig5.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0021998312443394">Figure 6</xref>, it is found that the loss modulus <italic>E″</italic> of the MWCNTs/TPNR composites is higher than that of TPNR for the nanocomposites sonicated for 1 h and 3 h, which may be due to the MWCNTs being more uniformly dispersed in the matrix. Therefore, the total surface area is more than that of the agglomerated MWCNTs, therefore, the interaction between the matrix and nanotube was more effective. Since the value of <italic>E″</italic> at lower temperatures has a great influence on the toughness of the matrix, it is obvious that MWCNTs contribute to the improvement of the toughness of the nanocomposites. A mesophase formed between the matrix and MWCNTs. Therefore, when the composites are subjected to an external stress, an external energy is dissipated by the friction between particle–particle and particle–matrix interaction through the mesophase. However, for a MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposite sonicated for 5 h, its loss modulus <italic>E″</italic> decreased due to the agglomeration of MWCNTs inside the matrix as we mentioned above. Due to the polymer–filler interaction, the adsorption of the polymer chains on the filler’s surface reduces the mobility of the macromolecular segments. This transition zone surrounding the nanoparticles exhibits a higher modulus which is gradually reduced with increasing distance from the filler surface.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0021998312443394">13</xref></sup>
<fig id="fig6-0021998312443394" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Loss modulus of TPNR and MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposites treated at different sonication times (US: Sonicated samples). MWCNTs: multi-walled carbon nanotubes; TPNR: thermoplastic natural rubber.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312443394-fig6.tif"/>
</fig></p>
<p>DMA data as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0021998312443394">Figure 7</xref> reflects that the glass transition temperature (<italic>T</italic><sub>g</sub>) of the MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposites was affected by the addition of MWCNTs. Analyzing tan delta (δ) variation curves of the nanocomposites at different sonication time, the tan δ peaks of the nanocomposites treated at 1 h and 3 h are higher than that of TPNR sample. The <italic>T</italic><sub>g</sub> of the nanocomposites treated at 1 h and 3 h are −56.3°C and −58.9°C, respectively. Comparing with the TPNR sample with <italic>T</italic><sub>g</sub> of −62.4°C, the <italic>T</italic><sub>g</sub> of MWCNTs mixed TPNR (nanocomposites) was tended to increase due to the interactions between the polymer chains and MWCNTs and the reduction of macromolecular chain mobility at the zone surrounding the MWCNTs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0021998312443394">14</xref></sup> For a nanocomposite treated at 5 h, its <italic>T</italic><sub>g</sub> was measured as −60.3°C.
<fig id="fig7-0021998312443394" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Tan delta (δ) of TPNR and MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposites treated at different sonication times (US: Sonicated samples). MWCNTs: multi-walled carbon nanotubes; TPNR: thermoplastic natural rubber.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312443394-fig7.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-0021998312443394"><title>Morphological characterization</title>
<p>A uniform dispersion of MWCNTs in the nanocomposites was reflected through scanning electronic microscopy (SEM) imaging. The nanocomposite sample without pretreated by sonication is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0021998312443394">Figure 8</xref>. A poor dispersion of MWCNTs in the matrix is shown as indicated by a few white spots. Agglomeration of the MWCNTs was found in TPNR. The MWNTs that had been pulled out from the matrix were still coated by a layer of polymer as indicated by small circles shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0021998312443394">Figure 9</xref>. It can prove that a good dispersion of MWNTs was resulted in the nanocomposites. A strong interfacial bonding for nanocomposites is essential for efficiently transferring stress form the matrix to the MWNTs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0021998312443394">Figure 10</xref> shows the dispersion condition of a nanocomposite after pretreated by 3 h of sonication.
<fig id="fig8-0021998312443394" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Scanning electron micrograph of MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposite without treated by sonication. MWCNTs: multi-walled carbon nanotubes; TPNR: thermoplastic natural rubber.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312443394-fig8.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig9-0021998312443394" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Scanning electron micrograph of MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposite after being sonicated for 1 h: (a) 1500 kX magnification, (b) 3000 kX. MWCNTs: multi-walled carbon nanotubes; TPNR: thermoplastic natural rubber.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312443394-fig9.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig10-0021998312443394" position="float"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p>Scanning electron micrograph of MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposite after being treated by sonication for 3 h. MWCNTs: multi-walled carbon nanotubes; TPNR: thermoplastic natural rubber.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312443394-fig10.tif"/>
</fig>
</p>
<p>Based on the results obtained, the mechanical properties of the MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposites can be significantly improved by properly controlling the sonication times. Sonication treatment is a form of vibration that provides energy to the MWCNTs to escape from the surrounding restraining force of polymer while at the same time it may cause agglomeration (big cluster) on the MWCNTs due to the high frequency collision<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0021998312443394">15</xref></sup> inside the matrix. After all experimental testing, it was found that, by introducing sonication treatment, three phenomena might happen in MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposites:
<list id="list1-0021998312443394" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>– if the sonication time is too short, MWCNTs may still agglomerate, and cause non-uniform dispersion inside the nanocomposites. This results in forming unrepeatable nanocomposites in which their mechanical properties cannot be controlled;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>– if the sonication time is too long (more than 1 h), the MWCNTs may entangle with each other. In addition, MWCNTs clusters may also be formed, which results in reducing the total surface areas for chemical reaction (as shown in Figure 11). The dangerous point is the existence of unfill cavities between the MWCNTs. This results in producing poor mechanical property nanocomposites, and</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>– if the sonication time (1 h) is at proper level, the MWCNTs can be dispersed evenly and all MWCNTs would separate from each others and fully take the loads transferred from the matrix.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-0021998312443394" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>In this study, it was found that control of sonication time during the manufacturing process significantly influences the dispersion properties, and, thus, the mechanical performance of MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposite. The tensile and impact properties of the composite were substantially improved after being sonicated for 1 h, as compared with pristine and other samples that were sonicated for a different length of time. The SEM images also show that a uniform dispersion of MWCNTs/TPNR with 1-h sonication resulted and the surface was still coated with TPNR, which reflects that a strong bonding between the MWCNTs and TPNR existed. The results obtained from this study can provide an important guideline for researchers to produce high strength nanocomposites, especially as normally the sonication time control is always ignored during the entire manufacturing process.
<fig id="fig11-0021998312443394" position="float"><label>Figure 11.</label><caption><p>SEM micrograph of MWCNTs/TPNR nanocomposite after being treated by sonication for 5 h. MWCNTs: multi-walled carbon nanotubes; TPNR: thermoplastic natural rubber.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998312443394-fig11.tif"/>
</fig></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec12-0021998312443394"><title>Funding</title>
<p>The authors would like to thank the Malaysian Government and Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia (UKM) under Science Fund Grant UKM-OUP-NBT-29-142/2011 for financial support.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec13-0021998312443394"><title>Conflict of Interest</title>
<p>None declared.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0021998312443394"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakason</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wannavilai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaesaman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of vulcanization system on properties of thermoplastic vulcanizates based on epoxidized natural rubber/polypropylene blends</article-title>. <source>Polym Test</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>34</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0021998312443394"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaffer</surname><given-names>MSP</given-names></name><name><surname>Windle</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fabrication and characterization of carbon nanotube/poly(vinyl alcohol) composites</article-title>. <source>Adv Mater</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>937</fpage>–<lpage>941</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0021998312443394"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernando</surname><given-names>KAS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Polymeric carbon nanocomposites from carbon nanotubes functionalized with matrix polymer</article-title>. <source>Macromolecules</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>7199</fpage>–<lpage>7205</lpage>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/ma0348876">http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/ma0348876</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0021998312443394"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pötschke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharyya</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Janke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Morphology and electrical resistivity of melt mixed blends of polyethylene and carbon nanotube filled polycarbonate</article-title>. <source>Polymer</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>8061</fpage>–<lpage>8069</lpage>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0032386103009054">http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0032386103009054</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0021998312443394"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schartel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Potschke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Knoll</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Goad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fire behaviour of polyamide 6/multiwall carbon nanotube nanocomposites</article-title>. <source>Eur Polym J</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1061</fpage>–<lpage>1070</lpage>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0014305704004410">http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0014305704004410</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0021998312443394"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Curran</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ajayan</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Blau</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A composite from poly(<italic>m</italic>-phenylenevinylene-<italic>co</italic>-2,5-dioctoxy-<italic>p</italic>-phenylenevinylene) and carbon nanotubes: a novel material for molecular optoelectronics</article-title>. <source>Adv Mater</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1091</fpage>–<lpage>1093</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0021998312443394"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Iukai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of ball milling on morphology of cup-stacked carbon nanotubes</article-title>. <source>Chem Phys Lett</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>355</volume>: <fpage>279</fpage>–<lpage>284</lpage>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0009261402002488">http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0009261402002488</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0021998312443394"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kooi</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlecht</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Burghard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Electrochemical modification of single carbon nanotubes</article-title>. <source>Angew Chem Int Edit</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1353</fpage>–<lpage>1355</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0021998312443394"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>PX</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>QH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Multi-step purification of carbon nanotubes</article-title>. <source>Carbon</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0008622301000756">http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0008622301000756</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0021998312443394"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koshio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yudasaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Iijima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A simple way to chemically react single-wall carbon nanotubes with organic materials using ultrasonication</article-title>. <source>Nano Letts</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>1</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>361</fpage>–<lpage>363</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0021998312443394"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>He</given-names></name><name><surname>Yong</surname><given-names>Gao</given-names></name><name><surname>Jie</surname><given-names>Lian</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Surface modification and ultrasonication effect on the mechanical properties of carbon nanofiber/polycarbonate composites</article-title>. <source>Composites: Part A</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>1270</fpage>–<lpage>1275</lpage>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1359835X05003222">http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1359835X05003222</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0021998312443394"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Avella</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cosco</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenzo</surname><given-names>Di</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nucleation activity of nanosized CaCO<sub>3</sub> on crystallization of isotactic polypropylene, in dependence on crystal modification, particle shape, and coating</article-title>. <source>Polymer</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>1548</fpage>–<lpage>1557</lpage>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0014305706000395">http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0014305706000395</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0021998312443394"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of polymer-filler and filler-filler interactions on dynamic properties of filled vulcanizates</article-title>. <source>Rubber Chem Technol</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>520</fpage>–<lpage>589</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0021998312443394"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Morphology, thermal stability, and dynamic mechanical properties of atactic polypropylene/carbon nanotube composites</article-title>. <source>J Appl Polym Sci</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>1087</fpage>–<lpage>1087</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0021998312443394"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mukhopadhyay</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwivedi</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathur</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Conversion of carbon nanotubes to carbon nanofibers by sonication</article-title>. <source>Carbon</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>40</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>1373</fpage>–<lpage>1376</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>