<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">WMR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spwmr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Waste Manag Res</journal-id>
<journal-title>Waste Management &amp; Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0734-242X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1096-3669</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0734242X11413328</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0734242X11413328</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Influence of semi-aerobic and anaerobic landfill operation with leachate recirculation on stabilization processes</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Yangfei</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0734242X11413328">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0734242X11413328">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>Bo</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0734242X11413328">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Yu</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0734242X11413328">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Qifei</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0734242X11413328">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0734242X11413328"><label>1</label>Research Institute of Solid Waste Management, Chinese Research Academy of Environmental Sciences, Beijing, China</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0734242X11413328"><label>2</label>Jiangxi University of Science and Technology, Faculty of Resource and Environmental Engineering, Jiangxi Ganzhou, China; Quzhou University, Zhejiang Quzhou, China</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0734242X11413328">Qifei Huang, 8, Dayangfang Anwai, Beijing 100012, China Email: <email>huangqf@vip.sina.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>30</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>255</fpage>
<lpage>265</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>27</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>17</day>
<month>5</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">International Solid Waste Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>To investigate the influence of semi-aerobic and anaerobic landfill operation on stabilization processes of landfill sites with leachate recirculation, <italic>in situ</italic> simulated semi-aerobic landfill sites with leachate recirculation (SLR) and anaerobic landfill sites with leachate recirculation (ALR) were constructed. Refuse properties and landfill settlement were determined. Leachate quality and landfill gas compositions were monitored regularly. Based on the data obtained, leachate quality, landfill gas and final refuse characteristics were adopted as assessment factors to quantitatively evaluate stabilization of landfill sites. The results showed that volatile solids (VS), total organic carbon (TOC) and biologically degradable matter (BDM) of aged refuse in SLR (15.8, 7.3 and 9.9%, respectively) were lower than those in ALR, which were 19.1, 9.2 and 11.3%, respectively. Settlement and reduction ratio of SLR were 1.71 m and 30.91%, respectively, and 1.40 m and 25.45% in the case of ALR. Concentrations of organic pollutants, especially ammonia, were reduced in SLR, and variation in leachate quality was also smoother than ALR. Throughout the experiment the average concentration of CH<sub>4</sub> in ALR was higher than that in SLR (36.7 and 14.5%, respectively). At the end of the experiment, SLR was moderately stable, while ALR was moderately unstable. The comprehensive assessment index (<italic>I</italic>) for SLR and ALR was 200 and 355, respectively.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Landfill operation</kwd>
<kwd>semi-aerobic landfill</kwd>
<kwd>leachate recirculation</kwd>
<kwd>stabilization evaluation</kwd>
<kwd>refuse</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0734242X11413328" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The situation for safe disposal of refuse in China is severe. According to available statistics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0734242X11413328">NBSC, 2009</xref>), the amount of refuse delivered to urban disposal facilities (up to 1.52 billion tons) was less than 70% of the estimated quantity produced. In rural areas, ∼2 billion tons of refuse requires safe disposal. In China, the main approach to managing refuse is landfill, with ∼81.9% of refuse being transported to such sites. Considered the best disposal option, landfill requires the acquisition of land. It is, therefore, important to determine landfill technologies and management methods that promote and accelerate refuse degradation and landfill-site stabilization to minimize the landfill space required.</p>
<p>Stabilization of landfill sites can be accelerated by bioreactor landfill, aerobic landfill, and semi-aerobic landfill approaches. The bioreactor landfill provides control and process optimization, primarily through the addition of leachate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0734242X11413328">Reinhart and Al-Yousti, 1996</xref>). Bioreactor landfill has the benefit of reducing leachate organic concentration and accelerating landfill stabilization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0734242X11413328">Pohland, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0734242X11413328">Reinhart and Al-Yousti, 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0734242X11413328">Reinhart and Townsend, 1998</xref>). However, during the refuse-decomposition process coupled to leachate recirculation, ammonia tends to accumulate and methane production increases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0734242X11413328">Calli et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0734242X11413328">Tada et al., 2005</xref>). In the context of minimizing global greenhouse gas emissions, the application of bioreactor landfills is accordingly restricted. Recently, interest in bioreactor landfills has increased with the practice of introducing air into the waste mass for aerobic degradation of refuse, and aerobic bioreactors have been promoted as a method for accelerating waste stabilization. Studies of aerobic biodegradation processes have demonstrated that the organic fraction of the refuse degrades in a relatively short time compared with anaerobic degradation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0734242X11413328">Sinan et al., 2007</xref>). However, more energy is consumed in the running of aerobic landfill sites because the air injection is continuous. There are currently no aerobic landfill sites operating in China.</p>
<p>In 1986, the semi-aerobic landfill approach was proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0734242X11413328">Hanashima et al. (1986)</xref>. An engineered design is employed, in which ambient air flows naturally into the waste body through leachate-collecting pipes, and the waste-stabilization process is improved along with leachate quality because of enhanced microbial activity in the waste body (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0734242X11413328">Matsufuji and Sinha, 1990</xref>). Following these initial studies, researchers have shown that semi-aerobic landfill reduces both the organic fraction and methane production and also reduces the leachate ammonia concentration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0734242X11413328">Berge et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0734242X11413328">Hanashima, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0734242X11413328">Powell et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0734242X11413328">Wang et al., 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>The above suggests that semi-aerobic landfills with leachate recirculation should have the advantage of reducing the leachate pollution load (especially ammonia) effectively and decreasing methane discharge. At present, dozens of semi-aerobic landfill sites are operating in China, but research on stabilization of those sites with leachate recirculation is still limited. Many studies on aerobic and anaerobic landfill-site stabilization have been conducted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0734242X11413328">Sanphotia et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0734242X11413328">Sinan et al., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0734242X11413328">Yang et al., 2007</xref>), but most of these were conducted on single measures of leachate quantity and quality, including pH, oxidation-reduction potential (OPR), suspended solids (SS), organic pollutants and ammonia concentration, landfill gas composition and production, and final refuse characteristics and landfill settling. Comprehensive research including all these indices and qualitative evaluation is even scarcer. Evaluation factors and parameters have been proposed by some researchers. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0734242X11413328">Jiang et al. (2009)</xref> suggested using such evaluation factors as leachate, landfill gas, and refuse. The associated evaluation parameters include concentrations of chemical oxygen demand (COD), biochemical oxygen demand (BOD) and NH<sub>3</sub>-N, BOD/COD ratio, percentage of CH<sub>4</sub> in the landfill gas, and refuse biochemical methane potential (BMP) and volatile solids (VS). Methods to evaluate landfill stabilization have been also proposed. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0734242X11413328">Kelly et al. (2006)</xref> proposed as evaluation parameters the content of cellulose, lignin, BMP, and VS along with plastics. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0734242X11413328">Wang et al. (2001)</xref> considered that in addition to leachate yield, COD, BOD, NH<sub>3</sub>-N, SS, and landfill gas yield, the settlement rate of landfill sites should also be used as an evaluation parameter. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0734242X11413328">Wang et al. (2001)</xref> also introduced methods for evaluating landfill stabilization based on environmental impact-assessment theory.</p>
<p>To characterize the influence of landfill operation on stabilization processes for landfill sites, both semi-aerobic and anaerobic landfill sites with leachate recirculation were constructed at pilot scales. Leachate and landfill gas were collected and evaluation parameters obtained. Refuse properties prior to filling (fresh refuse) and after 900 days (final refuse) were also investigated to assess the landfill reduction ratio. Landfill-site stabilization was evaluated quantitatively based on the methods of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0734242X11413328">Jiang et al. (2009)</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0734242X11413328" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and methods</title>
<sec id="section3-0734242X11413328">
<title><italic>In-situ</italic> landfill construction</title>
<p><italic>In-situ</italic> simulated landfills were located in the city of Jiujiang City, Jiangxi Province, of China; where the average annual rainfall and temperature for Jiujiang are about 1500 mm and 17°C, respectively. The simulated landfills were constructed outdoor but sealed and isolated from precipitation. The simulated semi-aerobic and anaerobic landfills were constructed based on current construction methods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0734242X11413328">Figure 1</xref>). The dimensions of the landfills were 21 m × 3.8 m × 6 m. High-density polyethylene (HDPE) membrane was laid at the bottom of the landfill, and leachate-collecting pipes (diameter 20 cm) were installed on the HDPE membrane. The pipes were covered with gravel to avoid becoming clogged by waste. In the semi-aerobic landfill site, three vertical windpipes (diameter 20 cm) were fixed on sections of the leachate-collecting pipe. The windpipes were perforated and protected by gravel (diameter 40 mm) so that air could flow into the bottom layer. Vertical pipes were not fixed at the anaerobic landfill site. Refuse was loaded without additional drying, and customized landfill gas collecting sets were installed at heights of 1.5, 3 and 4.5 m from the base of the landfill. Finally, the landfills were sealed with a plastic membrane.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0734242X11413328" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Schematic diagram of (a) SLR and (b) ALR.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11413328-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0734242X11413328">
<title>Refuse properties</title>
<p>The fresh refuse (mixture of domestic and commercial garbage) for experiment was collected from the municipal solid waste (MSW) transfer station of Jiujiang City. Its characteristics are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0734242X11413328">Table 1</xref>. Each of the two simulated landfills was filled with 250 tonnes of shredded (diameter 5–20 cm) and compacted fresh refuse.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0734242X11413328" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Properties of experimental refuse</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0734242X11413328" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11413328-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Item</th>
<th align="left">Moisture content (%)</th>
<th align="left">pH</th>
<th align="left">Conductivity (μs cm<sup>−1</sup>)</th>
<th align="left">Density (kg m<sup>−3</sup>)</th>
<th align="left">VS/TS (%)</th>
<th align="left">TOC/TS (%)</th>
<th align="left">BDM/TS (%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Value</td>
<td>64.3</td>
<td>7.21</td>
<td>2270</td>
<td>520</td>
<td>57.2</td>
<td>26.9</td>
<td>18.0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0734242X11413328">
<title>Leachate recirculation</title>
<p>Both semi-aerobic landfill sites (SLR) and anaerobic landfill sites (ALR) were fitted with leachate recirculation. Leachate recirculation started on the tenth day after filling the landfill volume and was completed and finished 900 days later. Leachate was withdrawn from the landfill via collecting pipes, and stored in a leachate accumulation tank. The two kinds of leachate were mixed, and the mixture was re-introduced equally into the landfill mass by means of a recirculation pipe with a constant rate of ∼15 L min<sup>−1</sup>. The volume of recirculated leachate each time was ∼1 m<sup>3</sup> (about one-third of the local annual rainfall).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0734242X11413328">
<title>Sampling</title>
<sec id="section7-0734242X11413328">
<title>Final refuse</title>
<p>Final refuse samples (original size) were collected from 50 sampling points in each of the three landfill layers. Each layer’s samples were mixed and 1000 g of homogenized sample was selected and stored at 4°C.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0734242X11413328">
<title>Leachate</title>
<p>Leachate generated was stored in the leachate storage tank (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0734242X11413328">Figure 1</xref>). The tank volume was recorded regularly, and ∼500 mL was sampled for analysis. After the leachate volume was measured, sampled and recirculated, the leachate was discharged. Sampling frequency was every 10 days until day 500, and every 20 days after 500 days.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0734242X11413328">
<title>Landfill gas</title>
<p>Landfill gas was collected in initial vacuum bags from the collecting sets. Gas from each sampling point was mixed in one large gas-storage bag. Because of the extensive size of the simulated landfill sites, accurate measurement of landfill gas volume was difficult and was not assessed here.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0734242X11413328">
<title>Analytical methods</title>
<p>Refuse pH was determined according to standard methods CJ/T99-1999 (Ministry of Construction P.R.China, 1999).</p>
<p>Moisture content was determined by modified Standard Method 2540-B (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0734242X11413328">APHA, AWWA, WEF, 2005</xref>). At least 1 kg of collected refuse was dried in an aluminium pan at 105°C to a constant weight after cooling under desiccation. The moisture content was determined by weight loss from the original sample and expressed as a percentage.</p>
<p>The VS procedure followed a modified version of Standard Methods APHA Method 2440-E. Samples were dried again at 105°C to a constant weight and stored in a desiccator. Approximately 2 g of dried refuse was placed in pre-weighed porcelain crucibles and heated in a muffle furnace at 550°C for 2 h. Samples were removed and allowed to cool in a desiccator to a constant weight. The percentage weight loss on ignition yielded the total amount of volatile matter. Total organic carbon (TOC) was determined using an OI Corporation TOC Analyzer M-700.Biodegradable matter (BDM) was analysed according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0734242X11413328">Wang et al. (2003)</xref>. About 100 kg refuse were collected in three layers and the inorganic materials such as metal, glasses, stone and un-degradable matter such as plastics and rubber were separated. Then, the refined refuse was mixed uniformly and 10 kg refuse was taken out to dry. After that, the dried refuse was milled to a size below 1 mm. A sample about 0.5 g was placed in a 250 mL volumetric flask, to which 15 mL potassium dichromate solution and 20 mL concentrated sulfuric acid were added. The flask was agitated in a shaker for 1 h; upon completion, the flask was removed and water added to the standard line. Then, 25 mL solutions were taken from the flask and put into a conical flask. Three drops of ferroin indicator were added, followed by ammonium ferrous sulfate solution until the colour of the liquid in the flask turned reddish brown. Based on the concentration and consumed volume of ammonium ferrous sulfate solution, the BDM value was calculated.</p>
<p>The pH was measured by a PHS-digital pH meter (DELTA 320). Leachates were analysed according to standard methods recommended by the US Environmental Protection Agency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0734242X11413328">APHA, AWWA, WEF, 2005</xref>). COD was measured with the K<sub>2</sub>Cr<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub> titration method. BOD<sub>5</sub> was measured by oxygen consumption for 5 days with a DO meter. NH<sub>3</sub>-N was measured by Nessler’s reagent spectrophotometry.</p>
<p>Landfill gas composition (CH<sub>4</sub>, CO<sub>2</sub> and O<sub>2</sub>) was monitored using a Geotechnical Instruments GA25 portable gas-extraction analyser.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0734242X11413328">
<title>Evaluating stabilization</title>
<p>Based on the stabilization-evaluation method of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0734242X11413328">Jiang et al. (2009)</xref>, COD, BOD, NH<sub>3</sub>-N, BOD/COD ratio, percentage of CH<sub>4</sub> in the landfill gas, and refuse VS were adopted as evaluation parameters to calculate a comprehensive stabilization–evaluation index.</p>
<sec id="section12-0734242X11413328">
<title>Evaluation indices for landfill stabilization</title>
<p>Evaluation indices were ranked based on values sourced from the report of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0734242X11413328">Jiang et al. (2009)</xref> on variations in leachate, landfill gas and refuse in the process of landfill-site stabilization (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0734242X11413328">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0734242X11413328" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Reference values for classification of landfill stabilization evaluation</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0734242X11413328" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11413328-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Ranking (i)</th>
<th align="left" colspan="6">Concentration or percentage of evaluation parameter (C<sub>i,j</sub>)</th>
<th align="left">Evaluationindex (<italic>I<sub>i</sub>,<sub>j</sub></italic>)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">COD (mg L<sup>−1</sup>)</th>
<th align="left">BOD (mg L<sup>−1</sup>)</th>
<th align="left">NH<sub>3</sub>-N (mg L<sup>−1</sup>)</th>
<th align="left">BOD/COD</th>
<th align="left">CH<sub>4</sub> (%)</th>
<th align="left">VS (%)</th>
<th/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>0.10</td>
<td>1.25</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>300</td>
<td>150</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>0.10</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>1000</td>
<td>600</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>0.15</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>200</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>2000</td>
<td>1000</td>
<td>200</td>
<td>0.30</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>300</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>6000</td>
<td>2000</td>
<td>1000</td>
<td>0.50</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>400</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>20000</td>
<td>8000</td>
<td>4000</td>
<td>0.80</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>500</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0734242X11413328">
<title>Calculation of evaluation index for each parameter (I<sub>j</sub>)</title>
<p>When the concentration or percentage of parameter <italic>j</italic> (<italic>C<sub>j</sub></italic>) equals (<italic>C<sub>i</sub></italic>, <italic><sub>j</sub></italic>), then the evaluation index (<italic>I<sub>j</sub></italic>) of parameter <italic>j</italic> is equal to <italic>I<sub>i</sub></italic>, <italic><sub>j</sub></italic>. As <italic>C</italic><sub><italic>i,j</italic></sub> &lt; <italic>C</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub> &lt; <italic>C</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>+1, <italic>j</italic></sub>, <italic>I</italic><sub>0</sub>, <italic><sub>j</sub></italic> is calculated according to:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0734242X11413328">
<label>(1)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math1-0734242X11413328">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-0734242X11413328" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11413328-eq1.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where <italic>I</italic><sub>0</sub>,<italic><sub>j</sub></italic> is the evaluation index of parameter <italic>j</italic>; <italic>C<sub>j</sub></italic> is the concentration or percentage of parameter <italic>j</italic>; <italic>C<sub>i</sub></italic>, <italic><sub>j</sub></italic> is the concentration or percentage of parameter <italic>j</italic> in rank <italic>i</italic>, and <italic>C<sub>i</sub></italic><sub>+1</sub>, <italic><sub>j</sub></italic> is in rank <italic>i</italic> + 1 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0734242X11413328">Table 2</xref>). <italic>I<sub>i</sub></italic>, <italic><sub>j</sub></italic> is the evaluation index of parameter <italic>j</italic> in rank <italic>i</italic>. For example, suppose that the concentration of COD (<italic>C<sub>j</sub></italic>) was 800 mg L<sup>−1</sup>, then <italic>i</italic> was rank 2, so <italic>C<sub>i</sub></italic>, <italic><sub>j</sub></italic> and <italic>C<sub>i</sub></italic><sub>+1</sub>, <italic><sub>j</sub></italic> were 300 mg L<sup>−1</sup> and 1000 mg L<sup>−1</sup>, respectively. <italic>I<sub>i</sub></italic>, <italic><sub>j</sub></italic> was 100 and <italic>I<sub>i</sub></italic><sub>+1</sub>,<italic><sub>j</sub></italic> was 200. The evaluation index of COD (<italic>I</italic><sub>COD</sub>) was calculated as follows:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0734242X11413328">
<mml:math display="block" id="math2-0734242X11413328">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>O</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>800</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>300</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1000</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>300</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>200</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>100</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>171</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula2-0734242X11413328" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11413328-eq2.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-0734242X11413328">
<title>Calculation of evaluation index for each factor (E<sub>j</sub>)</title>
<p>Landfill-site stabilization evaluation included three evaluation factors (leachate, landfill gas, and refuse). <italic>E<sub>j</sub></italic> of each factor was calculated according to:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula3-0734242X11413328">
<label>(2)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math3-0734242X11413328">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mstyle displaystyle="true">
<mml:munderover>
<mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
</mml:munderover>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mstyle>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula3-0734242X11413328" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11413328-eq3.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p>where <italic>n</italic> is the parameter value for each factor; <italic>I<sub>j</sub>
</italic> is the evaluation index of parameter <italic>j</italic>.</p>
<p>Take the leachate factor as an example, on the assumption that the values of <italic>I</italic><sub>COD</sub>, <italic>I</italic><sub>BOD</sub>, <italic>I</italic><sub>NH3-N</sub> calculated according to <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula1-0734242X11413328">Equation (1)</xref> were 171.4, 120 and 89, respectively, then the evaluation index for leachate factor (<italic>E</italic><sub>leachate</sub>) was calculated as follows:</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula4-0734242X11413328">
<mml:math display="block" id="math4-0734242X11413328">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>leachate</mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>171</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>120</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>89</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>126</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>8</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula4-0734242X11413328" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11413328-eq4.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0734242X11413328">
<title>Calculation of comprehensive evaluation index of stabilization (I)</title>
<p>After <italic>E<sub>j</sub></italic> of each evaluation factor was calculated, <italic>E<sub>j</sub></italic> was sorted from large to small. Assuming the sorting result was <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub> &gt; <italic>E</italic><sub>2</sub> &gt; <italic>E</italic><sub>3</sub>, and that <italic>X</italic> = <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>Y</italic> = (<italic>E</italic><sub>2</sub> + <italic>E</italic><sub>3</sub>)/2, then <italic>I</italic> can be calculated as follows (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0734242X11413328">Jiang et al. 2009</xref>):</p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula5-0734242X11413328">
<label>(3)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math5-0734242X11413328">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>If</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>Y</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>X</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>text</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.75em"/>
<mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>15</mml:mn>
<mml:msqrt>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msup>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msqrt>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula5-0734242X11413328" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11413328-eq5.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
<p><disp-formula id="disp-formula6-0734242X11413328">
<label>(4)</label>
<mml:math display="block" id="math6-0734242X11413328">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>If</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>5</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>Y</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>X</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mspace width="0.25em"/>
<mml:mtext>text</mml:mtext>
<mml:mspace width="0.75em"/>
<mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>15</mml:mn>
<mml:msqrt>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msup>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mi>Y</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msqrt>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula6-0734242X11413328" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11413328-eq6.tif"/>
</disp-formula></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0734242X11413328">
<title>Stabilization levels of landfill-site evaluation</title>
<p>Stabilization levels of landfill sites were classified into seven grades based on I (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0734242X11413328">Table 3</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0734242X11413328">Jiang et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0734242X11413328" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Classes of landfill stabilization</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0734242X11413328" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11413328-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Comprehensive assessment index</td>
<td>0–57</td>
<td>58–115</td>
<td>116–230</td>
<td>231–345</td>
<td>346–460</td>
<td>461–575</td>
<td>&gt; 576</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Stabilization degree</td>
<td>Very stable</td>
<td>stable</td>
<td>Moderately stable</td>
<td>Basically stable</td>
<td>Moderately unstable</td>
<td>Unstable</td>
<td>Very unstable</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0734242X11413328" sec-type="results|discussion">
<title>Results and discussion</title>
<sec id="section18-0734242X11413328">
<title>Stabilization properties of refuse</title>
<p>Refuse properties are key factors that reflect the degree of landfill stabilization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0734242X11413328">Haarstrick et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0734242X11413328">Kelly et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0734242X11413328">Wall and Zeiss, 1993</xref>). VS, TOC, and BDM were the main parameters used to determine refuse stability. Refuse properties in SLR and ALR are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0734242X11413328">Figure 2</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0734242X11413328" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Stabilization properties of refuse.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11413328-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The VS and TOC of the final refuse were greatly reduced in contrast to those in fresh refuse: from 57.2% to 15.8–17.4% and from 26.9% to 7.4–8.2%, respectively. This shows that refuse organic matter had mostly decomposed after a period of 3 years. The VS of final refuse in the SLR (15.8%) was lower than that of the ALR (19.1%). A <italic>t</italic>-test using the VS data of SLR and ALR refuse showed that the landfill operation significantly influenced (<italic>p &lt; </italic>0.05) refuse decomposition.</p>
<p>The BDM decreased from 18.0% of fresh refuse to 9.9%–11.3% of final refuse, similar values to those reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0734242X11413328">Yang et al. (2007)</xref> (9.8%) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0734242X11413328">Zhao et al. (2000)</xref> (8.9%) for landfill analysis after 5 years. The SLR facilitates refuse decomposition, as shown by the result that the BDM of final refuse in SLR (9.9%) was significantly (<italic>p &lt; </italic>0.05) lower than that of ALR (11.3%). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0734242X11413328">Figure 2</xref> shows a decrease in BDM by 50%, while VS was reduced by 70%. This inconsistency may be attributed to the fact that more VS granules had been leached out.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0734242X11413328">
<title>Leachate characteristics</title>
<sec id="section20-0734242X11413328">
<title>Chemical oxygen demand</title>
<p>The variation in COD concentration in leachate of SLR differs from that of ALR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0734242X11413328">Figure 3</xref>). After one month, a stable decreasing trend in COD concentration was observed in SLR, while in ALR it did not fluctuate greatly after 500 days. This shows that the buffer capacity of the organic load of SLR was better than for ALR. It may be due to the fact that there is a larger aerobic zone in the SLR, resulting in more stable and complete degradation of organic components than in the ALR. After 600 days, COD maintained a stable concentration (250–300 mg L<sup>−1</sup>) in SLR, whereas in ALR the COD concentration varied in the range 600–2000 mg L<sup>−1</sup>. From the COD variation, it can be concluded that the leachate attained stability more easily in SLR than in ALR.</p>
<fig id="fig3-0734242X11413328" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Concentration and cumulative production of COD in leachate (a) concentration in SLR, (b) concentration in ALR, (c) cumulative production of SLR, (d) cumulative production of ALR.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11413328-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>For the entire landfill stabilization process, COD concentration in SLR was lower than in ALR and dropped ultimately to 260 mg L<sup>−1</sup> and 700 mg L<sup>−1</sup>, with an overall reduction of 97.00 and 91.95%, respectively. The cumulative COD generation from ALR (599 kg) was almost two times higher than that from SLR (308 kg). Leachate recirculation to SLR promoted a more complete organic matter degradation than in ALR.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-0734242X11413328">
<title>Biochemical Oxygen Demand<sub>5</sub></title>
<p>Variations in biochemical ozyen demand after 5 days (BOD<sub>5</sub>) between the two landfills showed a similar trend to COD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0734242X11413328">Figure 4</xref>). The initial BOD<sub>5</sub> concentration in SLR was 3.8 g L<sup>−1</sup> and decreased ultimately to 0.03 g L<sup>−1</sup>, with a reduction of 99.21%. In ALR, the initial BOD<sub>5</sub> concentration decreased from 3.92 to 0.12 g L<sup>−1</sup>, with a 96.94% reduction. The cumulative generation of BOD<sub>5</sub> from ALR (237 kg) was more than two times higher than that of SLR (111 kg).</p>
<fig id="fig4-0734242X11413328" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Concentration and cumulative production of BOD<sub>5</sub> in leachate (a) concentration in SLR, (b) concentration in ALR, (c) cumulative production of SLR, (d) cumulative production of ALR.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11413328-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-0734242X11413328">
<title>BOD<sub>5</sub>/COD ratio and pH</title>
<p>The BOD<sub>5</sub>/COD ratio indicates the amount of biodegradable leachate compounds and is an important parameter for assessing landfill stability. As organic biodegradation occurs, the BOD<sub>5</sub>/COD ratio decreases. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0734242X11413328">Figure 5</xref> shows that BOD<sub>5</sub>/COD ratios of ALR were higher than those of SLR, which means that more soluble organics were dissolved into the leachate in ALR and also reflects the fact that organics were not degraded sufficiently in ALR to achieve prolonged stability. The average BOD<sub>5</sub>/COD ratio for SLR and ALR were 0.12 and 0.17, respectively, at the end of the experiment.</p>
<fig id="fig5-0734242X11413328" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Leachate pH and BOD<sub>5</sub>/COD (a) pH in SLR, (b) pH in ALR, (c) BOD<sub>5</sub>/COD of SLR, (d) BOD<sub>5</sub>/COD of ALR.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11413328-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Variations in pH over time are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0734242X11413328">Figure 5</xref>. In the prophase initial phase of landfill, the pH of both SLR and ALR was low (5.6–6.5), but the difference between the sites increased with time. The pH of SLR was &gt; 7 after 130 days and surpassed 8 on the 390th day. In contrast, the pH of ALR was<italic> &lt; </italic>7 before the 340th day and<italic> &lt; </italic>8 throughout the experiment.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-0734242X11413328">
<title>NH<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup>N and NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup></title>
<p>Leachate ammonia is mainly originated from biodegradation of organic compounds containing nitrogen. One significant characteristic of leachate is the high ammonia concentration, which limits microbial activity and slows waste biodegradation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0734242X11413328">Robinson, 1992</xref>). Organic nitrogen and ammonium are oxidized through a series of compounds, resulting in nitrate under aerobic conditions. In previous research, it was shown that both aerobic and anaerobic zones exist in a semi-aerobic landfill layer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0734242X11413328">Liu et al., 2006</xref>), and therefore both nitrification and denitrification are possible. Results for ammonium and nitrate concentrations are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0734242X11413328">Figure 6</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig6-0734242X11413328" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Leachate ammonia and nitrate concentration (a) ammonia concentration in SLR, (b) ammonia concentration in ALR, (c) nitrate concentration in SLR, (d) nitrate concentration in ALR.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11413328-fig6.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The SLR did not present ammonia accumulation in the initial stage, similar to ALR. This may be because aerobic and anaerobic zones coexist in the SLR, and ammonia was transformed to nitrate via nitrification. Degradable COD in the leachate being quickly removed was another reason for rapid ammonia reduction. The final ammonia concentrations for SLR and ALR declined to 50 mg L<sup>−1</sup> and 510 mg<sup>−1</sup>, respectively. Cumulative ammonia production in SLR was 50 kg and in ALR 104 kg (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0734242X11413328">Figure 7</xref>), suggesting that SLR is an effective mechanism for removing ammonium. Together, these results indicate accelerated landfill stabilization in SLR.</p>
<p>Variation in NO<sub>3</sub><sup>−</sup> profile over time is also shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0734242X11413328">Figure 6</xref>. The nitrate concentration in ALR was much lower than in SLR, indicating that nitrification in the latter was stronger. Cumulative nitrate production in SLR and ALR were 13.5 and 0.6 kg, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0734242X11413328">Figure 7</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig7-0734242X11413328" position="float">
<label>Figure 7.</label>
<caption>
<p>Leachate ammonia and nitrate cumulative production (a) ammonia cumulative production of SLR, (b) ammonia cumulative production of ALR, (c) nitrate cumulative production of SLR, (d) nitrate cumulative production of ALR.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11413328-fig7.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section24-0734242X11413328">
<title>Landfill gas</title>
<p>Variations in landfill-gas composition (CH<sub>4</sub>, CO<sub>2</sub>, and O<sub>2</sub> in volume percentage) over time are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0734242X11413328">Figures 8</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0734242X11413328">9</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0734242X11413328">10</xref>, respectively. The trends for CH<sub>4</sub> in SLR and ALR gas were similar, both at lower levels in initial phaseprophase (ca. 180th day) and reached their highest levels from the 230th to 400th day. Methane concentrations in SLR and ALR gas were 20–28% and 40–60%, respectively. Methane concentrations then decreased and fluctuated from 10 to 20% and 32 to 40%, in SLR and ALR gas, respectively. Throughout the experiment, the average CH<sub>4</sub> concentration in ALR gas (36.7%) was higher than in SLR gas (14.5%). It can be concluded that CH<sub>4</sub> production decreased effectively with leachate recirculation in the SLR.</p>
<fig id="fig8-0734242X11413328" position="float">
<label>Figure 8.</label>
<caption>
<p>Concentration (volume percent) of CH<sub>4</sub> in landfill gas.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11413328-fig8.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig9-0734242X11413328" position="float">
<label>Figure 9.</label>
<caption>
<p>Concentration (volume percent) of O<sub>2</sub> in landfill gas.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11413328-fig9.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig10-0734242X11413328" position="float">
<label>Figure 10.</label>
<caption>
<p>Concentration (volume percent) of CO<sub>2</sub> in landfill gas.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11413328-fig10.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The lower production of CH<sub>4</sub> in SLR compared to ALR gas may be attributed to oxygenated areas existing in the SLR. O<sub>2</sub> concentration in SLR landfill gas was much higher than in ALR. The O<sub>2</sub> concentration of SLR gas was ∼4.5–8.3% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0734242X11413328">Figure 9</xref>). In ALR, O<sub>2</sub> could be detected in the initial phaseprophase (∼1–4%), probably present in refuse pore spaces at the beginning of landfilling. After this, the concentration was below detection limits.</p>
<p>The primary reason for lower pollutant concentration in leachate and CH<sub>4</sub> in landfill gas in SLR was refuse aerobic degradation, in which organics were degraded completely to produce CO<sub>2</sub> and H<sub>2</sub>O. Thus, average CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in SLR gas (22.6%) was higher than in ALR gas (15.1%) throughout the experiment. The largest difference occurred from the 260th to 370th day, when CO<sub>2</sub> concentration reached 26.5% in SLR and 11% in ALR gas. The CH<sub>4</sub> concentration in ALR gas was much higher than in SLR. The sums of the concentrations of methane, oxygen, and carbon dioxide in ALR and SLR after 900 days amounted to approximately 50 and 42%, respectively. This difference is attributed to the difference in nitrogen concentration between ALR and SLR.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section25-0734242X11413328">
<title>Landfill settlement</title>
<p>Landfill stabilization is characterized by settling and the reduction ratio. Settling arises from organic biodegradation dominating in the long term (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0734242X11413328">Sowers, 1973</xref>). Settling in SLR and ALR was 1.70 and 1.40 m, respectively, and the corresponding volume reduction was 30.91 and 25.45%.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section26-0734242X11413328">
<title>Stabilization evaluation</title>
<p>Leachate, landfill gas, final refuse properties, and landfill settling were the main factors characterized in landfill stabilization. Based on the feasibility of the operation and sensitivity of factors for characterizing stabilization, leachate, landfill gas and final refuse properties were adopted as evaluating factors; the parameters used were COD, BOD<sub>5</sub>, NH<sub>3</sub>-N, BOD<sub>5</sub>/COD ratio, volume percentage of CH<sub>4</sub> in landfill gas, and VS content in final refuse. These were determined according to the experimental results (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0734242X11413328">Table 4</xref>). The resulting evaluation is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0734242X11413328">Table 5</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-0734242X11413328" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Parameter values for each evaluation factor</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0734242X11413328" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11413328-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Item</th>
<th align="left">COD (mg L<sup>–1</sup>)</th>
<th align="left">BOD<sub>5</sub> (mg L<sup>–1</sup>)</th>
<th align="left">NH<sub>3</sub>-N (mg L<sup>–1</sup>)</th>
<th align="left">BOD<sub>5</sub>/COD</th>
<th align="left">CH<sub>4</sub> (%)</th>
<th align="left">VS (%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>SLR</td>
<td>260</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>0.12</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>15.8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ALR</td>
<td>700</td>
<td>119</td>
<td>510</td>
<td>0.17</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>19.1</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table5-0734242X11413328" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Results of landfill site stabilization evaluation</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-0734242X11413328" xlink:href="10.1177_0734242X11413328-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Item</th>
<th align="left" colspan="3">Each factor index (<italic>E</italic>)</th>
<th align="left">Comprehensive assessment index (<italic>I</italic>)</th>
<th align="left">Stabilization degree</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Leachate</th>
<th align="left">LG</th>
<th align="left">Aged refuse</th>
<th/>
<th/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>SLR</td>
<td>120</td>
<td>200</td>
<td>108</td>
<td>200</td>
<td>Stable moderately</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ALR</td>
<td>199</td>
<td>355</td>
<td>141</td>
<td>355</td>
<td>Unstable moderately</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>As shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0734242X11413328">Table 4</xref>, each SLR parameter value was lower than that for ALR. The value for SLR was moderately stable (<italic>I</italic> = 200), while that for ALR was less stable (<italic>I</italic> = 355). Landfill gas was the primary factor in landfill stabilization evaluation since it had the highest factor index, followed by leachate and final refuse (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0734242X11413328">Table 5</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section27-0734242X11413328" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>This study investigated the influence of landfill operation with leachate recirculation on the stabilization processes. From our experimental results, the following conclusions can be drawn. VS, TOC, and BDM content of final refuse in SLR were all lower than in ALR, and settling and the reduction ratio were higher. Reduction of organic pollutants and ammonia in the SLR leachate was higher compared to the ALR leachate; the CH<sub>4</sub> content in SLR landfill gas decreased significantly. Quantitative evaluation of landfill stabilization suggested that the process was affected greatly by landfill operation. Leachate recirculated to the SLR was more beneficial than to the ALR in accelerating stability.</p>
<p>In a large-scale <italic>in situ</italic> experiment, it is difficult to seal the landfill, and so landfill gas generation cannot be measured, nor can the total mass of final refuse be weighed. Thus, no attempt was made to establish a mass balance or relate COD (or N) in the leachate to losses in the refuse mass or emitted gas. In addition, the results from a limited batch experiment differ from those in practical landfilling in semi-continuous operation owing to characteristics of the landfill, as well as climatic conditions.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>This work was financially supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China with Grant No. 50908220, and the central level, nonprofit, scientific research institutes for basic R &amp; D special fund business with Grant No. 2007KYYW24.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>APHA, AWWA, WEF</collab> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Standard Methods for Water and Wastewater Examination</source>, <edition>21st edn.</edition> <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Public Health Association</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berge</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reinhart</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dietz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>In situ ammonia removal in bioreactor landfill leachate</article-title>. <source>Waste Management</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>334</fpage>–<lpage>343</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Calli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mertoglu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roest</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Inanc</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Comparison of long term performances and final microbial compositions of anaerobic reactors treating landfill leachate</article-title>. <source>Bioresource Technology</source> <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>641</fpage>–<lpage>647</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>HaarstrickA Mora-Naranjo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meima</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hempel</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Modeling anaerobic degradation in municipal landfill</article-title>. <source>Environmental Engineering Science</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>471</fpage>–<lpage>484</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hanashima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matsufuji</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Higuchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>A method of designing leachate treatment systems for landfill sites</article-title>. <source>Cities and Waste</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hanashima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Pollution control and stabilization process by semi-aerobic landfill type. The Fukuoka method</article-title>. <source>Sardinia 99 Seventh Waste Management and Landfill Symposium</source>. <publisher-loc>Cagliari</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CISA</publisher-name>, <fpage>313</fpage>–<lpage>325</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A new method applied for the evaluation of municipal solid waste landfill stabilization</article-title>. <source>Environmental Engineering Science</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>1123</fpage>–<lpage>1130</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shearer</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Relationships between analytical methods utilized as tools in the evaluation of landfill waste stability</article-title>. <source>Waste Management</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>1349</fpage>–<lpage>1356</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>QF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Determination of oxygen consuming radius in semi-aerobic landfilling structure</article-title>. <source>China Environmental Science</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Matsufuji</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Landfill site improvement in design for sanitary landfill in Malaysia</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamid</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds.) <source>Hazardous Waste Regulations and Management</source>. <publisher-loc>Kuala Lumpur</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ensearch, Ministry of Construction P.R. China, 1999</publisher-name>. <comment>Municipal domestic refuse-determination of pH-glass electrode method</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>NBSC (National Bureau of Statistics of China)</collab> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Yearbook of China Statistics – 2009</source>. <publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>China Statistics Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pohland</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Landfill bioreactors: historical perspective, fundamental principles and new horizons in design and operations</article-title>. <source>EPA Seminar Publication: Landfill Bioreactor Design and Operation</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>US Environmental Protection Agency</publisher-name>, <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reinhart</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Changes in landfill gas quality as a result of controlled air injection</article-title>. <source>Environmental Science and Technology</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1029</fpage>–<lpage>1034</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reinhart</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Al-Yousfi</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The impact of leachate recirculation on municipal solid waste landfill operating characters</article-title>. <source>Waste Management and Research</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>337</fpage>–<lpage>346</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reinhart</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Landfill Bioreactor Design and Operation</source>. <publisher-loc>FL, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CRC Press LLC, Boca Raton</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Leachate collection, treatment and disposal</article-title>. <source>Water and Environmental Management</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>332</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sanphotia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Towprayoon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chaiprasertc</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nopharatana</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The effects of leachate recirculation with supplemental water addition on methane production and waste decomposition in a simulated tropical landfill</article-title>. <source>Journal of Environmental Management</source> <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sinan Bilgili</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Demir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zkaya</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Influence of leachate recirculation on aerobic and anaerobic decomposition of solid wastes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Hazardous Materials</source> <volume>143</volume>: <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>183</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sowers</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>Settlement of waste disposal fills</article-title>, In: <conf-name>Proceeding of 8th international Conference on Soil Mechanics and Foundation Engineering USSR</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Moscow</conf-loc>, pp. <fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>210</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tada</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hanaoka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sonodac</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ooic</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sawayama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Effect of natural zeolite on methane production for anaerobic digestion of ammonium rich organic sludge</article-title>. <source>Bioresource Technology</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>459</fpage>–<lpage>464</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zeiss</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Municipal landfill biodegradation andsettlement</article-title>. <source>Journal of Environment Engineering</source> <volume>121</volume>: <fpage>214</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Evaluating of refuse landf ill site stabilization</article-title>. <source>Environmental Sanitation Engineering</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>157</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Analysis of waste BDM and its application</article-title>. <source>Environmental Sanitation Engineering</source> <volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>6</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matsufuji</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>QF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Research on leachate recirculation from different types of landfills</article-title>. <source>Waste Management</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>815</fpage>–<lpage>824</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Study on degradation regulation in landfill</article-title>. <source>The Administration and Technique of Environmental Monitoring</source> <volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>43</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0734242X11413328">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zao</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Degradation of refuse in large-scale landfill</article-title>. <source>Acta Scientiae Circumstantiae</source> <volume>20</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>736</fpage>–<lpage>740</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>