<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ISS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spiss</journal-id>
<journal-title>International Sociology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0268-5809</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7242</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0268580913477954</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0268580913477954</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Reviews: Political identities and struggles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book review: Todd Landman and Edzia Carvalho, <italic>Measuring Human Rights</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Pospieszna</surname><given-names>Paulina</given-names></name>
</contrib>
 <aff id="aff1-0268580913477954">University of Mannheim, Germany</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>28</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>168</fpage>
<lpage>170</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Landman</surname><given-names>Todd</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>Edzia</given-names></name>
</person-group>, <source>Measuring Human Rights</source>, <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>, <year>2010</year>; <page-count count="162 "/>pp.: ISBN <isbn>9780415446495</isbn>, US<price>$123.46</price> (hbk), <isbn>9780415446501</isbn>, US<price>$4.87</price> (pbk)
</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">International Sociological Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Human rights</kwd>
<kwd>measurement in the social sciences</kwd></kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
 <p>The topic of human rights is certainly timely and will likely become even more relevant in the future. Many excellent new books in social sciences appear frequently today, contributing to a wide range of research and insight on human rights. The book by Landman and Carvalho is one of them. It demonstrates up-to-date efforts in measuring human rights and difficulties in creating a perfect measure. Therefore, scholars or practitioners who want to enhance their knowledge about strengths and weaknesses of human rights indicators, or aim to improve the way they monitor or analyse human rights, will definitely benefit from reading this fairly comprehensive overview.</p>
<p>Before the reader learns about the background to the development of human rights measures, their usefulness and limitations, the first three chapters locate the book in the academic literature, define the concept of human rights and explain the road from conceptualization to measurement. The authors do not engage in debate on the origin of human rights, but rather accept the meaning that is established in international law and commonly interpreted by institutions. However, the authors make an effort to delineate secondary levels of the human rights concept, such as principle, policy and practice, and thoroughly discuss them. The authors also carefully define ‘concepts’, ‘category’, ‘dimension’ and ‘indicators’ of human rights that may sound a little mystifying for beginner readers in human rights, but selected examples, tables and figures allow for a better comprehension of these terms. Undoubtedly, knowing the earlier work by Landman or Carvalho would be additionally helpful while reading Chapter 2. After being introduced to the concept of human rights, in the next section of the book, the reader learns what is the purpose and usefulness of measurement, and how the concept can be measured. The authors stress that the main goal of measurement is to provide a valid, meaningful and reliable measure of human rights through converting conceptual understanding of human rights into a quantitative score of some kind. Practitioners and academics can use such scores for monitoring purposes, demonstrating the improvement or deterioration in rights, for classifying states into different categories with respect to human rights protection/violation, and finally for testing the relationship between measures of human rights and other variables. Borrowing from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0268580913477954">Adcock and Collier (2001)</xref>, the authors demonstrate how the concept of human rights goes through different levels of measurement: from broad concept that is to be measured, to systematized and operationalized concepts, which finally produce the actual scores.</p>
<p>In Chapter 3, Landman and Carvahlo present their arguments to which they will try to convince the reader in the chapters to follow. They state that human rights are in many ways unobservable phenomena, which are not always easy to measure. Moreover, they argue that the efforts to develop measures have primarily focused on the government respect for civil and political rights, and less on providing measures of the protection and fulfilment of these rights as well as less on other types of rights (pp. 43–44). Finally, the authors acknowledge that progress has been made in the development of better measures, but methodological challenges associated with source materials and the measurement process itself remain.</p>
<p>The major merit of this book is that it is a valuable source of information that, as the authors highlight themselves, provides the most comprehensive review of human rights measures. The authors consequently specify the generation, design, use and limitation of each measure by which results are grouped: events-based, standard-based, survey-based and socioeconomic and administrative statistics. That said, I should briefly underline a number of issues raised by the authors in the chapters devoted to each human rights measure. For example, events-based statistics, namely ‘who did what to whom’, usually provide detailed information about the human rights violations that can be taken from found or narrative data as well as from official statements. Such data are particularly useful for the project seeking to analyse violations of human rights that have taken place. However, the authors suggest that future developments should include other violations of human rights than just counting deaths and disappearances, so that everyday violations, not just in moments of crisis, can be monitored. The next chapter focuses on standard-based measure that codes country-level information about human rights on a standardized scale that is ordinal and limited in range and provides the ability for analysts to compare performance of countries across space and over time. However, the authors point out that this measure is not suitable for single-country analysis across a wide range of human rights, because the score of a country does not change significantly over time, unless a country experiences significant political transition or civil conflict that may bring some changes in the human rights situation. I think that the authors make here a good point that is often neglected. Also, the authors demonstrate that these measures are often limited to a particular set of human rights, which supports their statement made earlier that political and civil rights are given primary focus in measuring human rights. Only a few data sources, like Cingranelli and Richards (CIRI) human rights data, have broken new ground by developing, for example, scales for workers’ rights and women’s economic and social rights. Furthermore, survey-based measures, presented in the next chapter, are often based on broad questions that ask about perceptions or experience of human rights in a given country rather than about specific rights. Given this gap in measurement, the authors show that socioeconomic and administrative statistics, which are indirect measures, have often been used to compensate for the lack of direct measures of other types of rights. The reader learns that, for example, such measures as Human Development Indicators (HDI) or the Physical Quality of Life Index (PQLI) have often been used as proxy measures of economic and social rights, or measures of the right to health, life and education.</p>
<p>By demonstrating the limitations of each measure of human rights presented in the book, Landman and Carvalho convincingly support their argument that there are many methodological challenges. A reader is alerted to weaknesses associated with each measure, and the trade-off that each measure brings. Whereas, consistency in the use of the same sources can be good, the measure can suffer from bias associated with an over-reliance on too few sources. Furthermore, on the one hand the major advantage of survey-based measures is that they use random samples, but on the other hand in order for the measure to be reliable, the sample sizes have to be large to capture significant numbers of people from various groups in society suffering human rights violations. Also, the authors discuss at length all stages in carrying out a survey, including survey design, sampling and inferences, and demonstrate how different types of error as well as problems can lead to an overestimation or underestimation of human rights problems. Additional limitations to all measures include: when coding is done by one team, when subnational variations exist within a country, and finally when ‘variance truncation’ occurs during the coding of all countries on a limited scale (much of that variation is lost into the various categories of the scale). In the case of socioeconomic data, which are collected by states, additional limitation relates to the question as to whether these data can be trusted, and the extent to which they reflect reality.</p>
<p>In short, the authors provide a greater clarity about the measures of human rights, and draw attention to the possible conceptual and methodological problems. Academics and practitioners need to continue to improve the degree to which they monitor, measure and analyse human rights, and this book certainly can be very helpful in achieving this.</p>
</body>
<back>
<bio>
<p><bold>Paulina Pospieszna</bold> has a PhD in political science from the University of Alabama, USA and is a Postdoctoral Fellow in the School of Social Sciences, University of Mannheim, Germany. Her main research interest is civil conflict mediation, post-conflict reconstruction, democratic transformation, links between international and domestic non-governmental actors and the role of political institutions. <italic>Address:</italic> Political Science IV, University of Mannheim, Parkring 47, 68159 Mannheim, Germany. Email: <email>paulina.pospieszna@uni-mannheim.de</email>.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>Reference</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0268580913477954">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Adcock</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Collier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Measurement validity: A shared standard for qualitative and quantitative research</article-title>. <source>The American Political Science Review</source> <volume>95</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>546</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>