<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TMT</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptmt</journal-id>
<journal-title>Traumatology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1534-7656</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1085-9373</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1534765612459892</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1534765612459892</article-id>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Dynamics of Cumulative Trauma and Trauma Types in Adults Patients With Psychiatric Disorders</article-title>
<subtitle>Two Cross-Cultural Studies</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>Ibrahim A.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1534765612459892">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Fawzi</surname><given-names>Mounir H.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1534765612459892">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Fawzi</surname><given-names>Mohab M.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1534765612459892">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1534765612459892"><label>1</label>Center for Cumulative Trauma Studies, Stone Mountain, GA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1534765612459892"><label>2</label>Zagazig University, Zagazig, Egypt</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1534765612459892">Ibrahim A. Kira, PhD, Center for Cumulative Trauma Studies, 4906 Woodhurst Way, Decatur, GA, 30088, USA. Email: <email>kiraaref@aol.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>179</fpage>
<lpage>195</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>There is an intricate divide between three major valid paradigms in studying traumatic processes: The psychiatric paradigm that focused mostly on the survival types of traumas and on posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD), the psychoanalytic and developmental theories that focused on the effects of abandonment, maltreatment and betrayal, and the intergroup paradigm that focused on discrimination, genocide, and torture. The goal was to test the validity and utility of a framework that integrated the three trauma paradigms on mental health clients (MHC). Two studies were conducted in the USA and Egypt. In the first study 399 MHC were tested using cumulative trauma scale that utilizes the new framework and measures of mental health variables. The second study tested 432 MHC in a university psychiatric clinic in Egypt, utilizing comparable measures. The trauma profiles were examined and matched to the symptom profiles, psychiatric comorbidities, and global level of functioning. Egyptian participants reported relatively higher level of poverty, personal identity traumas (i.e., sexual abuse), and role identity traumas, while participants in the U.S. sample, that included refugees in addition to Americans, have more traumas of oppression, discrimination, torture, uprootedness, and abandonment. While cumulative trauma was associated with physical and mental health symptoms and comorbidities in both studies, different trauma profile of each predicted different configurations of symptoms. Current studies provided evidence of the validity and utility of the integrated new traumatology model, and its potential contribution to driving trauma field forward.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>trauma profiles</kwd>
<kwd>cumulative trauma</kwd>
<kwd>Type III trauma</kwd>
<kwd>developmentally based integrative traumatology framework (DBTF)</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>There is an intricate divide between three major paradigms in studying traumatic processes: the psychiatric paradigm that focused mostly on the survival types of traumatic stress and on posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) model (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-1534765612459892">van der Kolk, Weisaeth, &amp; van der Hart,1996</xref>), the psychoanalytic, and developmental paradigms that focused more on studying the effects of abandonment, child maltreatment, and other betrayal traumas in early childhood (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1534765612459892">Bowlby, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1534765612459892">Cassidy, &amp; Shaver, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1534765612459892">Freyd, DePrince, &amp; Gleaves, 2007</xref>), and the intergroup paradigm as evidenced in studying discrimination, genocide, torture, and other shared politically motivated micro and macro aggressions (e.g., for theoretical analysis of discrimination as a trauma, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1534765612459892">Helms, Nicolas, &amp; Green, 2010</xref>). Until recently, the three paradigms and their perspective theories and research, while some times overlap; have developed along relatively independent lines. In the first paradigm, trauma is defined as an event that involves actual or threatened death or serious injury or a threat to the physical integrity of self or others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1534765612459892">American Psychiatric Association, 2004</xref>), and has potential of leading to PTSD symptoms.</p>
<p>In the second and third paradigms, trauma is mostly a process that can be triggered by internal or external events that threaten the person’s physical, personal, or social identities and this/her basic autonomy or dependence needs and have potential of yielding different symptoms that may include PTSD, and other syndromes(and not only PTSD). American Psychological Association APA trauma group’s (currently APA division 56) definition of trauma as “A process that leads to the disorganization of a core sense of self and world and leaves an indelible mark on one’s world views that psychological disorders often follow upon exposure to” represents this approach.</p>
<p>In the second paradigm traumatization process is mostly triggered by the caregiver failing to satisfy her/his natural responsibility to the dependency needs of the child, yielding feelings of insecurity and betrayal. Attachment disruptions and child maltreatment, in general, drives the child’s pathology in different areas of infant, adolescent, and adult life (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1534765612459892">Cassidy &amp; Shaver, 1999</xref>). An important aspect of attachment theory is its assertion that healthy dependence on a reliably sensitive and responsive <italic>attachment figure</italic> is important for optimal functioning, well-being, and child subsequent development toward autonomy and interdependence (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1534765612459892">Bowlby, 1988</xref>). Evidence for this process has been shown particularly with regard to mother–child relationships (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1534765612459892">Cassidy, &amp; Shaver, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1534765612459892">Kobak, Little, Race, &amp; Acosta, 2001</xref>). However, attachment disruptions can continue and accumulate during early childhood and adolescence through, father abandonment, foster care placements, frequent changes in caregivers, causing cumulative attachment traumas, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1534765612459892">Kira, 2001</xref>), and developmental disorders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-1534765612459892">van der Kolk, 2005</xref>), and suppress child IQ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1534765612459892">Kira, Somers, Lewandowski, &amp; Chiodo, 2012</xref>).</p>
<p>Child maltreatment, other than attachment disruptions, is one of the most stressful experiences that affect the development of children (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1534765612459892">Cicchetti &amp; Lynch, 1995</xref>). Betrayal trauma theory (for a review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1534765612459892">Freyd et al., 2007</xref>) suggests that when a victim is dependent on the person that caused the harm, feeling of betrayal is implicated as one possible mechanism by which individuals may maintain distress and develop subsequent symptoms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1534765612459892">Freyd et al., 2007</xref>). The literature on child maltreatment reveals its significant associations with different psychiatric symptoms and diagnoses, including depression, anxiety, conduct disorder, PTSD, personality disorders, substance abuse, suicidal and self-injurious behavior, somatization, and dissociation (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1534765612459892">Cicchetti &amp; Lynch, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1534765612459892">De Bellis, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1534765612459892">Kessler, Davis, &amp; Kendler, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1534765612459892">Macfie, Cicchetti, &amp; Toth, 2001</xref>; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1534765612459892">Baer, &amp; Martinez, 2006</xref> for a review).</p>
<p>In the third trauma paradigm the traumatization process is triggered by systemic social structural violence and interpersonal and intergroup macro and micro aggressions. Macro aggressions, for example targeted hate crimes, extreme poverty, cast system, and slavery (present, past or even those historical or cross-generationally transmitted), reverberate through secondary and tertiary interdependence and traumatization dynamics to those who belong to the same targeted group. While micro aggressions (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-1534765612459892">Sue, 2010</xref>), demean, or exclude the targeted persons, they act as reminders of the macro aggressions and their threats, triggering feeling of annihilation anxiety, societal betrayal, stereotype threats, decreased self-esteem, and self-efficacy, and trigger the process of retraumatization.</p>
<p>The links between perceived ethnic discrimination and poor physical and mental health are fairly well-established (for meta-analysis see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1534765612459892">Pascoe &amp; Richman, 2009</xref>). Prospective studies show that perceived ethnic discrimination precedes poor psychological and physical health, rather than the other way around (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1534765612459892">Brody et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1534765612459892">Gee &amp; Waslemann, 2009</xref>). Similar results were found for discrimination of sexual minorities (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1534765612459892">Gilman et al., 2001</xref>); Asian Americans (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1534765612459892">Gee, Spencer, Chen, &amp; Takeuchi, 2007</xref>), Mexican Americans (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1534765612459892">Flores, Tschann, Dimas, Pasch, &amp; de Groat, 2010</xref>), immigrants (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1534765612459892">Berg et al., 2011</xref>), and refugees (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1534765612459892">Kira, Smith, Lewandowski, &amp;Templin 2010a</xref>). Gender discrimination, was found to have negative mental health effects on females (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1534765612459892">Kira, Ashby, Lewandowski, Smith, &amp; Odenat, 2012d</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1534765612459892">Kira et al., 2010a</xref>).</p>
<p>To summarize, each of the three paradigms while developed along different lines, sometimes overlapping, found severe physical and mental health consequences for the trauma types that were of their focus. An important clinical consideration is that in clinical practice and research, focusing on a single trauma type (for example, hurricane) can be misleading, and is only legitimate, when the client has experienced only this trauma type in his life time, which may be a rare situation. Polyvictimization that involves one trauma type (e.g., child abuse), does not preclude the concurrent polyvctimization with another trauma type (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1534765612459892">Hamby, Finkelhor, Turner, &amp; Ormrod, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>A new bi-dimensional developmentally based trauma framework (DBTF) integrated these three main streams in a unified development-based traumatology perspective that promised to advance the understanding of the etiology of mental health symptoms (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1534765612459892">Kira, 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1534765612459892">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1534765612459892">Kira et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1534765612459892">Kira et al., 2008a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1534765612459892">Kira et al., 2010a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1534765612459892">2010b</xref>). The new DBTF that is empirically supported provided wider and defined boundaries of what are traumatic stressors and their cumulative dynamics. The first dimension of DBTF is horizontal and development-based and is mostly focused on human-made traumas and includes attachment traumas (e.g., abandonment by parents of a child), identity traumas are a violation of individuation process emerged in adolescence and adulthood, that has at least three or four subkinds: Personal identity trauma, (e.g., violation of self-autonomy by sexual abuse, incest and other betrayal traumas), collective identity trauma, (e.g., targeted genocide, holocaust, slavery, and discrimination), and role identity or self-actualization trauma, (e.g., significant loss of life-savings, serious business failure, get unexpectedly fired, failed or dropped out of school or college), and physical identity (physical survival). The source of physical trauma can be either internal, for example sever pain and life threatening illnesses, or external, for example, life threatening accident, or nature-made, for example major natural disaster. In addition, interdependence dynamics that are one of the landmarks of adolescent and adult development may yield socially made trauma. Socially made traumas include secondary (e.g., witnessing violence or media relevant violence exposure, compassion fatigue of therapist) and tertiary such as cross-generationally transmitted trauma, (e.g., historical trauma, cast systems and poverty or extreme inequality). Some traumas reverberate horizontally and vertically in the fabric of social network to produce waves of secondary and tertiary traumas and can continue cross-generationally. Most traumas yield different levels of feelings of insecurity, violation by others and or betrayal (betrayal in close relationship, and systemic structural betrayal by larger society or dominant groups) or self-betrayal (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1534765612459892">Freyd, 1996</xref>).</p>
<p>The second dimension in DBTF is more vertical in terms of changing degree or level of severity and chronicity, and is based on the objective characteristics of traumatic events. Traumatic events may include, at this level, at least two kinds: Single episode trauma (Type I; e.g., car accident) and complex traumas. Complex traumas, in terms of chronicity, include two kinds: Type II (repeated similar traumatic episodes that ceased, for example sexual abuse; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-1534765612459892">Terr, 1991</xref>), and Type III (continuous, repeated and ongoing, e.g. racism). Such socially made traumas are mostly inter-group and social structure-based traumas and include such conditions as extreme poverty, cast system, slavery, and backlash against minorities. The socially made traumas can be transmitted through secondary and tertiary traumatization dynamics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1534765612459892">Figley, 1995</xref>). The transmission course of socially made and other trauma types can either go in one step transmission, for example when it is transmitted from parent to child or vice versa, or in a multiple step transmission course. Multiple steps or cross-generation transmission of trauma (or tertiary trauma and beyond) can go either through family or through a collective experience (e.g., historical traumas, such as in the holocaust, and sociostructural traumas, such as in extreme poverty and relative deprivation; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1534765612459892">Cassiman, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1534765612459892">Kira, 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1534765612459892">2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1534765612459892">Kira et al., 2008a</xref>). Example of continuous collective identity traumas is protracted conflict. Examples of continuous chronic personal identity traumas are prostitution and trafficking. Type IV, in this taxonomy, is cumulative trauma (CT) across life time that have different cumulative dynamics. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1534765612459892">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1534765612459892">2</xref> illustrate some of the elements of this model, (for more clarifications see tables and diagrams published in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1534765612459892">Kira, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1534765612459892">Kira et al., 2008a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1534765612459892">Kira, Lewandowski, Somers, Yoon, &amp; Chiodo, 2012a</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1534765612459892" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>Illustration of the Horizontal and Vertical Dimensions of the DTBF.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1534765612459892" xlink:href="10.1177_1534765612459892-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="9">Human made<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="7">Person made<hr/></th>
<th/>
<th/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Taxonomy dimensions<hr/></th>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="5">Individuation identity formation<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Socially made<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="2">Development (Horizontal)/severity-chronicity(Vertical)</th>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Attachment<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Physical identity<hr/></th>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Interdependence<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="center">Nature made</th>
<th align="center">Child</th>
<th align="center">Adult</th>
<th align="center">Internal sources</th>
<th align="center">Outer sources</th>
<th align="center">Personal identity</th>
<th align="center">Collective identity</th>
<th align="center">Role identity</th>
<th align="center">Secondary</th>
<th align="center">Tertiary and beyond</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Type I</td>
<td>e.g., Tornado</td>
<td>e.g., Mother’s neglect</td>
<td>e.g., Failed relation</td>
<td>e.g., Severe pain</td>
<td>e.g., Car accident</td>
<td>e.g., Rape</td>
<td>e.g., Pearl Harbor attack</td>
<td>e.g., Serious failure school/business</td>
<td>e.g., Witness murder</td>
<td>Historical trauma</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Type II</td>
<td>e.g., Katrina epidemic</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>e.g., Life Threatening illness</td>
<td>e.g., Combat</td>
<td>e.g., Sexual abuse</td>
<td>e.g., Defeat/September 11, 2001</td>
<td>e.g., Drop-out/bankrupt</td>
<td>e.g., Domestic violence for child, therapist exposure (Vicarious trauma)</td>
<td>e.g., Genocide</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Type III continuous traumatic stress</td>
<td>Pathogens and ecology related traumas</td>
<td>Foster care</td>
<td/>
<td>Reproduction traumas</td>
<td>e.g., Violent conflict</td>
<td>Prostitution-trafficking</td>
<td>e.g., Racism slavery</td>
<td>e.g., Homeless</td>
<td>e.g., Violence media exposure</td>
<td>Systemic Structure violence e.g., Extreme Poverty- Cast system</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Type IV</td>
<td colspan="10">Unilateral and multilateral continuous traumatic stressors-Cumulative traumatic and nontraumatic stress across life span</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table2-1534765612459892" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption><p>Illustration of Some Elements of the Integrative DBTF Model, Sources, Types, Related Emotions and Associated Pathology.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1534765612459892" xlink:href="10.1177_1534765612459892-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Indirect/interdependence trauma dynamics<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-1534765612459892">a</xref></sup><hr/></th>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
<th/>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Direct traumas</th>
<th align="center">Secondary traumas</th>
<th align="center">Tertiary and beyond</th>
<th align="center">Potential related emotions</th>
<th align="center">Related pathology</th>
<th align="center">Trauma types</th>
<th align="center">Source of trauma</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Attachment trauma, e.g., mother’s abandonment</td>
<td>e.g., one step Transmission of attachment styles</td>
<td>Cross-generation flow of attachment styles</td>
<td>Attachment insecurity; betrayal by care-givers</td>
<td>Attachment and development disorders</td>
<td>Type II</td>
<td>Parents, caregivers</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Personal identity traumas e.g., rape, sexual abuse</td>
<td>Family members of the victim</td>
<td>traumatization flow to the community</td>
<td>Fear of self- or autonomy loss; betrayal by others</td>
<td>Complex PTSD</td>
<td>Type II</td>
<td>Person-made</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Collective identity (shared) traumas e.g., racism, slavery</td>
<td>One step transmission</td>
<td>Cross-generation transmission</td>
<td>Fear of group annihilation, subjugation; betrayal by society</td>
<td>Complex PTSD, CTD, and comorbidities</td>
<td>Type I, Type II, and Type III</td>
<td>Socially made</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Role identity trauma (Self-actualizations) e.g., traumatic loss of assets, job, serious failure</td>
<td>Family members of the victim</td>
<td>Organizational trauma</td>
<td>Fear of loss of self-achievements, Self-betrayal,</td>
<td>Depression, suicidality</td>
<td>Type I and Type II</td>
<td>Self-made- interpersonal-ecological</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Physical identity survival trauma e.g., car accident, attacked be a weapon</td>
<td>Family members of the victim</td>
<td>Immediate community</td>
<td>Fear of death or physical harm or of loss of functioning, betrayal</td>
<td>PTSD</td>
<td>Type 1 and Type II</td>
<td>Internal, nature-made, human-made</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cumulative life trauma- continuous traumatic stress</td>
<td>Family members of the victim</td>
<td>Intergroup conflict</td>
<td>All of the above</td>
<td>CTD-complex PTSD-Co-morbidities</td>
<td>Type IV</td>
<td>All of the above</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1534765612459892">
<label>a</label>
<p>e.g., identification, belonging, empathy, networking. PTSD = Posttraumatic stress disorder; CTD = Cumulative Trauma Related Disorder Measure.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The trans-theoretical DBTF framework allows measuring the effects of different trauma types including CT across life span. DBTF generated novel hypotheses, suggested new lines of research, attracted several new researchers and is promising to move us toward the “big picture” by integrating traumas across theories (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1534765612459892">Kira, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1534765612459892">Kira et al., 2008a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1534765612459892">2008b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1534765612459892">2011a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1534765612459892">2012a</xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1534765612459892">Kira, Lewandowski, Yoon, Somers, &amp; Chiodo, 2012b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1534765612459892">Martin, Cromer, DePrince, &amp; Freyd, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Cumulative trauma (the effects of all the trauma types the person endured across life time) as well as polyvictimizations (the effects of concurrent or subsequent traumatization from the same trauma types) found to contribute significant unique variance in mental health beyond that accounted for by the combination of all aggregate trauma and victimization types (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1534765612459892">Cloitre et al, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1534765612459892">Finkelhor, Turner, &amp; Hamby, 2005</xref>; Kira et al, 2008; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1534765612459892">Richmond, Elliott, Pierce, Aspelmeier, &amp; Alexander, 2009</xref>). The stress sensitization hypothesis suggests that repeated trauma exposure increases the likelihood of a pathological response (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1534765612459892">Peretz, Baider, Ever-Hadani, &amp; De-Nour, 1994</xref>). However, dose response model alone proved to be insufficient in explaining the risk for PTSD (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1534765612459892">Kaysan, Rosen, Bowman, &amp; Resick, 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>CT model involves different dynamics that are not present in the single trauma model of PTSD, or in the complex trauma and complex PTSD model (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1534765612459892">Courtois &amp; Ford, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1534765612459892">Herman, 1992</xref>). The accumulation and kindling dynamics can be present in CT. While Type I trauma (e.g., car accident) can yield PTSD, Type II trauma (e.g., sexual abuse) can yield complex PTSD, Type III traumas (e.g., discrimination and slavery) and the additive effects of combined different concurrent types of traumas can produce more severe symptoms of dissociation, hearing voices, suicidality and mental health comorbid syndromes (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1534765612459892">Kira, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-1534765612459892">Shevlin, Houston, Dorahy, &amp; Adamson, 2008</xref>). The dynamics of cumulative trauma is especially relevant for mental health patients and other cumulatively traumatized.</p>
<p>An important conceptual innovation in DBTF framework is the trauma profile analysis. Trauma profile describes the loads of different trauma types that endured by the individual, the group, or the culture. Trauma profile is usually presented in a contour or curve that outline the distribution of occurrence and intensity of each trauma types in the population. Trauma profile helps identify the core trauma/s for the individual or the group. Different trauma profiles entail different dynamics and outcomes and may require different interventions. The core trauma or dominant trauma types within the profile yield different symptoms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1534765612459892">Kira, 2010</xref>; Kira et al., 2008). Trauma profiles of victims of political oppression, victims of sexual abuse and victims of abandonment are mostly different. Trauma profile differential analysis is important tool for good clinical assessment of the patient.</p>
<p>CT involves, at least, three kinds of traumas: core, peripheral, and triggering traumas. Core traumas sensitize and bias responses to potential retraumatizing and or triggering events. Triggering trauma is the trauma that actually set off the postcumulative trauma response (the last straw that breaks the camel’s back). Such single trauma can be the triggering event, rather than the core trauma, in such cumulative dynamics. Peripheral traumas are other traumas that are less salient in the person’s over all life traumatic experiences. However, peripheral traumas can move to be salient if has been reactivated by similar traumatic events. This is important in clinical science, as we may be focusing on the triggering and not the core trauma/s, and ignoring the operating dynamics.</p>
<p>Previous studies of the etiology of mental disorders, in mental health patients, identified traumatic stress as major contributor to such disorders (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-1534765612459892">Rutter, 2000</xref>). Research, used the psychiatric paradigm showed that trauma victimizations (51%-98%) are highly prevalent among persons with severe mental illness (schizophrenia, bipolar disorder) who were served within public-sector clinics (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1534765612459892">Ford &amp; Fournier, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1534765612459892">Mueser et al., 1998</xref>). Most previous research used one paradigm, or the other that was less comprehensive to identify traumatization level. It is important to study the etiology of mental disorders from the integrated DBTF traumatology that consider all trauma types the individual endured.</p>
<p>To test the validity and utility of the DBTF, we plan to study mental health patients (MHP). One of the core traumas unique for MHP is internalized stigma of mental illness (ISMI). ISMI includes micro and macro aggressions perpetrated by the public, and internalized or resisted by MHP. ISMI has serious effects on their self-esteem, self-efficacy beliefs and mental health (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1534765612459892">Corrigan, Watson, &amp; Barr, 2006</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section1-1534765612459892">
<title>The Goals of the Research</title>
<p>The goal of this research is test the validity and utility of DBTF that integrated the three trauma paradigms, to evaluate the contribution of different trauma types and CT dynamics to clients’ physical and mental health and functioning. Another aim is to explore if these dynamics recur across two communities which each have different trauma profile. We will compare between outpatient MHP clients in Zaqazek University clinic, Egypt and those in another clinic in Dearborn Michigan (USA).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1534765612459892">
<title>The First Study: Dearborn, Michigan, USA Sample</title>
<sec id="section3-1534765612459892">
<title>Procedures</title>
<p>Participants were 95% of all active mental health clients that came for a psychiatrist, therapist, or case manager visit during the 6 months from August 2004 to February 2005 in a MH clinic in Dearborn Michigan, United States (95% consented to participate). Participants were interviewed face to face by licensed bilingual therapists or certified experienced bilingual clinical case managers for the duration of 45 to 60 min. The data was collected as part of a mental health antistigma outcome project which was authorized by federal authorities and approved by the IRB and research committees of the authors’ institution. Informed consents were obtained from participants. No identifying information, linking subject to the data, was recorded and the disclosure of the data could not reasonably place the subjects at any risk. Participants were 399 mental health clients and included 82.7% persons of Arabic immigrants or refugees. The balance included Americans as well as refugees and Asylum seekers from other countries. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1534765612459892">Table 3</xref> provides their demographics along with the demographics of participants of the second study.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1534765612459892" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption><p>Demographic Characteristics of the Two Samples.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1534765612459892" xlink:href="10.1177_1534765612459892-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Variable</th>
<th align="center">USA sample(<italic>n</italic>= 399)</th>
<th align="center">Egyptian sample (<italic>n</italic>= 432)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Gender</td>
<td>53.5% males and 46.5% females</td>
<td>52.1% males, and 47.9% females</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Age</td>
<td>ranged from 18 to 76, with mean of 39.66 and standard deviation of 11.45</td>
<td>ranged between 18 and 65, with mean of 33.01 and standard deviation of 11.99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Education</td>
<td>14.2% illiterate, 27.4% elementary 38% middle, and 15.5% high school, 4.7% college graduates</td>
<td>42.8% have basic education, and 57.2% have higher than basic education</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Marital status</td>
<td>70 % married, 30% single (.17 %,) separated (2.5%) divorced (7.6%)</td>
<td>47.5% were married and 52.5% were in other unmarried categories</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Employment and socioeconomic status</td>
<td>82% were making less than US$15.000 a year, with 48% had different level of employment while 52% were unemployed.</td>
<td>57.6% employed and 42.4% unemployed, 57.4% poor, 41% have average socioeconomic status, and 1.6% well off</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Religion</td>
<td>84.9% Muslims, 12.8% Christians, 3% Jewish</td>
<td>87% Muslim and 13% Christian</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Residence</td>
<td>Resided mostly in Dearborn and Detroit metropolitan area</td>
<td>56.7% resided in urban areas, 43.3% resided in rural area</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1534765612459892">
<title>Measures, Demographics and Clinical Data</title>
<p>The measures used in this study as identified in the following section have previously been shown to have adequate reliability and validity on Iraqi and Arab populations and in Arabic and English languages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1534765612459892">Kira, Clifford, Wiencek, &amp; Al-haidar, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1534765612459892">Kira et al., 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1534765612459892">2008a</xref>). These measures were previously constructed in English and subsequently translated into Arabic by three bilingual mental health professionals who each individually translated the measures and then met together to establish a consensus on the final version. A fourth mental health professional did the reverse translation. These measures were pilot tested in focus groups. We provided Arabic and English versions to our research subjects. In addition to these measures we collected demographic and clinic data from the clients files considering diagnoses, global assessment of functioning (GAF) as diagnosed by clinic psychiatrists. Further we developed, from this data, a mental health comorbidity index, which is the number of primary and secondary diagnoses the patient had. Comorbidity is important measure of the severity of illnesses.</p>
<sec id="section5-1534765612459892">
<title>Independent (Predictor) Variables Measures</title>
<p><italic>Cumulative Trauma Scale (CTS)</italic> includes 61 items and is based on the DBTF (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1534765612459892">Kira, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1534765612459892">Kira et al., 2008a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1534765612459892">2008b</xref>). Each item describes an extremely stressful event that belongs to 6 different types of traumas: Attachment, personal identity, collective identity, secondary, survival, and achievement traumas. Examples are as follows: I was led to sexual contact by one of my caregiver/parents, my mother has abandoned or left/or separated from me when I was a child. The participant is asked to report if he/she has experienced it or not, how many times he have experienced the event, the age of first one, and how much it affected him or her positively or negatively on a scale from 0 to 7 (positive and negative appraisal). The measure provides us with general scales for two of the cumulative trauma doses: Occurrence and frequency of happenings, two appraisal subscales: Negative and positive appraisal. It includes, at this level, four subscales for each trauma types. In the analysis, in this study, we used the occurrence of traumas of each type (e.g., personal identity traumas) as an index of polytraumatization of this trauma type, in addition to the cumulative occurrence of all trauma types (cumulative trauma or cumulative trauma load). This information allows for describing the trauma profile, in addition to conducting other advanced analyses. The measure has been used previously with different clinical and community populations of adults and children and proved to have adequate reliability (Alpha of .80-.90), good construct and predictive validity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1534765612459892">Kira et al., 2008a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1534765612459892">2008b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1534765612459892">Kira et al., 2011a</xref>). The reliability of the CTS was found adequate in the current study (alpha = .98).</p>
<p><italic>Internalized Stigma of Mental Illness Inventory (ISMI)</italic> is a 29-item scale. Each statement is rated on the following 4-point anchored Likert-type scale: 1 = strongly disagree, 2 = disagree, 3 = agree, 4 = strongly agree. Items were grouped thematically “a priori” into five subscales: Alienation, Stereotype Endorsement, Perceived Discrimination, Social Withdrawal, and Stigma Resistance. The 29-item ISMI had good internal consistency (α = .90, <italic>N</italic> = 127). The test-retest reliability coefficient was r = .92 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;.05, N=16; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1534765612459892">Ritsher, Otilingam, &amp; Grajales, 2003</xref>). The measure and its subscales proved to have adequate internal consistency except for the SR subscale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1534765612459892">Ritsher et al., 2003</xref>). The Arabic version of ISMI was found to have robust psychometrics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1534765612459892">Kira, Lewandowski, Templin, Mohanesh, &amp; Abdulkhalek, 2011b</xref>). It has good reliability in both versions in the current data for all groups. Alpha for the whole sample was .95. ISMI, for mental health patients can act as an independent and mediating variable.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1534765612459892">
<title>Dependent (Outcome) Variables Measures</title>
<p><italic>Annihilation Anxiety (AA) Scale</italic> is based on the assumption that there are at least three main sources of the emergence of annihilation threats: Threats to personal identity, to direct threats to collective identity such as discrimination, and indirect threats from severe societal structural inequalities. A three items that represents the three components were used, for example, because of what has happened to me personally or is happening to me personally, I sometimes worry that I just lose my sense of self (I worry that I will cease to exist as an individual person). The answer was structured on a 5 point-Likert-type scale: 5 = Strongly Agree, 4 = Agree, 3 = Not sure, 2 = Disagree, 1 = Strongly Disagree. The higher the sum of the three items provides the higher of feeling of AA. The scale had been used before on Iraqi refugees and on other three samples of Palestinians and found to have good reliability (alpha. ranged between. 90-95), convergent discriminant and predictive validity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1534765612459892">Kira et al., 2012c</xref>). It has an alpha of .93 in the current study.</p>
<p><italic>Anxiety Subscale of the Depression Anxiety Stress Scales-Anxiety DASS-A</italic>: (14 items): DASS is a 42-item scale developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1534765612459892">Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995</xref>, and includes three subscales that measure depression, anxiety, and stress. DASS-A subscale measures anxiety, which is increasingly used in different clinical and research settings. It has adequate convergent validity, with reliability of .84 in nonclinical and .91 in clinical samples (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1534765612459892">Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995</xref>). Its alpha reliability in the present study is .95.</p>
<p><italic>Clinician-Administered PTSD Scale</italic> (<italic>CAPS-2</italic>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1534765612459892">Blake et al., 1990</xref>) is widely used to assess PTSD. It is a structured clinical interview that assesses 17 symptoms rated on frequency and severity on a 5-point scale. CAPS demonstrated high reliability with a range from 0.92 to 0.99 and showed good convergent and discriminant validity. It has four factor subscales: re-experiencing, avoidance, arousal and emotional numbness, detachment or dissociation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1534765612459892">Palmieri, Weathers, Difede &amp; King, 2007</xref>). In this study, we used the frequency subscale of CAPS-2. It has high reliability with an alpha of 0.97 in current data.</p>
<p><italic>Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Measure, CES-D</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1534765612459892">Radloff, 1977</xref>): is a 20-item scale. Each item is assessed on a 4-point scale and reflects the frequency that each symptom was experienced (0 = <italic>none of the time</italic>, 3 = <italic>all of the time</italic>). A cutoff score of ≥16 is commonly used for the CES-D to indicate a need for further assessment of the presence of major depressive disorder (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1534765612459892">Radloff, 1977</xref>). High internal consistency (ranging from .85 to .92) and good convergent and discriminant validity, sensitivity and specificity had been reported (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1534765612459892">Mulrow et al., 1995</xref>). It has alpha of .91 in the present study.</p>
<sec id="section7-1534765612459892">
<title>Cumulative trauma related disorders measure (CTD)</title>
<p>This 15-item measure has been developed on five community and clinic samples of adults, adolescent Arab, and African Americans. It is an index measure that covers 13 different symptoms: Depression, anxiety, somatization, dissociation, auditory and visual hallucinations, avoidance of being with people, paranoid ideations, concentration and memory deficits, loss of self-control, feeling suicidal, and feeling like hurting self. Exploratory and confirmatory factor analyses found four factors (four subscales): Executive function deficits, suicidality, dissociation/psychosis, and depression/anxiety comorbidity. It has good reliability (ranged from .85 to .98). Test-retest reliability in a 6-week interval was .76. The measure has good predictive validity. Different kinds of traumas and cumulative trauma accounted for significant variance as predictors of CTD symptoms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1534765612459892">Kira, Clifford &amp; Al-Haider, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1534765612459892">Kira, Templin, &amp; Lewandowski, 2012</xref>). In the current data, its alpha was .91.</p>
<p><italic>Physical Health</italic>: Physical Health was measured by a single question asking the client to rate his/her current general health on a scale from 1 to 4. (1 = very good health, 2 = good, 3 = poor, 4 = very poor).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1534765612459892">
<title>Analyses</title>
<p>We analyzed the prevalence of trauma types and cumulative trauma load to identify the trauma profile in each sample. We calculated the prevalence of different mental health conditions in the sample to explore the severity of symptoms and levels of comorbidity. A series of simultaneous multiple regression analyses were conducted with cumulative trauma CT, different trauma types (personal identity, collective identity, attachment, survival, secondary and ISMI traumas) as independent variables, and depression, anxiety, annihilation anxiety, PTSD, CTD, mental health comorbidities, and global assessment of functioning (all are continuous variables), as dependent variables. We controlled for age, gender, cultural group, marital status, income, education, period of stay in the United States, and religion, as covariates to disentangle the significant effects of each. For all regression analyses that we conducted in the two studies, we tested for multicolinearity. VIF (variance inflation factor) for all predictor variables ranged between 1.00 and 1.50, which indicated low colinearity (the recommended cut off score for multicolinearity is 5.00, e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1534765612459892">O’Brien, 2007</xref>). Furthermore, we tested different plausible path models that reflected assumptions about the effects of CT and trauma types that have higher incidence rate, on mental health conditions, using structural equation modeling (SEM) with AMOS 7.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1534765612459892">Arbuckle, 2006</xref>). We used bootstrap (<italic>N</italic> = 200 samples) with bias-corrected confidence intervals to test the significance of the direct and indirect effects. Bootstrapping is more robust modern statistics that are used to generate a sampling distribution that is utilized to compute <italic>p</italic> values, and generate confidence intervals for the direct and indirect effects (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1534765612459892">Erceg-Hurn &amp; Mirosevich, 2008</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1534765612459892">
<title>Results</title>
<p><italic>Descriptive Results Trauma Profile</italic>: <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1534765612459892">Table 4</xref> describes the trauma profile characteristics of each sample. <italic>Mental Health Profile</italic>: For mental health symptoms, 82% scored 16 or higher on the CES-D scale (16 is the cutoff point for clinical depression recommended for this scale); 83.8% scored in the elevated range of PTSD symptoms (scoring 26 or above in PTSD frequent symptoms). For DASS-A (anxiety) 74% scored 10 or higher (10 is the recommended cutoff score for moderate to severe anxiety on this scale). For CTD items, over 38% reported that sometimes they hear voices and/or see things others do not hear or see; 17.1% felt very much or thought about killing themselves (suicidality). <italic>Mean</italic> GAF score was 48.85 with standard deviation (<italic>SD</italic>) of 4.18. For diagnoses by clinic psychiatrists, 45.4% have major depressive disorder, 42.3% have PTSD, 7.7% have anxiety disorder, 20.3% have psychotic disorder, 1.5% have bipolar disorder; and 8% have OCD as primary diagnoses. For comorbidity, 37% have at least one secondary diagnosis on Axis I, and 74% have at least one diagnosis on Axis III (diagnosed medical condition).</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-1534765612459892" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption><p>The Percentages of Trauma Types Endured by Each Sample.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1534765612459892" xlink:href="10.1177_1534765612459892-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Trauma types</th>
<th align="center">USA-based sample</th>
<th align="center">Egypt-based sample</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Cumulative trauma</td>
<td>All endured at least one type of trauma (mean of 10.34 and standard deviation of 7.70., only 4 suffered from a single trauma type, 11% suffered from at least 3 traumas, while 80% suffered from 4 or more traumas</td>
<td>All endured at least one type of trauma (6.46 trauma types and standard deviation of 3.96), 15% suffered from a single trauma type, over 60% suffered from at least 3 traumas, and 25% suffered from 4 or more traumas</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cumulative appraisal</td>
<td>30.6% expressed some positive appraisal; while 85% reported negative appraisals.</td>
<td>16% expressed some positive appraisal, 99.3% reported negative appraisals<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1534765612459892">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Collective identity (CIT)</td>
<td>99% endured at least one CIT</td>
<td>97.7% endured at least one CIT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Personal identity (PIT)</td>
<td>60% endured at least one PIT</td>
<td>53% endured at least one PIT (22% endured at least one type of sexual abuse)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Survival traumas</td>
<td>55% suffered at least one trauma</td>
<td>52% suffered at least one trauma</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Secondary traumas</td>
<td>76% suffered at least one trauma</td>
<td>44% suffered at least one trauma</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Achievement traumas</td>
<td>17% suffered at least one</td>
<td>8.3% suffered at least one</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Attachment</td>
<td>9.5% endured attachment disruption</td>
<td>3.2 % endured attachment disruptions</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Poverty</td>
<td>68% belong to a very poor family</td>
<td>95% belong to a very poor family</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Physical abuse</td>
<td>14% have been physically abused</td>
<td>41% reported to be physically abused</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Uprootedness</td>
<td>44% reported being uprootedness</td>
<td>25.7% reported being uprootedness</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Domestic violence</td>
<td>6% exposed to domestic violence</td>
<td>16.7% witnessed domestic violence</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Natural disaster</td>
<td>10% experienced national disaster</td>
<td>12% experienced natural disaster</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sexual Abuse</td>
<td>3.3% reported sexual abuse</td>
<td>10.6% reported sexual abuse</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Incest</td>
<td>1% reported to be victims of incest</td>
<td>4.1% reported to be victims of incest</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rape</td>
<td>2.5% reported to be raped</td>
<td>10.6% reported to be raped</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Combat</td>
<td>21% were involved in a combat</td>
<td>17.6% were involved in a combat</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Death of loved ones</td>
<td>27% witnessed death of loved ones</td>
<td>17.4% witnessed death of loved ones</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Frequent school failures</td>
<td>10% frequent failures in school</td>
<td>8% reported frequent failures in school</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Life threatening illness</td>
<td>6.5% experienced a life threatening illness</td>
<td>7.6% had life threatening illness</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Robbed</td>
<td>4.5% been robbed or mugged</td>
<td>7.2% been robbed or mugged</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Life threatening accident</td>
<td>26% experience life threatening accidents</td>
<td>8% experience life threatening accidents</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Torture</td>
<td>19% have been tortured</td>
<td>3% reported to be jailed and or tortured</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Discrimination</td>
<td>38% exposed to discrimination</td>
<td>2.5% exposed to discrimination</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Failed business</td>
<td>10% reported failed businesses</td>
<td>2% reported failed business</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Abandonment by mother</td>
<td>6% have been abandoned by mother</td>
<td>1.4% have been abandoned by mother</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Belong to oppressed race</td>
<td>50% reported to belong to oppressed race</td>
<td>1% reported to belong to oppressed race</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Internalized stigma of mental illness</td>
<td>Scored moderate to high (Mean = 60.32, standard deviation = 22.44), moderate stigma resistance (Mean = 9.275, standard deviation = 3.358).</td>
<td>Scored high (Mean = 68.27, standard deviation = 4.645), as well high stigma resistance (Mean = 14.79, standard deviation = 1.506)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1534765612459892">
<label>a</label>
<p>Positive appraisal was associated with positive self-esteem and futuristic orientation.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section10-1534765612459892">
<title>Multiple Regression Analyses Results</title>
<p><italic>CT</italic> predicted significant increase in depression, annihilation anxiety, general anxiety, PTSD, CTD, comorbidity, and reduced global functioning. <italic>Collective identity traumas</italic>, in this sample, were the highest trauma type that predicted all mental health (MH) conditions, especially of annihilation anxiety (β = .95***, <italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic> = .88), followed by personal identity traumas that predicted to a lesser degree all MH variables, however, their prediction of decreased GAF was the highest among all trauma types (β = −.47***, <italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic> = .37). Attachment traumas predicted depression, and to some degree CTD, however, their prediction of decreased GAF scores was the second highest among all trauma types (β = −.420***, <italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic> = .39). Secondary traumas predicted all MH variables with different degrees of intensity. Survival traumas predicted all MH variables except MH comorbidity and GAF. Internalized stigma of mental illness predicted all MH variables and was the highest predictor of CTD and PTSD. Collective identity and secondary traumas were the strongest predictors of mental health comorbidity. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1534765612459892">Table 5</xref> summarizes the results.</p>
<table-wrap id="table5-1534765612459892" position="float">
<label>Table 5.</label>
<caption><p>Multiple Regressions for The effects of Cumulative Trauma, Trauma Types on Mental and Physical Health Variables after Controlling for Demographics and for Other Relevant Variables in the USA and Egyptian Samples.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table5-1534765612459892" xlink:href="10.1177_1534765612459892-table5.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="5">USA sample<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="5">Egyptian sample<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Independent variables</th>
<th align="center">Dependent variables</th>
<th align="center"><italic>B</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center">β</th>
<th align="center"><italic>t</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup></th>
<th align="center"><italic>B</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>SE</italic></th>
<th align="center">β</th>
<th align="center"><italic>t</italic></th>
<th align="center"><italic>R</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Cumulative traumas</td>
<td>Depression</td>
<td>.77</td>
<td>.12</td>
<td>.39<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>6.27</td>
<td>.190</td>
<td>.73</td>
<td>.13</td>
<td>.31<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>5.59</td>
<td>.104</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Anxiety</td>
<td>.43</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td>.26<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>4.11</td>
<td>.141</td>
<td>.64</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td>.43<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>8.18</td>
<td>.170</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>AA</td>
<td>.17</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>.37<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>7.92</td>
<td>.179</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>PTSD</td>
<td>1.04</td>
<td>.22</td>
<td>.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>4.85</td>
<td>.185</td>
<td>.96</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>.46<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>9.27</td>
<td>.256</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>CTD</td>
<td>.54</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>4.99</td>
<td>.228</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>MHC</td>
<td>.13</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>3.89</td>
<td>.081</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>6.97</td>
<td>.244</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>PHC</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>.18</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>.48<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>9.55</td>
<td>.227</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GAF</td>
<td>−.35</td>
<td>.17</td>
<td>−.24<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">*</xref></td>
<td>2.11</td>
<td>.288</td>
<td>−.37</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>−.31<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>−6.21</td>
<td>243</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Personal identity traumas</td>
<td>Depression</td>
<td>1.21</td>
<td>.27</td>
<td>.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>4.40</td>
<td>.073</td>
<td>1.24</td>
<td>.32</td>
<td>.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>3.84</td>
<td>.070</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Anxiety</td>
<td>.75</td>
<td>.26</td>
<td>.15<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">**</xref></td>
<td>2.89</td>
<td>.083</td>
<td>1.38</td>
<td>.19</td>
<td>.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>7.15</td>
<td>.143</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>AA</td>
<td>.63</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td>.37<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>7.61</td>
<td>.170</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>PTSD</td>
<td>3.02</td>
<td>.59</td>
<td>.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>5.12</td>
<td>.158</td>
<td>1.98</td>
<td>.26</td>
<td>.36<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>7.69</td>
<td>.215</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>CTD</td>
<td>1.32</td>
<td>.29</td>
<td>.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>4.53</td>
<td>.172</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>MHC</td>
<td>.75</td>
<td>.12</td>
<td>.32<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>6.08</td>
<td>.133</td>
<td>.22</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.31<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>6.86</td>
<td>.241</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>PHC</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>.40</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>.40<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>8.53</td>
<td>.198</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GAF</td>
<td>−1.99</td>
<td>.50</td>
<td>−.47<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>−3.77</td>
<td>.372</td>
<td>−1.13</td>
<td>.14</td>
<td>−.36<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>−8.14</td>
<td>.286</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Collective identity traumas</td>
<td>Depression</td>
<td>1.03</td>
<td>.12</td>
<td>.40<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>8.45</td>
<td>.178</td>
<td>1.24</td>
<td>.40</td>
<td>.15<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">**</xref></td>
<td>3.08</td>
<td>.038</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Anxiety</td>
<td>.97</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>.40<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>8.55</td>
<td>.211</td>
<td>.44</td>
<td>.25</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>1.76</td>
<td>.036</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>AA</td>
<td>.77</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>.95<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>50.98</td>
<td>.876</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>PTSD</td>
<td>2.56</td>
<td>.26</td>
<td>.45<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>9.97</td>
<td>.284</td>
<td>1.90</td>
<td>.34</td>
<td>.26<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>5.62</td>
<td>.095</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>CTD</td>
<td>1.13</td>
<td>.13</td>
<td>.40<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>8.82</td>
<td>.273</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>MHC</td>
<td>.45</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>.43<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>8.92</td>
<td>.220</td>
<td>.32</td>
<td>.04</td>
<td>.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>7.78</td>
<td>.146</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>PHC</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>.21</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>3.26</td>
<td>.048</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GAF</td>
<td>−.45</td>
<td>.22</td>
<td>−.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">*</xref></td>
<td>−2.03</td>
<td>.284</td>
<td>−1.38</td>
<td>.19</td>
<td>−.34<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>−7.37</td>
<td>.141</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Attachment trauma</td>
<td>Depression</td>
<td>1.54</td>
<td>.77</td>
<td>.11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">*</xref></td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>.037</td>
<td>3.91</td>
<td>2.60</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td>1.50</td>
<td>.022</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Anxiety</td>
<td>.15</td>
<td>.72</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>.20</td>
<td>.063</td>
<td>2.78</td>
<td>1.60</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td/>
<td>.035</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>AA</td>
<td>.22</td>
<td>.24</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>.92</td>
<td>.049</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>PTSD</td>
<td>1.05</td>
<td>1.68</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.63</td>
<td>.102</td>
<td>5.80</td>
<td>2.22</td>
<td>.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">**</xref></td>
<td>2.61</td>
<td>.043</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>CTD</td>
<td>1.37</td>
<td>.82</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>1.68</td>
<td>.134</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>MHC</td>
<td>−.12</td>
<td>.41</td>
<td>−.02</td>
<td>−.28</td>
<td>.041</td>
<td>.45</td>
<td>.28</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td>1.57</td>
<td>.030</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>PHC</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>.77</td>
<td>.41</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>1.88</td>
<td>.032</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GAF</td>
<td>−8.76</td>
<td>2.13</td>
<td>−.42<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>−4.11</td>
<td>.391</td>
<td>−1.35</td>
<td>1.27</td>
<td>−.05</td>
<td>−1.06</td>
<td>.033</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Survival trauma</td>
<td>Depression</td>
<td>1.02</td>
<td>.22</td>
<td>.24<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>4.63</td>
<td>.078</td>
<td>2.80</td>
<td>.37</td>
<td>.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>7.65</td>
<td>.136</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Anxiety</td>
<td>.89</td>
<td>.21</td>
<td>.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>4.32</td>
<td>.106</td>
<td>.77</td>
<td>.24</td>
<td>.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>3.22</td>
<td>.052</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>AA</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td>.30<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>6.18</td>
<td>.132</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>PTSD</td>
<td>1.90</td>
<td>.48</td>
<td>.19<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>3.95</td>
<td>.136</td>
<td>1.29</td>
<td>.33</td>
<td>.19<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>3.91</td>
<td>.061</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>CTD</td>
<td>.62</td>
<td>.17</td>
<td>.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>3.62</td>
<td>.173</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>MHC</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.62</td>
<td>.042</td>
<td>.14</td>
<td>.04</td>
<td>.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>3.34</td>
<td>.049</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>PHC</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>.35</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>.28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>5.85</td>
<td>.097</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GAF</td>
<td>−.40</td>
<td>.30</td>
<td>−.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">*</xref></td>
<td>−1.33</td>
<td>.262</td>
<td>−.20</td>
<td>.19</td>
<td>−.05</td>
<td>−1.07</td>
<td>.033</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Secondary trauma</td>
<td>Depression</td>
<td>1.73</td>
<td>.31</td>
<td>.28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>5.59</td>
<td>.099</td>
<td>.77</td>
<td>.31</td>
<td>.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">**</xref></td>
<td>2.46</td>
<td>.031</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Anxiety</td>
<td>1.24</td>
<td>.30</td>
<td>.21<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">**</xref></td>
<td>4.19</td>
<td>.104</td>
<td>1.05</td>
<td>.19</td>
<td>.26<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>5.60</td>
<td>.095</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>AA</td>
<td>.95</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>.47<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>10.57</td>
<td>.259</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>PTSD</td>
<td>4.95</td>
<td>.65</td>
<td>.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>7.60</td>
<td>.217</td>
<td>1.85</td>
<td>.26</td>
<td>.33<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>7.22</td>
<td>.134</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>CTD</td>
<td>1.82</td>
<td>.33</td>
<td>.26<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>5.54</td>
<td>.192</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>MHC</td>
<td>1.08</td>
<td>.13</td>
<td>.42<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>8.49</td>
<td>.206</td>
<td>.16</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>4.65</td>
<td>.072</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>PHC</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>.30</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>6.22</td>
<td>.106</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GAF</td>
<td>−1.86</td>
<td>.57</td>
<td>−.38<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>−3.26</td>
<td>.343</td>
<td>−.52</td>
<td>.14</td>
<td>−.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>−3.65</td>
<td>.199</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Internalized stigma</td>
<td>Depression</td>
<td>.25</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.40<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>8.48</td>
<td>.179</td>
<td>.21</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td>1.99</td>
<td>.046</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Anxiety</td>
<td>.23</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.39<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>8.35</td>
<td>.205</td>
<td>.32</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td>.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>4.74</td>
<td>.087</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>AA</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>.37<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>7.42</td>
<td>.189</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>PTSD</td>
<td>.63</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>.45<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>10.39</td>
<td>.296</td>
<td>.66</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>.37<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>7.67</td>
<td>.214</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>CTD</td>
<td>.34</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.49<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>11.73</td>
<td>.356</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>MHC</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>.32<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>6.17</td>
<td>.136</td>
<td>.16</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>.73<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>20.11</td>
<td>.569</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>PHC</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>.34<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>6.71</td>
<td>.151</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GAF</td>
<td>−.08</td>
<td>.04</td>
<td>−.28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">*</xref></td>
<td>−2.08</td>
<td>.124</td>
<td>−.90</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>−.99<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>−37.30</td>
<td>.808</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GD</td>
<td>Depression</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>3.56</td>
<td>2.93</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>1.21</td>
<td>.041</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Anxiety</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>3.69</td>
<td>1.81</td>
<td>.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">*</xref></td>
<td>2.03</td>
<td>.048</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>PTSD</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>7.72</td>
<td>2.42</td>
<td>.15<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">***</xref></td>
<td>3.19</td>
<td>.126</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>MHC</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>.32</td>
<td>.30</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>1.08</td>
<td>.159</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>PHC</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>1.16</td>
<td>.45</td>
<td>.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1534765612459892">**</xref></td>
<td>2.56</td>
<td>.074</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>GAF</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>XX</td>
<td>−2.07</td>
<td>1.33</td>
<td>−.07</td>
<td>−1.56</td>
<td>.179</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1534765612459892">
<p>Note: GAF = global assessment of functioning; AA = annihilation anxiety; MHC = mental health comorbidities; PHC = physical health comorbidity; GD = gender discrimination; PTSD = posttruamatic stress disorder; CTD = Cumulative Trauma Related Disorder Measure; XX= variables were not measured.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn4-1534765612459892">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. ***<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1534765612459892">
<title>Path Models</title>
<p>Type III traumas, for example, political oppression, discrimination, and to some degree poverty, are higher than other trauma types in the trauma profile of the American sample. We tested different plausible path models that represented this profile. The model included poverty, torture, political oppression and discrimination, as predictors, ISMI as mediator, and PTSD, depression, anxiety, CTD and physical health as dependent variables. The model had good fit with the data (<italic>Chi Square</italic> = 32.473, <italic>df</italic> = 19, <italic>p</italic> = .028. CFI = .991, RMSEA = .042). <italic>Poverty</italic> had direct significant positive effects (increased severity of their symptoms) on PTSD, ISMI, CTD and poor health. Further, it had indirect significant positive effects on PTSD, CTD, depression, anxiety, and poor health. <italic>Stereotyping and Racial Profiling</italic> had direct significant positive effects on PTSD and indirect positive significant effects on CTD, depression, anxiety, and poor health. <italic>Social and Political Oppression</italic> had positive direct significant effects on ISMI and depression and indirect significant positive effects on increased PTSD, CTD, depression, anxiety and poor health. <italic>Torture</italic> had direct significant positive effects on PTSD and indirect significant positive effects on CTD, depression, anxiety, and poor health. <italic>Internalized Stigma of Mental Illness (ISMI)</italic> had direct significant positive effects on PTSD and CTD and indirect significant positive effects on depression, anxiety, and poor health. ISMI partially mediated the effects of poverty and political oppression on PTSD, CTD, and anxiety (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table6-1534765612459892">Table 6</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table6-1534765612459892" position="float">
<label>Table 6.</label>
<caption><p>Decomposition of Standardized Direct, Indirect, Total Effects of Poverty, Political Oppression, Racial Profiling, and Torture and Their Confidence Intervals on Health and Mental Health (Michigan Clinic).</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table6-1534765612459892" xlink:href="10.1177_1534765612459892-table6.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="6">Outcome variables<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Causal variables</th>
<th align="center">Internalized stigma of mental illness</th>
<th align="center">Posttruamatic stress disorder</th>
<th align="center">Cumulative trauma related disorder measure</th>
<th align="center">Depression</th>
<th align="center">Anxiety</th>
<th align="center">Poor health</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="7"><italic>Poverty</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Direct effects</td>
<td>.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">*</xref> (.11//.29)</td>
<td>.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.18/.32)</td>
<td>.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">*</xref> (.01/.18)</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">*</xref> (.05/.23)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Indirect effects</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.073<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">*</xref> (.05/.11)</td>
<td>.21<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.16/.26)</td>
<td>.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.15/.25)</td>
<td>.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.16/.25)</td>
<td>.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.07/.15)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total effects</td>
<td>.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">*</xref> (.11//.29)</td>
<td>.33<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.26/.39)</td>
<td>.31<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">*</xref> (.21/.38)</td>
<td>.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.15/.25)</td>
<td>. .20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.16/.25)</td>
<td>.26<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.17/.33)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7"><italic>Torture</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Direct effects</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.15<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.09/.21)</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Indirect effects</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.04/.11)</td>
<td>.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.05/.12)</td>
<td>.07<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.04/.11)</td>
<td>.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.02/.05)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total effects</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.15<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.09/.21)</td>
<td>.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.04/.11)</td>
<td>.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.05/.12)</td>
<td>.07<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.04/.11)</td>
<td>.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.02/.05)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7"><italic>Stereotyping and racial profiling</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Direct effects</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.19<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.13/.27)</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Indirect effects</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.06/.14)</td>
<td>.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.07/.14)</td>
<td>.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.05/.12)</td>
<td>.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.03/.07)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total effects</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.19<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.13/.27)</td>
<td>.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.06/.14)</td>
<td>.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.07/.14)</td>
<td>.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.05/.12)</td>
<td>.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.03/.07)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7"><italic>Social and political oppression</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Direct effects</td>
<td>.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.17/.31)</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">*</xref> (.05/.20)</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Indirect effects</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.06/.12)</td>
<td>.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.06/.13)</td>
<td>.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.04/.08)</td>
<td>.11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.08/.15)</td>
<td>.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.02/.05)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total effects</td>
<td>.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.17/.31)</td>
<td>.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.06/.12)</td>
<td>.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.06/.13)</td>
<td>.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.10/.24)</td>
<td>.11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.08/.15)</td>
<td>.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.02/.05)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="7"><italic>Internalized stigma of mental illness</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Direct effects</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.34<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.27/.41)</td>
<td>.21<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">*</xref> (.11/.28)</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.063 (−.02/.15)</td>
<td>.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Indirect effects</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.13/.22)</td>
<td>.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.17/.27)</td>
<td>.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">*</xref> (.166/.269)</td>
<td>13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.076/.173)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Total effects</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.34<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.27/.41)</td>
<td>.38<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">*</xref> (.29/.46)</td>
<td>.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.17/.27)</td>
<td>.28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.20/.37)</td>
<td>.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.07/.17)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Squared R</italic></td>
<td>.136</td>
<td>.379</td>
<td>.454</td>
<td>.397</td>
<td>.412</td>
<td>.158</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn5-1534765612459892">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1534765612459892">
<title>The Second Study: Zagazik University MH Clinic, Egypt (Egyptian Study)</title>
<p><italic>Procedures</italic>: Data were collected from patients who attended the Zagazik University out-patients mental health clinic, Egypt. They included all patients admitted from May 1, 2010 to April 30, 2011. Interviews were conducted face to face by clinic professionals as part of a routine assessment. Confidentiality and anonymity were strictly enforced. Research protocol was approved by the university’s IRB. Furthermore, a detailed information of the <italic>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</italic> (4th ed.) five axes diagnoses for each client were carefully assessed by university psychiatry professors and residents as part of routine clinic assessment. The information was collected from clients’ records and included primary and secondary diagnosis in Axis I and Axis II, as well the physical illnesses on Axis III, and the range of problems on Axis IV and the general level of functioning score on Axis V (GAF). We used this wealth of diagnostic data, collected from clients’ records, to develop indices of mental and physical health comorbidity. Mental health comorbidity index is the number of primary and secondary diagnoses the clients had on the Axis I and II. Physical health comorbidity index is the number of health diagnoses the client had on Axis III.</p>
<p><italic>Participants</italic> were 432 mental health clients. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1534765612459892">Table 3</xref> includes their demographic characteristics.</p>
<p><italic>Measures</italic> In addition to CES-D, PTSD, DASS, and ISMI, which have been used in the first study, we added Rosenberg measure of self-esteem and a short measure for futuristic orientation. We used the short version of cumulative trauma CTS that has added subscale of gender discrimination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1534765612459892">Kira et al., 2008a</xref>), instead of the long version used in the previous study (the short form correlation with long version was <italic>R</italic> = .82***).</p>
<sec id="section13-1534765612459892">
<title>Cumulative Trauma Scale CTS-S (short form)</title>
<p>The CTS-S is a 32-item instrument that measures cumulative trauma in terms of frequency, types, and impact as indicated in the long versionFactor analysis found six types of trauma: Collective identity trauma, family trauma, secondary trauma, personal identity trauma, survival trauma, and attachment trauma. The instrument followed the same instructions used in the long version discussed earlier. This instrument has shown adequate internal consistency (a = .85) for adults. The instrument has shown predictive validity as cumulative trauma was significantly correlated with PTSD (r = .54,<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001), cumulative trauma related disorders (r = .24, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001), and poor health (r = .37, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001). The instrument also showed divergent validity as it was significantly negatively correlated with sociocultural adjustment (r = −.25, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001), and futuristic orientation (r = −.37, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1534765612459892">Kira et al., 2008a</xref>). It has adequate reliability in the current data (alpha = .83).</p>
<p><italic>The Rosenberg self-esteem scale (RSES</italic>), was developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1534765612459892">Dr. Morris Rosenberg (1965)</xref>. It is a 10-item scale with items answered on a 4-point Likert-type scale—from strongly agree to strongly disagree and scored from 0 to 3. Five of the scale items have positively worded statements and five have negatively worded ones. The scale measures global self-esteem. The RSES has been translated and adapted to various languages including Arabic. Rosenberg reported good psychometrics for the scale and its reliability ranging from .85 to .88. The scale α was (.87) in the current sample.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1534765612459892">
<title>Futuristic optimistic orientation (FOO)</title>
<p>This 2-item scale assesses the degree to which the individual look to the future optimistically and perceive adversity as an opportunity to grow. It was developed in previous studies of Iraqi refugees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1534765612459892">Kira et al., 2003</xref>). It includes the following items: (a) I feel optimistic and enthusiastic about the future. (b) I have very clear goals and vision. The participant was asked if he agrees or disagrees on 5-point scale. Higher scores indicated higher futuristic orientation. It was found to have good reliability (alpha 0.72), construct, and concurrent and discriminant validity and found to have one factor structure. It was associated with sociocultural adjustment, posttraumatic growth, and was negatively correlated with CTD. It had alpha of .66 in the current data.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1534765612459892">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section16-1534765612459892">
<title>Descriptive Results</title>
<p><italic>Trauma Profile</italic>: <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1534765612459892">Table 4</xref> includes the parameters of trauma profile of the sample.</p>
<p><italic>Mental Health Profile</italic>: Hundred percent scored 16 or higher on the CES-D scale (16 is the cutoff point for clinical depression recommended for this scale); 90% scored in the elevated range of the presence of PTSD symptoms. For DASS-A (anxiety) 67.2% scored 10 or higher (10 is the recommended cutoff score for moderate to severe anxiety on this scale). For comorbidity, 35% had 3 to 4 diagnoses; the mean comorbidity for the sample is 2.06, with SD of 1.043. 45.6% had at least one or physical health condition, with mean physical comorbidity of 1.16 and <italic>SD</italic> of 1.50. Psychiatrists diagnosed 26.4% to have schizophrenia or other psychotic disorders, 37.7% to have mood disorders, 18.8% to have anxiety disorders, and 17.1 to have other diagnosis as primary diagnosis. <italic>Mean</italic> GAF score was 52.48 with <italic>SD</italic> of 4.67.</p>
<p><italic>Multiple Regression analyses results</italic> Multiple regression analyses were conducted with cumulative trauma, different trauma types (personal identity, collective identity, attachment, survival, secondary, gender discrimination, and ISMI traumas), as independent variables, and depression, anxiety, PTSD, mental health comorbidities, physical disorders comorbidity, and global assessment of functioning, as dependent variable, controlling for gender, marital status, age, education, residency (rural vs. city), SES (socioeconomic status), employment status and religion as covariates. Cumulative trauma predicted, as hypothesized, highly significant elevation in depression, anxiety, PTSD, mental health comorbidity, physical disorders comorbidity, and reduced GAF. In this sample ISMI was the highest predictor of mental health comorbidity (β = .73****, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = .57), and of reduced global level of functioning (β =.-.90****, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = .81), and was a strong predictor of all mental and physical health variables. Personal identity traumas, in this sample, were relatively the second highest trauma types predictor of all mental and physical health (MH) conditions, especially of physical disorders comorbidity (β = .40****, <italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic> = .20), and PTSD (β = .36****, <italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic> = .22), followed by collective identity traumas that predicted to a lesser degree all MH variables. Attachment traumas predicted PTSD. Secondary traumas predicted all MH variables with different degrees of intensity. Survival traumas predicted all MH variables except GAF. Gender discrimination predicted anxiety, PTSD, and physical disorders comorbidity (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-1534765612459892">Table 5</xref>).</p>
<p><italic>Path analysis Results</italic> To check the effects of specific Type III traumas of poverty, as well as sexual abuse (Type II trauma) which are more present in the trauma profile of Egypt based sample, and the mediation hypothesis of ISMI, we tested different plausible path models. The model that had the best fit includes poverty, sexual abuse, life threatening accidents (a survival trauma), torture, and gender discrimination (Type III trauma for females) as independent variables, ISMI as a mediating variable, and PTSD, anxiety, depression, psychiatric comorbidity, health disorders comorbidity, GAF, as well as self-esteem and futuristic orientation as dependent variables. The model has excellent fit with the data (Chi Square = 47.727, <italic>df</italic> = 51, <italic>p</italic> = .604, CFI = 1.000, RMSEA = .000).</p>
<p>In the model, poverty had highly significant direct positive effects on ISMI, PTSD and depression, and negative effects on self-esteem. Poverty had highly significant indirect positive effects on PTSD, depression, anxiety, psychiatric disorders comorbidity (PDC), physical health disorders comorbidity (PHDC) and negative effects on self-esteem, futuristic orientation and GAF. Sexual abuse had significant direct positive effects on ISMI, PTSD, anxiety, and PHDC. It had significant indirect effects on PTSD, depression, anxiety, PDC, PHDC, and negative effects on self-esteem, futuristic orientation and GAF. ISMI had highly significant direct effects on PTSD, PDC, PHDC, and highly significant negative effects on in self-esteem, futuristic orientation, and global level of functioning. ISMI has significant indirect effects on anxiety. ISMI mediated the effects of poverty, sexual abuse, torture, and gender discrimination on PDC, PHDC, and negative effects on self-esteem, futuristic orientation and GAF. Life threatening accident had significant direct effects on PTSD and direct and indirect effects on depression. It had indirect effects on anxiety, PDC, PHDC, and negative effects on self-esteem, futuristic orientation and GAF. The indirect effects may be small but significant. Torture had direct effects on PTSD and anxiety, and indirect effects on depression and anxiety. It had small but significant negative effects on futuristic orientation. Gender discrimination had direct effects on PTSD and direct and indirect effects on PHDC. It had indirect small but significant effects on depression and anxiety and negative effects on self-esteem (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table7-1534765612459892">Table 7</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table7-1534765612459892" position="float">
<label>Table 7.</label>
<caption><p>Decomposition of Standardized Direct, Indirect, Total Effects and Their Confidence Intervals and Significance on Poverty, Torture, Life Threatening Accident, Gender Discrimination, Sexual Abuse, ISMI, on PTSD, Depression, Anxiety, Self-Esteem, Future Orientation, Mental Health Comorbidity, Physical Health Comorbidity, and Global Level of Functioning.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table7-1534765612459892" xlink:href="10.1177_1534765612459892-table7.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="9">Dependent variables<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Causal variables</th>
<th align="center">Internalized stigma of mental illness</th>
<th align="center">Posttraumatic stress disorder</th>
<th align="center">Self-esteem</th>
<th align="center">Depression</th>
<th align="center">Future orientation</th>
<th align="center">Mental health comorbidity</th>
<th align="center">Physical health comorbidity</th>
<th align="center">Anxiety</th>
<th align="center">Global assessment of functioning</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="10"><italic>Poverty</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Direct effects</td>
<td>.36<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref>(.29/.44)</td>
<td>.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.05/.19)</td>
<td>−.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.25/−.12)</td>
<td>.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">*</xref> (.01/.18)</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Indirect effects</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.08/.15)</td>
<td>−.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.28/−.18)</td>
<td>.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">*</xref> (.02/.06)</td>
<td>−.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.30/−.21)</td>
<td>.28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.23/.34)</td>
<td>.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.09/.17)</td>
<td>.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.07/.14)</td>
<td>−.33<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.40/−.26)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Total effects</italic></td>
<td>.36<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.29/.44)</td>
<td>.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.18/.31)</td>
<td>−.43<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.49/−.36)</td>
<td>.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.07/.22)</td>
<td>−.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.30/−.21)</td>
<td>.28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.23/.34)</td>
<td>.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.09/.17)</td>
<td>.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.07/.14)</td>
<td>−.33<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.40/−.26)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="10"><italic>Torture</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Direct effects</td>
<td>.09 (−.05/.21)</td>
<td>.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.14/.33)</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.09/.22)</td>
<td>.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Indirect effects</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.03 (.−.01/.07)</td>
<td>−.08 (−.16/−.01)</td>
<td>.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.02/.08)</td>
<td>−.07<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">*</xref> (−.14/−.02)</td>
<td>.07 (−.03/.17)</td>
<td>.03 (.00/.08)</td>
<td>.11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.07/.15)</td>
<td>−.09 (−.19/.04)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Total effects</italic></td>
<td>.09 (−.05/.21)</td>
<td>.26<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.17/.34)</td>
<td>−.08 (−.16/−.01)</td>
<td>.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.02/.08)</td>
<td>−.07<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">*</xref> (−.14/−.02)</td>
<td>.07 (−.03/.17)</td>
<td>.03 (.00/.08)</td>
<td>.27<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.17/.36)</td>
<td>−.09 (−.19/.04)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="10"><italic>Life threatening accident</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Direct effects</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.03/.14)</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.17/.27)</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Indirect effects</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>−.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.02/−.00)</td>
<td>.02<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.01/.03)</td>
<td>−.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.03/−.01)</td>
<td>.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.01/.04)</td>
<td>.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">*</xref> (.01/.05)</td>
<td>.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.02/.07)</td>
<td>−.001<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">*</xref> (−.002/.00)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Total effects</italic></td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.03/.14)</td>
<td>−.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.02/−.00)</td>
<td>.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.18/.29)</td>
<td>−.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.03/−.01)</td>
<td>.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.01/.04)</td>
<td>.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">*</xref> (.01/.05)</td>
<td>.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.02/.07)</td>
<td>−.001<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">*</xref> (−.002/.00)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="10"><italic>Gender discrimination</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Direct effects</td>
<td>.09 (−02/.17)</td>
<td>.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.03/.17)</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">*</xref> (.04/.19)</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Indirect effects</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.03 (−.01/.06)</td>
<td>−.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">*</xref> (−.11/−.00)</td>
<td>.02<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.01/.04)</td>
<td>−.05 (−.09/−.00)</td>
<td>.07 (−.01/.13)</td>
<td>.03 (−.00/.06)</td>
<td>.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.03/.09)</td>
<td>−.08 (−.16/.02)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Total effects</italic></td>
<td>.09 (−02/.17)</td>
<td>.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.07/.18)</td>
<td>−.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">*</xref> (−.11/−00)</td>
<td>.02<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.01/.04)</td>
<td>−.05 (−.09/−.00)</td>
<td>.07 (−.01/.13)</td>
<td>.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">*</xref> (.04/.23)</td>
<td>.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.03/.09)</td>
<td>−.08 (−.16/.02)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="10"><italic>Sexual abuse</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Direct effects</td>
<td>.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.09/.24)</td>
<td>.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.13/.24)</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.07/.26)</td>
<td>.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">*</xref> (.02/.15)</td>
<td>.000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Indirect effects</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.03/.08)</td>
<td>−.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.18/−.07)</td>
<td>.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.02/.07)</td>
<td>−.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.14/−.06)</td>
<td>.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.06/.18)</td>
<td>.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.03/.08)</td>
<td>.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.07/.14)</td>
<td>−.15<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">*</xref> (−.21/−.08)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Total effects</italic></td>
<td>.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.09/.24)</td>
<td>.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.18/.30)</td>
<td>−.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.18/−.07)</td>
<td>.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.02/.07)</td>
<td>−.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.14/−.06)</td>
<td>.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.06/.18)</td>
<td>.21<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.12/.32)</td>
<td>.19<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.12/.26)</td>
<td>−.15<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">*</xref> (−.21/−.08)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="10"><italic>Internalized stigma of mental illness</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Direct effects</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.30<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.23/.38)</td>
<td>−.55<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.60/−.49)</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>−.19<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.27/−.10)</td>
<td>.74<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.70/.78)</td>
<td>.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.23/.37)</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>−.87<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.91/−.83)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Indirect Effects</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>−.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.06/−.02)</td>
<td>.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">*</xref> (.03/.08)</td>
<td>−.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.32/−.21)</td>
<td>.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">*</xref> (.00/.01)</td>
<td>.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">*</xref> (.00/.01)</td>
<td>.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.01/.18)</td>
<td>−.03 (−.05/.00)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Total Effects</italic></td>
<td>.000</td>
<td>.30<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.23/.38)</td>
<td>−.59<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.64/−.54)</td>
<td>.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">*</xref> (.03/.08)</td>
<td>−.44<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.51/−.38)</td>
<td>.74<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.71/.78)</td>
<td>.30<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.23/38)</td>
<td>.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (.01/.18)</td>
<td>−.90<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn6-1534765612459892">**</xref> (−.92/−.86)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><italic>Squared R</italic></td>
<td>.195</td>
<td>.312</td>
<td>.509</td>
<td>.113</td>
<td>.335</td>
<td>.571</td>
<td>.181</td>
<td>.297</td>
<td>.808</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn6-1534765612459892">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-1534765612459892">
<title>Summary of Comparative Results</title>
<p>Egyptians are mostly Muslims that live in a Muslim majority, while most of U.S. participants are Muslims, who live, as a minority, in a Christian majority. Most of them are refugees. For <italic>cumulative trauma</italic> load, both communities are multiply traumatized; however, their trauma profiles are different. U.S. participants had more trauma load, but their appraisal of trauma was relatively more positive. Poverty and ISMI were relatively a shared core <italic>collective identity trauma</italic> for samples; oppression, discrimination and up-rootedness were unique core collective identity traumas in the U.S. sample. The Egyptian participants reported relatively higher level of poverty (95% compared to 68% in the American Sample) and much less level of discrimination (2% compared to 38% in the U.S. sample). The participants in the U.S. sample have added trauma of oppression and much higher torture trauma (19% compared to 3% in the Egyptian sample), and being uprooted from their favorite environment (47% compared to 25% for the Egyptian sample).</p>
<p>Sexual abuse and role identity were core <italic>personal identity</italic> traumas, as well as secondary traumas, in the Egyptian sample. Egyptian participants reported higher level of sexual abuse (22% compared to less than 5% reported in the American sample). They reported higher levels of role identity (achievement traumas; 17%% compared to 8.3% for the American participants). They reported higher level of secondary traumas (76% compared to 44% for the American sample). Abandonment trauma seemed to be one of the core traumas in the American sample participants. They reported higher abandonment traumas (9.5% compared to 3.2% for the Egyptian sample).</p>
<p>The results of multiple regressions and path analyses reflected the salient consistent effects of CT and the differential effects of different trauma profiles. The effects of cumulative trauma in both samples were similar as it was associated with, significant increase in depression, anxiety, PTSD, mental and physical disorders comorbidities, and reduced global functioning. The effects of different traumas reflected similarities and differences according to the different representations of each trauma in the trauma profile for each. In the U.S. study where participants were exposed to more oppression, discrimination and torture, collective identity traumas were the strongest predictor of mental health variables followed by personal identity traumas. Oppression and discrimination (Type III traumas) have significant effects on increased PTSD, CTD, depression, anxiety, and poor health. In the Egyptian sample personal identity (e.g., sexual abuse), and attachment traumas were more prevalent. Personal identity traumas (sexual abuse) in the Egyptian sample was strong predictor of increased ISMI, PTSD, anxiety, depression, psychiatric disorders comorbidity, physical health disorders comorbidity and decreased self-esteem, futuristic orientation and GAF. However, ISMI and poverty were salient predictors of different mental health indicators in both samples. Poverty, and ISMI in both samples, had highly significant effects on increased, PTSD, anxiety, psychiatric disorders comorbidity, physical health disorders comorbidity and decreased self-esteem, futuristic orientation and GAF. Secondary and survival trauma occurrence were comparable in both samples. Secondary traumas predicted all MH variables with different degrees of intensity in both samples. Survival traumas predicted all MH variables except global level of functioning in both samples. Attachment traumas predicted depression, and to some degree CTD, and high decrease in global level of functioning in U.S. sample (participants have relatively higher attachment traumas). Attachment traumas, which were less in the Egyptian sample, predicted PTSD only in this sample.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-1534765612459892">
<title>Discussion and Conclusions</title>
<p>The trans-theoretical model we developed crossed over the intricate divide between the three traumatology paradigms. Results highlighted the DBTF model’s flexibility and sensitivity and provided preliminary evidence of the validity and utility of the integrated new model, and its potential contribution to driving trauma field forward. The results confirmed the relevance of trauma profile analysis in determining the health and mental health consequences of traumatic stress. Type III trauma (e.g., poverty, ISMI), in both samples have more serious effects than Type I (car accident), and Type II (e.g., sexual abuse).</p>
<p>The results replicated the three trauma paradigms findings of the negative effects of each trauma type. Previous studies found that ethnic and racial discrimination have serious mental and physical health effects (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1534765612459892">Brody et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1534765612459892">Gee &amp; Waslemann, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1534765612459892">Pascoe &amp; Richman, 2009</xref>). Gender discrimination was found to have negative mental health on females and relatively positive mental health effects for males (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1534765612459892">Kira et al., 2010b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1534765612459892">Kira et al., 2012d</xref>). Abandonment, child maltreatment, and sexual abuse literatures provide convincing evidence of their negative effects (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1534765612459892">Baer, &amp; Martinez, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1534765612459892">Cassidy, &amp; Shaver, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1534765612459892">Cicchetti &amp; Lynch, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1534765612459892">Kessler et al., 1997</xref>). The negative effects of survival traumas, for example, war and violence are well documented, especially their effects on veterans (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-1534765612459892">van der Kolk et al., 1996</xref>). It is important to assess for all trauma variables represented in the three trauma paradigms and tailor treatment to the relevant core traumas for the individual person.</p>
<p>One of the especially neglected aspect of trauma assessment is the construction of cultural/gender identity, discrimination, poverty, and ethnicity. The effects of different identity traumas collective, personal and role identity on global level of functioning, comorbidity, different mental health variables, are highly negative in both samples. The effects of poverty, as well as ISMI in mental health patients, are especially extremely negative in both samples. Torture, gender discrimination, oppression, and stereotyping have direct significant effects on PTSD. The results of the effects of gender discrimination by society on PTSD, physical disorders comorbidity, depression, anxiety, and decreased self-esteem replicated previous studies that put gender discrimination, often ignored in assessment, on the trauma map (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1534765612459892">Kira et al., 2010, 2012d</xref>). Results indicated that it is increasingly important to address the origins of structural violence and intergroup traumas in affected individuals and groups.</p>
<p>The new integrated model has more promise to explore the cumulative dynamics in all trauma types without ignoring any. The new trans-theoretical paradigm would enrich and enhance the contributions of different theories in their related focused and applications, through comparative analysis, reconfiguration, and looking to the big picture.</p>
<p>DBTF and its applications have important implications for trauma assessment, clinical intervention, and research. The results highlighted the importance of assessing trauma profile and cumulative trauma dynamics, for each patient, using the integrative framework, and not only one type of trauma. Limited assessment that focuses on one trauma type, or a single trauma, can be misleading, prevent clear case conceptualization and impede effective treatment. When studying the effects of trauma or cumulative trauma that drives pathology, each trauma paradigm, used its trauma types to determine the outcomes, ignoring the other potential operating dynamics of the other trauma types. Each trauma type that was the main concern of each of the three trauma paradigms has significant role in the mental health symptom production. Focusing on only one type or ignoring any one of them would be a serious clinical mistake that can amount, at least in some cases, to clients’ neglect. The presenting problem can mask the core trauma/s and the cumulative dynamics. Some used the triggering trauma ignoring the cumulative dynamics that hide the core salient (index) trauma/s.</p>
<p>To conclude, there are at least four lessons that are derived from current research. First, the integrative model of trauma assessment that evaluate all trauma types using the DBTF integrative approach has more clinical utility, theoretical, and empirical validity. Second, the configuration of trauma profile that determine empirically which is the core more salient trauma/s the individual encountered is important clinical tool derived from the new DBTF paradigm. Third, relying on the assessment of single trauma type, ignoring the dynamics of polyvictimization within each trauma types and cumulative trauma that measure concurrent traumatization/victimization by different trauma types may be a wrong approach and can amount to clients neglect and or faulty spurious research approach. More studies are needed to identify the different or similar dynamics of different trauma types in different populations and cultures and to perfect the integrated measurement model to be more inclusive and parsimonious. Finally, the innovations of the current trauma framework may help in charting the terrain for optimal sound and updated guidelines for trauma and complex trauma treatment and service-delivery for the trauma victims.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>American Psychiatric Association</collab>. (<year>1994</year>). <source>Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders</source> (<edition>4th ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>American Psychological Association Trauma Group</collab>. (<year>2000</year>, <month>August</month> <day>6</day>). <source>Members meeting minutes update</source>. <publisher-loc>Minneapolis, MN</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>VAMC</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Arbuckle</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Amos 7.0 user’s guide</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Statistical Package for the Social Sciences</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Child maltreatment and insecure attachment: A meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Reproductive &amp; Infant Psychology</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>187</fpage>-<lpage>197</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>A. O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Melle</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rossberg</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Romm</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lagerberg</surname><given-names>T. V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Hauff</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>, <month>May</month> <day>6</day>). <article-title>Perceived discrimination is associated with severity of positive and depression/anxiety symptoms in immigrants with psychosis: A cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>BMC Psychiatry</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>77</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weathers</surname><given-names>F. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaloupek</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klauminzer</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Charney</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keane</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>A clinician rating scale for assessing current and lifetime PTSD: The CAPS–1</article-title>. <source>Behavior Therapist</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>187</fpage>-<lpage>188</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bowlby</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <source>A secure base: Parent child attachment and healthy human development</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brody</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kogan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murry</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Linking perceived discrimination to longitudinal changes in African American mothers’ parenting practices</article-title>. <source>Journal of Marriage and Family</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>319</fpage>-<lpage>331</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Cassidy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shaver</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds). (<year>1999</year>) <source>Handbook of attachment: Theory, research, and clinical applications</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cassiman</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Toward more inclusive poverty knowledge: Traumatological contributions to the poverty discourse</article-title>. <source>Social Policy Journal and Cutting Edge of Social Policy Research</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>93</fpage>-<lpage>106</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cicchetti</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Failures in the expectable environment and their impact on individual development: The case of child maltreatment</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Cicchetti</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Developmental psychopathology: Vol. 2. Risk, disorder, and adaptation</source> (<edition>2nd ed.</edition>, pp. <fpage>32</fpage>-<lpage>71</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cloitre</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stolbach</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Herman.</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van der Kolk</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pynoos</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petkova</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>A developmental approach to complex PTSD: Childhood and adult cumulative trauma as predictors of symptom complexity</article-title>. <source>Journal of Traumatic Stress</source>, <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>399</fpage>-<lpage>408</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Corrigan</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The self-stigma of mental illness: Implications for self-esteem and self-efficacy</article-title>. <source>Journal of Social &amp; Clinical Psychology</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>875</fpage>-<lpage>884</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Courtois</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds). (<year>2009</year>). <source>Treating complex traumatic stress disorder</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>De Bellis</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Developmental traumatology: The psychobiological development of maltreated children and its implications for research, treatment, and policy</article-title>. <source>Developmental Psychopathology</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>539</fpage>-<lpage>564</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Erceg-Hurn</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mirosevich</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Modern robust statistical methods: An easy way to maximize the accuracy and power of your research</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>, <volume>63</volume>, <fpage>591</fpage>-<lpage>601</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Figley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.). (<year>1995</year>). <source>Compassion fatigue: Coping with secondary traumatic stress disorder in those who treat the traumatized</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brunner/Mazel</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Finkelhor</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>H. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamby</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The victimization of children and youth: A comprehensive, national survey</article-title>. <source>Child Maltreatment</source>, <volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tschann</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dimas</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pasch</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Groat</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Perceived racial/ethnic discrimination, posttraumatic stress symptoms, and health risk behaviors among Mexican American adolescents</article-title>. <source>Journal of Counseling Psychology</source>, <volume>57</volume>, <fpage>264</fpage>-<lpage>273</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fournier</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Psychological trauma and post-traumatic stress disorder among women in community mental health aftercare following psychiatric intensive care</article-title>. <source>Journal of Psychiatric Intensive Care</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>27</fpage>-<lpage>34</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Freyd</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <source>Betrayal trauma: The logic of forgetting childhood abuse</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Freyd</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DePrince</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gleaves</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The State of Betrayal Trauma Theory: Reply to McNally (2007)—Conceptual issues and future directions</article-title>. <source>Memory</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>295</fpage>-<lpage>311</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gee</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>D. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>A nationwide study of discrimination and chronic health conditions among Asian Americans</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Public Health</source>, <volume>97</volume>, <fpage>1275</fpage>-<lpage>1282</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gee</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walsemann</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Does health predict the reporting of racial discrimination or do reports of discrimination predict health? Findings from the national longitudinal study of youth</article-title>. <source>Social Science &amp; Medicine</source>, <volume>68</volume>, <fpage>1676</fpage>-<lpage>1684</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gilman</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cochran</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mays</surname><given-names>V. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ostrow</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Risk of psychiatric disorders among individuals reporting same-sex sexual partners in the National Comorbidity Survey</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Public Health</source>, <volume>91</volume>, <fpage>933</fpage>-<lpage>939</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hamby</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Finkelhor</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ormrod</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The overlap of witnessing partner violence and child maltreatment and other victimizations in a nationally representative survey of youth</article-title>. <source>Child Abuse &amp; Neglect</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>734</fpage>-<lpage>741</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Helms</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Racism and ethno-violence as trauma: Enhancing professional training</article-title>. <source>Traumatology</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>53</fpage>-<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <source>Trauma and recovery</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaysan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Resick</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Duration of exposure and dose-response model of PTSD</article-title>. <source>Journal of Interpersonal Violence</source>, <volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>63</fpage>-<lpage>74</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>C. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kendler</surname><given-names>K. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Childhood adversity and adult psychiatric disorder in the U.S. National Comorbidity Survey</article-title>. <source>Psychological Medicine</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>1101</fpage>-<lpage>1119</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Taxonomy of trauma and trauma assessment</article-title>. <source>Traumatology</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>14</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Secondary trauma in treating refugee survivors of torture and their families</article-title>. <source>Torture</source>, <volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>38</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Etiology and treatments of post-cumulative traumatic stress disorders in different cultures</article-title>. <source>Traumatology: An International Journal</source>, <volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>128</fpage>-<lpage>141</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ashby</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewandowski</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Odenat</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012d</year>). <article-title>Gender inequality and its effects in females torture survivors</article-title>. <source>Psychology</source>, <volume>3</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>352</fpage>-<lpage>363</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clifford</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Al-haider</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Iraqi refugees in Southeast Michigan: First report</source>. <publisher-name>ACCESS community Health and Research Center</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clifford</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Al-haider</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>, <month>August</month> <day>7-11</day>). <source>Assessing and treating cumulative trauma disorders (CTD) in Iraqi refugees</source>. <conf-name>Paper presented in the American Psychological Association Annual Convention</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Toronto, Canada</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewandowski</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chiodo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012a</year>). <article-title>PTSD, trauma types, cumulative trauma, and IQ: The case of African American and Iraqi refugee adolescents</article-title>. <source>Psychological Trauma: Theory, Research, Practice, and Policy</source>, <volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>128</fpage>-<lpage>139</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewandowski</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Templin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mohanesh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abdulkhalek</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011b</year>, <month>August</month>). <source>The dynamics of internalized stigma of mental illness among Arab Americans, Muslims, and refugees patients: A traumatology perspective</source>. <conf-name>Paper presented in the American Psychological Association Annual Convention</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Washington, DC</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewandowski</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Templin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ramaswamy</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chiodo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ozkan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mohanesh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008b</year>, <month>August</month>). <source>Measuring cumulative trauma dose, types and profiles using a development-based taxonomy of traumas: The long version</source>. <conf-name>Paper presented in American Psychological Association 116th Annual Convention</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Boston, MA</conf-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewandowsk</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Templin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ramaswamy</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ozkan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mohanesh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008a</year>). <article-title>Measuring cumulative trauma dose, types and profiles using a development-based taxonomy of trauma</article-title>. <source>Traumatology</source>, <volume>14</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>62</fpage>-<lpage>87</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewandowsi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Templin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ramaswamy</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ozkan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mohanesh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010b</year>). <article-title>The effects of perceived discrimination and backlash on Iraqi refugees’ physical and mental health</article-title>. <source>Journal of Muslim Mental Health</source>, <volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>59</fpage>-<lpage>81</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewandowski</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chiodo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012b</year>). <article-title>The linear and non-linear associations between multiple types of trauma and IQ discrepancy indexes in African American and Iraqi refugee adolescents</article-title>. <source>Journal of Child &amp; Adolescent Trauma</source>, <volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewandowski</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Templin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010a</year>).<article-title>The effects of perceived gender discrimination on refugee torture survivors: A cross-cultural traumatology perspective</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Psychiatric Nurses Association</source>, <volume>16</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>299</fpage>-<lpage>306</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewandowski</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chiodo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Attachment disruptions, IQ and PTSD in African American adolescents (AAA): A traumatology perspective</article-title>. <source>Journal of Aggression, Maltreatment, and Trauma</source>, <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>665</fpage>–<lpage>690</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Templin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewandowski</surname></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Cumulative Trauma Disorder Scale: Two studies</article-title>. <source>Psychology</source>, <volume>3</volume>(<issue>9</issue>), <fpage>642</fpage>-<lpage>655</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Templin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewandowski</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clifford</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wiencek</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hammad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Mohanesh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The effects of torture: Two community studies</article-title>. <source>Peace and Conflict: Journal of Peace Psychology</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>205</fpage>-<lpage>228</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Templin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewandowski</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ramaswamy</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bulent</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abu-Mediane</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Alamia</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011a</year>). <article-title>Cumulative tertiary appraisal of traumatic events across cultures: Two studies</article-title>. <source>Journal of Loss and Trauma: International Perspectives on Stress &amp; Coping</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>43</fpage>-<lpage>66</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kira</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Templin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lewandowski</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ramaswamy</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bulent</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mohanesh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abdulkhaleq</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012c</year>). <article-title>Collective and personal annihilation anxiety: Measuring annihilation anxiety AA</article-title>. <source>Psychology</source>, <volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>90</fpage>-<lpage>99</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kobak</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Little</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Race</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Acosta</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Attachment disruptions in seriously emotionally disturbed children: Implications for treatment</article-title>. <source>Attachment &amp; Human Development</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>243</fpage>-<lpage>258</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lovibond</surname><given-names>P. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lovibond</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>The structure of negative emotional states: Comparison of the Depression Anxiety and Stress Scales (DASS) with the Beck Depression and Anxiety Inventories</article-title>. <source>Behavior Research and Therapy</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>335</fpage>-<lpage>342</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Macfie</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cicchetti</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Toth</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The development of dissociation in maltreated preschool-aged children</article-title>. <source>Development and Psychopathology</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>233</fpage>-<lpage>254</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cromer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DePrince</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Freyd</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>, <month>November</month> <day>28</day>). <article-title>The role of cumulative trauma, betrayal, and appraisals in understanding trauma symptomatology</article-title>. <source>Psychological Trauma: Theory, Research, Practice, and Policy</source>. Advance online publication. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0025686</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mueser</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trumbetta</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Osher</surname><given-names>F. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vidaver</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>. . . Foy</surname><given-names>E.W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Trauma and posttraumatic stress disorder in severe mental illness</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology</source>, <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>493</fpage>-<lpage>499</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mulrow</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gerety</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Montiel</surname><given-names>O. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kerber</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Case-finding instruments for depression in primary care settings</article-title>. <source>Annals of Internal Medicine</source>, <volume>122</volume>, <fpage>913</fpage>-<lpage>921</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>O’Brien</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>A caution regarding rules of thumb for variance inflation factors</article-title>. <source>Quality &amp; Quantity</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>673</fpage>-<lpage>690</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Palmieri</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weathers</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Difede</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Confirmatory factor analysis of the PTSD Checklist and the Clinician-Administered PTSD Scale in disaster workers exposed to the World Trade Center Ground Zero</article-title>. <source>Journal of Abnormal Psychology</source>, <volume>116</volume>, <fpage>329</fpage>-<lpage>341</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pascoe</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richman</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Perceived discrimination and health: A meta-analytic review</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>135</volume>, <fpage>531</fpage>-<lpage>554</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peretz</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baider</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ever-Hadani</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De-Nour</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Psychological distress in female cancer patients with Holocaust experience</article-title>. <source>General Hospital Psychiatry</source>, <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>413</fpage>-<lpage>418</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Radloff</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>). <article-title>The CES-D scale: A self-report depression scale for research in the general population</article-title>. <source>Applied Psychological Measurement</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>385</fpage>-<lpage>401</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Richmond</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>A. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aspelmeier</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Polyvictimization, childhood victimization, and psychological distress in college women</article-title>. <source>Child Maltreatment</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>127</fpage>-<lpage>147</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ritsher</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Otilingam</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grajales</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Internalized stigma of mental illness: Psychometric properties of a new measure</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry Research</source>, <volume>121</volume>, <fpage>31</fpage>-<lpage>49</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1965</year>). <source>Society and the adolescent self-image</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Psychosocial influences: Critiques, findings, and research needs</article-title>. <source>Developmental Psychopathology</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>375</fpage>-<lpage>405</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shevlin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Houston</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dorahy</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adamson</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Cumulative traumas and psychosis: An analysis of the National Comorbidity Survey and the British Psychiatric Morbidity Survey</article-title>. <source>Schizophrenia Bulletin</source>, <volume>34</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>193</fpage>-<lpage>199</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sue</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Microaggressions in everyday life: Race, gender, and sexual orientation</source>. <publisher-loc>Hoboken, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Terr</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Childhood traumas: An outline and overview</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Psychiatry</source>, <volume>148</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>10</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Van der Kolk</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Developmental trauma disorder: Toward a rational diagnosis for children with complex trauma histories</article-title>. <source>Psychiatric Annals</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>401</fpage>-<lpage>408</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-1534765612459892">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>van der Kolk</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weisaeth</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van der Hart</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>History of trauma in psychiatry</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>van der Kolk</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McFarlane</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weisaeth</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Traumatic stress. The effects of overwhelming experience on mind, body, and society</source> (pp. <fpage>47</fpage>-<lpage>74</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>