<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JCN</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjcn</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Child Neurol</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Child Neurology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0883-0738</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1708-8283</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0883073812463609</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0883073812463609</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Topical Review Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Clobazam</article-title>
<subtitle>A Newly Approved But Well-Established Drug for the Treatment of Intractable Epilepsy Syndromes</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Wheless</surname>
<given-names>James W.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0883073812463609">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0883073812463609"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Phelps</surname>
<given-names>Stephanie J.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>PharmD, BCPS</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0883073812463609">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0883073812463609">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0883073812463609"><label>1</label>LeBonheur Children’s Hospital, University of Tennessee Health Science Center, Memphis, TN, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0883073812463609"><label>2</label>Department of Clinical Pharmacy, College of Pharmacy, University of Tennessee Health Science Center, Memphis, TN, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0883073812463609">James W. Wheless, MD, UTHSC–Pediatric Neurology, 355 Le Bonheur Physician’s Office Building, 777 Washington Avenue, Memphis, TN 38105. Email: <email>jwheless@uthsc.edu</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>28</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>219</fpage>
<lpage>229</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Clobazam, a 1,5-benzodiazepine, was introduced in the 1970s as an anxiolytic and antiepileptic drug. Despite worldwide usage, it was only recently approved in the United States (seizures associated with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome). This article reviews historical and recent data to help practitioners better understand clobazam’s clinical properties and usage. In many clinical trials, open-label studies, and retrospective reviews, clobazam was generally associated with ≥50% seizure reduction for more than half of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome patients, with approximately 10% achieving freedom from drop attacks. Efficacy is persistent, with little evidence for development of tolerance. Clobazam’s safety profile appears to be similar to that of other benzodiazepines, but with substantially decreased sedation and increased psychomotor performance. Studies suggest clobazam acts through potentiation of gamma-aminobutyric acid type A receptors in a manner similar to other benzodiazepines. However, clobazam appears to display greater selectivity for receptors responsible for anticonvulsant activity than for those involved in sedation.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>clobazam</kwd>
<kwd>Lennox-Gastaut syndrome</kwd>
<kwd>benzodiazepine</kwd>
<kwd>epilepsy</kwd>
<kwd>antiepileptic drugs</kwd>
<kwd>refractory</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0883073812463609">
<title>Global and Historical Perspectives</title>
<p>Clobazam is a 1,5-benzodiazepine first synthesized in 1966 in the anticipation of improving on the efficacy and decreasing the sedative effects associated with the 1,4-benzodiazepines.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0883073812463609">1</xref>
</sup> It was initially approved in Australia in 1970<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0883073812463609">2</xref>
</sup> and France in 1974 as an anxiolytic.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0883073812463609">1</xref>
</sup> Its anticonvulsant properties in both animals<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0883073812463609">3</xref>
</sup> and humans<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0883073812463609">4</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0883073812463609"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0883073812463609"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0883073812463609">7</xref>
</sup> were quickly recognized.</p>
<p>The efficacy of clobazam as a broad-spectrum anticonvulsant was initially demonstrated in animal studies. Clobazam was protective against the tonic phase of pentylenetetrazol-, electroshock-, and sound-induced seizures in mice and against photo-induced seizures in baboons.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0883073812463609">3</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0883073812463609">8</xref>
</sup> Additional comparative studies demonstrated equal or greater protective effects at nontoxic doses of clobazam relative to diazepam, phenobarbital, and valproate in chemically induced seizures in mice and rats<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0883073812463609">9</xref>
</sup> and to 10 different 1,4-benzodiazepines in an electroshock model in mice.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0883073812463609">10</xref>
</sup> Importantly, clobazam was associated with substantially reduced sedative and myorelaxant effects relative to the 1,4-benzodiazepines.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0883073812463609">10</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Since its introduction in humans, clobazam has been used broadly as both an anxiolytic and anticonvulsant, with more than 3.4 million patient-years of exposure worldwide documented from November 1994 to February 2010.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0883073812463609">11</xref>
</sup> It has been useful as monotherapy for partial and generalized pediatric epilepsy, as adjunctive therapy with stiripentol in the treatment of Dravet syndrome, and as adjunctive therapy in combination with valproate and other anticonvulsants in the treatment of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0883073812463609">2</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0883073812463609">12</xref>
</sup> Its clinical benefits and safety have been established through nearly 40 years of continuous use, as well as through more than 50 European studies of more than 3000 pediatric and adult patients with epilepsy.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0883073812463609">1</xref>
</sup> Recent US clinical trials of clobazam as adjunctive therapy for the treatment of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome support the established efficacy and safety profile.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0883073812463609">13</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0883073812463609">14</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0883073812463609">
<title>Current Regulatory Status</title>
<p>Clobazam has been approved in more than 100 countries worldwide.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0883073812463609">1</xref>
</sup> In Europe, it is used broadly as an anxiolytic and as “adjunctive therapy in patients with epilepsy who are not adequately stabilized with their anticonvulsant therapies.”<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0883073812463609">15</xref>
</sup> Despite the widespread acceptance of clobazam throughout the world, it has only recently been approved for use by the Food and Drug Administration in the United States. Several marketing and regulatory hurdles contributed to the delay. An investigational new drug application for clobazam was filed with the Food and Drug Administration in 2005 by the first US company to sponsor it (Ovation Pharmaceuticals, Inc, which was acquired by H. Lundbeck A/S in March 2009). The Food and Drug Administration granted orphan drug status to clobazam in December 2008 for the adjunctive treatment of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome, and the 2 clinical trials required by the FDA for approval were completed by April 2010. The Food and Drug Administration approved clobazam in October 2011 as adjunctive therapy for the treatment of seizures associated with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome in patients aged 2 years and older.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0883073812463609">
<title>Background on Lennox-Gastaut Syndrome</title>
<p>Lennox-Gastaut syndrome is one of several catastrophic epilepsy syndromes with early-childhood onset and progression into adulthood. Although relatively rare (incidence is approximately 0.1/100 000),<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0883073812463609">12</xref>
</sup> Lennox-Gastaut syndrome is notoriously intractable to treatment with antiepileptic drugs, such that its prevalence in childhood epilepsies is 3% to 10%.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0883073812463609">16</xref>
</sup> Published, comprehensive descriptions of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome features and diagnostic criteria include those by Arzimanoglou et al,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0883073812463609">17</xref>
</sup> Giarratano et al,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0883073812463609">12</xref>
</sup> and Markand.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0883073812463609">16</xref>
</sup> These descriptions suggest that Lennox-Gastaut syndrome is distinguished from related epilepsy syndromes through a core triad of features that includes the presence of several seizure types (of which generalized tonic, atonic, and atypical absence are the most common), a characteristic slow spike-and-wave complex on electroencephalogram, and developmental delay associated with cognitive impairment and behavioral problems (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0883073812463609">Box 1</xref>). Diagnosis of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome is frequently difficult owing to heterogeneous clinical presentation and/or lack of all diagnostic features upon disease onset.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0883073812463609">12</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0883073812463609">17</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0883073812463609">18</xref>
</sup> However, because of the substantial differences in prognosis and treatment, it is essential to distinguish Lennox-Gastaut syndrome from other epilepsy disorders.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0883073812463609">12</xref>
</sup> The clinical and electroencephalogram features associated with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome evolve with time, and adults should be considered part of the Lennox-Gastaut syndrome spectrum.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0883073812463609">12</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0883073812463609">17</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0883073812463609" position="float">
<label>Box 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Core Features of Lennox-Gastaut Syndrome.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0883073812463609" xlink:href="10.1177_0883073812463609-table3.tif"/>
<table frame="box">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Age of onset</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Usually before 8 y, peak between 3 and 5 y</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Etiology</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Brain damage</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Focal or multifocal abnormalities of cortical development</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Tuberous sclerosis</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Acquired destructive lesions</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Metabolic disorders</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Cryptogenic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Seizure types</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Common and defining types, frequent in the early stages of disease</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Tonic, atonic, and atypical absence (most common)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Focal, with or without secondary generalization</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Nonconvulsive status epilepticus</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Associated but not defining, usually occur in later stages of disease</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Myoclonic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Tonic-clonic, generalized, and unilateral clonic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Electroencephalogram features</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Slow spike-wave complexes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Diffuse or bilateral fast rhythm patterns, or polyspikes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Developmental issues</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Developmental delay, increasing with time</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Personality or behavioral disorder, psychosis</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0883073812463609">
<p>Source: Arzimanoglou et al.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0883073812463609">17</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>First-line treatment for Lennox-Gastaut syndrome typically includes broad-range antiepileptic drugs such as valproate, topiramate, and lamotrigine, all of which can be useful for controlling the dangerous drop attacks (seizures resulting in uncontrolled falls) that predominate during the early stages of the disease. Benzodiazepines, particularly nitrazepam, clonazepam, and clobazam, are also useful for controlling a broad range of seizure types, including drop attacks.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0883073812463609">17</xref>
</sup> In the United States, felbamate (Felbatol<sup>®</sup>, Medpoint Pharmaceuticals); lamotrigine (Lamictal<sup>®</sup>, GlaxoSmithKline); topiramate (Topamax<sup>®</sup>, Janssen Pharmaceuticals); rufinamide (Banzel<sup>®</sup>, Eisai); and, most recently, clobazam (Onfi<sup>®</sup>, Lundbeck) are all approved as adjunctive treatment for Lennox-Gastaut syndrome. Additional nonpharmacologic therapeutic options include ketogenic diet, vagus nerve stimulation, resective surgery, and complete corpus callostomy.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0883073812463609">17</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0883073812463609"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0883073812463609"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0883073812463609">20</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>We conducted a comprehensive review of historical and recent data in the medical literature on clobazam, including clinical efficacy and safety, pharmacology, and pharmacoeconomics to provide perspective on its use in epileptology.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0883073812463609" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>PubMed, Embase, and selected abstract databases were searched using the term <italic>clobazam</italic> plus additional terms including but not limited to <italic>safety</italic>, <italic>efficacy</italic>, <italic>open-label</italic>, and <italic>clinical trial</italic>. Papers related mainly to anxiolytic properties were excluded. Given the breadth of literature related to clobazam, recent reviews were used to guide selection of primary references. Regulatory documents were also surveyed for pertinent references. No date or language restrictions were given. However, we relied on review articles to summarize non-English language reports.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0883073812463609">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section6-0883073812463609">
<title>Clinical Pharmacology</title>
<sec id="section7-0883073812463609">
<title>Description/overview</title>
<p>Benzodiazepines are effective antiepileptic drugs that are useful for controlling a broad range of seizure types. However, they are also commonly associated with a number of adverse effects, notably sedation, hypotonia, and ataxia.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0883073812463609">1</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0883073812463609">2</xref>
</sup> Clobazam is a 1,5-benzodiazepine first synthesized in 1966 as an alternative to the common 1,4-benzodiazepines, such as diazepam and clonazepam.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0883073812463609">1</xref>
</sup> Its unique chemical structure, in which nitrogens occupy the 1 and 5 positions of the diazepine ring with a keto group at the 4 position (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0883073812463609">Figure 1</xref>), confers different pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic properties relative to 1,4-benzodiazepine. It is a long-acting benzodiazepine (median half-life in serum &gt;36 hours based on population pharmacokinetics analyses) and is the only 1,5-benzodiazepine currently in clinical use.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0883073812463609">2</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<fig id="fig1-0883073812463609" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Chemical structures of (A) the 1,5-benzodiazepine clobazam and (B) the 1,4-benzodiazepine diazepam. The 2 classes differ in the relative positioning of nitrogen within the diazepine ring.</p>
<p>Source: Adapted with permission from Sankar et al.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0883073812463609">2</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0883073812463609-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Like the 1,4-benzodiazepines, clobazam is thought to act mainly through allosteric activation of gamma-aminobutyric acid type A (GABA<sub>A</sub>) receptors, but with better selectivity for those receptors responsible for anticonvulsant activity relative to those responsible for sedation.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0883073812463609">1</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0883073812463609">2</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0883073812463609">21</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0883073812463609">22</xref>
</sup> Clobazam also up-regulates the GABA transporters GAT1 and GAT3.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0883073812463609">23</xref>
</sup> In clinical use, clobazam is associated with decreased sedation and increased psychomotor performance relative to the 1,4-benzodiazepines.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0883073812463609">2</xref>
</sup> A biologically active metabolite of clobazam, <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam, is characterized by similar potency but lesser efficacy and a longer half-life than the parent compound (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0883073812463609">Table 1</xref>).<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0883073812463609">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0883073812463609">24</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0883073812463609"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0883073812463609">26</xref>
</sup> Plasma concentrations of clobazam and particularly <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam are sensitive to cytochrome P450 3A4 and 2C19 enzyme activity.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0883073812463609" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Pharmacokinetic Parameters of Clobazam and <italic>N</italic>-Desmethylclobazam.<sup>a</sup>
</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0883073812463609" xlink:href="10.1177_0883073812463609-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th colspan="2">Clobazam</th>
<th colspan="2">
<italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Pharmacokinetic parameter</th>
<th>Single dose</th>
<th>Steady state</th>
<th>Single dose</th>
<th>Steady state</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>C<sub>max</sub> (ng/mL), mean (% CV)</td>
<td>848 (25)</td>
<td>1 373 (25)</td>
<td>141 (27)</td>
<td>2 566 (43)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>t<sub>max</sub> (hr), median (range)</td>
<td>1.5 (0-6)</td>
<td>2.0 (0.8-6.0)</td>
<td>24.0 (16-24)</td>
<td>7.0 (0-48)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AUC<sub>0–lqc</sub> (ng·hr/mL), mean (% CV)</td>
<td>8 783 (19)</td>
<td>39 932 (34)</td>
<td>2 363 (25)</td>
<td>147 459 (52)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>t<sub>½</sub> (hr), mean (% CV)</td>
<td>NA</td>
<td>32 (36)</td>
<td>NA</td>
<td>57 (16)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0883073812463609">
<p>Abbreviations: C<sub>max</sub>, maximum plasma concentration; CV, coefficient of variation; t<sub>max</sub>, time to maximum plasma concentration; AUC<sub>0–lqc</sub>, area under the concentration time curve from time zero to last quantifiable concentration; t<sub>½</sub>, terminal elimination half-life.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-0883073812463609">
<p>
<sup>a</sup>Data are from Walzer et al.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0883073812463609">26</xref>
</sup> Eighteen healthy volunteers aged 18 to 45 years were given single doses or daily dosages of 40 mg of oral clobazam.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0883073812463609">
<title>Mechanism of action</title>
<p>Clobazam and its active metabolite, <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam, regulate GABA activity through allosteric enhancement of GABA<sub>A</sub> receptor function, a mechanism shared with that of the 1,4-benzodiazepines. As with other benzodiazepines, clobazam binds to a unique site (the “benzodiazepine site”) at the interface of GABA<sub>A</sub> subunits α and γ.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0883073812463609">2</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0883073812463609">27</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0883073812463609">28</xref>
</sup> Occupancy of the benzodiazepine site potentiates the effect of GABA binding to a distinct site within the receptor, increasing the rate (but not duration) of calcium channel opening. The resulting calcium flux leads to inhibitory postsynaptic membrane hyperpolarization.</p>
<p>Although this core mechanism appears to be shared by all benzodiazepines, important differences in pharmacology have been observed between individual benzodiazepine family members. These differences are thought to arise from differential binding to a broad spectrum of receptor subtypes. The GABA<sub>A</sub> receptor family is highly heterogeneous, comprising several subtypes that differ in subunit composition, subcellular localization, and distribution throughout the central nervous system.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0883073812463609">2</xref>
</sup> Although classic 1,4-benzodiazepines such as diazepam are frequently nonselective, full agonists of GABA<sub>A</sub> receptor function, clobazam is thought to be a selective, partial agonist.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0883073812463609">2</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0883073812463609">29</xref>
</sup> For example, in in vitro experiments with recombinant GABA<sub>A</sub> receptors, clobazam and <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam displayed lesser potency than diazepam but similar maximum efficacy.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0883073812463609">30</xref>
</sup> Moreover, clobazam appears to exhibit better selectivity toward those GABA<sub>A</sub> subunits (ω2; α<sub>2/3</sub>β<sub>1/2</sub>γ<sub>2</sub>) responsible for anxiolytic and anticonvulsant effects than for those (ω1; α<sub>1</sub>β<sub>1/2</sub>γ<sub>2</sub>) involved in sedation.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0883073812463609">21</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0883073812463609">22</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0883073812463609">31</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0883073812463609">
<title>Pharmacokinetics</title>
<sec id="section10-0883073812463609">
<title>Absorption and distribution</title>
<p>Clobazam oral formulations are rapidly absorbed, with 87% to 100% bioavailability. Time to maximum plasma concentration is approximately 1 to 4 hours (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0883073812463609">Table 1</xref>).<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0883073812463609">1</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0883073812463609">26</xref>
</sup> Absorption is largely unaffected by food.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0883073812463609">32</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0883073812463609"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0883073812463609">34</xref>
</sup> Clobazam is lipophilic and distributes rapidly throughout the body.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0883073812463609">34</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0883073812463609"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0883073812463609"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0883073812463609"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0883073812463609"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0883073812463609">36</xref>
</sup> It is 80% to 90% protein–bound in serum (ie, predominantly albumin),<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0883073812463609">34</xref>
</sup>
<sup>-</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0883073812463609">36</xref>
</sup> as is its active metabolite, <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0883073812463609">
<title>Metabolism and elimination</title>
<p>Clobazam is metabolized in the liver via the cytochrome P450 system in 2 distinct steps.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0883073812463609">37</xref>
</sup> First, it is demethylated to <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam, primarily by cytochrome P450 3A4 and, to a lesser extent, by cytochrome P450 2C19. <italic>N</italic>-Desmethylclobazam is then hydroxylated to 4'-hydroxydesmethylclobazam, primarily by cytochrome P450 2C19. This metabolic pathway is distinct from that of most of the 1,4-benzodiazepines. For example, although some 1,4-benzodiazepines such as alprazolam, triazolam, and midazolam utilize cytochrome P450 3A4, diazepam appears to be the only other benzodiazepine that is a cytochrome P450 2C19 substrate.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0883073812463609">38</xref>
</sup> In addition, some benzodiazepines are metabolized in a P450-independent manner. For example, clonazepam appears to be acetylated by NAT2 and eliminated without further conjugation.</p>
<p>The unique role of cytochrome P450 2C19 in the metabolism of clobazam has important implications for both pharmacogenomics and drug-drug interactions, as substrates and inhibitors of this enzyme affect the metabolism of both clobazam and <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam. For example, stiripentol, which is a potent inhibitor of cytochrome P450 2C19, strongly inhibits the hydroxylation of <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam in vitro and was associated with a threefold increase in the plasma concentrations of <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam for patients receiving combination therapy with stiripentol and clobazam relative to those receiving clobazam alone.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0883073812463609">39</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0883073812463609">40</xref>
</sup> The effects of cytochrome P450 2C19 substrates such as carbamazepine, phenytoin, and phenobarbital are more controversial, but appear to be of minimal clinical relevance.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0883073812463609">26</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0883073812463609">41</xref>
</sup> However, the ratio of <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam to clobazam for patients who carry cytochrome P450 2C19 alleles that confer poor metabolizer status is substantially elevated relative to wild type. Although clobazam treatment may be more effective, it may be associated with increased adverse effects in these patients.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0883073812463609">42</xref>
</sup>
<sup>-</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0883073812463609">45</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>During drug-drug interaction phase I studies, the mean elimination half-life of clobazam in healthy adult volunteers was found to be approximately 32 hours (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0883073812463609">Table 1</xref>). Bun et al reported that elimination appeared to be faster for both children and adults with epilepsy.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0883073812463609">46</xref>
</sup> However, in population pharmacokinetic analyses, there did not appear to be significant differences in the elimination of clobazam between healthy participants and those with epilepsy. <italic>N</italic>-Desmethylclobazam is longer-lived than clobazam, with a mean half-life of approximately &gt;57 hours,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0883073812463609">26</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0883073812463609">46</xref>
</sup> leading to steady-state plasma concentrations up to 8 times greater than the parent compound.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0883073812463609">2</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0883073812463609">43</xref>
</sup> However, in several trials conducted by Lundbeck LLC, steady-state plasma concentrations of <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam were found to be approximately 3 to 5 times greater than clobazam.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0883073812463609">34</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Per the US prescribing information,<italic> N</italic>-desmethylclobazam, the demethylated active metabolite of clobazam, has a considerably longer mean half-life than clobazam (71–82 hours and 36–42 hours, respectively).<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0883073812463609">34</xref>
</sup> The clinical efficacy of clobazam is likely a result of this metabolism, and studies indicate that <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam produces fewer adverse effects than clobazam.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0883073812463609">24</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-0883073812463609">47</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0883073812463609">
<title>Drug-Drug Interactions</title>
<p>Because polytherapy is used frequently in the treatment of intractable epilepsy such as Lennox-Gastaut syndrome, drug-drug interactions are an important consideration. Of particular concern are possible interactions with other antiepileptic drugs or psychotropic medications that may be used in conjunction with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome treatments. As noted previously, clinically meaningful drug-drug interactions appear to be mediated by cytochrome P450 3A4 and cytochrome P450 2C19 activity. For example, in addition to the clear synergistic interaction that is observed with stiripentol, felbamate, another cytochrome P450 2C19 inhibitor, has been reported to increase <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam concentrations when added to polytherapy.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0883073812463609">48</xref>
</sup> Moreover, clobazam has been reported to be an inhibitor of valproate metabolism.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0883073812463609">49</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0883073812463609">50</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The clinical relevance of interactions between clobazam and valproate was challenged in a recent report examining drug-drug interactions between clobazam and a variety of cytochrome P450 inducers, inhibitors, and common antiepileptic drugs. This report included the results from a population pharmacokinetic analysis of 7 trials and revealed no clinically relevant drug-drug interactions.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0883073812463609">26</xref>
</sup> The following antiepileptic drugs were examined and classified for cytochrome P450 effects in the study: phenobarbital, phenytoin, carbamazepine (inducers of both cytochrome P450 3A4 and 2C19); valproic acid, felbamate and oxcarbazepine (cytochrome P450 2C19 inhibitors); and lamotrigine.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0883073812463609">26</xref>
</sup> Results indicated that stable dosages of these antiepileptic drugs did not affect clobazam exposure, and clobazam did not affect the pharmacokinetics of valproic acid or lamotrigine. Moreover, a population pharmacokinetic analysis of the OV-1012 trial revealed no significant effect of clobazam or <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam on either valproate (<italic>P</italic> = .2157) or lamotrigine (<italic>P</italic> = .7262).<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0883073812463609">51</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Stiripentol is an antiepileptic drug commonly used in conjunction with clobazam and other antiepileptic drugs to treat Dravet syndrome. Like clobazam, stiripentol is thought to be an allosteric enhancer of GABA<sub>A</sub> receptors. However, it appears to bind at a site on the α3 subunit that is distinct from the benzodiazepine site, with synergistic agonistic effects.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0883073812463609">30</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0883073812463609">39</xref>
</sup> As noted previously, stiripentol is a potent inhibitor of cytochrome P450 2C19<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0883073812463609">39</xref>
</sup> and has been associated with in vitro and in vivo inhibitory effects on clobazam metabolism<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-0883073812463609">40</xref>
</sup> via noncompetitive and competitive inhibition of cytochrome P450 3A4 and 2C19, respectively. Stiripentol is not approved for use in the United States.</p>
<p>Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors and other psychotropic drugs are frequently used to treat behavioral problems and psychosis in patients with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome. Although drug-drug interactions between clobazam and these drugs have not been formally studied, the potential for meaningful interactions exists. For example, the selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor fluvoxamine is an inhibitor of cytochrome P450 2C19 and escitalopram (another selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor) is a substrate of both cytochrome P450 3A4 and 2C19. Concomitant use of these drugs with clobazam has the potential to increase serum concentrations of clobazam and <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam and warrants careful monitoring.</p>
<p>Results of 2 phase I clinical studies validated the involvement of cytochrome P450 3A4 and 2C19 in clobazam metabolism.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0883073812463609">26</xref>
</sup> For example, inhibition of cytochrome P450 3A4 by ketoconazole affected clobazam pharmacokinetics, as evidenced by a 1- to 2-hour increase in time to maximum plasma concentration, a 54% increase in area under the concentration time curve from 0 to infinity, and a 15% decrease in maximum plasma concentration. Similarly, inhibition of cytochrome P450 2C19 by omeprazole affected <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam pharmacokinetics as evidenced by a 36% increase in area under the concentration time curve from 0 to infinity and a 15% increase in maximum plasma concentration. Coadministration of clobazam with a drug cocktail of caffeine, midazolam, and dextromethorphan did not affect caffeine (a cytochrome P450 1A2 substrate) or tolbutamide (a cytochrome P450 2C19 substrate) metabolism. In contrast, a 27% decrease in midazolam (a cytochrome P450 A4 substrate) exposure and 4-fold increase in exposure to the 1-hydroxy metabolite was observed, whereas dextromethorphan (a cytochrome P450 2D6 substrate) exposure was increased by 95%. Importantly, none of these changes were interpreted as clinically meaningful given the broad therapeutic range of clobazam (ie, it is titrated to effect).<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0883073812463609">26</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0883073812463609">
<title>Efficacy</title>
<sec id="section14-0883073812463609">
<title>Overview</title>
<p>A long history of global experience has supported the safety and efficacy of clobazam as adjunctive therapy for pediatric epilepsy. It has been used broadly as both a first-line and add-on therapy since its introduction in the 1970s, and its therapeutic value continues to be recognized, despite the introduction of a number of newer compounds.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0883073812463609">18</xref>
</sup> Pivotal trials in the United States support the view that clobazam is well tolerated and efficacious in the treatment of seizures related to Lennox-Gastaut syndrome.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0883073812463609">
<title>International trials</title>
<p>The literature regarding the efficacy of clobazam in the treatment of refractory epilepsy outside of the United States has been well reviewed.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0883073812463609">1</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0883073812463609">18</xref>
</sup> Together, these reviews summarize efficacy data for a number of double-blind studies, open-label studies, and retrospective reviews. These studies of clobazam’s effectiveness included more than 300 patients with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome and more than 1300 patients with epilepsy types other than Lennox-Gastaut syndrome. An overview is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0883073812463609">Table 2</xref>. Notably, in the 20 studies of seizures associated with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome reviewed by Ng and Collins,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0883073812463609">1</xref>
</sup> clobazam treatment was associated with 50% to 100% seizure reduction in more than half of patients, with seizure freedom achieved in 10% of patients. Clobazam was associated with &gt;50% seizure reduction in 56.3% of patients in open-label studies that differentiated Lennox-Gastaut syndrome from other epilepsy types,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0883073812463609">1</xref>
</sup> and was associated with &gt;50% reduction in seizure frequency in 54% to 85% of patients in open-label studies that did not differentiate Lennox-Gastaut syndrome populations.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0883073812463609">1</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0883073812463609">18</xref>
</sup> In retrospective reviews of patients with several epilepsy and seizure types,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0883073812463609">52</xref>
</sup>
<sup>-</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0883073812463609">54</xref>
</sup> clobazam was associated with &gt;50% reductions in seizure frequency for 37% to 61% of patients, with seizure freedom achieved in 9% to 14% of patients.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0883073812463609">1</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0883073812463609">18</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0883073812463609" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Summary of Clobazam Efficacy Studies.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0883073812463609" xlink:href="10.1177_0883073812463609-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Study type and diagnosis</th>
<th colspan="4">Outcome (% of patients achieving a specified decrease in seizure frequency)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th> </th>
<th>Unspecified decrease</th>
<th>≥50% decrease</th>
<th>≥75% decrease</th>
<th>100% decrease</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Open-label</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Lennox-Gastaut syndrome (N &gt; 300)<sup>a</sup>
</td>
<td>62.5</td>
<td>56.3</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Refractory epilepsy (N ≥ 971)<sup>b</sup>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td align="center">31-68</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Refractory focal</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Retrospective</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Epilepsy (N = 100)<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0883073812463609">52</xref>
</sup>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Epileptic encephalopathy (N = 97)<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0883073812463609">53</xref>
</sup>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Refractory epilepsy (N = 832)<sup>c,54</sup>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td align="center">40-61</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Double-blind</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Lennox-Gastaut syndrome </td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  OV-1002 (N = 68)<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0883073812463609">13</xref>
</sup>
</td>
<td>
</td>
<td>83</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  OV-1012 or CONTAIN (N = 238)<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0883073812463609">14</xref>
</sup>
</td>
<td> </td>
<td>77.6</td>
<td>63.3</td>
<td>24.5</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn6-0883073812463609">
<p>
<sup>a</sup>Several studies were summarized<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0883073812463609">1</xref>
</sup>; Lennox-Gastaut syndrome subpopulations in patients with refractory epilepsy.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn7-0883073812463609">
<p>
<sup>b</sup>Several studies were summarized<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0883073812463609">1</xref>
</sup>; 31% to 68% were seizure-free, with an additional 26% to 45% having &gt;50% reduction.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn8-0883073812463609">
<p>
<sup>c</sup>61% had ≥50% reduction in 1 or more seizure types, whereas 40% had ≥50% reduction in all seizure types.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0883073812463609">
<title>Pivotal trials for United States approval (Lennox-Gastaut syndrome–specific)</title>
<p>The results from 2 United States trials support the view that clobazam is efficacious in the treatment of drop attacks related to Lennox-Gastaut syndrome. The first was a phase II, randomized, double-blind, dosage-ranging study that evaluated the safety and efficacy of clobazam as adjunctive therapy in 68 patients with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome (OV-1002).<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0883073812463609">13</xref>
</sup> The trial consisted of a 3-week titration period and a 4-week maintenance period, followed by either a taper period or extension into an open-label study (OV-1004). Efficacy was dosage-dependent. After a 3-week titration and 4-week maintenance period, drop seizure frequency was reduced in both low-dosage (0.25 mg/kg/d) and high-dosage (1 mg/kg/d) groups (by 12% and 85%, respectively). Eighty-three percent of patients in the high-dosage group had &gt;50% reduction in weekly drop seizures. The rates of other seizure types also decreased significantly, and global scores showed significant improvements.</p>
<p>The second was a phase III trial (the Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Efficacy and Safety Study of <bold>C</bold>l<bold>O</bold>bazam in Patie<bold>NT</bold>s with Lennox-G<bold>A</bold>staut Sy<bold>N</bold>drome or CONTAIN study) to evaluate the safety and efficacy of clobazam as adjunctive therapy in 238 patients (217 in modified intention-to-treat population) with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome (OV-1012).<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0883073812463609">14</xref>
</sup> Study design was similar to the phase II trial and consisted of a 3-week titration period, a 12-week maintenance period, and either a 2- to 3-week taper period or extension into the open-label study (OV-1004). Efficacy was dosage-dependent, with decreases in drop seizure frequency in the low- (0.25 mg/kg/d), medium- (0.5 mg/kg/d), and high-dosage (1 mg/kg/d) groups of 41%, 49%, and 68%, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0883073812463609">Figure 2</xref>). In both the medium- and high-dosage groups, more patients had decreases in weekly drop seizures &gt;50% relative to those in the placebo group. Rates of other seizure types also decreased. Response to treatment was both early and persistent. For example, the mean decrease in drop seizure frequency during the first 4 weeks of the maintenance period was 71% for the high-dosage group and was maintained at 68% during the last 4 weeks of treatment.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0883073812463609">55</xref>
</sup> Importantly, clobazam exhibited similar efficacy for older patients as well as younger patients. In the high-dosage group, mean reductions in weekly drop seizures of 65% and 82% were observed in patients in the age groups of 2 to 12 years and &gt;17 years, respectively.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0883073812463609">56</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<fig id="fig2-0883073812463609" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Mean percentage decreases in weekly rate of seizures from baseline to the maintenance period in the phase III clinical trial OV-1012 (95% confidence intervals are shown in parentheses).</p>
<p>Source: Adapted with permission from Ng et al.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0883073812463609">14</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0883073812463609-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>A total of 267 patients were enrolled in the open-label extension study OV-1004 as of December 15, 2009, with 213 (80%) remaining as of July 1, 2010.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0883073812463609">57</xref>
</sup> Results at 24 months indicated sustained efficacy for the majority of these patients. For example, of the 88 patients who had received clobazam for 24 months, the median percentage decrease in weekly drop seizures was 91.6%, whereas 79.5% of these patients exhibited a reduction in weekly drop seizures ≥50% versus baseline. Although dosage adjustments of up to a maximum of 2 mg/kg/d were permitted in the unblinded phase, dosages did not appear to change dramatically relative to the controlled periods. Decreases in seizure frequency were accompanied by improved global scores and by substantial reductions in use of concomitant antiepileptic drugss.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0883073812463609">57</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>An indirect comparison of the results from the phase III trial of clobazam to clinical trials of other approved adjunctive treatments for Lennox-Gastaut syndrome suggested greater efficacy for high-dosage clobazam relative to felbamate, lamotrigine, rufinamide, and topiramate.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0883073812463609">58</xref>
</sup> In this study, effect-size analysis using Cohen’s <italic>d</italic> was used to transform the endpoints of several studies identified in a Cochrane review.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0883073812463609">59</xref>
</sup> Clobazam treatment was associated with a greater effect size for reductions in both total seizure and drop seizure frequencies.</p>
<p>
<italic>Tolerance. </italic>Tolerance to clobazam has been reported to develop in 10% to 87% of patients.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0883073812463609">18</xref>
</sup> However, the assessment of tolerance in refractory epilepsy is complicated by many factors, including disease progression and widespread use of polytherapy. In addition, there is no strict universal definition by which to evaluate tolerance. For example, in one study of clobazam as monotherapy in the treatment of childhood epilepsy, tolerance was defined as the development of seizures following a 3- to 6-month seizure-free period and was reported for 7.4% of patients.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0883073812463609">60</xref>
</sup> In the 15-week OV-1012 or CONTAIN trial, tolerance was defined as return to baseline seizure frequency after an initial reduction of ≥50% and was observed in 5.3% of patients in the high-dosage group after a 4-week maintenance period. The significance of this result is unclear, as the tolerance observed with clobazam was not significantly different from placebo (5.6%). Moreover, no patients exhibited tolerance after an 8-week maintenance period. In general, the high retention rates in CONTAIN and its open-label extension study (OV-1004) and the persistence of efficacy in these studies support overall low tolerance.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0883073812463609">11</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0883073812463609">
<title>Tolerability and Safety</title>
<sec id="section18-0883073812463609">
<title>Overview</title>
<p>The safety profile of clobazam has been clearly established in many clinical trials and 4 decades of worldwide clinical use. The most common dosage-related adverse events reported with clobazam include sedation, dizziness, and ataxia. These are similar to the adverse effects of other benzodiazepines and are mild to moderate for approximately 40% of patients.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0883073812463609">1</xref>
</sup> Although adverse events are the most common reasons for discontinuation or dosage reduction, they appear to be less severe with clobazam relative to 1,4-benzodiazepines. Sedation, in particular, appears to be substantially less common with clobazam.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0883073812463609">1</xref>
</sup> There are a few reports of unspecified, “severe behavioral changes” associated with clobazam.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0883073812463609">61</xref>
</sup> This is of particular concern in patients with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome, as baseline behavioral issues are elevated in this population. Serious adverse events such as hepatic failure or status epilepticus have been reported but are infrequent. According to Ng and Collins “of the greater than 1.1 million patient-years of exposure documented from November 1994 to February 2004, hepatic failure, status epilepticus, and/or mortality were observed in a total of five patients.”<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0883073812463609">1</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>In 1999, Bawden and colleagues<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0883073812463609">62</xref>
</sup> evaluated the cognitive and behavioral effects of clobazam and then-standard monotherapy (ie, carbamazepine) at 3 Canadian pediatric epilepsy centers. The study investigators found no differences between therapies in measures of memory, psychomotor speed, attention, and impulsivity once study medications had been stabilized or at 1-year follow-up assessments.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0883073812463609">62</xref>
</sup> Further, neuropsychological measures were not correlated with clobazam dosage or serum concentrations of either clobazam or <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0883073812463609">62</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0883073812463609">
<title>United States clinical trials</title>
<p>Results from CONTAIN were generally consistent with those from other studies. Adverse events with ≥10% difference between placebo and any clobazam group in CONTAIN were somnolence, pyrexia, lethargy, drooling, and constipation. Sedation was reported for 8 (4.5%) clobazam-treated patients (1 in the low-dosage group, 2 in the medium-dosage group, and 5 in the high-dosage group).<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0883073812463609">14</xref>
</sup> Of these events, somnolence and drooling increased in frequency with increasing clobazam dosage. In addition, there was a dosage-related trend in adverse events leading to discontinuation. Discontinuation rates were 6.9%, 12.9%, and 20.3% of patients in the low- (0.25 mg/kg/d), medium- (0.5 mg/kg/d), and high-dosage (1 mg/kg/d) groups, respectively. Adverse events leading to discontinuation included lethargy, somnolence, aggression, ataxia, insomnia, and fatigue. The most frequent serious adverse event reported was pneumonia. However, it was not dosage-related. There were no reports of hepatic failure or death related to clobazam in either of the US clinical trials,<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0883073812463609">13</xref>
</sup>
<sup>,</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0883073812463609">14</xref>
</sup> or in the open-label extension study.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0883073812463609">57</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Toxicology data from preclinical studies have been thoroughly reviewed by Ng and Collins.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0883073812463609">1</xref>
</sup> Results from these studies are consistent with low toxicity for both clobazam and <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam, with little evidence for genotoxicity and low risk for acute over-dosage. They are also consistent with low carcinogenicity, with the exception of 1 report of increased incidence of thyroid follicular cell adenomas in Sprague-Dawley rats. Although animal studies have suggested low potential for teratogenicity, the data are limited and clobazam is listed as pregnancy category C. Like other benzodiazepines, clobazam is a schedule IV compound, owing to risk of dependence and abuse.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0883073812463609">
<title>Safety in Relation to Other Antiepileptic Drugs</title>
<p>Clinical experience has shown that the safety profile of clobazam compares favorably with other antiepileptic drugs used in the treatment of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome. The spectrum of adverse events associated with clobazam treatment is relatively benign when compared with the events associated with other antiepileptic drugs. For example, serious adverse events associated with valproate treatment include hepatic failure and pancreatitis, lamotrigine is associated with serious rashes, and felbamate is associated with increased incidence of aplastic anemia and hepatotoxicity.</p>
<sec id="section21-0883073812463609">
<title>Dosing and Administration</title>
<p>Clobazam is available in 5-, 10-, and 20-mg tablet formulations. According to the prescribing information, patients ≤30 kg in body weight should be initiated at 5 mg/d and titrated as tolerated to 20 mg/d.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0883073812463609">34</xref>
</sup> Patients &gt;30 kg in body weight should be initiated at 10 mg/d and titrated up to 40 mg/d. Dosages &gt;5 mg/d should be divided into 2 daily doses. Tablets may be crushed and mixed in applesauce without a meaningful effect on pharmacokinetics.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0883073812463609">32</xref>
</sup>
<sup>-</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0883073812463609">36</xref>
</sup> The dosage should be adjusted for geriatric patients, cytochrome P450 2C19 poor metabolizers, and those with mild or moderate hepatic impairment (no information was collected regarding severe hepatic impairment).</p>
<p>No formal studies or guidelines are available regarding converting patients from 1,4-benzodiazepines to clobazam. However, we suggest converting patients on 1 to 2 mg/d of clonazepam to 5 to 10 mg/d of clobazam, consistent with the prescribing information. The family should be given the flexibility to adjust the dosage based on seizures or adverse effects (ie, increase the dosage if there is an increase in seizures or decrease the dosage if sedation occurs). As with other benzodiazepines, discontinuation of clobazam should be gradual, and the patient should be monitored for withdrawal-related symptoms, such as increased seizures, behavioral disorders, and anxiety.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0883073812463609">34</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-0883073812463609">
<title>Cost and Economic Considerations</title>
<p>The economic burden of intractable epilepsy and the cost effectiveness of treatment are of considerable concern to patients, caregivers, and payers. A classic study of the cost of epilepsy in the United States by Begley and coworkers<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0883073812463609">63</xref>
</sup> estimated that the lifetime cost of intractable epilepsy (defined as patients who continued to have seizures after 6 years of treatment) was $8.8 billion (in 1995 dollars), with $1.1 billion in direct cost related to medical care and 7.7 billion in indirect cost related to productivity loss. Of the direct costs, antiepileptic drug therapy and inpatient care were the greatest cost categories. Intractable epilepsy accounted for 62% of the total lifetime direct medical cost. This was attributed to greater inpatient care utilization and antiepileptic drug use in this group.</p>
<p>Three pharmacoeconomics studies that reported results specifically for patients with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome were recently presented.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0883073812463609">64</xref>
</sup>
<sup>-</sup>
<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0883073812463609">66</xref>
</sup> The main conclusions from these studies are that inpatient cost resulting from injuries sustained in association with drop seizures is a primary driver of overall medical cost in Lennox-Gastaut syndrome and that antiepileptic drugs offering the most effective seizure control are associated with the most overall cost savings. The first study estimated economic burden of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome, based on an analysis of medical and pharmacy claims associated with patients whose diagnosis codes were consistent with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0883073812463609">66</xref>
</sup> Median total health care cost in this population was $44 797 per annum. Epilepsy-related cost was $29 911, of which $18 119 was attributable to inpatient care and $13 038 could be directly associated with seizure-related events. This suggests that medical cost associated with medically attended drop seizures is the primary cost driver in Lennox-Gastaut syndrome. The second study estimated the cost effectiveness of clobazam relative to lamotrigine, rufinamide, and topiramate in the treatment of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome, based on a pharmacoeconomics model that used seizure rates derived from clinical trials (including the phase III CONTAIN trial for clobazam<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0883073812463609">14</xref>
</sup>) and cost inputs from administrative claims.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0883073812463609">64</xref>
</sup> Clobazam treatment was associated with lesser overall annual medical cost ($29 000) than alternative treatments ($32 000-33 000). The cost savings was attributed to a lesser rate of drop seizures with clobazam relative to the other antiepileptic drugs. Finally, an economic model was derived to evaluate the overall budget impact of adding clobazam to the formulary of a hypothetical 100 000-member health care plan.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0883073812463609">65</xref>
</sup> The model assumed Lennox-Gastaut syndrome prevalence of 0.04% in the covered population, with medical cost and seizure rates derived from the cost-effectiveness study. Addition of clobazam was associated with cost savings of $78 600 in the first year and $104 000 in the second year, with cost savings again driven by a lesser rate of drop seizures.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-0883073812463609">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Clobazam is well established as an anxiolytic and anticonvulsant, and its reputation as a well-tolerated and effective treatment is well established through more than 3.4 million patient-years of exposure.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0883073812463609">11</xref>
</sup> Recent pivotal US trials supported this view, and clobazam was approved by the Food and Drug Administration in October 2011 for use as adjunctive therapy for the treatment of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome in patients 2 years of age and older.</p>
<p>As a 1,5-benzodiazepine, clobazam represents a unique class of antiepileptic drugs. It exhibits somewhat improved safety and tolerability profiles and a lesser potential for drug-drug interactions relative to other benzodiazepines. These observations, together with its well-established efficacy in seizure reduction across several syndromes and seizure types, make clobazam an attractive treatment option to patients, providers, caregivers, and payers. Clobazam may be a good treatment option for many patients, since it, potentially, may have fewer serious adverse events associated with its use than many other antiepileptic drugs. For example, valproate treatment may be associated with hepatic toxicity, pancreatitis, and drug-drug interactions, and felbamate is associated with hepatic failure and aplastic anemia.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0883073812463609">18</xref>
</sup> In practice, given the diverse etiology, presentation, progression, and intractability of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome and related epilepsy syndromes, virtually all antiepileptic drugs are used in treatment.<sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0883073812463609">12</xref>
</sup> Practitioners are advised to try many drugs in the treatment of individual patients to find the best response, overcome tolerance, and avoid drug-drug interactions when additional medications are introduced.</p>
<p>In managing a patient with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome who is experiencing frequent seizures, physicians consider clobazam an attractive treatment option, as it allows rapid titration to therapeutic dosage, with a predictable adverse-effect profile. The only other antiepileptic drugs routinely used in the treatment of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome that may be introduced as quickly and also show rapid therapeutic responses are valproic acid and rufinamide.</p>
<p>Clobazam was synthesized with the goals of increasing the effectiveness and decreasing the adverse effects of common benzodiazepines. It appears to at least partially fulfill these goals through improved selectivity for GABA<sub>A</sub> receptor subtypes that are involved in anticonvulsant activity relative to those involved in sedation. Although much is understood regarding the molecular pharmacology of clobazam and other benzodiazepines that modulate GABA signaling, additional investigations of GABA<sub>A</sub> receptor subunit composition and distribution and benzodiazepine-binding modes are warranted. Together, these may lead to better overall treatment regimens for individual patients.</p>
<p>Throughout the US clinical development program for clobazam in Lennox-Gastaut syndrome, no new safety issues were identified. Adverse events were as expected, given what is known about clobazam from extensive previous clinical development efforts. There may be different incidences and severities of sedation between clobazam and other benzodiazepines and antiepileptic drugs, but this has not been fully evaluated through long-term data.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section24-0883073812463609">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Clobazam is a structurally unique member of the benzodiazepine class of anticonvulsants. Its utility as a well-tolerated and effective anticonvulsant has been established through nearly 40 years of international use in the treatment of intractable epilepsy. Data from 2 US pivotal trials supported this view and led to Food and Drug Administration approval of clobazam in 2011 for use as adjunctive therapy in the treatment of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome. This approval provides US practitioners with an additional option for the treatment for intractable epilepsy.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgment</title>
<p>Medical writing and editing assistance were provided by Eric B. Bertelsen, PhD, of Arbor Communications, Inc (Ann Arbor, Michigan), and Michael A Nissen, ELS, of Lundbeck LLC (Deerfield, Illinois) and was funded by Lundbeck. The authors also thank Jouko Isojarvi, MD, PhD, of Lundbeck’s US Medical Affairs department, for his critical review of the manuscript.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0883073812463609">
<label>Author Contributions</label>
<p>JW directed the development of an outline, first draft, and all revisions of the manuscript by the acknowledged medical writers. JW and SP reviewed and revised all drafts of the manuscript and approved the final version for submission.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn2-0883073812463609">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>JW has received grant support from Lundbeck, Eisai, GlaxoSmithKline, King Pharmaceuticals, Supernus, The Shainberg Foundation, and the National Institutes of Health. He has served as a consultant to Lundbeck, Cyberonics, Pfizer, Eisai, and Sunovion, and has received speaking fees from Lundbeck, Questcor, Cyberonics, and Eisai. SP has no conflicts of interest relative to this article to disclose. </p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn3-0883073812463609">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. </p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0883073812463609">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Collins</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clobazam</article-title>. <source>Neurotherapeutics</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>138</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0883073812463609">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sankar</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>GABA<sub>A</sub> receptor physiology and its relationship to the mechanism of action of the 1,5-benzodiazepine clobazam</article-title>. <source>CNS Drugs</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0883073812463609">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Barzaghi</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fournex</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mantegazza</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacological and toxicological properties of clobazam (1-phenyl-5-methyl-8-chloro-1,2,4,5-tetrahydro-2,4-diketo-3<italic>H</italic>-1,5-benzodiazepine), a new psychotherapeutic agent</article-title>. <source>Arzneimittelforschung</source>. <year>1973</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>683</fpage>–<lpage>686</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0883073812463609">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gastaut</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Exceptional and unrecognized antiepileptic properties of a commercial anxiolytic: clobazam [in French]</article-title>. <source>Concours Med</source>. <year>1978</year>;<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>3697</fpage>–<lpage>3701</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0883073812463609">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wieck</surname>
<given-names>HH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Blaha</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Heerklotz</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <article-title>A clinical view of clobazam</article-title>. <source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source>. <year>1979</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>109S</fpage>–<lpage>112S</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0883073812463609">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gastaut</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Low</surname>
<given-names>MD.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <article-title>Antiepileptic properties of clobazam, a 1-5 benzodiazepine, in man</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>. <year>1979</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>446</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0883073812463609">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Robertson</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Current status of the 1,4- and 1,5-benzodiazepines in the treatment of epilepsy: the place of clobazam</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>S27</fpage>–<lpage>S41</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0883073812463609">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Meldrum</surname>
<given-names>BS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chapman</surname>
<given-names>AG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Horton</surname>
<given-names>RW.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <article-title>Clobazam: anticonvulsant action in animal models of epilepsy</article-title>. <source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source>. <year>1979</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>59S</fpage>–<lpage>60S</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0883073812463609">
<label>9</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shenoy</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Miyahara</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Swinyard</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Comparative anticonvulsant activity and neurotoxicity of clobazam, diazepam, phenobarbital, and valproate in mice and rats</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>. <year>1982</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>399</fpage>–<lpage>408</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0883073812463609">
<label>10</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Steru</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chermat</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Millet</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Comparative study in mice of ten 1,4-benzodiazepines and of clobazam: anticonvulsant, anxiolytic, sedative, and myorelaxant effects</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>S14</fpage>–<lpage>S17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0883073812463609">
<label>11</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lundbeck</surname>
<given-names>LLC</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <source>Data on File. Integrated Summary of Efficacy</source>. <publisher-loc>Deerfield, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lundbeck LLC</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0883073812463609">
<label>12</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Giarratano</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Standley</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Benbadis</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clobazam for treatment of epilepsy</article-title>. <source>Expert Opin Pharmacother</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>233</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0883073812463609">
<label>13</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Conry</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ng</surname>
<given-names>YT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Paolicchi</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clobazam in the treatment of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>50</volume>:<fpage>1158</fpage>–<lpage>1166</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0883073812463609">
<label>14</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ng</surname>
<given-names>YT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Conry</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Drummond</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Randomized, phase III study results of clobazam in Lennox-Gastaut syndrome</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>1473</fpage>–<lpage>1481</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0883073812463609">
<label>15</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<article-title>Rapporteur’s Public Assessment Report for paediatric studies submitted in accordance with article 45 of regulation (ED) no 1901/2006, as amended</article-title>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hma.eu/fileadmin/dateien/Human_Medicines/CMD_h_/Paediatric_Regulation/Assessment_Reports/Article_45_work-sharing/Clobazam_2011_04_45PeadPAR.pdf">http://www.hma.eu/fileadmin/dateien/Human_Medicines/CMD_h_/Paediatric_Regulation/Assessment_Reports/Article_45_work-sharing/Clobazam_2011_04_45PeadPAR.pdf</ext-link>. <comment>Accessed May 14, 2012</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0883073812463609">
<label>16</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Markand</surname>
<given-names>ON</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Lennox-Gastaut syndrome (childhood epileptic encephalopathy)</article-title>. <source>J Clin Neurophysiol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>426</fpage>–<lpage>441</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0883073812463609">
<label>17</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Arzimanoglou</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>French</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Blume</surname>
<given-names>WT</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Lennox-Gastaut syndrome: a consensus approach on diagnosis, assessment, management, and trial methodology</article-title>. <source>Lancet Neurol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>82</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0883073812463609">
<label>18</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Leahy</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chu-Shore</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fisher</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clobazam as an adjunctive therapy in treating seizures associated with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>673</fpage>–<lpage>681</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0883073812463609">
<label>19</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kossoff</surname>
<given-names>EH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Intractable childhood epilepsy: choosing between the treatments</article-title>. <source>Semin Pediatr Neurol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>149</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0883073812463609">
<label>20</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wheless</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Nonpharmacologic treatment of the catastrophic epilepsies of childhood</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>suppl 5</issue>):<fpage>17</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0883073812463609">
<label>21</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McKernan</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rosahl</surname>
<given-names>TW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Sedative but not anxiolytic properties of benzodiazepines are mediated by the GABA(A) receptor alpha1 subtype</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>587</fpage>–<lpage>592</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0883073812463609">
<label>22</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nakajima</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A pharmacological profile of clobazam (Mystan), a new antiepileptic drug [in Japanese]</article-title>. <source>Nihon Yakurigaku Zasshi</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>118</volume>:<fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>122</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0883073812463609">
<label>23</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Doi</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ueda</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tokumaru</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Molecular regulation of glutamate and GABA transporter proteins by clobazam during epileptogenesis in Fe(+++)-induced epileptic rats</article-title>. <source>Brain Res Mol Brain Res</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>142</volume>:<fpage>91</fpage>–<lpage>96</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0883073812463609">
<label>24</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kinoshita</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ikeda</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Begum</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of low-dose, add-on therapy of clobazam (CLB) is produced by its major metabolite, <italic>N</italic>-desmethyl-CLB</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Sci</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>263</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0883073812463609">
<label>25</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mehndiratta</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Krishnamurthy</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rajesh</surname>
<given-names>KN</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clobazam monotherapy in drug naïve adult patients with epilepsy</article-title>. <source>Seizure</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>226</fpage>–<lpage>228</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0883073812463609">
<label>26</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Walzer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bekersky</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Blum</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacokinetic drug interactions between clobazam and drugs metabolized by cytochrome P450 isoenzymes</article-title>. <source>Pharmacotherapy</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>340</fpage>–<lpage>353</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0883073812463609">
<label>27</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jensen</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ebert</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <article-title>Clobazam and its active metabolite, <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam, are high-affinity ligands for the benzodiazepine sites of GABA<sub>A</sub> receptors</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>78</volume>
<comment>(Meeting Abstracts 1):P05.086</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0883073812463609">
<label>28</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bruun</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jensen</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ebert</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <article-title>Modeling of clobazam’s interactions with the benzodiazepine binding site and analysis of structural receptor subtype differences</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>78</volume>
<comment>(Meeting Abstracts 1):P05.084</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0883073812463609">
<label>29</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jensen</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hammer</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ebert</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clobazam and its active metabolite, <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam, are partial benzodiazepine receptor agonists at cloned GABA<sub>A</sub> receptors expressed in <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> oocytes</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>78</volume>
<comment>(Meeting Abstracts 1):P05.085</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0883073812463609">
<label>30</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fisher</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Interactions between modulators of the GABAA receptor: stiripentol and benzodiazepines</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pharmacol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>654</volume>:<fpage>160</fpage>–<lpage>165</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0883073812463609">
<label>31</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rudolph</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Crestani</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Benke</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Benzodiazepine actions mediated by specific gamma-aminobutyric acid(A) receptor subtypes</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>401</volume>:<fpage>796</fpage>–<lpage>800</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0883073812463609">
<label>32</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Divoll</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Greenblatt</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ciraulo</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clobazam kinetics: intrasubject variability and effect of food on adsorption</article-title>. <source>J Clin Pharmacol</source>. <year>1982</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>73</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0883073812463609">
<label>33</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cenraud</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Guyot</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Levy</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>No effect of food intake on clobazam absorption</article-title>. <source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>728</fpage>–<lpage>730</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0883073812463609">
<label>34</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">ONFI (clobazam)</collab> <article-title>[prescribing information]</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Deerfield, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lundbeck Inc</publisher-name>; <year>2011</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0883073812463609">
<label>35</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rupp</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Badian</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Christ</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacokinetics of single and multiple doses of clobazam in humans</article-title>. <source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source>. <year>1979</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>51S</fpage>–<lpage>57S</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0883073812463609">
<label>36</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Volz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Christ</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kellner</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Kinetics and metabolism of clobazam in animals and man</article-title>. <source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source>. <volume>1979</volume>;<issue>7</issue>:<fpage>41S</fpage>–<lpage>50S</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0883073812463609">
<label>37</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Giraud</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tran</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rey</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>In vitro characterization of clobazam metabolism by recombinant cytochrome P450 enzymes: importance of CYP2C19</article-title>. <source>Drug Metab Dispos</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>1279</fpage>–<lpage>1286</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0883073812463609">
<label>38</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McDonagh</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Whirl-Carrillo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Garten</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>From pharmacogenomic knowledge acquisition to clinical applications: the PharmGKB as a clinical pharmacogenomic biomarker resource</article-title>. <source>Biomark Med</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>795</fpage>–<lpage>806</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0883073812463609">
<label>39</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chiron</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dulac</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The pharmacological treatment of Dravet syndrome</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>suppl 2</issue>):<fpage>76</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0883073812463609">
<label>40</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Giraud</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Treluyer</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rey</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>In vitro</article-title> <article-title>and in vivo inhibitory effect of stiripentol on clobazam metabolism</article-title>. <source>Drug Metab Dispos</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>608</fpage>–<lpage>611</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0883073812463609">
<label>41</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bardy</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Seppälä</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Salokorpi</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Monitoring of concentrations of clobazam and norclobazam in serum and saliva of children with epilepsy</article-title>. <source>Brain Dev</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>174</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0883073812463609">
<label>42</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bertilsson</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <article-title>Geographical/interracial differences in polymorphic drug oxidation. Current state of knowledge of cytochrome P450 (CYP) 2D5 and 2C19</article-title>. <source>Clin Pharmacokinet</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>192</fpage>–<lpage>209</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0883073812463609">
<label>43</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Contin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sangiorgi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Riva</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Evidence of polymorphic CYP2C19 involvement in the human metabolism of <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam</article-title>. <source>Ther Drug Monit</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>737</fpage>–<lpage>741</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0883073812463609">
<label>44</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kosaki</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tamura</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sato</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A major influence of CYP2C19 genotype on the steady-state concentration of <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam</article-title>. <source>Brain Dev</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>530</fpage>–<lpage>534</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0883073812463609">
<label>45</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Seo</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nagata</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ishitsu</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Impact of CYP2C19 polymorphisms on the efficacy of clobazam therapy</article-title>. <source>Pharmacogenomics</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>527</fpage>–<lpage>537</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0883073812463609">
<label>46</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bun</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Monjanel-Mouterde</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Noel</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of age and antiepileptic drugs on plasma levels and kinetics of clobazam and <italic>N</italic>-desmethylclobazam</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Toxicol</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>136</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0883073812463609">
<label>47</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Haigh</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pullar</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gent</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dailley</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Feely</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <article-title>N-Desmethylclobazam: a possible alternative to clobazam in the treatment of refractory epilepsy?</article-title> <source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>218</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0883073812463609">
<label>48</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Contin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Riva</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Albani</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of felbamate on clobazam and its metabolite kinetics in patients with epilepsy</article-title>. <source>Ther Drug Monit</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>604</fpage>–<lpage>608</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0883073812463609">
<label>49</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Theis</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Koren</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Daneman</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Interactions of clobazam with conventional antiepileptics in children</article-title>. <source>J Child Neurol</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>208</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0883073812463609">
<label>50</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sennoune</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mesdjian</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bonneton</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Interactions between clobazam and standard antiepileptic drugs in patients with epilepsy</article-title>. <source>Ther Drug Monit</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>274</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0883073812463609">
<label>51</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Renfroe JB Conry</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of concomitant lamotrigine or valproate therapy on clobazam for Lennox-Gastaut syndrome: subanalyses of the CONTAIN trial</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>. <year>2011</year>. <comment>Presented at: 65th Annual Meeting of the American Epilepsy Society. Abstract 1.249</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0883073812463609">
<label>52</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>da Silveira</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Montenegro</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Franzon</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effectiveness of clobazam as add-on therapy in children with refractory focal epilepsy</article-title>. <source>Arq Neuropsiquiatr</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>705</fpage>–<lpage>710</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0883073812463609">
<label>53</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Silva</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Montenegro</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Guerreiro</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clobazam as add-on therapy in children with epileptic encephalopathy</article-title>. <source>Can J Neurol Sci</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0883073812463609">
<label>54</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab collab-type="author">Canadian Clobazam Cooperative Group</collab>. <article-title>Clobazam in treatment of refractory epilepsy: the Canadian experience. A retrospective study</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>407</fpage>–<lpage>416</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0883073812463609">
<label>55</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Conry</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Drummond</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Early and sustained response to clobazam by patients with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome during the CONTAIN trial. AES 2011</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>. <year>2011</year>. <comment>Presented at: 65th Annual Meeting of the American Epilepsy Society. Abstract 2.242</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0883073812463609">
<label>56</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mitchell</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Conry</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clobazam is efficacious for drop attacks in patients with Lennox-Gastaut syndrome across the age spectrum: Subgroup analysis of the CONTAIN trial</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>. <year>2011</year>; <comment>abstract B.04 presented at the 65th annual meeting of the American Epilepsy Society</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0883073812463609">
<label>57</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Conry</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Paolicchi</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Long-term safety and efficacy of clobazam for Lennox-Gastaut syndrome: 2-year results of an open-label extension study</article-title>. <source>Ann Neurol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>70</volume>
<comment>(suppl S15):S140. Poster presented at: 40th Annual Meeting of the Child Neurology Society; October 27, 2011; Savannah, GA. Abstract DD-26</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0883073812463609">
<label>58</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cramer</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sapin</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Indirect comparison of clobazam and felbamate, lamotrigine, rufinamide, and topiramate as adjunctive therapy for Lennox-Gastaut syndrome (LGS): results of an effect-size analysis</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>. <year>2011</year>. <comment>Presented at: 65th Annual Meeting of the American Epilepsy Society. Abstract 1.273</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0883073812463609">
<label>59</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hancock</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cross</surname>
<given-names>HH.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <article-title>Treatment of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>. <year>2009</year>;(<volume>3</volume>):<fpage>CD003277</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0883073812463609">
<label>60</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab collab-type="author">Canadian Study Group for Childhood Epilepsy</collab>. <article-title>Clobazam has equivalent efficacy to carbamazepine and phenytoin as monotherapy for childhood epilepsy</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>952</fpage>–<lpage>959</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0883073812463609">
<label>61</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Seif-Eddeine</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ng</surname>
<given-names>Y-T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clobazam for patients with Lennox–Gastaut syndrome and epilepsy</article-title>. <source>Expert Rev Neurother</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>385</fpage>–<lpage>393</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0883073812463609">
<label>62</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bawden</surname>
<given-names>HN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Camfield</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Camfield</surname>
<given-names>PR</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The cognitive and behavioural effects of clobazam and standard monotherapy are comparable</article-title>. <source>Epilepsy Res</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>143</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0883073812463609">
<label>63</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Begley</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Famulari</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Annegers</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The cost of epilepsy in the United States: an estimate from population-based clinical and survey data</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>342</fpage>–<lpage>351</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0883073812463609">
<label>64</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Clements</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Skornicki</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>O’Sullivan</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cost-effectiveness analysis of antiepileptic drugs in the treatment of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome</article-title>. <source>Value Health</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>A141</fpage>–<lpage>A144</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0883073812463609">
<label>65</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Skornicki</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Clements</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>O’Sullivan</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Budget impact analysis of antiepileptic drugs in the treatment of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome</article-title>. <source>Value in Health</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>A141</fpage>–<lpage>A142</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0883073812463609">
<label>66</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Swindle</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Economic burden of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome</article-title>. <source>Value Health</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>A143</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>