<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AJS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">amjsports</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Sports Med</journal-id>
<journal-title>The American Journal of Sports Medicine</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0363-5465</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3365</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0363546512445997</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0363546512445997</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll">
<subject>4</subject>
<subject>27</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Correlation of Coracoid Thickness and Glenoid Width</article-title>
<subtitle>An Anatomic Morphometric Analysis</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Bueno</surname><given-names>Rogerio Serpone</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0363546512445997">*</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546512445997">†</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ikemoto</surname><given-names>Roberto Yukio</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546512445997">†</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Nascimento</surname><given-names>Luis Gustavo Prata</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546512445997">†</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>Luiz Henrique de Oliveira</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546512445997">†</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Strose</surname><given-names>Eric</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546512445997">†</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Murachovsky</surname><given-names>Joel</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546512445997">†</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0363546512445997"><label>†</label>Faculdade de Medicina do ABC, Sao Paulo, Brazil</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0363546512445997">Investigation performed at Faculdade de Medicina do ABC, Sao Paulo, Brazil</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0363546512445997"><label>*</label>Rogerio Serpone Bueno, MD, Faculdade de Medicina do ABC, Rua Drausio 383, Sao Paulo, 05511010 Brazil (e-mail: <email>rsbueno@hotmail.com</email>).</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>7</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>40</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<fpage>1664</fpage>
<lpage>1667</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">American Orthopaedic Society for Sports Medicine</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-0363546512445997">
<title>Background:</title>
<p>The coracoid has been widely used as a graft to reconstruct anterior glenoid bone defects, as described by the Latarjet and Bristow procedures, with successful results. Nevertheless, at the present, there are no studies correlating the size of the coracoid graft and its relation to the glenoid.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0363546512445997">
<title>Purpose:</title>
<p>To assess the mediolateral (M-L) and anteroposterior (A-P) thickness of the coracoid process as well as the widest anterior-to-posterior glenoid distance (glenoid width) and to analyze the correlation between these measurements, while comparing these with the A-P coracoid process thickness.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0363546512445997">
<title>Study Design:</title>
<p>Descriptive laboratory study.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0363546512445997">
<title>Methods:</title>
<p>Sixty-one unpaired, adult human cadaveric scapulae were evaluated. Three examiners performed 3 independent measurements of the largest M-L thickness of the coracoid process and also the widest anterior-to-posterior distance of the glenoid. The A-P coracoid process thickness was also measured to compare for correlations with M-L coracoid thickness.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0363546512445997">
<title>Results:</title>
<p>The glenoid width was 26.38 ± 2.69 mm (range, 20.03-32.35 mm), and the M-L coracoid thickness was 14.51 ± 1.90 mm (range, 9.60-19.31 mm). Calculating the ratio between the M-L thickness of the coracoid and glenoid width, we observed that the coracoid represented 43% to 70% of the glenoid width (54% on average). The A-P coracoid process thickness was 8.37 ± 0.93 mm (range, 6.61-9.76 mm), representing 31% of the glenoid width on average.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0363546512445997">
<title>Conclusion:</title>
<p>A strong positive and statistically significant relationship between the coracoid process M-L thickness and the anterior-to-posterior glenoid width exists; the coracoid represents, on average, 54% of the glenoid width.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0363546512445997">
<title>Clinical Relevance:</title>
<p>Most cases of glenoid bone loss in recurrent shoulder dislocation can be reconstructed with the coracoid process to re-establish its anatomy.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Scapula</kwd>
<kwd>shoulder joint</kwd>
<kwd>anatomy</kwd>
<kwd>shoulder dislocation</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Patients with chronic anterior shoulder dislocations may gradually erode and flatten the cartilage and bone of the anterior glenoid rim.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0363546512445997">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0363546512445997">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0363546512445997">10</xref></sup> This change in anatomy can facilitate new shoulder dislocations,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0363546512445997">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0363546512445997">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0363546512445997">14</xref></sup> as a direct relationship between glenoid rim damage and the number of dislocation episodes exists.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0363546512445997">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0363546512445997">11</xref></sup> Therefore, when orthopaedic surgeons deal with glenoid bone loss, it is important to restore the native glenoid area with a bone graft to re-establish the shoulder biomechanics.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0363546512445997">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0363546512445997">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0363546512445997">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0363546512445997">13</xref></sup></p>
<p>In 1954, Latarjet<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0363546512445997">15</xref></sup> described the technique in which the coracoid process was used as a bone graft to treat shoulder instability, increasing the glenoid’s rim area. Itoi et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0363546512445997">14</xref></sup> observed that glenoid erosions greater than 21% of the glenoid length may cause instability and limit the range of motion of the shoulder after the Bankart repair alone.</p>
<p>In spite of the fact that this surgery aims to replace glenoid bone loss, it is not well documented how much glenoid bone loss can be restored by a coracoid bone graft.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0363546512445997">2</xref></sup> As the Latarjet procedure has gained popularity, the authors decided to study the amount of glenoid bone loss that can be corrected with this method. The aim of this study was to measure the mediolateral (M-L) and anteroposterior (A-P) distance of the coracoid process and the largest anterior-to-posterior glenoid distance (glenoid width) and to analyze the correlation between these measurements. We hypothesized that a positive relationship would exist between the M-L coracoid process thickness and glenoid width measurements and that the coracoid could be used as a bone graft in the majority of cases. We also hypothesized that the M-L coracoid distance was significantly greater than the A-P coracoid distance.</p>
<sec id="section8-0363546512445997" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<p>All procedures performed for this study were approved by our institution’s ethical committee. Sixty-one unpaired, human cadaveric scapulae from the Federal University of Sao Paulo Anatomy Laboratory were evaluated (41% right side). Specimens that had any anatomic deformities, evidence of previous surgery, or fractures were excluded from the study. We did not have any information regarding the specimens’ gender, race, and age at the time of death.</p>
<p>The largest M-L thickness of the coracoid process (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0363546512445997">Figure 1</xref>) and the largest A-P distance of the glenoid (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0363546512445997">Figure 2</xref>) were measured with a digital caliper (model 100.306 PLUS, Digimess, Sao Paulo, Brazil), with an accuracy of 0.01 mm (according to the manufacturer). Three examiners performed the measurements 3 times each (with a 1-week interval between measurements), always blinded to the previous results and to the other examiners’ measurements. The measurements were analyzed to determine their variability and reproducibility. The correlation between the thickness of the coracoid process in the M-L plane and the largest anterior-to-posterior glenoid distance was also evaluated.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0363546512445997" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Measurement of the coracoid thickness with the digital caliper.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512445997-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig2-0363546512445997" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Measurement of the glenoid width with the digital caliper.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512445997-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Later, it was decided to add the A-P coracoid process thickness to compare it with the M-L distance. We re-evaluated 31 of the original 61 scapulae of the study, considered sufficient for statistical comparison. The measurements were done with the same technique and equipment described above.</p>
<sec id="section9-0363546512445997">
<title>Statistical Analysis</title>
<p>Intraobserver and interobserver reliability were represented by intraclass correlation coefficients (ICCs). The average measure ICC was used to evaluate interobserver reliability by comparing the averages of 3 measurements of each variable. A measurement was considered reliable if the ICC was higher than .70.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0363546512445997">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0363546512445997">19</xref></sup></p>
<p>The Spearman correlation test was used to evaluate the correlation between the coracoid thickness and the glenoid width. A simple linear regression was also performed between these variables. The Kolmogorov-Smirnov test was employed to study whether the variability of the ratio between the coracoid thickness and the glenoid width had a normal distribution. The Wilcoxon test was used to compare the A-P and M-L coracoid process measurements. Data are presented as mean ± standard deviation (the average from the 3 measurements of the examiner with the higher intraobserver ICC was used). SPSS 13.0 software (SPSS Inc, Chicago, Illinois) was utilized for statistical calculation.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0363546512445997" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The anterior-to-posterior glenoid width was 26.38 ± 2.69 mm (range, 20.03-32.35 mm). The M-L coracoid thickness was 14.51 ± 1.90 mm (range, 9.60-19.31 mm), and its A-P thickness was 8.37 ± 0.93 mm (range, 6.61-9.76 mm). The relationship between the coracoid thickness and glenoid width was also investigated. The coracoid M-L thickness represents 54% ± 5% (range, 43%-70%) of the glenoid width, and the coracoid A-P thickness represents 31% ± 3% (range, 25%-37%) of the glenoid. Spearman correlation showed a positive (<italic>r</italic> = .677) and statistically significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) correlation between the glenoid width and the M-L coracoid thickness, meaning that as the thickness of the coracoid increases, the glenoid width also increases (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0363546512445997">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0363546512445997" position="float">
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Spearman Correlation Analysis Based on the Averages of All Measurements Performed<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0363546512445997"><italic>a</italic></xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0363546512445997" xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512445997-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Pair of Variables</th>
<th align="center">Correlation Coefficient</th>
<th align="center">Significance (<italic>P</italic>)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>GLE 1 × COR 1</td>
<td>+.474</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GLE 2 × COR 2</td>
<td>+.677</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GLE 3 × COR 3</td>
<td>+.585</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0363546512445997">
<label>a</label>
<p>GLE, largest anterior-to-posterior glenoid width; COR, largest mediolateral width of the coracoid; 1, average of the first measurement of all examiners; 2, average of the second measurement of all examiners; 3, average of the third measurement of all examiners.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The simple linear regression between the glenoid and the coracoid A-P measurements showed <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = .992, meaning that the relation between the 2 variables tends to be linear. Also, the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test showed a normal distribution when we analyzed the variability of this correlation, which means that the coracoid thickness and the glenoid width ratio had a 95% confidence level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0363546512445997">Figure 3</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig3-0363546512445997" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Measurement distribution graph (normal distribution). GLE, largest anterior-to-posterior glenoid width; COR, largest mediolateral thickness of the coracoid.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512445997-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The ICC for the glenoid width was .977, .997, and .989 for the 3 examiners, and for the coracoid thickness, it was .954, .985, and .977. Based on these results, the data from the second examiner (ICC, .997 and .985, respectively) were used for all calculations. Interobserver Intraclass correlation coefficients are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0363546512445997">Table 2</xref>. The Wilcoxon test showed that the coracoid A-P distance was significantly smaller than the M-L coracoid thickness (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .001).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0363546512445997" position="float">
<label>Table 2</label>
<caption>
<p>Analysis of Interobserver Reliability Among the 3 Measurements Performed by Each Examiner<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-0363546512445997"><italic>a</italic></xref></sup></p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0363546512445997" xlink:href="10.1177_0363546512445997-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Measurement</th>
<th align="center">ICC</th>
<th align="center">Minimum ICC</th>
<th align="center">Maximum ICC</th>
<th align="center"><italic>P</italic> Value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>GLE 1</td>
<td>.961</td>
<td>.943</td>
<td>.974</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>COR 1</td>
<td>.814</td>
<td>.742</td>
<td>.874</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GLE 2</td>
<td>.936</td>
<td>.907</td>
<td>.958</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>COR 2</td>
<td>.785</td>
<td>.705</td>
<td>.853</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GLE 3</td>
<td>.961</td>
<td>.943</td>
<td>.975</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>COR 3</td>
<td>.830</td>
<td>.763</td>
<td>.885</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0363546512445997">
<label>a</label>
<p>ICC, intraclass correlation coefficient; GLE, largest anterior-to-posterior glenoid width; COR, largest mediolateral width of the coracoid; 1, average of the first measurement of all examiners; 2, average of the second measurement of all examiners; 3, average of the third measurement of all examiners.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0363546512445997" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>In this study, we have shown a strong positive and statistically significant relationship between the coracoid process’ M-L thickness and the anterior-to-posterior glenoid width. The coracoid’s M-L thickness was used, as it is already known that once the medial border of the coracoid is fixed to the anterior glenoid rim, to restore the glenoid area, the coracoid and the glenoid virtually have the same radius of curvature.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0363546512445997">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0363546512445997">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0363546512445997">7</xref></sup> The largest anterior-to-posterior glenoid distance was chosen, as the mean orientation of the glenoid defect points toward the 3-o’clock position of the glenoid for right shoulders or the 9-o’clock position for left shoulders.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0363546512445997">17</xref></sup></p>
<p>The results found in this study are in concordance with the literature. Mallon et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0363546512445997">16</xref></sup> performed a radiographic (true anteroposterior, scapula outlet, and axillary views) and anatomic evaluation of 28 cadaveric scapulae. The authors found an average value of 24 mm (range, 16-29.5 mm) for the glenoid width. Dolan et al,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0363546512445997">8</xref></sup> in a cadaveric study, obtained an M-L coracoid thickness of 16.1 ± 2.3 mm (range, 12.1-18.9 mm). The measurements of other authors found are listed in the Appendix (available in the online version of this article at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ajs.sagepub.com/supplemental/">http://ajs.sagepub.com/supplemental/</ext-link>).</p>
<p>Patients with shoulder dislocations may have erosions or fractures of the anteroinferior glenoid rim, which can cover more than 25% of the glenoid area.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0363546512445997">13</xref></sup> These patients can dislocate their shoulder, even during sleep, and may slip this joint in the midrange of motion in which many of the activities of daily living are performed<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0363546512445997">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0363546512445997">10</xref></sup>; in addition to this, these patients often develop shoulder osteoarthritis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0363546512445997">3</xref></sup> In such cases, a bone graft must be placed at the anterior glenoid rim, as the arthroscopic Bankart repair may lead to a 67% recurrence rate.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0363546512445997">10</xref></sup> On the other hand, the Latarjet technique used for anterior shoulder dislocations has a low recurrence rate that varies from 1% to 6%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0363546512445997">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0363546512445997">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0363546512445997">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0363546512445997">12</xref></sup> and has a 4.9% recurrence rate when used for cases of severe glenoid bone loss.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0363546512445997">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0363546512445997">7</xref></sup> In addition to this, Itoi et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0363546512445997">14</xref></sup> demonstrated that after bone grafting a glenoid erosion (greater than 21% of the superior-inferior axis or greater than 6.8 mm of the A-P glenoid distance), there was an increase in the translation force necessary to cause a shoulder dislocation to levels similar to those without glenoid erosions.</p>
<p>The A-P coracoid thickness is the dimension relevant to perform the “classic” Latarjet procedure. This study has shown that the M-L coracoid thickness represents 43% to 70% of the glenoid width, with an average of 54%. It was also shown that the A-P coracoid thickness represents 31% of the glenoid width on average. This is important information for surgeons planning to perform a bone graft for glenoid bone loss. It was described in a previous study that the coracoid process could be insufficient to correct bone defects that have had more than 33% of bone loss,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0363546512445997">9</xref></sup> and probably, the authors made their opinion based on the A-P coracoid thickness. With the aim to increase the opportunity for bone graft healing to the glenoid neck, it is recommended to remove the coracoid cortical surface. This decreases the coracoid thickness regardless of the technique being used, and when performing the classic Latarjet procedure, it would probably lower the A-P coracoid thickness below 30% of the glenoid width, limiting its indication to smaller erosions. According to the data from the present study, when performing a modified Latarjet technique using the M-L coracoid thickness, most cases of glenoid bone loss can be reconstructed with the coracoid process in order to re-establish its anatomy.</p>
<p>Yamamoto et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0363546512445997">18</xref></sup> observed that in the Latarjet procedure, the grafted coracoid process reconstructs the glenoid concavity, re-establishing the articular curvature, the glenoid depth, and the arc length, which increase stability in the midrange of motion, whereas the conjoined tendon and the subscapularis work together to stabilize the shoulder in both the midrange and the end range of motion. This makes us believe that the coracoid has full capability to replace bone loss of the glenoid, and the stability achieved by the bone block is enhanced by the sling effect of the conjoined tendon.</p>
<p>This study has limitations. First, the measurements were done manually with a digital caliper. In spite of the fact that there was a high interobserver and intraobserver ICC, nowadays, there are better measuring methods like the use of laser scans or 3-dimensional computed tomography scans. Second, the lack of anthropometric data from the cadaveric specimens is another limitation. Unfortunately, these cadaveric specimens were from a large anatomic laboratory, and no information on the specimens was available. Further studies measuring the coracoid M-L thickness and the anterior-to-posterior glenoid distance, as well as their relationship in different genders and races, would be necessary to confirm this.</p>
<p>A strong positive and statistically significant relationship between the coracoid process M-L thickness and the glenoid anterior-to-posterior width exists, and the M-L coracoid thickness represents 54% of the glenoid width.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors thank Professor Ricardo Luiz Smith for kindly allowing them to use the specimens of the Unifesp’s Anatomy Laboratory. They also thank Dr Henrique P. Soutello for assistance with the laboratory measurements.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>One or more of the authors has declared the following potential conflict of interest or source of funding: Ipiranga Hospital at Sao Paulo allowed the use of the radiographic equipment, and Lumen Radiology at Santo Andre allowed the use of the 3-dimensional computed tomography scanning.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0363546512445997">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Allain</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goutallier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glorion</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Long-term results of the Latarjet procedure for the treatment of anterior instability of the shoulder</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>80</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>841</fpage>-<lpage>852</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0363546512445997">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Boileau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Villalba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hery</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Balg</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahrens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neyton</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors for recurrence of shoulder instability after arthroscopic Bankart repair</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>88</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1755</fpage>-<lpage>1763</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0363546512445997">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burkhart</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Beer</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Traumatic glenohumeral bone defects and their relationship to failure of arthroscopic Bankart repairs: significance of the inverted-pear glenoid and the humeral engaging Hill-Sachs lesion</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>677</fpage>-<lpage>694</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0363546512445997">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Burkhart</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Beer</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barth</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cresswell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Results of modified Latarjet reconstruction in patients with anteroinferior instability and significant bone loss</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1033</fpage>-<lpage>1041</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0363546512445997">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Churchill</surname><given-names>GA</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>
</person-group> <source>Marketing Research: Methodological Foundations</source>. <edition>7th ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Thomson Publishing</publisher-name>; <year>1995</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0363546512445997">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Churchill</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brems</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kotschi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Glenoid size, inclination, and version: an anatomic study</article-title>. <source>J Shoulder Elbow Surg</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>327</fpage>-<lpage>332</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0363546512445997">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>De Beer</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Glenoid bone defects: open Latarjet with congruent arc modification</article-title>. <source>Orthop Clin North Am</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>407</fpage>-<lpage>415</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0363546512445997">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hariri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McAdams</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>An anatomic study of the coracoid process as it relates to bone transfer procedures</article-title>. <source>J Shoulder Elbow Surg</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>497</fpage>-<lpage>501</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0363546512445997">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The Latarjet procedure for recurrent anterior shoulder instability: rationale and technique</article-title>. <source>Oper Tech Sports Med</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>25</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0363546512445997">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gartsman</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roddey</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hammerman</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Arthroscopic treatment of anterior-inferior glenohumeral instability: two to five-year follow-up</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>82</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>991</fpage>-<lpage>1003</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0363546512445997">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hovelius</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Akermark</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Albrektsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Bristow-Latarjet procedure for recurrent anterior dislocation of the shoulder: a 2-5 year follow-up study on the results of 112 cases</article-title>. <source>Acta Orthop Scand</source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>284</fpage>-<lpage>290</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0363546512445997">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hovelius</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Korner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lundberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The coracoid transfer for recurrent dislocation of the shoulder: technical aspects of the Bristow-Latarjet procedure</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>926</fpage>-<lpage>934</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0363546512445997">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ikemoto</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murachovsky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strose</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nascimento</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bueno</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Recurrent shoulder dislocation: aspects between the first episode and surgical treatment</article-title>. <source>Rev Bras Ortop</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>524</fpage>-<lpage>528</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0363546512445997">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Itoi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berglund</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berge</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>An</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The effect of a glenoid defect on anteroinferior stability of the shoulder after Bankart repair: a cadaveric study</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>82</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>46</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0363546512445997">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Latarjet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. [<article-title>Treatment of recurrent dislocation of the shoulder</article-title>]. <source>Lyon Chir</source>. <year>1954</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>994</fpage>-<lpage>997</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0363546512445997">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mallon</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vogler</surname><given-names>JB</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Radiographic and geometric anatomy of the scapula</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>277</volume>:<fpage>142</fpage>-<lpage>154</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0363546512445997">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Itoi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sugaya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Minagawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tuoheti</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Location of the glenoid defect in shoulders with recurrent anterior dislocation</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>889</fpage>-<lpage>893</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0363546512445997">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muraki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sperling</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Stabilizing mechanism in bone-grafting of a large glenoid defect</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>92</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2059</fpage>-<lpage>2066</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0363546512445997">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>An introduction to computing and interpreting Cronbach coefficient alpha in SAS</article-title>. In <source>SUGI 26 proceedings, Long Beach California</source> <month>April</month> <day>22-25</day>, <year>2001</year>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www2.sas.com/proceedings/sugi26/p246-26.pdf">www2.sas.com/proceedings/sugi26/p246-26.pdf</ext-link></comment></citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>