<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PIA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sppia</journal-id>
<journal-title>Proceedings of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers, Part A: Journal of Power and Energy</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0957-6509</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2041-2967</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0957650912453536</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0957650912453536</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Original Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Experimental study of friction damping of blade with loosely assembled dovetail attachment</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Shangguan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0957650912453536">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0957650912453536">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0957650912453536"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0957650912453536"><label>1</label>School of Energy and Power Engineering, Xi’an Jiaotong University, China</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0957650912453536"><label>2</label>State Key Laboratory for Strength and Vibration of Mechanical Structure, Xi’an Jiaotong University, China</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0957650912453536">Z Xu, State Key Laboratory for Strength and Vibration of Mechanical Structure, Xi’an Jiaotong University, Xi’an 710049, China. Email: <email>zlxu@mail.xjtu.edu.cn</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>226</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<fpage>738</fpage>
<lpage>750</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>8</month><year>2011</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© IMechE 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Institution of Mechanical Engineers</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>In order to study the friction damping characteristics of blade with loosely assembled dovetail attachment, an experimental method and a test rig are presented in this article. In the experiment, a axial load is imposed at the bottom of blade attachment to simulate the blade centrifugal force. A harmonic force is imposed on the blade as airflow force. The forced responses of a group of plane blades and a compressor blade are measured at different centrifugal forces. The results show that the resonant frequency increases with the centrifugal force, and gradually reaches the maximum. When the centrifugal force increases, the amplitude of resonant response decreases at the beginning and then increases. There is an optimal centrifugal force under which the resonant amplitude is minimal and the friction damping effect is the best. There is softening spring effect when the friction forces worked on blade system. From the results of compressor blade, it is found that when the centrifugal force is 1.5 kN, the resonant amplitude reaches the least value of 3.42 g, which is only 22.4% of the biggest value 39.88 g. This means that 1.5 kN is the optimal centrifugal force.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Blade</kwd>
<kwd>friction damping</kwd>
<kwd>dovetail attachment</kwd>
<kwd>experimental method</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-0957650912453536" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>Blades are core components of turbomachinery. Many turbomachinery accidents are caused by blades failure. The blades are vibrated by airflow force during the process of startup, shutdown or operation. High vibratory stress is one of major reasons of blade failure. To prevent blade failure, the vibratory response needs to be attenuated to an acceptable level. Some kinds of friction dampers are employed to suppress blade vibration for providing additional damping, for example, blade-to-ground, blade-to-blade and blade dovetail-to-disk groove.</p>
<p>The blade with loosely assembled dovetail attachment is usually used in gas turbine and aeroengine, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0957650912453536">Figure 1</xref>. This style of blade attachment is easy to manufacture and assemble. When the blade starts up, the friction contact joints are formed between the blade dovetail attachment and disk dovetail groove because of the centrifugal force of blade. When the blade is excited to vibrate by airflow force, the interfacial friction damping arises out from the two surfaces between the blade dovetail attachment and disk moving relative to each other. In other words, there is a dry friction force on the blade dovetail attachment, which dissipates blades’ vibratory energy and increase blades’ damping. There are some reasons to affect the friction damping of blade, such as the centrifugal force, the angle of dovetail attachment, the area of dovetail attachment interfaces and so on.
<fig id="fig1-0957650912453536" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Schematic of a blade with loosely assembled dovetail attachment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912453536-fig1.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>In the past, considerable research works focused on blade vibration control by friction damping and several kinds of blade friction dampers were investigated. Griffin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0957650912453536">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0957650912453536">2</xref></sup> reviewed the strongpoint of friction damped blade in view of dynamics analysis method, friction force model, structural model and damper optimization. Srinivasan and Cutts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0957650912453536">3</xref></sup> studied the dry friction damping of blade shroud and platform by analytical and experimental methods. Yang and Chu,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0957650912453536">4</xref></sup> proposed a friction model to characterize the contact kinematics that imposed both friction nonlinearity and intermittent separation nonlinearity on the constrained structures. Ren and Zhu<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0957650912453536">5</xref></sup> used theoretical and experimental approaches to research the vibration characteristics and dry friction damping effect of shrouded blades. Ji et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0957650912453536">6</xref></sup> experimentally investigated the dynamic characteristics of damping blade by using a lacing wire damper. Xu et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0957650912453536">7</xref></sup> calculated the forced response of a five-blade group by a macroslip friction model and finite element method. Laxalde et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0957650912453536">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0957650912453536">9</xref></sup> investigated a damping strategy for bladed disks of turbomachinery involving a friction ring by a lumped parameter model of the system, and the use of friction ring dampers for integrally bladed disks by numerical and experimental method. Yang and Menq<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0957650912453536">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0957650912453536">11</xref></sup> investigated the coupling contact kinematics, the analytical criteria for stick-slip transitions, the experimental verification for the dynamic response, and their applications in design of blade wedge dampers. Petrov and Ewins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0957650912453536">12</xref></sup> developed a structural model for wedge and split underplatform dampers, whose models took into account inertia forces and the effects of normal force variation on stick-slip transitions at contact interfaces. The wedge damper works between two neighboring blades. It is used as an independent part. The friction contact surfaces of wedge damper are similar to one of dovetail attachment. The dovetail attachment belongs to blade, and it works between the blade and disk. There are some researches about contact stresses and dissipation energy on the dovetail attachments. Beisheim and Sinclair<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0957650912453536">13</xref></sup> investigated the contact stress of dovetail attachments by three-dimensional finite element method without considering friction. Alonso et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0957650912453536">14</xref></sup> presented a detailed study of the sensitiveness of different blade attachments to normal stress distribution along the contact face and the influences of distribution on damping results. Asai et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0957650912453536">15</xref></sup> evaluated the friction damping in dovetail attachment joints based on dissipation energy from the experimental results and simulation results. Shangguan et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0957650912453536">16</xref></sup> predicted the forced responses of blades with loosely assembled dovetail attachment by using a lumped parameters model and harmonic balance method. Oloffson and Hagman<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0957650912453536">17</xref></sup> derived a model for micro-slip between flat surfaces based on modeling the asperities as ellipsoidal elastic bodies. Rao et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0957650912453536">18</xref></sup> employed Oloffson–Hagman micro-slip damping model to determine analytically an effective friction coefficient, which is a function of the tangential and normal forces, contact stiffness and slip amplitude. In a word, many kinds of friction dampers are studied by designers for blade vibration control.</p>
<p>In this article, a test system is presented for studying the dynamic responses of blade with loosely assembled dovetail attachment, in which centrifugal force is simulated by an axial load. The normal loads can be applied on two friction interfaces by the simulation centrifugal force. The measurement method of the centrifugal force is introduced. The dynamic responses of a group of plane blades with different dovetail attachment angles are measured in consideration of the variable simulation centrifugal force. The influences of centrifugal force and dovetail angle on the friction damping of blade with dovetail attachment are investigated. The damping characteristics of a compressor blade with dovetail attachment are measured and the influences of centrifugal force on responses are investigated too.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0957650912453536"><title>Test systems</title>
<sec id="sec3-0957650912453536"><title>Testing facility</title>
<p>The test system for measuring the friction damping characteristics of blade with loosely assembled dovetail attachment is designed as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0957650912453536">Figure 2</xref>. A loading arm is used to fix the dovetail attachment into dovetail groove, which is clamped at the base. A cushion block is placed between the loading arm and dovetail attachment for stress measurement by a strain meter. The loading arm imposes an external axial load, <italic>N</italic>, at the bottom of dovetail attachment to simulate the blade centrifugal force. The external axial load <italic>N</italic> is increased gradually to imitate the diversification of centrifugal force during the start-up process.
<fig id="fig2-0957650912453536" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Test system.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912453536-fig2.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>A vibration exciter is placed at the base. A power amplifier which connects the vibration exciter and signal generator is used to enhance harmonic excitation signal. The excitation point is distanced 80 mm to dovetail attachment. The excitation force is given by <italic>P</italic> = <italic>P<sub>a</sub></italic> sin(2<italic>πf</italic> · <italic>t</italic>), where <italic>P<sub>a</sub></italic> denotes the amplitude of harmonic excitation force, and <italic>f</italic> denotes the harmonic frequency. The amplitude of excitation force <italic>P<sub>a</sub></italic> is 10<bold> </bold>N and is invariable in this test. The direction of excitation force is perpendicular to blade. A acceleration sensor is placed at the end of blade for acquiring the vibration data.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-0957650912453536"><title>Testing blades</title>
<p>Three plane blades have the same dimensions, but the different dovetail angles as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0957650912453536">Figure 3</xref>. The blade dimensions are 240 mm long, 36 mm wide and 6 mm thick. The dovetail angles are 40°, 80° and 120°, respectively. The blade material is 2Cr13, and its density is 7750 kg/m<sup>3</sup>. The first natural frequency is 88.758 Hz. The total contact area between dovetail attachment and groove is 1440 mm<sup>2</sup>, which is not changed with the different dovetail angle <italic>θ</italic>.
<fig id="fig3-0957650912453536" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Dimensions of plane blades.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912453536-fig3.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>A last stage blade of compressor is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0957650912453536">Figure 4</xref>. Its dovetail angle <italic>θ</italic> is 72°. The total contact area between the dovetail attachment and groove is 478.08 mm<sup>2</sup>. The dimensions of the each side contact area are 72 mm long and 3.32 mm wide.
<fig id="fig4-0957650912453536" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>The last stage blade of a compressor.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912453536-fig4.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0957650912453536"><title>Measuring methods</title>
<p>In this experiment, the forced responses of three plane blades and the compressor blade are measured at six different centrifugal forces. The test rig is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0957650912453536">Figure 5</xref>. A group of time-domain vibration response curves are acquired when the excitation frequency is changed from 70 to 100 Hz at each centrifugal force for plane blades. The response amplitudes at different excitation frequency are collected to draw the amplitude–frequency curve. Once the centrifugal force is changed, this testing process can be repeated to get a group of amplitude–frequency curves at variant centrifugal force.
<fig id="fig5-0957650912453536" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Test rig.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912453536-fig5.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The semi-power points method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0957650912453536">6</xref></sup> is applied approximately to measure the damping ratio of the friction damping blade in this article.</p>
<p>The strain of cushion block between the loading arm and dovetail attachment is measured by strain gage. The load value at the bottom of dovetail attachment is obtained according to Hooke’s law. In order to reduce the measuring error, 4 strain gages are put on the 4 sides of the cushion block, and the strains of cushion block 4 sides are measured at one time. And then the average of 4 strains is used to compute the axial load.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0957650912453536" sec-type="results"><title>Results and discussion</title>
<sec id="sec7-0957650912453536"><title>Influence of friction damping on steady response</title>
<p>In order to investigate the influence of friction damping of steady response, the time-domain steady-state response of 40° angle dovetail attachment blade are measured at two assembled ways, tightly and loosely. The results are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0957650912453536">Figure 6</xref>. The acceleration is used as ordinate and its unit is gravity acceleration marked as ‘g’. The time is used as abscissa and its unit is second marked as ‘s’. It is known that hysteresis damping is through in this test and friction damping depends on the relation movement of contact surfaces. In this section, the comparison of steady responses of two assembled ways is presented.
<fig id="fig6-0957650912453536" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Time domain steady-state response.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912453536-fig6.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0957650912453536">Figure 6</xref>, the dotted line denotes the steady response of blade system in which the dovetail attachment is tightly assembled into groove. There is no macro-slip and only micro-slip or fretting damping left, and it is slightly for blade vibration in macro view. The frequency is 88 Hz, which is about the first natural frequency. It can be seen that the response of linear blade system is a regular sine curve, and has larger oscillation amplitude which is about 25 g. The real line denotes the resonant response of blade system in which the dovetail attachment is loosely assembled into groove, and there exists relative movement and friction damping when the blade is vibrating. The response of loosely assembled blade system is an irregular periodic curve and the oscillation amplitude becomes smaller and is about 5 g, which is 20% of linear blade system. The resonant frequency is 77 Hz, which is 11 Hz less than 88 Hz of linear blade system.</p>
<p>The spectrum bar chart of steady-state response of loosely assembled blade is given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0957650912453536">Figure 7</xref>. The first 12-order harmonics are presented. And the percentages of each order harmonic coefficient in the first order are shown at the tip of bars. From <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0957650912453536">Figure 7</xref>, the first-order harmonic coefficient is about 3.4 g, which is the biggest of all. The contributions of the 3rd to 7th orders are 3.96%, 5.04%, 9.67%, 10.9% and 4.21%, respectively, which are more than other higher order harmonics. The contributions of these order harmonics are not neglected and the first 10-order harmonics should be considered at least for calculating the responses of friction damping blade by numerical methods, such as the multi-harmonic balance method.
<fig id="fig7-0957650912453536" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Spectrum of time domain steady-state response.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912453536-fig7.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-0957650912453536"><title>Influence of centrifugal force on responses</title>
<p>The forced responses of plane blade with 40° angle dovetail attachment are measured at different centrifugal forces. The amplitude–frequency curves at different centrifugal forces are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0957650912453536">Figure 8</xref>. The correlative parameters including damping ratio are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0957650912453536">Table 1</xref>. It can be seen that, when the centrifugal force increases from 0.54 to 3.74 kN, the resonant amplitude increases from 5.64 to 25.9 g and the resonant frequency increases from 77.28 to 87.2 Hz. When the centrifugal force equals 3.74 kN, the resonant amplitude and the resonant frequency get the biggest values, 25.9 g and 87.2 Hz, respectively. When the centrifugal force is 0.54 kN, the resonant amplitude is the least, 5.64 g, which is 21.7% of the biggest amplitude. The least resonant frequency is 77.28 Hz which is about 10 Hz less then the biggest resonant frequency. The damping ratio of Curve 1, 0.07, is 7 times bigger than Curve 6. In Curve 1, it is found that softening spring effect gives rise to nonlinear response with the resonance peak bending towards lower frequencies. The resonant amplitude and frequency increase gradually, and the damping ratio decreases in the test centrifugal force range. The resonant response remains when the centrifugal force reaches a certain big value, 2 kN, which is called a saturated centrifugal force <italic>N<sub>s</sub></italic>. When the centrifugal force exceeds this big value, there is big normal pressure on contact surfaces. In this situation, the contact state between the blade dovetail attachment and disk groove is close to rigidness, the support stiffness achieves the saturated situation, and there is no relative movement and no dry friction damping.
<fig id="fig8-0957650912453536" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Amplitude–frequency curves at different centrifugal forces.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912453536-fig8.tif"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="table1-0957650912453536" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Resonant frequency and damping ratio at different centrifugal forces.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0957650912453536" xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912453536-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Curve no.</th>
<th>Strain value</th>
<th>Centrifugal force (kN)</th>
<th>Resonant frequency (Hz)</th>
<th>Resonant amplitude (g)</th>
<th>Damping ratio</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>6.6</td>
<td>0.54</td>
<td>77.28</td>
<td>5.64</td>
<td>0.070</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>9.9</td>
<td>0.82</td>
<td>80.81</td>
<td>13.53</td>
<td>0.021</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>11.55</td>
<td>0.95</td>
<td>83.14</td>
<td>18.50</td>
<td>0.009</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>18.15</td>
<td>1.50</td>
<td>84.87</td>
<td>21.15</td>
<td>0.013</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>23.1</td>
<td>1.90</td>
<td>86.59</td>
<td>25.25</td>
<td>0.011</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>45.375</td>
<td>3.74</td>
<td>87.20</td>
<td>25.90</td>
<td>0.010</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0957650912453536"><title>Influence of dovetail angle on resonant response</title>
<p>In order to investigate the damping effect of blades with different angle dovetail attachments, the resonant amplitudes of three plane blades with different dovetail angles at variable centrifugal forces are measured. The relation curves of resonant amplitude, resonant frequency and damping ratio versus centrifugal force are shown in Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0957650912453536">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0957650912453536">10</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0957650912453536">11</xref>, respectively. In the three figures, the line with circle symbols is the result of 40° dovetail attachment blade, the line with square symbols is the result of 80° dovetail attachment blade, and the line with delta symbols is the result of 120° dovetail attachment blade.
<fig id="fig9-0957650912453536" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Resonant amplitude versus centrifugal force.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912453536-fig9.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig10-0957650912453536" position="float"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p>Resonant frequency versus centrifugal force.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912453536-fig10.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig11-0957650912453536" position="float"><label>Figure 11.</label><caption><p>The damping ratio versus centrifugal force.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912453536-fig11.tif"/></fig>
</p>
<p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0957650912453536">Figure 9</xref>, when the centrifugal force increases from 0.3 to 3.7 kN, three resonant amplitudes increase from about 5 to 25 g. They saturate finally when the centrifugal force exceeds the saturated centrifugal force <italic>N<sub>s</sub></italic>. The saturated centrifugal force, <italic>N<sub>s</sub></italic>, is about 2 kN for each plane blade. The least resonant amplitudes are almost the same. The range of centrifugal force can be divided into two parts, one part is from 0.3 to 2 kN, and the other is from 2 kN to the infinite. When centrifugal force is in the first part, the blade vibration system is nonlinear. In this situation, there is a relative movement occurring on contact surfaces when blade is vibrating. When the centrifugal force increases in this range, the resonant amplitude rises because the relative movement becomes difficult and the damping effect decreases. When the centrifugal force increases from 0.3 to 1 kN, the change rate of the resonant amplitude of 80° dovetail blade is biggest, and the change rate of 120° dovetail blade is least. When the centrifugal force increases from 1 to 2 kN, the change rate of the resonant amplitude of 80° dovetail blade is least. In this situation, the resonant amplitude of 80° dovetail blade is insensitive to centrifugal force. If centrifugal force is in the second part, the blade vibration system is almost a linear vibration system. In this situation, there is no relative movement on the contact surfaces, and the damping effect disappears. The resonant amplitude retains a constant value.</p>
<p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0957650912453536">Figure 10</xref>, the resonant frequency increases with centrifugal force, then saturates when centrifugal force exceeds <italic>N<sub>s</sub></italic> which is same as the saturation force in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0957650912453536">Figure 9</xref>. The least resonant frequency is 72 Hz for the blade dovetail angle 80°, which is 16 Hz less than the natural frequency 88 Hz. When the centrifugal force increases from 0.3 to 2 kN, the resonant amplitude of blade with dovetail angle 120° increases slowly, but the resonant frequency increases fast. The effect of dovetail angle on resonant frequency is obvious.</p>
<p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0957650912453536">Figure 11</xref>, the damping ratio of blade decreases with the centrifugal force increasing, then reaches a certain small value at the centrifugal force <italic>N</italic> = <italic>N<sub>s</sub></italic>. When the centrifugal force increases from 0.3 to 2 kN, the damping ratio of blade with dovetail angle 120° decreases slowly, and the damping ratio of blade with dovetail angle 80° decreases fast. The test results of blades with different dovetail angles show that the dovetail angle can influence the dynamic response of blade system, especially on the change rate of dynamic response. Therefore, the blade designers should choose an appropriate dovetail angle to make the blade dynamic response insensitive to centrifugal force.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-0957650912453536"><title>Responses of the compressor blade</title>
<p>The amplitude–frequency curves at six different centrifugal forces are depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0957650912453536">Figure 12</xref>, and the correlative parameters including damping ratio are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0957650912453536">Table 2</xref>.
<fig id="fig12-0957650912453536" position="float"><label>Figure 12.</label><caption><p>Amplitude–frequency curves at different centrifugal forces.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912453536-fig12.tif"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="table2-0957650912453536" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Resonant frequency and damping ratio at different centrifugal forces.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0957650912453536" xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912453536-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Curve no.</th>
<th>Strain value</th>
<th>Centrifugal force (kN)</th>
<th>Resonant frequency (Hz)</th>
<th>Resonant amplitude (g)</th>
<th>Damping ratio</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>6.6</td>
<td>0.54</td>
<td>76</td>
<td>8.94</td>
<td>0.085</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>18.15</td>
<td>1.50</td>
<td>137</td>
<td>3.42</td>
<td>0.84</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>50.325</td>
<td>4.15</td>
<td>177</td>
<td>5.03</td>
<td>0.51</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>54.45</td>
<td>4.49</td>
<td>326</td>
<td>13.59</td>
<td>0.13</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>71.5</td>
<td>5.89</td>
<td>555</td>
<td>38.69</td>
<td>0.020</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>92.0</td>
<td>7.58</td>
<td>593</td>
<td>39.88</td>
<td>0.028</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0957650912453536">Figure 12</xref>, the curves 3 and 4 show the softening spring effect on the amplitude frequency responses. The resonant frequency 76 Hz is the lowest resonance frequency in experimental frequency range in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0957650912453536">Table 2</xref>, which has 500 Hz difference when compared with the highest resonance frequency 593 Hz. The least peak amplitude 3.42 g is only 22.4% of the biggest value 39.88 g in experimental frequency range. These data indicate that the damping effect of blade with dovetail attachment is obvious. The various values of centrifugal forces not only affect the resonance frequency in test systems, but also impact the peak amplitude of blade, and there is an optimal centrifugal force makes the minimum amplitude peak and the best damping effect.</p>
<p>The relationship between resonant amplitude and the applied centrifugal force is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0957650912453536">Figure 13</xref>. When the centrifugal force is less than 1.5 kN, the curve exhibits downward status. The resonant amplitude increases when centrifugal force changes from 1.5 to 6 kN. When the centrifugal force exceeds 6 kN, the resonant amplitude maintains a constant value. According to this test data, when centrifugal force gets 1.5 kN, the resonant amplitude is the minimum and is about 3.42 g. That is to say 1.5 kN is the optimal centrifugal force for the compressor blade in experimental frequency range. The minimum value 3.42 g is about 8.5% of the biggest value 40 g. Another special centrifugal force in this test is 4 kN. The peak amplitude climbs very small just from 3.42 to 5.03 g, when the centrifugal force changes from 1.5 to 4 kN. While, in the range of 4 to 6 kN, the change rate of peak amplitude becomes very sensitive and it means that the damping effect is significant during this centrifugal force range. When the centrifugal force exceeds 6 kN, the contact surface between dovetail attachment and groove becomes too tight to produce friction force, the peak amplitude is saturated. As the friction damping does not work, the test blade system is similar to a linear system.The relationship between resonant frequency and applied centrifugal force is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14-0957650912453536">Figure 14</xref>. The curve in this figure is relatively simple compared with others, in which the resonance frequency increases from 76 to 593 Hz with the increase of centrifugal force. Corresponding to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0957650912453536">Figure 13</xref>, in different centrifugal force range, the curve behaves in different change rate expressing different damping characteristics.The damping ratio versus applied centrifugal force curve is depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig15-0957650912453536">Figure 15</xref>. The damping ratio climbs quickly at the beginning until the point (centrifugal force 1.5 kN, damping ratio 0.84), which gives optimal damping characteristics, then, the curve decreases with the centrifugal force increasing. From <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0957650912453536">Figure 13</xref> when centrifugal force achieves 1.5 kN the resonant amplitude is the minimum value in experimental frequency range, at this time, the damping ratio reaches the biggest 0.84, which is 42 times bigger than the minimum damping ratio 0.02. When the centrifugal force exceeds 6 kN, the two contact surface stick very tight, the friction damping faded away and the damping ratio reaches the minimum.
<fig id="fig13-0957650912453536" position="float"><label>Figure 13.</label><caption><p>Resonant amplitude versus centrifugal force.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912453536-fig13.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig14-0957650912453536" position="float"><label>Figure 14.</label><caption><p>Resonant frequency versus centrifugal force.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912453536-fig14.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig15-0957650912453536" position="float"><label>Figure 15.</label><caption><p>Damping ratio versus centrifugal force.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0957650912453536-fig15.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>When the centrifugal force is a small value, the rubbing effect of the contact surfaces is very slight, the friction consumed energy is very small, accordingly, and the blade vibration attenuation is a little. The consumed energy will increase with centrifugal force because of the increased rubbing. When the centrifugal force exceeds the saturation value, friction damping disappears and the system becomes a linear cantilever beam system.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-0957650912453536" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title>
<p>A test system is presented to investigate the dynamic responses of blade with dovetail attachment. The dynamic responses of a group of plane blades and a compressor blade are measured in consideration of variable centrifugal force. The experimental results show that the amplitude of resonant response decreases at the beginning and then increases when the centrifugal force increases. There is an optimal centrifugal force under which resonant amplitude is minimal and damping effect is the best. There is softening spring effect when friction forces worked on the blade system. When centrifugal force is changed from 0.3 to 2 kN, the dynamic response of plane blade is sensitive to centrifugal force. From the results of compressor blade, it is found that, when centrifugal force is 1.5 kN, the resonant amplitude reaches the least value 3.42 g, which is only 22.4% of the biggest value 39.88 g. It means that 1.5 kN is the optimal centrifugal force. The resonant response of compressor blade retains a low level when the centrifugal force in the range from 1.5 to 4 kN.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec12-0957650912453536"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This work is financially supported by the National Basic Research Program of China (Grant No. 2011CB706505), Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant No. 50675169), and state 863 Programs of China (Grant No. 2007AA04Z1A1).</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0957650912453536"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A review of friction damping of turbine blade vibration</article-title>. <source>Int J Turbo Jet Eng</source> <year>1990</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0957650912453536"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Friction damping of resonant stress in gas turbine engine airfoil</article-title>. <source>J Eng Gas Turbines Power-Trans ASME</source> <year>1980</year>; <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>329</fpage>–<lpage>333</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0957650912453536"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Cutts</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dry friction damping mechanisms in engine blades</article-title>. <source>J Eng Power-Trans ASME</source> <year>1983</year>; <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>332</fpage>–<lpage>341</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0957650912453536"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Menq</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Stick-slip-separation analysis and non-linear stiffness and damping characterization of friction contacts having variable normal load</article-title>. <source>J Sound Vib</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>210</volume>: <fpage>461</fpage>–<lpage>481</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0957650912453536"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The theoritical analysis and experimental investigation of vibration on blades with dry friction damping</article-title>. <source>Acta Aeronaut Astronaut Sin</source> <year>1994</year>; <volume>15</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>1306</fpage>–<lpage>1314</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0957650912453536"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Experimental investigation of the dynamic characteristics of the damped blade</article-title>. <source>J Sound Vib</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>213</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>234</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0957650912453536"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>ZL</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>QJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Analysis on response of blades with friction damping interconnection using a new friction model</article-title>. <source><italic>In: </italic>ASME ASIA’97</source>. <comment>Singapore, October 1997, 97-AA-19</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0957650912453536"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laxalde</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Thouverez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinou</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Qualitative analysis of forced response of blisks with friction rings dampers</article-title>. <source>Eur J Mech A/Solids</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>676</fpage>–<lpage>687</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0957650912453536"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laxalde</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Thouverez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Experimental and numerical investigation of friction rings damping of blisks, GT2008-50862</article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings of ASME turbo expo</source>, <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0957650912453536"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Menq</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of contact kinematics and application to the design of wedge dampers in turbomachinery blading: Part 1—Stick-slip contact kinematics</article-title>. <source>J Eng Gas Turbines Power-Trans ASME</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>120</volume>: <fpage>410</fpage>–<lpage>417</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0957650912453536"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Menq</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of contact kinematics and application to the design of wedge dampers in turbomachinery blading: Part 2—Predicition of forced response and experimental verification</article-title>. <source>J Eng Gas Turbines Power-Trans ASME</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>120</volume>: <fpage>418</fpage>–<lpage>423</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0957650912453536"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petrov</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ewins</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Advanced modeling of underplatform friction dampers for analysis of bladed disk vibration</article-title>. <source>J Turbomach-Trans ASME</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>143</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0957650912453536"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beisheim</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>On the three-dimensional finite element analysis of dovetail attachments</article-title>. <source>J Turbomach-Trans ASME</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>125</volume>: <fpage>372</fpage>–<lpage>379</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0957650912453536"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquina</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Coro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Static normal stress influence in friction damping of blade attachments</article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings of ASME turbo expo</source>, <publisher-loc>Orlando, USA, GT2009-59596</publisher-loc>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0957650912453536"><label>15</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakurai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kudo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of friction damping in dovetail root joints based on dissipation energy on contact surfaces</article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings of ASME turbo expo</source>, <publisher-loc>Orlando, USA, GT2009-59508</publisher-loc>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0957650912453536"><label>16</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shangguan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>ZL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>QL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Forced response prediction of blades with loosely assembled dovetail attachment by HBM</article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings of ASME turbo expo</source>, <publisher-loc>Orlando, USA, GT2009-59778</publisher-loc>, <year>2009</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0957650912453536"><label>17</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olofsson</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagman</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A model for micro-slip between flat surfaces based on deformation of ellipsoidal bodies</article-title>. <source>Tribol Int</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>599</fpage>–<lpage>603</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0957650912453536"><label>18</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratnakar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Narayan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Analytical estimation of microslip damping in bladed-disks</article-title>. In: <source>5th international conference on the future of gas turbine technology</source>, <publisher-loc>Brussels</publisher-loc>, <year>2010</year>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<app-group>
<app id="app1-0957650912453536"><title>Appendix</title>
<sec id="sec13-0957650912453536"><title/>
<sec id="sec14-0957650912453536"><title>Notation</title>
<p>
<def-list id="duolist1-0957650912453536">
<def-item><term><italic>f</italic></term><def><p>frequency of the harmonic excitation force (Hz)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>g</italic></term><def><p>gravity acceleration (m/s<sup>2</sup>)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>N</italic></term><def><p>axial load/centrifugal force (kN)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>N<sub>s</sub></italic></term><def><p>saturated centrifugal force (kN)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>P</italic></term><def><p>exciting force (N)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>P<sub>a</sub></italic></term><def><p>amplitude of the excitation force (N)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>R</italic></term><def><p>response of the blade (g)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>t</italic></term><def><p>time variable (s)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>θ</italic></term><def><p>angle between two contact surfaces of the dovetail attachment (degree)</p></def></def-item>
<def-item><term><italic>ζ</italic></term><def><p>damping ratio</p></def></def-item></def-list></p>
</sec>
</sec></app></app-group>
</back>
</article>