<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">APY</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spapy</journal-id>
<journal-title>Australasian Psychiatry</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1039-8562</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1440-1665</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1039856212459583</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1039856212459583</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Psychiatric services</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Prevalence of parents within an adult mental health service: <italic>Census</italic> results 2008–2011</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>Deb</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-1039856212459583">Director, Children and Young People’s Mental Health, Central Coast Local Health District, Gosford, NSW, Australia</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Batchelor</surname><given-names>Samantha</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-1039856212459583">Research Officer, Children and Young People’s Mental Health, Central Coast Local Health District, Gosford, NSW, Australia</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Bochynska</surname><given-names>Kataryzna</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff3-1039856212459583">Research and Evaluation officer, Children and Young People’s Mental Health, Central Coast Local Health District, Gosford, NSW, Australia</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1039856212459583">Deb Howe, Children and Young People’s Mental Health, Central Coast Local Health District, Suite 1, Level 2, Gateway Building, 237 Mann Street, Gosford, NSW 2250, Australia Email: <email>dhowe@nsccahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>20</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>413</fpage>
<lpage>418</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">The Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Psychiatrists</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-1039856212459583">
<title>Objective:</title>
<p>The objective of this article is to determine the prevalence of parents of children (aged 0–17 years) within a mental health service system and gather contextual data regarding this population.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1039856212459583">
<title>Method:</title>
<p>The study uses a census approach. The <italic>Census</italic> is conducted annually across Central Coast Adult Mental Health Services, NSW, Australia. All five community mental health teams and four acute inpatient units within the service participate, with each team completing <italic>Census</italic> forms for active clients identified as parents on <italic>Census</italic> day. The <italic>Census form</italic> collects data on parents and children including demographic data, parental diagnosis, parental contact and risk factors.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1039856212459583">
<title>Results:</title>
<p>Consecutive data shows 25–28% of active clients are parents. Annually, at least 400 children are identified; approximately 60% reside permanently with their parent with a mental illness.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1039856212459583">
<title>Conclusions:</title>
<p>The <italic>Census</italic> is a valuable tool to determine the prevalence of parenthood. Moreover, it collects contextual data on this population. Data show an emerging relationship between parental diagnosis and parental contact. A picture of level of risk across the system has also been highlighted. Results add to the evidence regarding parental mental illness and circumstances of these families. The data clearly articulate a large need for interventions for children of parents with a mental illness (COPMI) within this population, given the high proportion of children who permanently reside with their parent with a mental illness.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>children of parents with a mental illness</kwd>
<kwd>mental health services</kwd>
<kwd>risk factors</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Children living within families experiencing parental mental illness are at greater risk of adverse outcomes than children not living with parental mental illness.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1039856212459583">1</xref></sup> These children are more likely to experience negative outcomes, including an increased risk of psychological and behavioural problems,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1039856212459583">2</xref></sup> disruptions in home life and schooling, and development of maladaptive coping strategies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1039856212459583">3</xref></sup> Additionally, attachment issues may result because parents with mental illness may have reduced capacity to demonstrate love, security, nurturing and sensitive parenting practices.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1039856212459583">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1039856212459583">3</xref></sup> The overrepresentation of parental mental illness among families where child maltreatment is identified is also concerning.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1039856212459583">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>Impacts of parental mental illness can continue well beyond childhood into adolescence and adulthood. An association between maternal mental health problems and poorer academic outcomes for youth has been identified.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1039856212459583">5</xref></sup> Evidence also suggests up to two-thirds of adult children will experience a psychosocial disorder and/or mental illness.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1039856212459583">6</xref></sup> Additionally, adult children report childhood neglect, increased caregiver responsibilities (impacting on vocational goals and social relationships), stigma and lack of support, and have been shown to experience lower levels of social functioning, greater work and marriage problems, decreased self-esteem and increased alcohol use.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1039856212459583">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>Consequently, the provision of appropriate services and interventions to meet the needs of parents with mental illness and their children is essential. A recent systematic review provides evidence that individual, group and family-based interventions can prevent poor outcomes for children of parents with a mental illness.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1039856212459583">8</xref></sup> Maybery et al. suggest ‘adult mental health services are a central point for interventions to stop the family cycle of mental illness’<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1039856212459583">9</xref></sup> (p.125). Moreover, the provision of preventive family interventions and psychoeducation with parents within adult mental health settings has demonstrated positive outcomes for children as well as improving parenting practices.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1039856212459583">10</xref></sup> Acknowledging and working with children has been shown to have positive impacts on family functioning and children’s understanding of parental mental illness, and decreased internalising problems for children.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1039856212459583">11</xref></sup></p>
<p>Historically, mental health services have been slow to respond to this need, with children of parents with mental illness often referred to as ‘hidden’.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1039856212459583">12</xref></sup> Barriers that may explain why these children remain ‘hidden’ include a lack of family- and child-friendly policies; limited clinician knowledge, skills and understanding of their role when working with families; and an inability to identify consumers who are parents.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1039856212459583">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1039856212459583">14</xref></sup> Confounding this, workers may be trained to work with parents or children but not both.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1039856212459583">11</xref></sup></p>
<p>Adequate identification of the number of parents and children affected by mental illness within a mental health service system is one mechanism to inform the need for service provision and to raise awareness of the need for a family-focused approach. Indeed, the 2009 Council of Australian Governments’ <italic>National Framework for Protecting Australia’s Children</italic> emphasises the need to increase the capacity and capability of adult services to identify and respond to the needs of children at risk.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1039856212459583">15</xref></sup> Moreover, highlighting to workers the numbers of parent clients has shown some effect in changing worker attitudes to become more family focussed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1039856212459583">13</xref></sup></p>
<p>Within Central Coast Mental Health Services (CCMHS) in NSW, Australia, clinical practice identifies individual parents through assessment and triage. However, the ability to gain a service-wide perspective of parents and their children and contextual data about this population has been limited. The Mental Health and Parenting Census (<italic>Census)</italic> was developed to address this limitation. The <italic>Census</italic> is an annual ‘snapshot’ of the parent client population, allowing CCMHS to examine issues regarding parental mental illness on a broader scale. This paper will describe the <italic>Census</italic> process, and compare and discuss <italic>Census</italic> results from 2008 to 2011. Implications for use of <italic>Census</italic> data will be discussed.</p>
<sec id="section5-1039856212459583" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="section6-1039856212459583">
<title>The Mental Health and Parenting Census</title>
<p>The <italic>Census</italic> is conducted annually across CCMHS. The <italic>Census</italic> identifies the prevalence of parenthood amongst active clients of CCMHS, gathering contextual data about these parents and their children.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1039856212459583">
<title>Data collection</title>
<p>Clinicians complete a <italic>Census</italic> form for each active client identified as a parent of child/children aged 0–17 years and/or pregnant. Data collected include demographic information, mental health status, parental contact and risk factors for children. A full description of the <italic>Census</italic> development and implementation has been outlined by the first author (DH);<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1039856212459583">16</xref></sup> a copy of the <italic>Census</italic> form is available on request.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1039856212459583">
<title>Sample</title>
<p>On <italic>Census</italic> day, all teams within CCMHS (five community mental health teams and four acute mental health inpatient units) complete <italic>Census</italic> forms for identified parent clients. The overall number of active clients for each clinician is also indicated on the <italic>Census</italic> form. This is used to determine the total number of active clients (parent and non-parent clients) across the service on <italic>Census</italic> day.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1039856212459583">
<title>Data analysis</title>
<p><italic>Census</italic> data are entered into Statistical Package for Social Science (SPSS) version 19 for Windows.</p>
</sec></sec>
<sec id="section10-1039856212459583" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Data from consecutive <italic>Census</italic> periods (2008–2011) are reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1039856212459583">Table 1</xref> and show the number of parents and children identified by the <italic>Census</italic> annually and the proportion of active clients of CCMHS who are parents.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1039856212459583" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>The number of parents and children across each <italic>Census</italic> period</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1039856212459583" xlink:href="10.1177_1039856212459583-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">2008</th>
<th align="left">2009</th>
<th align="left">2010</th>
<th align="left">2011</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Parents of children 0–17 years</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Reported by <italic>Census</italic> forms (<italic>n</italic>)</td>
<td>222</td>
<td>251</td>
<td>227</td>
<td>199</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Proportion of active clients who are parents (%)</td>
<td>28.2</td>
<td>28.1</td>
<td>25.3</td>
<td>26.3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5"><bold>Children of parents with a mental illness</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Total recorded by <italic>Census</italic> forms (<italic>n</italic>)</td>
<td>405</td>
<td>486</td>
<td>448</td>
<td>400</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></table-wrap>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1039856212459583">Table 2</xref> provides a snapshot of identified parents including gender, marital status, social support, mental health diagnosis, alcohol and other drug and domestic violence issues. The number of parents in the analysis is lower than reported in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1039856212459583">Table 1</xref>, as some <italic>Census</italic> forms were removed from analysis because the data were incomplete.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1039856212459583" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Demographic data and identified risk factors of parents</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1039856212459583" xlink:href="10.1177_1039856212459583-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="4" valign="top">Parental data</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">2008</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">2009</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">2010</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">2011</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th colspan="8"><hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="2">(<italic>n</italic>=211)<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">(<italic>n</italic>=246)<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">(<italic>n</italic>=227)<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">(<italic>n</italic>=199)<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="left">%</th>
<th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="left">%</th>
<th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="left">%</th>
<th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="left">%</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><bold>Demographics</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"> Gender</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Female</td>
<td>140</td>
<td><italic>(66.4)</italic></td>
<td>167</td>
<td><italic>(67.6)</italic></td>
<td>158</td>
<td><italic>(69.6)</italic></td>
<td>136</td>
<td><italic>(68.3)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Male</td>
<td>71</td>
<td><italic>(33.6)</italic></td>
<td>71</td>
<td><italic>(28.9)</italic></td>
<td>69</td>
<td><italic>(30.4)</italic></td>
<td>63</td>
<td><italic>(31.7)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Not specified</td>
<td>0</td>
<td><italic>(0.0)</italic></td>
<td>8</td>
<td><italic>(3.3)</italic></td>
<td>0</td>
<td><italic>(0)</italic></td>
<td>0</td>
<td><italic>(0)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"> Marital status</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Married/de facto</td>
<td>95</td>
<td><italic>(45.0)</italic></td>
<td>107</td>
<td><italic>(43.5)</italic></td>
<td>100</td>
<td><italic>(44.1)</italic></td>
<td>82</td>
<td><italic>(41.2)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Single</td>
<td>39</td>
<td><italic>(18.5)</italic></td>
<td>46</td>
<td><italic>(18.7)</italic></td>
<td>42</td>
<td><italic>(18.5)</italic></td>
<td>43</td>
<td><italic>(21.6)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Separated/divorced</td>
<td>72</td>
<td><italic>(34.1)</italic></td>
<td>81</td>
<td><italic>(33.0)</italic></td>
<td>70</td>
<td><italic>(30.8)</italic></td>
<td>72</td>
<td><italic>(36.2)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Widowed</td>
<td>0</td>
<td><italic>(0.0)</italic></td>
<td>5</td>
<td><italic>(2.0)</italic></td>
<td>3</td>
<td><italic>(1.3)</italic></td>
<td>0</td>
<td><italic>(0)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Not specified</td>
<td>5</td>
<td><italic>(2.4)</italic></td>
<td>7</td>
<td><italic>(2.8)</italic></td>
<td>12</td>
<td><italic>(5.3)</italic></td>
<td>2</td>
<td><italic>(1.0)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"> Ethnicity</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  CALD</td>
<td>10</td>
<td><italic>(4.7)</italic></td>
<td>6</td>
<td><italic>(2.4)</italic></td>
<td>10</td>
<td><italic>(4.4)</italic></td>
<td>4</td>
<td><italic>(2.0)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Indigenous</td>
<td>7</td>
<td><italic>(3.3)</italic></td>
<td>6</td>
<td><italic>(2.4)</italic></td>
<td>14</td>
<td><italic>(6.2)</italic></td>
<td>7</td>
<td><italic>(3.5)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Other</td>
<td>182</td>
<td><italic>(86.2)</italic></td>
<td>214</td>
<td><italic>(87.0)</italic></td>
<td>202</td>
<td><italic>(89.0)</italic></td>
<td>181</td>
<td><italic>(91.0)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Not specified</td>
<td>12</td>
<td><italic>(5.8)</italic></td>
<td>20</td>
<td><italic>(8.1)</italic></td>
<td>1</td>
<td><italic>(0.4)</italic></td>
<td>7</td>
<td><italic>(3.5)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"> Social support</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  None</td>
<td>10</td>
<td><italic>(4.7)</italic></td>
<td>14</td>
<td><italic>(5.7)</italic></td>
<td>7</td>
<td><italic>(3.1)</italic></td>
<td>9</td>
<td><italic>(4.5)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Minimal</td>
<td>91</td>
<td><italic>(43.1)</italic></td>
<td>110</td>
<td><italic>(44.7)</italic></td>
<td>87</td>
<td><italic>(38.3)</italic></td>
<td>95</td>
<td><italic>(47.8)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Good</td>
<td>100</td>
<td><italic>(47.7)</italic></td>
<td>108</td>
<td><italic>(43.9)</italic></td>
<td>120</td>
<td><italic>(52.9)</italic></td>
<td>90</td>
<td><italic>(45.2)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>  Not specified</td>
<td>10</td>
<td><italic>(4.3)</italic></td>
<td>14</td>
<td><italic>(5.7)</italic></td>
<td>13</td>
<td><italic>(5.7)</italic></td>
<td>5</td>
<td><italic>(2.5)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><bold>Diagnosis</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mood disorders</td>
<td>89</td>
<td><italic>(42.2)</italic></td>
<td>94</td>
<td><italic>(38.2)</italic></td>
<td>83</td>
<td><italic>(36.6)</italic></td>
<td>69</td>
<td><italic>(34.7)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Psychotic disorders</td>
<td>51</td>
<td><italic>(24.2)</italic></td>
<td>53</td>
<td><italic>(21.5)</italic></td>
<td>63</td>
<td><italic>(27.8)</italic></td>
<td>70</td>
<td><italic>(35.2)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Anxiety disorders</td>
<td>23</td>
<td><italic>(10.9)</italic></td>
<td>50</td>
<td><italic>(20.3)</italic></td>
<td>45</td>
<td><italic>(19.8)</italic></td>
<td>31</td>
<td><italic>(15.6)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Personality disorders</td>
<td>9</td>
<td><italic>(4.3)</italic></td>
<td>7</td>
<td><italic>(2.8)</italic></td>
<td>9</td>
<td><italic>(3.9)</italic></td>
<td>7</td>
<td><italic>(3.5)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Substance disorders</td>
<td>3</td>
<td><italic>(1.4)</italic></td>
<td>8</td>
<td><italic>(3.3)</italic></td>
<td>4</td>
<td><italic>(1.8)</italic></td>
<td>4</td>
<td><italic>(2.0)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Adjustment disorders</td>
<td>14</td>
<td><italic>(6.6)</italic></td>
<td>9</td>
<td><italic>(3.7)</italic></td>
<td>3</td>
<td><italic>(1.3)</italic></td>
<td>4</td>
<td><italic>(2.0)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>12</td>
<td><italic>(5.7)</italic></td>
<td>20</td>
<td><italic>(8.1)</italic></td>
<td>20</td>
<td><italic>(8.8)</italic></td>
<td>10</td>
<td><italic>(5.0)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Not specified</td>
<td>10</td>
<td><italic>(4.7)</italic></td>
<td>5</td>
<td><italic>(2.0)</italic></td>
<td>0</td>
<td><italic>(0)</italic></td>
<td>4</td>
<td><italic>(2.0)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><bold>DV</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Current</td>
<td>11</td>
<td><italic>(5.2)</italic></td>
<td>16</td>
<td><italic>(6.5)</italic></td>
<td>5</td>
<td><italic>(2.2)</italic></td>
<td>19</td>
<td><italic>(9.5)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Past</td>
<td>65</td>
<td><italic>(30.8)</italic></td>
<td>97</td>
<td><italic>(39.4)</italic></td>
<td>89</td>
<td><italic>(39.2)</italic></td>
<td>55</td>
<td><italic>(27.6)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> None</td>
<td>17</td>
<td><italic>(8.1)</italic></td>
<td>82</td>
<td><italic>(33.3)</italic></td>
<td>78</td>
<td><italic>(34.4)</italic></td>
<td>65</td>
<td><italic>(32.7)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Unknown</td>
<td>106</td>
<td><italic>(50.2)</italic></td>
<td>36</td>
<td><italic>(14.6)</italic></td>
<td>49</td>
<td><italic>(21.6)</italic></td>
<td>57</td>
<td><italic>(28.6)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Not specified</td>
<td>12</td>
<td><italic>(5.7)</italic></td>
<td>15</td>
<td><italic>(6.1)</italic></td>
<td>6</td>
<td><italic>(2.6)</italic></td>
<td>3</td>
<td><italic>(1.5)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><bold>AOD issues</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yes (current)</td>
<td>78</td>
<td><italic>(37.0)</italic></td>
<td>52</td>
<td><italic>(21.1)</italic></td>
<td>39</td>
<td><italic>(17.2)</italic></td>
<td>45</td>
<td><italic>(22.6)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No (none)</td>
<td>123</td>
<td><italic>(58.3)</italic></td>
<td>97</td>
<td><italic>(39.5)</italic></td>
<td>92</td>
<td><italic>(40.5)</italic></td>
<td>95</td>
<td><italic>(47.8)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Past</td>
<td>0</td>
<td><italic>(0.0)</italic></td>
<td>74</td>
<td><italic>(30.1)</italic></td>
<td>89</td>
<td><italic>(39.2)</italic></td>
<td>52</td>
<td><italic>(26.1)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Not specified</td>
<td>10</td>
<td><italic>(4.7)</italic></td>
<td>23</td>
<td><italic>(9.3)</italic></td>
<td>7</td>
<td><italic>(3.1)</italic></td>
<td>7</td>
<td><italic>(3.5)</italic></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1039856212459583">
<p>CALD: culturally and linguistically diverse; DV: domestic violence; AOD: alcohol and other drugs.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1039856212459583">Table 3</xref> provides a snapshot of children identified through the <italic>Census</italic>. Data reported on includes age, parental contact, Community Services involvement and proportion of children residing permanently with a parent experiencing current domestic violence (DV) and/or alcohol and other drug (AOD) issues. Of children permanently residing with their parent, 11.7–31.9% reside with a parent experiencing current AOD issues, and 1.1–13.3% reside with a parent experiencing current DV.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1039856212459583" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Demographic data and risk factors for children</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1039856212459583" xlink:href="10.1177_1039856212459583-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="5" valign="top">Child data</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">2008</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">2009</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">2010</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">2011</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th colspan="8"><hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="2">(<italic>n</italic>=405)</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">(<italic>n</italic>=486)</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">(<italic>n</italic>=448)</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">(<italic>n</italic>=400)</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th colspan="8"><hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="left">(%)</th>
<th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="left">(%)</th>
<th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="left">(%)</th>
<th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th>
<th align="left">(%)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><bold>Ages</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0–5 years</td>
<td>132</td>
<td><italic>(32.6)</italic></td>
<td>134</td>
<td><italic>(27.5)</italic></td>
<td>131</td>
<td><italic>(29.2)</italic></td>
<td>113</td>
<td><italic>(28.25)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6–11 years</td>
<td>146</td>
<td><italic>(36.0)</italic></td>
<td>180</td>
<td><italic>(37.0)</italic></td>
<td>143</td>
<td><italic>(31.9)</italic></td>
<td>126</td>
<td><italic>(31.5)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12–17 years</td>
<td>123</td>
<td><italic>(30.4)</italic></td>
<td>166</td>
<td><italic>(34.2)</italic></td>
<td>170</td>
<td><italic>(37.9)</italic></td>
<td>140</td>
<td><italic>(35.0)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Not specified</td>
<td>4</td>
<td><italic>(1.0)</italic></td>
<td>6</td>
<td><italic>(1.2)</italic></td>
<td>4</td>
<td><italic>(0.9)</italic></td>
<td>21</td>
<td><italic>(5.25)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><bold>Parental contact</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Permanent</td>
<td>235</td>
<td><italic>(58.0)</italic></td>
<td>291</td>
<td><italic>(59.9)</italic></td>
<td>273</td>
<td><italic>(60.9)</italic></td>
<td>232</td>
<td><italic>(58.0)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Substantial</td>
<td>33</td>
<td><italic>(8.1)</italic></td>
<td>43</td>
<td><italic>(8.8)</italic></td>
<td>32</td>
<td><italic>(7.1)</italic></td>
<td>32</td>
<td><italic>(8.0)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Minimal</td>
<td>97</td>
<td><italic>(23.9)</italic></td>
<td>103</td>
<td><italic>(21.2)</italic></td>
<td>95</td>
<td><italic>(21.2)</italic></td>
<td>97</td>
<td><italic>(24.3)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>None</td>
<td>34</td>
<td><italic>(8.4)</italic></td>
<td>43</td>
<td><italic>(8.8)</italic></td>
<td>47</td>
<td><italic>(10.5)</italic></td>
<td>33</td>
<td><italic>(8.3)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Not specified</td>
<td>6</td>
<td><italic>(1.5)</italic></td>
<td>6</td>
<td><italic>(1.2)</italic></td>
<td>1</td>
<td><italic>(0.2)</italic></td>
<td>6</td>
<td><italic>(1.5)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><bold>Exposure to AOD</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Children permanently reside with parent with: current issue</td>
<td>75</td>
<td><italic>(31.9)</italic></td>
<td>38</td>
<td><italic>(13.0)</italic></td>
<td>32</td>
<td><italic>(11.7)</italic></td>
<td>32</td>
<td><italic>(13.8)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>past issue<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn2-1039856212459583">*</xref></td>
<td>—</td>
<td>—</td>
<td>79</td>
<td><italic>(37.1)</italic></td>
<td>105</td>
<td><italic>(38.5)</italic></td>
<td>65</td>
<td><italic>(28.0)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><bold>Exposure to DV</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Children permanently residing with parent with: current issue</td>
<td>14</td>
<td><italic>(5.9)</italic></td>
<td>25</td>
<td><italic>(8.5)</italic></td>
<td>3</td>
<td><italic>(1.1)</italic></td>
<td>31</td>
<td><italic>(13.3)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>past issues</td>
<td>85</td>
<td><italic>(36.0)</italic></td>
<td>114</td>
<td><italic>(39.1)</italic></td>
<td>100</td>
<td><italic>(36.6)</italic></td>
<td>83</td>
<td><italic>(35.9)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><bold>Exposure to AOD and DV</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Children permanently residing with parent</td>
<td>7</td>
<td><italic>(3.0)</italic></td>
<td>10</td>
<td><italic>(3.4)</italic></td>
<td>0</td>
<td><italic>(0)</italic></td>
<td>7</td>
<td><italic>(3.0)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="9"><bold>Community services involvement</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Current</td>
<td>66</td>
<td><italic>(16.2)</italic></td>
<td>91</td>
<td><italic>(18.7)</italic></td>
<td>103</td>
<td><italic>(23.0)</italic></td>
<td>71</td>
<td><italic>(17.8)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Previous</td>
<td>78</td>
<td><italic>(19.3)</italic></td>
<td>100</td>
<td><italic>(20.6)</italic></td>
<td>61</td>
<td><italic>(13.6)</italic></td>
<td>39</td>
<td><italic>(9.8)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>None</td>
<td>162</td>
<td><italic>(40.0)</italic></td>
<td>214</td>
<td><italic>(44.0)</italic></td>
<td>192</td>
<td><italic>(42.9)</italic></td>
<td>158</td>
<td><italic>(39.5)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Unknown</td>
<td>97</td>
<td><italic>(24.0)</italic></td>
<td>54</td>
<td><italic>(11.1)</italic></td>
<td>68</td>
<td><italic>(15.2)</italic></td>
<td>117</td>
<td><italic>(29.3)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Not specified</td>
<td>2</td>
<td><italic>(0.5)</italic></td>
<td>27</td>
<td><italic>(5.5)</italic></td>
<td>24</td>
<td><italic>(5.4)</italic></td>
<td>15</td>
<td><italic>(3.8)</italic></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1039856212459583">
<p>AOD: alcohol and other drugs; DV: domestic violence. <bold>*</bold> Past AOD issues are not included for 2008, as the response options at that time were ‘yes’ and ‘no’ only.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1039856212459583">Table 4</xref> shows the number of children of a parent with a particular diagnosis and the proportion of these children who reside with their parent on a permanent or substantial basis. Consecutive <italic>Census</italic> results suggest a relationship between parental diagnosis and contact. Children are more likely to reside on a permanent or substantial basis with a parent who has a mood or anxiety disorder than with a parent who has a psychotic disorder or a personality disorder.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-1039856212459583" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Number of children by parental diagnosis and proportion who reside with parent on a permanent or substantial basis</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1039856212459583" xlink:href="10.1177_1039856212459583-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left" rowspan="4" valign="top">Parental diagnosis class</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">2008</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">2009</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">2010</th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">2011</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th colspan="8"><hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left" colspan="2">(<italic>n</italic>=405)<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">(<italic>n</italic>=486)<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">(<italic>n</italic>=448)<hr/></th>
<th align="left" colspan="2">(<italic>n</italic>=400)<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th align="left">Total children</th>
<th align="left">% Residence</th>
<th align="left">Total children</th>
<th align="left">% Residence</th>
<th align="left">Total children</th>
<th align="left">% Residence</th>
<th align="left">Total children</th>
<th align="left">% Residence</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Psychotic disorders</td>
<td><italic>87</italic></td>
<td><italic>(41.4)</italic></td>
<td>103</td>
<td><italic>(34.0)</italic></td>
<td>117</td>
<td><italic>(56.4)</italic></td>
<td>142</td>
<td><italic>(51.4)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mood disorders</td>
<td>179</td>
<td><italic>(75.4)</italic></td>
<td>190</td>
<td><italic>(83.2)</italic></td>
<td>167</td>
<td><italic>(74.3)</italic></td>
<td>142</td>
<td><italic>(83.8)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Anxiety disorders</td>
<td>57</td>
<td><italic>(87.7)</italic></td>
<td>96</td>
<td><italic>(75.0)</italic></td>
<td>90</td>
<td><italic>(85.5)</italic></td>
<td>56</td>
<td><italic>(75.0)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Personality disorders</td>
<td>15</td>
<td><italic>(33.4)</italic></td>
<td>13</td>
<td><italic>(53.9)</italic></td>
<td>24</td>
<td><italic>(20.8)</italic></td>
<td>13</td>
<td><italic>(46.2)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Substance use disorders</td>
<td>4</td>
<td><italic>(50.0)</italic></td>
<td>12</td>
<td><italic>(50.0)</italic></td>
<td>7</td>
<td><italic>(42.9)</italic></td>
<td>6</td>
<td><italic>(50.0)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Adjustment disorders</td>
<td>26</td>
<td><italic>(73.1)</italic></td>
<td>19</td>
<td><italic>(84.2)</italic></td>
<td>8</td>
<td><italic>(25.0)</italic></td>
<td>13</td>
<td><italic>(69.2)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Other</td>
<td>16</td>
<td><italic>(43.8)</italic></td>
<td>44</td>
<td><italic>(72.7)</italic></td>
<td>35</td>
<td><italic>(82.8)</italic></td>
<td>22</td>
<td><italic>(54.5)</italic></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Not specified</td>
<td>0</td>
<td><italic>(0)</italic></td>
<td>0</td>
<td><italic>(0)</italic></td>
<td>0</td>
<td><italic>(0)</italic></td>
<td>6</td>
<td><italic>(0)</italic></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1039856212459583" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The <italic>Census</italic> is an effective and accurate process for generating prevalence data regarding the number of parent clients (of children 0–17 years) within a mental health service system. The findings show that in any one year 25–28% of active mental health service clients are parents of no fewer than 400 children aged 0–17 years. Moreover, approximately 60% of these children reside permanently with their parent. This finding is consistent with evidence from other community mental health settings which report 57% of minor children live with a parent with mental illness.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1039856212459583">17</xref></sup></p>
<p>The <italic>Census</italic> provides important contextual information about these families. Consecutive data indicate a relationship between parental diagnosis and parental contact. Although children of a parent with a psychotic disorder are less likely to reside permanently with them, our results demonstrate that 34–56% of these children permanently reside with their parent. This dispels the often-held myth that children do not reside with a parent with a serious mental illness.</p>
<p>An indication of the levels of risk and vulnerability for these families is also captured by the <italic>Census.</italic> The proportion of children residing with parents with current or past DV and/or AOD issues has been determined. Modifications to the response options for these variables may explain some of the larger variances seen. It will be interesting to note how this data evolves in future years. Furthermore, 28–39% of children had current or previous Community Services involvement, demonstrating that vulnerabilities within these families are regularly identified and acted on.</p>
<sec id="section12-1039856212459583">
<title>Future directions</title>
<p>The <italic>Census</italic> data can inform service planning and capacity-building initiatives that strengthen CCMHS response to future needs. An evaluation of the national COPMI web-based training resource ‘Keeping families and children in mind’ reported changes in knowledge, skills and confidence, and heightened awareness of the need to work with families and children for mental health clinicians.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1039856212459583">18</xref></sup> CCMHS COPMI coordinators facilitate workshops for clinicians utilising this resource. To strengthen service capacity, an information kit for families has been developed. A clinical tools and tips guide is also available to support mental health clinicians to identify and respond to parenting issues. Additionally, the development of partnerships with non-government agencies to implement programs such as SMILES (The Simplifying Mental Illness and Life Enhancement Skills Program), which enhances coping skills for children living in a family with mental illness,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1039856212459583">19</xref></sup> will also address COPMI needs.</p>
<p><italic>Census</italic> results highlight the need for a more strategic and systematic approach to addressing COPMI issues across the area. Subsequently, the CCMHS COPMI implementation committee will oversee COPMI initiatives across CCMHS and address state priorities as identified in <italic>NSW Children of Parents with a Mental Illness (COPMI): Framework for Mental Health Services 2010–2015</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1039856212459583">20</xref></sup> <italic>Census</italic> data has informed the pilot enhancements to the CCMHS electronic database to record COPMI service milestones and outcomes.</p>
<p>A file audit project to determine consistency of <italic>Census</italic> data compared to that reported in client medical records (completed in 2010) demonstrated the <italic>Census</italic> has some limitations. A complete discussion of these findings is beyond the scope of this paper. However, some inconsistencies were noted. Although higher levels of consistency were seen relating to basic demographic variables, less consistency was seen relating to risk variables. This may reflect how information is documented within medical records, the accessibility of this information for clinicians or the complexity of assessing risk.</p>
<p>Within CCMHS, the <italic>Census</italic> has increased awareness of mental health and parenting issues. Additionally, the <italic>Census</italic> has provided opportunities to consider service planning based on need and has informed the development of CCMHS services, including the Whole Family Team and Perinatal Infant Mental Health Team. It is envisaged that the <italic>Census</italic> data can further inform the development of initiatives to support parents and children into the future.</p>
</sec></sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Disclosure</label>
<p>The authors report no conflict of interest. The authors alone are responsible for the contentand writing of this paper.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1039856212459583">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maybery</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reupert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Workforce capacity to respond to children whose parents have a mental illness</article-title>. <source>Aust N Z J Psychiatry</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>657</fpage>–<lpage>664</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1039856212459583">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Silberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Connor</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genetics and child psychiatry: II Empirical research findings</article-title>. <source>J Child Psychol Psychiatry</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1039856212459583">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reupert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maybery</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Families affected by parental mental illness: A multiperspective account of issues and interventions</article-title>. <source>Am J Orthopsychiatry</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>362</fpage>–<lpage>369</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1039856212459583">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huntsman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Literature Review – Parents with mental health issues: Consequences for children and effectiveness of interventions designed to assist children and their families</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Ashfield</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Centre for Parenting &amp; Research, Service System Development and Division, NSW Department of Community Services</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1039856212459583">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Allen-Meares</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blazevski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bybee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Independent effects of paternal involvement and maternal mental illness on child outcomes</article-title>. <source>Social Service Review</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>127</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1039856212459583">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>‘You’d think this roller coaster was never going to stop’: Experiences of adult children of parents with serious mental illness</article-title>. <source>J Clin Nurs</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>3143</fpage>–<lpage>3151</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1039856212459583">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mowbray</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bybee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oyserman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Psychosocial outcomes for adult children of parents with severe mental illnesses: Demographic and clinical history predictors</article-title>. <source>Health Soc Work</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>108</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1039856212459583">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Siegenthaler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Munder</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of preventive interventions in mentally ill parents on the mental health of the offspring: Systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source> <year>2012</year>; <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>8</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1039856212459583">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maybery</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goodyear</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reupert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The family-focused mental health practice questionnaire</article-title>. <source>Arch Psychiatr Nurs</source> <year>2012</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>144</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1039856212459583">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Solantus</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paavonen</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Toikka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Preventive interventions in families with parental depression: Children’s psychosocial symptoms and prosocial behaviour</article-title>. <source>Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>883</fpage>–<lpage>892</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1039856212459583">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bearslee</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gladstone</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term effects from a randomized trial of two public health preventive interventions for parental depression</article-title>. <source>J Fam Psychol</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>703</fpage>–<lpage>713</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1039856212459583">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fudge</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Consulting with young people about service guidelines relating to parental mental illness</article-title>. <source>Australian e-Journal for the Advancement of Mental Health</source> <year>2004</year>; <fpage>3</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1039856212459583">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maybery</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reupert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Parental mental illness: A review of barriers and issues for working with families and children</article-title>. <source>J Psychiatr Mentl Health Nurs</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>784</fpage>–<lpage>791</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1039856212459583">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Brien</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Korhonen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Developing resilient children and families when parents have mental illness: A family-focused approach</article-title>. <source>Int J Ment Health Nurs</source> <year>2012</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1039856212459583">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="gov"><collab>Commonwealth of Australia (COA)</collab>. <article-title>Protecting Children is Everyone’s Business: National Framework for Protecting Australia’s Children 2009–2020 — An initiative of the Council of Australian Governments</article-title>, <year>2009</year>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fahcsia.gov.au/sites/default/files/documents/child_protection_framework.pdf">http://www.fahcsia.gov.au/sites/default/files/documents/child_protection_framework.pdf</ext-link> (<year>2009</year>, <access-date>accessed 20 August 2009</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1039856212459583">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Batchelor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bochynska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Estimating consumer parenthood within mental health services: A census approach</article-title>. <source>Australian e-Journal for the Advancement of Mental Health</source> <year>2009</year>; <fpage>8</fpage>: <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>241</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1039856212459583">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ahern</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>At-risk children: A demographic analysis of the children of clients attending mental health community clinics</article-title>. <source>Int J Ment Health Nurs</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>228</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1039856212459583">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reupert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maybery</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>‘Keeping families and children in mind’: An evaluation of a web-based workforce resource</article-title>. <source>Child &amp; Family Social Work</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>192</fpage>–<lpage>200</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1039856212459583">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pitman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matthey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The SMILES program: A group program for children with mentally ill parents or siblings</article-title>. <source>Am J Orthopsychiatry</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>383</fpage>–<lpage>388</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1039856212459583">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="gov"><collab>NSW Health</collab>. <article-title>NSW Children of Parents with a Mental Illness (COPMI): Framework for Mental Health Services 2010–2015</article-title>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.health.nsw.gov.au/policies/pd/2010/pdf/PD2010_037.pdf">http://www.health.nsw.gov.au/policies/pd/2010/pdf/PD2010_037.pdf</ext-link> (<year>2010</year>, <access-date>accessed 13 April 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref></ref-list>
</back>
</article>