<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CTJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spctj</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Trials</journal-id>
<journal-title>Clinical Trials</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1740-7745</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1740-7753</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1740774512465496</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1740774512465496</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Data Management and Trial Conduct</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Using scratch card technology for random allocation concealment in a clinical trial with a crossover design</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Beksinska</surname><given-names>Mags E</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1740774512465496">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1740774512465496">b</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Joanis</surname><given-names>Carol</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1740774512465496">c</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Smit</surname><given-names>Jenni A</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1740774512465496">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Pienaar</surname><given-names>Jacqueline</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1740774512465496">a</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Piaggio</surname><given-names>Gilda</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-1740774512465496">d</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1740774512465496"><label>a</label>MatCH (Maternal, Adolescent and Child Health), Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Faculty of Health Sciences, University of the Witwatersrand, Durban, South Africa</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1740774512465496"><label>b</label>Faculty of Epidemiology and Public Health, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, London, UK</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1740774512465496"><label>c</label>Joanis Consulting, Kennesaw, GA, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff4-1740774512465496"><label>d</label>Department of Medical Statistics, Faculty of Epidemiology and Public Health, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, London, UK</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1740774512465496">Mags E Beksinska, MatCH (Maternal, Adolescent and Child Health), Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Faculty of Health Sciences, University of the Witwatersrand, 151 Juniper Road, Overport, Durban 4091, South Africa. Email: <email>mbeksinska@match.org.za</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>2</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>125</fpage>
<lpage>130</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s), 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">The Society for Clinical Trials</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-1740774512465496">
<title>Background</title>
<p>To avoid selection bias in clinical trials, random allocation concealment is crucial to ensure that participants and or researchers remain unaware of assignments.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1740774512465496">
<title>Purpose</title>
<p>We aimed to design an allocation concealment method that reduced the possibility of selection bias for a randomized, open-label, crossover trial to evaluate device function of four female condom (FC) types.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1740774512465496">
<title>Methods</title>
<p>Using scratch card technology, we devised a simple method of concealment, whereby the treatment sequence was printed on a single card for each participant, and the codes for each treatment in the sequence were concealed beneath foil squares on a stiff A6-sized card. On the first and subsequent follow-up visits, the foil corresponding to that visit was scratched from the square to reveal the condom type allocation for the next condom-use period. Staff in the South African and Chinese trial sites were trained in use and care of the card, and on completion of the study completed a questionnaire on their experience of use.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1740774512465496">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Research staff in both countries found the card easy to use and those who had previously used the sequentially numbered, opaque, sealed envelopes (SNOSE) system for random allocation reported the scratch card easier to use. Research staff most commonly used a coin to remove the foil square and some used their fingernails. In both South Africa and China, no errors in allocation sequence were found during study monitoring.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1740774512465496">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>Scratch card system of allocation cannot be printed in-house.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1740774512465496">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>This novel, effective method of concealment for a crossover random allocation was well liked by study staff. The most important advantage of this method is the ability to conceal consecutive allocations of a crossover design using a single card, thus eliminating the need for multiple envelopes per participant. While we used this method in a clinical trial of FCs, it could be employed in a range of other clinical trials and other randomized studies.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section7-1740774512465496">
<title>Background</title>
<p>Random allocation concealment to ensure that researchers and participants remain unaware of assignments is crucial in clinical trials, to avoid bias [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1740774512465496">1</xref>]. The preferred method is central randomization, for security reasons, but in many settings, its use is not feasible. Sequentially numbered, opaque, sealed envelopes (SNOSE) is one of the most commonly used methods to achieve proper concealment in these settings. The use of the SNOSE system is both inexpensive and effective; however, it has drawbacks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1740774512465496">2</xref>]. For instance, there is nothing to prevent investigators from opening an unassigned envelope until the desired treatment is found for a particular subject, a definite risk in placebo-controlled trials. In the case of a crossover trial, if all assignments for a participant are printed in a single envelope, the entire assigned sequence for that participant will be revealed once the envelope is opened. In order to prevent bias, it is preferable to reveal only the next treatment in the sequence and conceal the following. However, this would require a number of envelopes per participant equal to the number of arms, thus increasing the total number of envelopes required. Such an approach increases the potential for randomization errors through misallocation or loss of envelopes.</p>
<p>In our randomized crossover trial, participants were asked to use four different female condom (FC) types (treatments) over a period of approximately 3 months. In designing the scratch card, our aim was to conceal each condom type allocation from the study staff and participants until needed, and to eliminate the requirement for four separate envelopes per participant.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1740774512465496" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="section9-1740774512465496">
<title>Overview of the study</title>
<p>This was a randomized comparative crossover trial to evaluate device function, safety, and acceptability of three new and one currently marketed FC types, including the Woman’s Condom (WC), FC2, VA w.o.w., and Cupid. The trial could not be blinded as all four condom designs are quite distinct and each required product-specific training for correct use. The target population was 600 urban, sexually active women in two countries who were either novice or experienced users of FCs. Each woman was asked to use five each of the four FC types. In South Africa, women were recruited from a large urban reproductive health service clinic in Durban (n = 300). In China, women were recruited from the Shanghai Institute of Planned Parenthood Research (SIPPR) Hospital (n = 30) and two affiliated family planning (FP) districts: Xujiahui (n = 120) and Xuhui (n = 150) in Shanghai, China. Primary endpoints were total clinical failure and total device failure for each condom type. Secondary endpoints included rates of invagination, complete slippage, misdirection, and breakage. Safety and acceptability data were also collected.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1740774512465496">
<title>Randomization</title>
<p>For the trial described above, a randomization sequence for the crossover design stratified by site was generated for 600 eligible women, randomizing women to condom type order within site in four sites (30, 120, and 150 women in the 3 sites in China, and 300 women in one site in South Africa). A Williams design was used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1740774512465496">3</xref>], which consists of the random construction of a Williams square (first step) and the random assignment of the treatment sequences to the women (second step). Balance was maintained across sequences (i.e., equal numbers of women were randomized to each of the four sequences). These sequences are balanced for period and treatment, and each treatment has a different preceding treatment. To ensure such balance, block randomization was used.</p>
<p>A statistical programmer (not otherwise involved in this study) developed the random allocation sequence, using a validated statistical program [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1740774512465496">4</xref>] in SAS<sup>®</sup> Software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1740774512465496">5</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1740774512465496">
<title>Development of the scratch card concept and design</title>
<p>In order to devise a simple and effective method of concealment, we designed a scratch card per participant, containing the allocated treatment sequence, where each code for a given condom type was concealed beneath a separate foil square. In the case of our research the following one-letter codes were used to denote each condom type: WC denoted as W, FC2 denoted as F, VA w.o.w. denoted as V, and Cupid denoted as C. On the first and subsequent follow-up visits, research staff would remove (scratch) the foil from the undisclosed square according to the visit number printed above the square, thereby revealing the next visit allocation in the sequence. A review of the literature in allocation concealment revealed no reports of previous use of scratch card methodology for random allocation concealment in clinical trials with a crossover design.</p>
<p>Initially, it was difficult to identify a company prepared to, or with the capacity to, undertake this task. Typically, scratch card manufacturers work on printing hundreds of thousands or in some cases millions of cards per print run, in particular for national lottery requirements. Our study sample size was 600 participants, and most companies were unable to consider such a small print run. In addition, each card was unique and required printing with a specific randomization code sequence, an individual study participant identification number (PIN), one of four different site numbers, and four visit number designations. Other features key in the design were a need to minimize the potential for the research staff to scratch off the foil from the neighboring square, that the card was not likely to be torn or damaged through handling, and that the foil would completely obscure the code to minimize tampering.</p>
<p>After considerable investigation, we found a small enterprise specializing in scratch card games manufacture, with local and international experience and interested in working with us to design a concealment card that would suit our requirements. With their assistance, we designed a card to be assigned to a participant according to the randomization sequence from the crossover design. Each participant would have a single card, where the codes for each treatment in the sequence would be concealed beneath foil squares on a stiff A6-sized card. Each of the four squares was separated by over a centimeter to minimize the potential for removing the foil from the neighboring square. The selected card was 105 mm × 148 mm in size and made of stiff card stock (300 g/m<sup>2</sup> art board quality)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1740774512465496">*</xref></sup> and unlike some SNOSE envelopes, the printing is not visible when the card is held to a light source. The final design of the randomization card can be seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1740774512465496">Figure 1</xref></p>
<fig id="fig1-1740774512465496" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Randomization card with four foil squares, each concealing a study visit assignment code.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1740774512465496-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>To ensure that the cards would be protected from inadvertent damage, we purchased thin, resealable plastic sleeve covers similar to those used for standard greeting cards. In South Africa, during the study, the randomization cards were kept in a locked cabinet at the Maternal, Adolescent, and Child Health (MatCH) research offices. They were stored in six batches of 50 cards in use order. At the start of the study, the first batch of 50 cards were signed out of the research office and taken to the research site, checked, and signed in. Assignment of cards was monitored so that the next batch was delivered just prior to the assignment of all 50 of the batch of current cards at the site. On completion of allocation, the cards were kept in the plastic covers in the participant files. In China, the cards were divided according to the assigned research site. At each research site, participant notebooks were assembled and the randomization card corresponding to a given participant was placed in the notebook in a protective document sleeve cover. The cards were contained in the participants’ notebooks for the duration of the study and removed only during participant visits. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1740774512465496">Figure 2</xref> shows the condom type code allocation once a foil is removed from one allocation.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1740774512465496" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Randomization scratch card with code revealed for first assignment.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1740774512465496-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1740774512465496">
<title>Card production and verification procedure</title>
<p>We worked closely with the manufacturer of the card to build in quality assurance (QA) checks during the setup and printing processes. The details of the cards, including PIN, site number, and allocation codes, were provided in an Excel spreadsheet by the statistical programmer who generated the allocation sequence, and the cards were printed directly from this file. During the typical printing process of scratch cards used for prize draws and lotteries, some cards are damaged during the print run. This wastage occurs in about 1% of the cards printed and usually happens when the foil is damaged or does not adequately cover the hidden item (e.g., code, number, picture) on the card. It was anticipated that the wastage rate may be higher in line with our more complex production requirements. As such, a second identical set of cards was printed concurrently so that any unusable card could be replaced. This was a more cost-effective approach since the reprint of a handful of cards on a one-by-one basis was as costly as multiple print runs. As a final check to ensure that the correct allocation was printed on each card, a third unfoiled set (codes visible) was printed to allow confirmation with the randomization list by an independent person. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1740774512465496">Figure 3</xref> shows an example of a unfoiled card (not one of the real study allocation code sequences). The final print run consisted of printing each card in triplicate (original, duplicate, and unfoiled). The cost of printing 600 original cards, duplicates, and unfoiled sets in 2011 was £2000.00 (approximately US$3240). The authors attempted to contact several research groups to ascertain the cost for a similar sized study using SNOSE. Most organizations complete the SNOSE process internally with different staff running randomization lists, printing the list on the special paper within the opaque envelopes and dealing with the administration of the envelopes. They were unable to disaggregate the cost of the process from broader project costs.</p>
<fig id="fig3-1740774512465496" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>An example of an unfoiled randomization scratch card.</p>
<p>W: Woman’s Condom; F: FC2; V: VA w.o.w.; C: Cupid.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1740774512465496-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>An internal monitor checked the cards on a regular basis to ensure that only the correct squares had been revealed and that cards remained in their protective sleeves and were filed correctly. Internal QA was verified by external, independent monitoring of the appropriate use of the scratch cards. Research staff gave feedback on use of the cards during study site training and after use of the cards during the trial.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1740774512465496" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="section14-1740774512465496">
<title>Card performance in the trial setting</title>
<p>A total of 116 cards in the first set of 600 had imperfections in the foil squares. The majority of flaws was small and did not reveal the hidden allocation code. These were, however, replaced from the duplicate foiled set resulting in a wastage rate of 19.3%. The set of unfoiled cards was checked against the randomization list by a research administrator not connected with the study, and no errors were found. During the study training, the staff were shown mock-up pictures of the card and allowed to see a card with foil intact. A brief questionnaire was compiled for interviewers to complete at the end of the study to document their experience with the use of the cards during the study.</p>
<sec id="section15-1740774512465496">
<title>Experience at the South African site</title>
<p>The South African research staff had previous experience with use of scratch cards in the lottery/prize context, and the cards were well received during the training. Both interviewers had previously experienced use of the SNOSE system for randomization in a behavioral trial. Both research staff completed the questionnaire on their experience of scratch card use. During the trial, a coin was used to remove the foil, and this was done in front of the participants. They reported that the cards were ‘very easy to use’. Feedback from research staff indicated that the participants were generally surprised and intrigued by the randomization process, and comments were often related to winning something in the typical scratch card prize scenario, ‘is this the lotto or something?’ – a typical comment from a participant. Others were interested in what condom type they might get next, ‘I am curious to see what the type will be’. Monitoring during the trial found no instances where the foil was accidentally removed from a part or all of the adjoining square, and no allocation mistakes were found in South Africa.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1740774512465496">
<title>Experience at the China site</title>
<p>Research staff in China reported that they had no previous experience with lottery/prize scratch cards and that they had no previous experience in the use of SNOSE. A total of 11 research staff completed the questionnaire and all said that the scratch card method was easy or very easy to use. Almost all used a coin or a fingernail to remove the foil. The research staff reported that the participants were curious to know which product they would receive next when the foil was removed. During monitoring, in four cases (two sites and two research staff), the foil had been removed from the next allocation on the card; however, the sequence of condoms used was correct in these four cases. In all four instances, the second square had been removed at the same time, and this occurred within the recruitment of the first five participants at each of the two sites involved. This was attributed to human error resulting from the use of a novel technology. It was not clear whether the participant saw the next code. Past use of FCs was nonexistent in the Chinese participants, and they were trained on only one condom at each visit and were not shown the other condoms. No other allocation mistakes were found in China.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-1740774512465496" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Randomization of participants to treatments prevents selection bias in clinical trials. However, producing an unpredictable allocation sequence is not enough to protect the trial against bias. If the treatment allocation sequence is known to the person assigning the treatment or to the participant receiving it, treatment order could be changed due to prior beliefs or preference [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1740774512465496">2</xref>]. In particular, for this crossover trial, if the sequence of treatment allocations became known to the participant, and she had a preference for one particular type of FC, she could have requested the interviewer to alter the sequence determined by randomization or to skip use of a particular condom type. Therefore, the randomization sequence had to be protected by concealing it as much as possible. The design of the scratch cards fulfilled this purpose.</p>
<p>This method requires minimal QA and easily conforms to requirements in terms of good clinical practice (GCP) and statistical QA, since it lends itself to easy verification of quality parameters in randomization sequencing. This method can easily be checked to verify correct PIN per participants enrolled, and order of randomization in accordance with their progress in the study.</p>
<p>The main challenge was sourcing a company equipped to undertake the card development, otherwise the final process was straightforward, and we would recommend its use. If this method was used again we would consider not printing the unfoiled set as we would be confident that the manufacturers had printed the correct sequence from the spreadsheet as no errors were found in the crosscheck. Thewastage during printing is unavoidable, so this method would always require the printing of individual replacements or a duplicate set as was done in this study. This novel method of concealment for a crossover random allocation was well liked and correctly used by research staff. The advantages of this method include the ability to conceal consecutive allocations of a crossover trial on one card, the robustness of the cards, and dispensing with the need for and the problems associated with the use of multiple envelopes per participant.</p>
<p>This method could be employed in any research study requiring randomization, including both qualitative and quantitative research, clinical trials, and behavioral studies. In particular, it has the advantage of blinding both the researcher and the participant to the next allocation. This would be particularly useful method where there are more than two allocations as all allocations can be printed on one card. In the case of SNOSE, if all assignments for a participant are printed in a single envelope, the entire assigned sequence for a given participant is revealed once the envelope is opened. To conceal the next allocation code using SNOSE, each code would have to be concealed in individual envelopes in a manner that ensured each envelope was opened in the correct sequence. In this trial of four allocations, it ensured that research staff presented no hint or bias to the next FC assigned.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This work was supported by (a) William and Flora Hewlett Foundation and (b) Universal Access to Female Condoms Joint Programme (UAFC).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Conflict of interest</label>
<p>None declared.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1740774512465496">
<label>*</label>
<p>The unit g/m<sup>2</sup> or gsm is the weight by surface area and is used to describe weight of paper.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1740774512465496">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chalmers</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Empirical evidence of bias: Dimensions of methodological quality associated with estimates of treatment effects in controlled trials</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source> <year>1995</year>; <volume>273</volume>: <fpage>408</fpage>–<lpage>12</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1740774512465496">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Allocation concealment in randomized trials: Defending against deciphering</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>359</volume>: <fpage>614</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1740774512465496">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Experimental designs balanced for the estimation of residual effects of treatments</article-title>. <source>Aust J Sci Res Ser A</source> <year>1949</year>; <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>68</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1740774512465496">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The construction of a Williams design and randomization in cross-over clinical trials using SAS</article-title>. <source>J Stat Softw</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>29</volume>(Code Snippet 1). Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jstatsoft.org/">http://www.jstatsoft.org/</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1740774512465496">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>SAS Institute Inc</collab>. <article-title>SAS/STAT software (version 9.1)</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Cary, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAS Institute Inc</publisher-name>, <year>2003</year>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sas.com/">http://www.sas.com/</ext-link>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>