<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JFN</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjfn</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Fam Nurs</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Family Nursing</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1074-8407</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-549X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1074840713485924</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1074840713485924</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Family Nursing Network</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Dr. Lorraine M. Wright Awarded the Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Medal in Canada</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>281</fpage>
<lpage>282</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Lorraine M. Wright, RN, PhD, was awarded the Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Medal by the College and Association of Alberta Registered Nurses for her leadership, commitment, and passion to nursing and health care in Alberta, in Canada, and beyond. The commemorative medal marks the 2012 celebrations of the 60th anniversary of Her Majesty Queen Elizabeth II’s accession to the throne as the Queen of Canada. It honors Canadians who have dedicated themselves to the service of their fellow citizens, their community, and their country.</p>
<p>Dr. Lorraine M. Wright is a professor emeritus of nursing, University of Calgary, Calgary, Alberta, Canada: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.lorrainewright.com">http://www.lorrainewright.com</ext-link>. She is a towering local and international leader in the field of family nursing—brilliant teacher, scholar, clinician, founder of the Family Nursing Unit, University of Calgary (1982-2007), researcher, and a generous mentor to many nurses in Canada and around the globe. Lorraine Wright’s clinical scholarship has changed the face of family nursing with important contributions to theory, practice, and research in the areas of (a) illness beliefs of patients, families, and health care professionals; (b) spirituality, illness suffering, hope, and healing; and (c) interventions for generalist and advanced nursing practice that promote individual, couple, and family healing. Her work has been valued by a local and international community of nurses and interdisciplinary health professionals who encounter families in their clinical practice. Through the creation and dissemination of clinical practice models for generalist and advanced practice, she has brought particular distinction to Calgary, to the province of Alberta, and to Canada. Lorraine’s scholarship to date has included writing 10 books, lecturing about family nursing in 30 countries, and obtaining two honorary doctorates.</p>
<p>Dr. Wright was one of six nurses to receive the Queen Elizabeth II Diamond Jubilee Medal from the lieutenant governor of Alberta in a special luncheon ceremony hosted by the College and Association of Alberta Registered Nurses in Edmonton, Alberta, Canada on January 25, 2013: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nurses.ab.ca/carna/index.aspx?WebStructureID=7265">https://www.nurses.ab.ca/carna/index.aspx?WebStructureID=7265</ext-link>. She was also honored at a special ceremony in Ottawa, Ontario on March 5, 2013 by the Canadian Nurses Association: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cna-aiic.ca/en/events/awards/queen-elizabeth-ii-diamond-jubilee-medals/">http://www.cna-aiic.ca/en/events/awards/queen-elizabeth-ii-diamond-jubilee-medals/</ext-link>.</p>
</body>
</article>