<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">LIS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">splis</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Librarianship and Information Science</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0961-0006</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-6477</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0961000611434758</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0961000611434758</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Identifying knowledge sharing barriers in the collaboration of traditional and western medicine professionals in Chinese hospitals: A case study</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Lihong</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-0961000611434758">Wuhan University, China</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>Miguel Baptista</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-0961000611434758">University of Sheffield, UK</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0961000611434758">Miguel Baptista Nunes, Information School, University of Sheffield, Regent Court, 211 Portobello Street, Sheffield, S1 4DP, UK Email: <email>j.m.nunes@sheffield.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>44</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>238</fpage>
<lpage>248</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This paper reports on a research project that aims at identifying knowledge sharing (KS) barriers between traditional and western medicine practitioners co-existing and complementing each other in Chinese healthcare organisations. The study focuses on the tacit aspects of patient knowledge, rather than the traditional technical information shared through patient records. The project adopted a grounded theory approach as the overarching methodology to guide the analysis of data collected in a single case-study research design. A public hospital in central China was selected as the case-study site, at which 49 professionals were interviewed by using semi-structured and evolving interview scripts. The research findings reveal four main categories of KS barriers, namely philosophical divergence, interprofessional tensions, lack of interprofessional common ground, and insufficient interprofessional education and training. The conclusion advocates the establishment of top-down policies for mutual understanding and the creation of an interprofessional common ground between the two types of healthcare professionals. It is proposed that these policies should have two strands. The first strand should be at the grass roots of Chinese Healthcare Higher Education and should actively introduce complementary teaching and practice in these programmes. The second strand should take place in the hospital environment, through interprofessional dialogue, seminars and teamwork, as well as professional training. This paper contributes to the fields of KS and interprofessional collaboration in healthcare heterogeneous groups.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Chinese healthcare organisation</kwd>
<kwd>interprofessional common ground</kwd>
<kwd>knowledge sharing</kwd>
<kwd>knowledge-sharing barrier</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-0961000611434758" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>In 1950, immediately after the establishment of the People’s Republic of China (PRC), and as advocated by the first communist president Chairman Mao Zedong, the First National Healthcare Conference approved the creation of a national healthcare system, based on the provision of two very different types of medicine, namely traditional Chinese medicine (TCM) and western medicine (WM) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0961000611434758">Hillier and Jewell, 1983</xref>). TCM has been a consistent element of the Chinese culture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0961000611434758">Wong et al., 1993</xref>) and was developed as the result of the accumulation of experience and medical practices for over 2300 years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0961000611434758">Cheng, 2000</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0961000611434758">Hyatt (1978)</xref> asserts that TCM is not just ‘folk’ medicine, but a highly developed art and science. However, at the beginning of the 20th century, TCM lost the dominant position it had held for thousands of years over the Chinese public health systems to WM. WM, based on the scientific paradigm and evidence-based practice, was developed in Europe and North America after the industrial revolution and is largely considered to be the main component of today’s Chinese healthcare system, despite its coexistence with TCM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0961000611434758">Chi, 1994</xref>).</p>
<p>The political decision for the collaboration between TCM and WM was particularly important to the Chinese Communist Government. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0961000611434758">Taylor (2004)</xref> points out that, after the establishment of the PRC, the Chinese Communist Government used TCM as a strategic tool to distinguish the new communist China from its superstitious and feudal past as well as to illustrate the Chinese cultural heritage. Therefore, in 1954, two main strategies were formulated, not only to bridge the two distinct professional communities, but also to explore possible areas of collaboration. First, a number of TCM universities were established all over the country to provide formalised TCM education and to conduct systematic and scientific research on both TCM and its collaboration with WM. Second, a nation-wide search was conducted to selecting 2000 good WM professionals, who were pulled away from their jobs for full-time study of TCM and to explore approaches to collaboration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0961000611434758">Taylor, 2004</xref>). These initial political decisions encouraged the two medical communities to work together and created the condition for a complementary relationship that still exists today.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, and since then, the coexistence and the complementary relationship between TCM and WM communities have not always been harmonious and stable. Not long after the formulation of the complementary relationship and the establishment of specialised higher education (HE) in TCM, TCM was put under stress during the ‘Great Cultural Revolution’ (1966–1976), since the Government at that time considered TCM as a feudal product of the old China, which needed to be eliminated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0961000611434758">Chen et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0961000611434758">Fruehauf, 1999</xref>). In this period, not only was the number of Chinese traditional medicine colleges dramatically reduced from 21 to 11, but also the practitioners of TCM were criticised as feudalists and some were even persecuted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0961000611434758">Fruehauf, 1999</xref>). On the other hand, during this crisis in TCM, WM reinforced its dominance over the Chinese healthcare system and services.</p>
<p>Mao Zedong’s death in 1976 brought an end to the Great Cultural Revolution as well as the crisis of TCM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0961000611434758">Hesketh and Zhu, 1997</xref>). The position of TCM was reinstated by The Official Document no. 52 issued by the central government in 1978 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0961000611434758">Lv, 2005</xref>). According to this author, the official document emphasised two points, namely, equality in the support of western medicine and traditional medicine and equal development of the two types of medicines. Since then, the official political statements have consistently declared that TCM and WM should be equally supported, despite the dominance of WM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0961000611434758">Liu, 2003</xref>). Again, a recent public statement made by Chen Zhu, the Minister for Health, restated that the Chinese Government supported both TCM and WM equally in the national healthcare system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0961000611434758">Cai and Ju, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Nevertheless, and despite the political nature of the decision creating this interprofessional relationship, many researchers (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0961000611434758">Fruehauf, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0961000611434758">Hyatt, 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0961000611434758">Taylor, 2004</xref>) have claimed that this collaboration was unexpectedly successful, since it created a complementary relationship between the two types of professionals working cooperatively against a number of diseases deemed to be untreatable solely by WM doctors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0961000611434758">Taylor, 2004</xref>: 103).</p>
<p>In any case, the complementary relationship and the collaboration of the two types of healthcare professionals should be patient centred. However, these policies, arrangements and statements are often made more for political purposes, and their implementation does not necessarily benefit the patient. In fact, this politically minded collaboration and complementarity does not guarantee per se that the interests of patients are always protected and placed at the centre of the collaborative processes. If the benefits to the patient are not very well protected by these political decisions, then there is a contradiction with the patient-centred care advocated by the Chinese central government.</p>
<p>In order to ensure that the collaboration between TCM and WM is patient centred, it is essential for healthcare professionals to communicate and share technical and patient knowledge with each other. This is necessary to protect the needs, requirements and benefits of the patient (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0961000611434758">Maizes et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0961000611434758">Steward, 2001</xref>). Nonetheless, in practice, the two types of healthcare professionals do not necessarily communicate and share knowledge (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0961000611434758">Zhou et al., 2010</xref>). In truth, there are barriers impeding the processes of sharing knowledge. This paper identifies, criticises and discusses these knowledge-sharing barriers in the context of Chinese healthcare organisations.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0961000611434758">
<title>Theoretical sensitisation</title>
<sec id="section3-0961000611434758">
<title>Complementarity of TCM and WM</title>
<p>As discussed above, the current Chinese healthcare system fully integrates TCM and WM healthcare methodologies and incorporates both communities in the same hospitals.</p>
<p>TCM emphasises the integrity of the human body as a whole and its close relationship with the environment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0961000611434758">Cheng, 2000</xref>). According to the study of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0961000611434758">Ma (1999)</xref>, traditional Chinese healing practice is intended to enhance the immune system of the human body, antiviral effects, anti-inflammation, balance of mind and body, aches and pain relief, and cholesterol reduction. There are four main categories of Chinese medical treatments, namely herbal medicine (oral intake and external use), heat therapy (moxibustion, and cupping), massage (oriental massage, Gua Sha and magnets) and acupuncture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0961000611434758">Sherman et al., 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Conversely, WM employs a scientific attitude in diagnosis and treatments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0961000611434758">Dally, 2003</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0961000611434758">Unschuld (1985)</xref> claims that achievements from intensive and evidence-based fundamental scientific research have brought WM to an unchallengeable dominant position in world health care as well as in China. In fact, and despite the plurality, WM takes the primary position in the Chinese healthcare system, being complemented by TCM as an alternative healthcare therapy. It is widely accepted in China that WM is more effective in the acute stage of many diseases and works much faster than TCM in treating these acute diseases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0961000611434758">Ma, 1999</xref>). However, it is also acknowledged that WM creates more adverse side effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0961000611434758">Kaptchuk, 2000</xref>). Nevertheless, healing herbs, acupuncture, massage and other health methods from TCM may be more appropriate in health promotion, prevention, treatment and rehabilitation. Moreover, TCM may be used as a last resort, when western medicine is either too toxic or unable to provide any further expected benefit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0961000611434758">Chen, 1989</xref>).</p>
<p>The advantages and benefits of integrating TCM and WM services into a single healthcare system, as well as the implementation of complementary treatment, have become evident. However, this very specific healthcare system demands effective interactions between TCM and WM practitioners on a range of aspects not limited to technical medical knowledge. These interactions are an essential and indispensable foundation to the provision of efficient combined patient-centred services.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0961000611434758">
<title>Patient-centred healthcare</title>
<p>There are many different definitions of patient-centred care. A very succinct and clear one is provided by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0961000611434758">Maizes et al. (2009)</xref>:
<disp-quote>
<p>Care that informs and involves patients in medical decision making and self-management, coordinates and integrates medical care, provides physical comfort and emotional support, understands the patients’ concept of illness and their cultural beliefs, and understands and applies principles of disease prevention and behavioural change appropriate to diverse populations.</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>In 2006, the Chinese central government announced that the patient-centred approach should be taken as the most essential guideline for healthcare professionals and organisations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0961000611434758">Zhong, 2009</xref>). The adoption of the patient-centred approach reinforced the principle that the role of the patient must be maintained at the centre of all medical procedures and entails that patients’ rights, benefits and requirements should be ensured in the collaboration between TCM and WM. Therefore, effective communication and adequate KS between TCM and WM healthcare professionals is the centrepiece of the implementation of patient-centred care (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0961000611434758">Maizes et al., 2009</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0961000611434758">
<title>Knowledge sharing in patient-centred healthcare</title>
<p>KS is an effective strategy to build competitive advantages for all types of organisations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0961000611434758">McEvily et al., 2000</xref>). In the health sector, there is a universal perception that appropriate processes of KS, based on good practices of knowledge creation, storage, transfer and utilisation, are fundamental to resolving daily medical problems challenging healthcare professionals, and, more importantly, can dramatically improve the quality of healthcare services (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0961000611434758">Abidi, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0961000611434758">Nicolini et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0961000611434758">Zhou et al., 2010</xref>). KS in healthcare was defined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0961000611434758">Abidi (2007</xref>: 69) as follows:
<disp-quote>
<p>Healthcare knowledge sharing can be characterised as the explication and dissemination of context-sensitive healthcare knowledge by and for healthcare stakeholders through a collaborative communication medium in order to advance the knowledge quotient of the participating healthcare stakeholders.</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>To develop this definition further, according to the needs of this research project, KS can be defined as the interaction of patient knowledge between WM and TCM healthcare professionals. In this case KS should occur through collaborative communication channels so that patient knowledge is always available and is used to provide the best possible healthcare services to patients, to improve the quality of patient care and to achieve patient satisfaction.</p>
<p>Patient knowledge can be defined by the following typology:</p>
<list id="list1-0961000611434758" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Technical Knowledge – includes identification of patient conditions and problems, reasons and objectives of patient care, patient background, agreement to treatment strategy, and explicit patient requirements and needs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0961000611434758">Smith, 1996</xref>).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Ethical and Emotional Knowledge – focuses on ethically dealing ethically with patient feelings, emotions, and psychological status, approaches to communication, persuasion and management of individual patients, and ultimately maintaining trusting and collaborative professional-patient relationships (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0961000611434758">Fennessy and Burstein, 2007</xref>).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Social and Behavioural Knowledge – is concerned with anticipating how others will behave, and perception of patients’ implicit requirements, as well as their behaviour, reactions and expectations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0961000611434758">Fennessy and Burstein, 2007</xref>).</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Of the three types of patient knowledge, the sharing of technical knowledge is the least problematic, since this type of knowledge is easier to share and is usually recorded explicitly in the patient records. Moreover, as discussed above, the two types of healthcare professionals adopt two entirely different medical systems and their philosophical beliefs and technical insights do not seem to be paramount in the complementary provision of medical services (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0961000611434758">Guo, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0961000611434758">Yang, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>On the other hand, ethical and emotional knowledge and social and behavioural knowledge consist of the experiences and perceptions of individual professionals, which are accumulated through processes of dealing and interacting with individual patients, their families and their communities. Therefore, when compared with the technical knowledge, the sharing of these two types of tacit patient knowledge among healthcare professionals is much more difficult and more important. Thus, this project focuses on the sharing of ethical and emotional knowledge and social and behavioural knowledge between the TCM and WM healthcare professionals.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0961000611434758" sec-type="methods">
<title>Research methodology</title>
<sec id="section7-0961000611434758">
<title>General research approach</title>
<p>The general aim of this project is to identify, characterise and discuss KS barriers between TCM and WM practitioners in the context of the Chinese National Healthcare. Ultimately the intention behind the project is to seek understanding of these barriers and propose strategies to improve collaboration and patient-centred care.</p>
<p>Due to the very specific characteristics of the Chinese healthcare environment it was very difficult to establish a base theory for the problem. In fact, there are other examples of coexistence between WM and traditional medicines (e.g. homeopathy, herbal medicine, chiropractic, etc.). However, in no other circumstances are these different health professionals working together by political design and in the same hospital, sometimes even in the same building. This makes it almost impossible to use a deductive approach.</p>
<p>Therefore, the research approach selected for the project is inductive in nature. Specifically, and among the different possible choices, grounded theory (GT) was adopted. GT is widely recognised as particularly useful for theory generation purposes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0961000611434758">Strauss and Corbin, 1998</xref>). Nonetheless, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0961000611434758">Pickard (2007)</xref> points out that GT is a series of qualitative analysis processes, rather than a complete research methodology. Therefore, GT is usually applied in a combined approach with other research methodologies, such as ethnography and case study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0961000611434758">Pickard, 2007</xref>). Many researchers suggest that case study and GT are not just compatible with each other, but are in fact a combination that is ideal for establishing a valid and reliable inductive theory (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0961000611434758">Allan, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0961000611434758">Eisenhardt, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0961000611434758">Glaser, 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0961000611434758">Glaser and Strauss, 1967</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0961000611434758">Pickard, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0961000611434758">Tellis, 1997</xref>). Consequently, this project adopted a combined approach of grounded theory (GT) and case study. Finally, it is important to stress that a Straussian GT approach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0961000611434758">Strauss and Corbin, 1998</xref>) was employed as the overarching research methodology to guide the data collection and analysis.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0961000611434758">
<title>Research design</title>
<p>The basic research design for this project was based on a single case study to contextualise the application of GT in the Chinese healthcare system. Case-study approaches enable the investigation of contemporary phenomena in real-life contexts (Yin, 1994), and are useful for exploratory purposes and for initiating a theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0961000611434758">Benbasat et al., 1987</xref>). Therefore, a case-study approach is suitable for this project, because this study investigates a contemporary problematic situation existing in the current Chinese healthcare system. Moreover, considering China is one of the largest countries in the world, with a population exceeding 1.3 billion, it would be virtually impossible to generate a theory that would encompass the whole nation.</p>
<p>Consequently, since this project aimed at generating a first set of insights into this problem, a single case-study design was adopted. A public hospital in the city of Xiangfan, in the province of Hubei, was selected for the case study. This hospital was chosen for two main reasons. First, it provides both WM and TCM services to patients and has done so for several decades. Second, the researcher obtained guaranteed and management-supported access to the informants and the project.</p>
<p>Implementing of GT in the context of this case study was planned according to a three-stage design, namely: a pilot study, a main study and a follow-up study.</p>
<sec id="section9-0961000611434758">
<title>The pilot study</title>
<p>This study aimed to confirm if the KS problems anticipated did present themselves in the reality of practice of a Chinese hospital, and to identify early results and insights to guide the remaining research stages. Overall, seven healthcare professionals and workers were purposively approached and interviewed. These participants were two WM doctors, one WM nurse, two TCM doctors, one ICT manager and one hospital administrator. Findings from this stage suggested that different departments in the hospital exhibit very different patterns of KS behaviour between the two medical communities. The study also showed that very different levels of integration of complementary treatments may be found in different departments. This resulted in the decision to choose one specific department, the Department of Neurosurgery. This department has a proven history of using WM and TCM compound treatments for rehabilitating patients after craniotomies.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0961000611434758">
<title>The main study</title>
<p>The purpose of the main study was to identify KS barriers between the two communities when dealing with problems from neurosurgical patients. At this stage, 11 neurosurgeons, eight neurosurgical nurses and six TCM doctors were selected as participants, approached and interviewed. The data collected were analysed using open and axial coding through the constant comparison method of analysis. The findings indicated a need for further study on the external influences on KS.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0961000611434758">
<title>The follow-up study</title>
<p>This study aimed at exploring these external influences on KS. Furthermore, it aimed at exploring and studying those categories for which theoretical saturation could not be achieved in the previous stage. Theoretical sampling, further coding and constant comparison analysis were used at this stage. This exercise of gaining a deeper understanding implied the interviewing of specific informants, namely two neurosurgeons, two TCM doctors, three neurosurgical nurses, one TCM educator, one public administrator in the local healthcare department, and eight patient carers.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0961000611434758">
<title>Data collection, analysis and theoretical saturation</title>
<p>Overall, data collection followed the theoretical sampling strategy, and included 46 interview participants in a total of 49 interviews. The demographic profile of the participants is illustrated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0961000611434758">Table 1</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0961000611434758" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Demographic profile of participants (<italic>N</italic> = 46).</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0961000611434758" xlink:href="10.1177_0961000611434758-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Gender</th>
<th align="left">Number of participants</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Male</td>
<td>24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Female</td>
<td>22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">Professional position</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Senior neurosurgeons</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Junior &amp; middle-level neurosurgeons</td>
<td>10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Neurosurgical nurses</td>
<td>12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Senior TCM doctors</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Junior &amp; middle-level TCM doctors</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Orthopaedics doctors</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Chief hospital managers</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hospital ICT managers</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TCM educators</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Healthcare politicians in local government</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Patient relatives/carers</td>
<td>8</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>These informants were sampled by the emerging theory and were interviewed by using semi-structured and evolving interview scripts. The data analysis used the GT analysis approach, which is widely recognised as particularly useful to generate theory closely related to the context of the phenomena being studied (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0961000611434758">Creswell, 1998</xref>). Therefore, the questions in the interview script changed and evolved as new and sometimes unexpected codes emerged and other concepts became fully explained or saturated, that is new questions were added to script while some were actually withdrawn or refocused.</p>
<p>As required by the GT methodology, the processes of data collection and analysis were operationalised. That is, immediately after each individual interview, the collected data were transcribed and analysed. Results from this analysis were used not only for the theory building, but also to direct subsequent interviews, as proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0961000611434758">Strauss and Corbin (1998)</xref>.</p>
<p>The practice of data analysis adopted two GT analytical techniques, namely coding (open, axial and selective) and constant comparative analysis, which <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0961000611434758">Strauss and Corbin (1998)</xref> emphasise as critically essential to the GT data analysis. The coding and data analysis instrument that supported constant comparison for this project is illustrated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0961000611434758">Table 2</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="table2-0961000611434758" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>The presentation of emerging main themes, barriers and representative quotations.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0961000611434758" xlink:href="10.1177_0961000611434758-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Category</th>
<th align="left">Barriers</th>
<th align="left">Representative statements (Q = interview quote)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Philosophical divergence</td>
<td>Different conceptual system</td>
<td>Q1: ‘WM has a specific treatment system. On the other side, TCM has a different treatment system. We have different perspectives to take care of our patients.’ WMD 9.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Terminology discrepancy</td>
<td>Q2: ‘[WM and TCM] have two terminological systems. Maybe both of them have an identical purpose, but how they express the purpose is entirely different.’ TCM 15.35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Interprofessional tensions</td>
<td>Philosophical tension</td>
<td>Q3: ‘Perhaps, TCM philosophy is scientific and effective in a few cases, but many TCM theories are very ridiculous. […] From our perspective [neurosurgeons], TCM as a healthcare philosophy is unscientific, is a wrong mechanism, and is a superstition.’ WMD 12.22<break/>Q4: ‘I know that TCM is very effective against various diseases, but TCM is considered as unscientific when evaluated in the WM methodology. In fact, TCM and WM have rather distinct systems, there is no similarity. You cannot define TCM by using WM theories.’ TCM 20.7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Professional tension</td>
<td>Q5: ‘Before collaborative works, we need to inform TCM doctors what problem this patient has, what treatments have already been conducted, what we want you TCM doctors to do. All these details, they [TCM doctors] need to know.’ WMD 2.140<break/>Q6: ‘Theoretically, TCM and WM are equally important. But we are a general hospital. TCM departments and practitioners are weaker in general hospitals.’ TCM 17.27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Lack of interprofessional common ground</td>
<td/>
<td>Q7: ‘Communication, if without a knowledge basis, is impossible. […] If WM doctors do not learn TCM, they will never accept our philosophy.’ TCM 6.72<break/>Q8: ‘WM students learn TCM, but in a very limited way. These students do not have enough TCM knowledge. In this case, WM doctors usually do not have a natural motivation to voluntarily collaborate with TCM colleagues.’ WMD 1.36</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Insufficient interprofessional education and training</td>
<td>Lack of interprofessional education in healthcare HE</td>
<td>Q9: ‘Generally speaking, WM practitioners had limited TCM learning in their education. Therefore, WM practitioners are taking a suspicious attitude toward TCM. […] We think treatments like acupuncture and some herbal treatments are effective. Although we are taking a suspicious attitude, we usually use it.’ WMD 39.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td>Absence of interprofessional training</td>
<td>Q10: ‘Professional training is mostly limited in our specific subjects. For example, as I am a neurosurgeon, my professional training would only focus on the area of neurosurgery, or focus on a specific disease [related to neurosurgery].’ WMD 20.41</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Consequently, data collection and analysis coexisted until theoretical saturation was achieved, that is, until no new open codes emerged from the data analysis. The evolution of this emergence of new open codes and the theoretical saturation can be demonstrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0961000611434758">Figure 1</xref>.</p>
<fig id="fig1-0961000611434758" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Coding and theoretical saturation.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0961000611434758-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0961000611434758">Figure 1</xref>, the burgeoning emergence of new open codes in the pilot study suggested a more focused data collection in the main study. The new codes that emerged in the 21st to 31st interviews suggested new areas to be explored in the follow-up study. The theoretical saturation was considered as achieved after the 41st interview, but the process was continued until interview 49 in order to obtain a better degree of certainty.</p>
<p>The emergent theory saturated on four main categories: philosophical divergence, interprofessional tensions, lack of interprofessional common ground and insufficient interprofessional education and training. A tabular presentation of the emerging main categories, barriers and supporting quotations is shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0961000611434758">Table 2</xref>.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0961000611434758">
<title>Research findings</title>
<p>From the data collected it became clear that neurosurgical and TCM professionals were actually collaborating with patient interests and needs in mind. When dealing with patient problems, WM is the primary methodology for the patient treatment and was always used in the first instance. TCM methods are usually considered as more effective at the post-craniotomy and rehabilitation stages. Thus, TCM healthcare professionals are frequently invited by neurosurgical practitioners for intervention at these stages. The two teams have now established a strong complementary and collaborative relationship.</p>
<sec id="section14-0961000611434758">
<title>Knowledge-sharing process</title>
<p>Interaction and collaboration usually occur in consultation sessions, which are also the main vehicle for the sharing of patient knowledge. A consultation is usually requested by a neurosurgeon, when a patient’s condition is perceived to be more suitable for treatment by TCM doctors. The nurse in charge usually initiates the process at the request of the neurosurgeon and contacts the TCM doctor directly to make an informal enquiry. If the TCM doctor agrees his/her commitment to the patient, the neurosurgeon initiates a consultation note as a formal invitation for collaboration. The consultation note records all procedures and medical decisions that are made during the consultation session. After this consultation session, WM and TCM professionals never meet again to discuss that particular patient, except in the case of emergencies. The consultation note must be signed by doctors from both sides and documented in the patient records.</p>
<p>Both sides perceive these consultation sessions as a relatively good communication channel for KS. However, as a communication channel, these meetings can only play a very limited role in real KS between the two professional groups.</p>
<p>In reality, as expressed by a number of informants, the meetings usually last no more than 20 minutes, during which the diagnosis of the patient is presented by the WM professional and a brief discussion occurs between all participants. This is of course not conducive to in-depth interprofessional discussions.</p>
<p>Moreover, all the participants, as in any other hospital in the world, are extremely pressed for time. This was evident from a number of informants’ statements:
<disp-quote>
<p>[In the consultation] usually they do not ask many questions, and we do not talk that much. We all are very busy. As long as we can treat the patient, that is all right. We all are too busy to actually sit down and to have a deep conversation. (Interview TCM 37.63)</p>
<p>[In consultation] sometimes neurosurgeons can introduce patient conditions. But normally they [neurosurgical professionals] are very busy. Therefore, we mainly rely on the patient records. (Interview TCM 15.23)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Thus, the consultation meeting becomes a formal handover of patients and not a vehicle for the interchange of knowledge and interprofessional communication.</p>
<p>Also, the knowledge on which this research is focused, is inherently tacit and centred around patient needs, requirements and expectations. Crucially, the healthcare professionals that usually possess more of this knowledge, the nurses, are mere spectators in these consultation meetings.</p>
<p>Nurses, as the closest healthcare practitioners to the patient, are the ones that have a better understanding of the ethical and emotional knowledge about a particular patient as well as the social and behavioural knowledge pertaining to their family, social and even religious background. However, due to a combination of Chinese and hospital culture their role in the consultation meetings is secondary at best. Nurses, although present in the meetings, very rarely intervene and never have direct contact with their counterparts on the other side.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>I rarely get into deep conversation with TCM doctors. We [neurosurgical nurses] never talk in such details [for the purpose of sharing patient knowledge]. (Interview WMN 33.15)</p>
<p>We after all are just nurses. If a patient needs help from TCM doctors, it is entirely the neurosurgeon’s responsibility. They need to make decisions. Then, we just work on those decisions. (Interview WMN 31.13)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Thus, all the knowledge accumulated by direct care and interaction with a particular patient is lost and never transmitted to the TCM professionals.</p>
<p>Finally, these very rushed and short consultation meetings will never be a vehicle for the two professional groups to resolve the KS barriers identified in this research and discussed in the next sections.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0961000611434758">
<title>Knowledge-sharing barriers</title>
<p>The research findings point to four main categories of KS barriers. These categories are: philosophical divergence, tension of philosophical conflicts, lack of interprofessional common ground and insufficient interprofessional education and training.</p>
<sec id="section16-0961000611434758">
<title>Philosophical divergence</title>
<p>The collaboration between TCM and WM united the two types of healthcare professionals, who have entirely different basic philosophical perspectives and beliefs. From the data gathered, it became evident that these divergent philosophical foundations result in two KS barriers, namely (1) different conceptual systems and (2) discrepancy in terminology.</p>
<list id="list2-0961000611434758" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>1. Different conceptual systems. A number of the healthcare professionals who were interviewed, for instance in Q1 in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0961000611434758">Table 2</xref>, stated that TCM and WM do not just have very different theoretical foundations, but also have extremely distinctive diagnosis and treatment methods.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>It is almost impossible to integrate both TCM and WM methods into one medical procedure. It is because TCM takes a holistic view of the human body, which is the philosophical foundation for TCM. (Interview TCM 18.07)</p>
<p>Because we are WM practitioners and we were educated as WM practitioners, we are used to analysing from the WM perspective. But TCM is very different. Sometimes I think TCM makes sense. WM always localises diseases into particular parts of the human body. If you have a head problem, then treat the head. If you have problems with your feet, then treat the feet. However, TCM treats a patient as a whole. They [TCM doctors] are not just dealing with the disease itself. Therefore, WM is from a micro perspective, TCM is holistic. (Interview WMD 24.9)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>TCM doctors adopt a holistic view of the human body as an integral entity in a close relationship with the environment. Very differently, WM practitioners are more interested in localising a specific health problem at a specific area of the human body. Moreover, WM doctors rely almost exclusively on tangible and explicit evidence (e.g. radiology, lab tests), whereas the practice of TCM largely depends on doctors’ perceptions and judgements and their accumulation of personal medical experiences.</p>
<p>This significant philosophical divergence poses severe difficulties in understanding each other’s diagnosis, clashes in indications for treatment, difficulties in interpreting requirements for complementarity of treatments and difficulties in understanding interpretations of healthcare problems. These difficulties may result not only in different discourses that may not be entirely compatible, but also in a professional reluctance in accepting each other’s opinions, diagnoses and interpretations.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>TCM diagnosis uses inspection, listening and smelling examination, inquiry, and palpation. These methods are far different from ours. Sometimes we suspect how accurate these methods are. (Interview WMN 27.15)</p>
<p>They [TCM doctors] have a totally different theoretical system, which we [WM professionals] do not understand. They have very special understandings of some common problems. Why they have those understandings, I don’t know. But their methods are effective [to patients]. Undeniably, there are a number of conflicts between the two theoretical systems, but their [TCM] methods are effective. Nevertheless, WM is probably more effective and as a WM doctor, I believe in our system. They believe in theirs. There are clear conflicts. (Interview WMD 9.25)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Moreover, the philosophical divergence and different professional discourses may result in the use of entirely different, sometimes conflicting professional terminologies.</p>
<list id="list3-0961000611434758" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>2. Terminology discrepancy.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Most of the time, when TCM doctors are proposing their ideas, we can’t understand. We ask for further explanation, but still, we can’t understand. It’s not like in WM, very demonstrative and clear, such as in some cases we focus on the evidences. (Interview WMN 7.135)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>This quotation clearly shows that there are important difficulties in communication, let alone knowledge sharing. It was apparent from a number of interviews (e.g. Q2 in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0961000611434758">Table 2</xref>) that the differences in philosophical foundations actually result in very different discourses, terminologies and technical jargons, which make the processes of sharing patient knowledge extremely difficult.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>If I talk TCM language to WM doctors, it would be like they are reading a sealed book [Chinese expression that implies a book that is impossible to understand]. None of them can understand. (Interview TCM 4.106)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0961000611434758">
<title>Interprofessional tensions</title>
<p>Also, arising from the combination of the historical process described in the introduction and the philosophical divergence discussed above, two very different types of interprofessional tension seemed to have developed since the beginning of last century, namely (1) philosophical and (2) professional tensions. These tensions emerged very strongly across the data collected and seem to be one of the important barriers preventing the necessary interprofessional interactions.</p>
<list id="list4-0961000611434758" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>1. Philosophical tension. During the interviews, TCM and WM healthcare professionals showed a consistent lack of belief in each other’s practices. Attitudes ranged from respectful disbelief to entire disregard of the other’s roles in the healthcare system. This latter attitude was more evident in WM practitioners who often harshly criticised TCM beliefs and methodology, describing them as useless ‘superstition’ (Interview WMD 6.44).</p></list-item>
</list>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Theories of TCM and WM are very different; for example, TCM requires thinking by heart, but as we know actually thinking is by brain. TCM does not have a clear definition and description about the brain. I think TCM and WM are two different systems. I can generally understand TCM, but from a professional point of view I think TCM is not good, not accurate, not rich. (Interview WMD 39.13)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>As asserted by many of the neurosurgical interviewees, for example in Q3 in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0961000611434758">Table 2</xref>, WM is seen as pure scientific methodology and ‘superior’ (Interview WMN 14.15) to TCM, which is perceived to be based exclusively on ‘personal experiences instead of scientific evidences’ (Interview WMD 2.96) and ‘lacks a scientific foundation’ (Interview WMD 2.101).</p>
<p>Conversely, many TCM doctors (e.g. Q4 in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0961000611434758">Table 2</xref>) defended their methodology as a ‘solid medical methodology’ (Interview TCM 4.9), which consists of a systematic and consistent set of diagnostic and treatment methods, and that it has a credibility and an understanding of the human body that has been revised through an evolution of thousands of years. Consequently, many TCM interviewees disagree with some of the WM beliefs and methods, which they find are not always appropriate and which sometimes have adverse effects on patients’ well-being.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>In many cases, we have different opinions from WM doctors. For example, when dealing with a patient with symptoms of urination difficulty, we think acupuncture would be the best solution. But WM doctors think differently, they always use methods to force the patient to urinate. It is wrong, very wrong. (Interview TCM 15.25)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Therefore, the philosophical divergence at the core of the two professional groups’ beliefs has created an ongoing professional tension between the two groups. These tensions have fuelled conflicts of opinions and perspectives, which in turn have created a climate of distrust, disregard and unwillingness to communicate in the two communities.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>Some WM doctors, who think they are very good at what they are doing, are so arrogant. Even though they do not understand TCM at all, they consider TCM is a lie and a superstition. [In fact, WM is not perfect], when treating a patient, we would use the traditional herbal medicines as much as possible. We normally do not suggest the patient to take any WM drugs, which are bad for the heart and the liver, because they are all chemicals. (Interview TCM 19.39)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<list id="list5-0961000611434758" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>2. Professional tension. In addition to the philosophical tension, the two medical communities showed evidence of substantial asymmetries of positional power and professional standing. The analysis of the transcribed data clearly revealed that neurosurgeons have a relatively higher professional standing and almost complete control over patients. Therefore, as stated in Q5, they often explicitly instructed and regulated TCM doctors in what they should do about the patient.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>If a neurosurgical patient needs acupuncture treatments, neurosurgeons would initiate a consultation note and telephone us. Then we go to treat the patient with acupuncture. […] In this process, we do not have decision power. For example, this patient clearly needs TCM treatment, but we cannot do anything about it, because neurosurgeons need to make this decision, not us. (Interview TCM 16.17)</p>
<p>In collaborative patient treatments, we of course have the decision making power, because the patient is in our department. We just need TCM doctors to help us. (Interview WMD 8.31)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In contrast, TCM doctors have a lower professional standing and hold less power. Therefore, TCM doctors (as shown in Q6) are most likely to maintain a passive position, avoid any confrontations and to follow instructions, instead of actively, spontaneously and voluntarily proposing their understandings and treatment suggestions. For them, even if they intend to share knowledge, there are probably very few occasions for them to do so, and they hold very little power to have their views recognised.</p>
<p>This professional tension prevents KS, not only because the tension reinforces the professional boundary and distance, but also because it creates an atmosphere of professional distance and, at times, hostility between the two professional communities.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0961000611434758">
<title>Insufficient interprofessional education and training</title>
<p>The research findings indicate that the lack of interprofessional common ground was related to (1) inadequate interprofessional education in Chinese healthcare HE and (2) the absence of interprofessional training in the hospital environment.</p>
<list id="list6-0961000611434758" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Inadequate interprofessional education in healthcare HE. It is important to note that Chinese healthcare HE consists of two parallel and almost insulated educational systems, one for TCM practitioners and the other for WM ones. Interviewees from both educational systems, for instance Q9 in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0961000611434758">Table 2</xref>, stated that there were very few interprofessional modules, lectures, and practical sessions concentrating on the possible overlap of the healthcare systems. There is therefore virtually no education to support interprofessional collaboration and communication. In this case, students from either system had very limited mutual knowledge and interprofessional common ground, and more importantly lack motivation for interprofessional collaboration and communication.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Absence of interprofessional training.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>We have many training activities. But training for WM practitioners is only in WM. There is no requirement for WM practitioners to learn TCM. We are only required to learn professional knowledge in our subject. (Interview WMD 19.06)</p>
<p>The hospital management established several professional training strategies. But none of them concentrates on us to learn WM, or on WM professionals so they can have better TCM understandings. (Interview TCM 17.81)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Therefore, in addition to the insufficient interprofessional education in healthcare HE, it was clearly identified that there is also a significant absence of interprofessional training schemes, sessions and programmes to bridge the gap in understanding between the two professional communities and to develop an appropriate interprofessional common ground.</p>
<p>As expressed by the neurosurgeon in Q10, the professional training programmes are mostly focused on their respective professional subjects and methods, rarely on the interprofessional areas. This reflects a perception that hospital management and leadership places very little importance on communication and professional cooperation between the two groups, thus reinforcing philosophical divergence and educational problems. In this case, healthcare professionals not only begin with very limited common ground to facilitate KS, but also are actively demotivated to engage in interprofessional activities and the sharing of patient ‘real needs’ (Interview WMN 14.35).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0961000611434758">
<title>Lack of interprofessional common ground</title>
<p>As discussed above, it is evident that neurosurgical professionals and TCM doctors have entirely different conceptual systems, philosophical foundations, educational systems and training programmes. Therefore, and despite governmental policies and a genuine interest in supporting patient needs, the two professional communities are collaborating to treat the patients with a clear lack of interprofessional common ground to facilitate their communication and KS.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>[Communication and collaboration] depends on how much a WM doctor knows about TCM. If you know less, you are less motivated. If you know more, you are more motivated. According to our current situation, WM practitioners do not know TCM very well. (Interview WMD 9.21)</p>
<p>[Communication and collaboration] requires WM practitioners to accept TCM. For instance, doctor A accepts acupuncture, therefore he invites us for collaboration. He introduces patients to us. If a WM doctor has no basic TCM knowledge, he would not trust TCM, therefore no [collaborations]. (Interview TCM 16.18)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>As discussed by medical practitioners from both groups (Q7 and Q8), this interprofessional common ground could be conceptualised as a knowledge base of overlapping interests and mutual conceptual understandings. This lack of interprofessional common ground exacerbates the philosophical divergence and results in conflicting understandings of patient symptoms and conditions. Moreover, the lack of interprofessional common ground reinforces the philosophical divergence and the professional boundary and distance, as well as philosophical and professional tensions.</p>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>I do not have a deep understanding of the TCM system. I am taking a suspicious attitude toward TCM. I think there is something that cannot be explained in TCM. I do not have a deep understanding about TCM, because I do not believe in TCM. In this case, I am not particularly interested in it. Once you enter the [metaphoric professional] door of WM, you have nothing to do with TCM. (Interview WMD 24.29)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section20-0961000611434758" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>The research reported in this paper shows that, despite a strong governmental commitment and the implementation of national policies that placed TCM and WM practitioners in the same hospitals and healthcare organisations, KS between the two groups is very limited. A clear absence of interprofessional common ground causes and aggravates identified KS barriers shaped mainly by philosophical divergences, very different medical practices, conflicting understandings of patient symptoms and conditions, insulated HE systems and lack of integrative training programmes. Moreover, the lack of interprofessional common ground reinforces rigid professional boundaries and inequalities in status and power within the hospital, and therefore creates philosophical and professional tensions.</p>
<p>These strong interprofessional tensions alienate the TCM and WM healthcare professionals, who are supposed to work together, side by side, and to communicate unconditionally in order to provide the best possible medical treatments to patients. While technical information will always be present in patient records due to stringent healthcare system regulations, this alienation and the consequent lack of knowledge sharing will be particular crucial in tacit aspects of patient knowledge, namely in terms of the two categories identified in this paper: (a) ethical and emotional and (b) social and behavioural.</p>
<p>Thus, the key to improving KS and reducing the effect of the identified barriers lies in creating working environments and training programmes in the hospitals that develop the interprofessional common ground. It is clear that it is critically important to embed and increase interprofessional education programmes in both TCM and WM universities and educational institutions. Nevertheless, the effect of these changes in HE will need a considerable amount of time to permeate the national Chinese healthcare system. Therefore, the short- and medium-term changes need to be carried out at the hospital level by establishing very specific interprofessional training schemes and activities. This solution must be supported by the hospital management and medical professional leaders, who should realise that the collaboration between TCM and WM is not just a political imperative, but may bring tangible benefits through mutual trust with the aim of maximising the patients’ welfare.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<title>Author biographies</title>
<p><bold>Lihong Zhou</bold> – BSc, MSc, PhD, is an Associate Professor at the School of Information Management in Wuhan University, China. He obtained his MSc and PhD in Information Studies from the Information School, the University of Sheffield. His research interests focus on healthcare knowledge sharing; risk mitigation and management; and information systems project management.</p>
<p><bold>Miguel Baptista Nunes</bold> – BSc, MSc, PhD, MBCS, FHEA, FIMIS, is a Senior Lecturer and the Head of the Information Systems Research Group at the top ranked Information School in the University of Sheffield, united Kingdom. He has been involved in research in information systems for the last 18 years. He has published widely in the field (more than 150 academic articles) and participated in a a number of EU and UK funded projects.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Abidi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Healthcare knowledge sharing: purpose, practices, and prospects</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Bali</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dwivedi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Healthcare Knowledge Management: Issues, Advances, and Successes</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>, <fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Allan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>A critique of using grounded theory as a research method</article-title>. <source>Electronic Journal of Business Research Methods</source> <volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>10</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Benbasat</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mead</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>The case research strategy in studies of information systems</article-title>. <source>MIS Quarterly</source> <volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>369</fpage>–<lpage>386</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Waiting for the spring of traditional Chinese medicine: A public statement by Chen Zhu, the Minister of Health</article-title>. <source>Chinese Journal of the Practical Chinese with Modern Medicine</source> (in Chinese) <volume>22</volume>(<issue>16</issue>): <fpage>2</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <source>Medicine in Rural China</source>. <publisher-loc>Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Brief introduction of the development of Chinese medicine in New China</article-title>. <source>Magazine of Chinese Medicine Management</source> (in Chinese) <volume>9</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Review: Drug therapy in Chinese traditional medicine</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</source> <volume>40</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>450</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Integrating traditional medicine into modern health care systems: Examining the role of Chinese medicine in Taiwan</article-title>. <source>Social Science &amp; Medicine</source> <volume>39</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>321</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Creswell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Qualitative Inquiry and Research Design: Choosing among Five Traditions</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dally</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>The Trouble with Doctors: Fashions, Motives and Mistakes</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Robson Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eisenhardt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Building theories from case study research</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Review</source> <volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>532</fpage>–<lpage>550</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fennessy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burstein</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Role of information professionals as intermediaries for knowledge management in evidence-based healthcare</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Bali</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dwivedi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Healthcare Knowledge Management: Issues, Advances, and Successes</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>, <fpage>28</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fruehauf</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Chinese medicine in crisis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Chinese Medicine</source> <volume>61</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>) <source>Advances in the Methodology of Grounded Theory: Theoretical Sensitivity</source>. <publisher-loc>Mill Valley, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sociology Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1967</year>) <source>The Discovery of Grounded Theory: Strategies for Qualitative Research</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Aldine Transaction</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Discussion of the theories of the integration of traditional Chinese medicine and western medicine</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical and Experimental Medicine</source> (in Chinese) <volume>5</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>408</fpage>–<lpage>409</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hesketh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Health in China: The healthcare market</article-title>. <source>British Medical Journal</source> <volume>314</volume>: <fpage>1616</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jewell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <source>Health Care and Traditional Medicine in China, 1800– 1982</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hyatt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>) <source>Chinese Herbal Medicine: Ancient Art and Modern Science</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wildwood House</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kaptchuk</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>The Web that Has No Weaver: Understanding Chinese Medicine</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Considering Traditional Chinese Medicine</source> (in Chinese). <publisher-loc>Guilin, China</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guangxi Normal University</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Integration of Chinese and western medicine and westernisation of Chinese medicine</article-title>. <source>Chinese Journal of Integrated Traditional and Western Medicine</source> (in Chinese) <volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>6</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Between two worlds: The use of traditional and western health service by Chinese immigrants</article-title>. <source>Journal of Community Health</source> <volume>24</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>421</fpage>–<lpage>437</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McEvily</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Avoiding competence substitution through knowledge sharing</article-title>. <source>Academy of Management Review</source> <volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>296</fpage>–<lpage>311</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maizes</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rakel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Niemiec</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Integrative medicine and patient-centred care</article-title>. <source>Explore: The Journal of Science of Healing</source> <volume>5</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>277</fpage>–<lpage>289</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nicolini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Conville</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Managing knowledge in the healthcare sector. A review</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Management Reviews</source> <volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>245</fpage>–<lpage>263</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pickard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Research Methods in Information</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Facet</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cherkin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The practice of acupuncture: Who are the providers and what do they do?</article-title> <source>Annals of Family Medicine</source> <volume>3</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>158</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Information in practice</article-title>. <source>British Medical Journal</source> <volume>313</volume>: <fpage>1062</fpage>–<lpage>1068</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Steward</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Towards a global definition of patient centred care: The patient should be the judge of patient centred care</article-title>. <source>British Medical Journal</source> <volume>322</volume>: <fpage>444</fpage>–<lpage>445</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Corbin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Basics of Qualitative Research: Techniques and Procedures for Developing Grounded Theory</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Divergent interests and cultivated misunderstanding: The influence of the West on modern Chinese medicine</article-title>. <source>Social History of Medicine</source> <volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>111</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tellis</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Introduction to case study</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Report</source> <volume>3</volume>(<issue>2</issue>). Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nova.edu/ssss/QR/QR3-2/tellis1.html">http://www.nova.edu/ssss/QR/QR3-2/tellis1.html</ext-link> (<access-date>accessed 9 January 2012</access-date>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Unschuld</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <source>Medicine in China: A History of Ideas</source>. <publisher-loc>Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Donna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Traditional Chinese medicine and western medicine in Hong Kong: A comparison of the consultation processes and side effects</article-title>. <source>Journal of Hong Kong Medical Association</source> <volume>45</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>278</fpage>–<lpage>284</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Discussion of the integration of traditional Chinese medicine and western medicine</article-title>. <source>China and Foreign Medical Journal</source> (in Chinese) <volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Case Study Research: Design and Methods</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The patient-centred care and hospital marketing strategies</article-title>. <source>Management Observation</source> (in Chinese) <volume>October</volume>: <fpage>234</fpage>–<lpage>235</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0961000611434758">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Identifying knowledge sharing barriers in interprofessional healthcare collaboration of traditional and western medicine in China</article-title>. In: <conf-name>Proceedings of IADIS international conference on information systems, 2010</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Porto, Portugal</conf-loc>, <conf-date>18–20 March 2010</conf-date>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>