<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TSO</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sptso</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Teach Sociol</journal-id>
<journal-title>Teaching Sociology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0092-055X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1939-862X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0092055X11430638</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0092055X11430638</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Assessment of Student Learning</article-title>
<subtitle>Estudios Chicana/o Cultivating Critical Cultural Thinking</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Muñoz</surname><given-names>Ed A.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0092055X11430638">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Jaime</surname><given-names>Angela M.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0092055X11430638">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>McGriff</surname><given-names>Deborah L.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0092055X11430638">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>Adrian H.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0092055X11430638">4</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0092055X11430638"><label>1</label>Chicano Studies/Criminal Justice, University of Wyoming, Laramie, WY, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0092055X11430638"><label>2</label>American Indian Studies/Education Studies, University of Wyoming, Laramie, WY, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0092055X11430638"><label>3</label>African American Studies/Professional Studies, University of Wyoming, Laramie, WY, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0092055X11430638"><label>4</label>Chicano Studies/Sociology/Criminal Justice, University of Wyoming, Laramie, WY, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0092055X11430638">Ed A. Muñoz, Chicano Studies Program, Dept. #4297, Ross Hall 106, 1000 E. University Ave., Laramie, WY 82071, USA Email: <email>emunoz@uwyo.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio1-0092055X11430638">
<p>Ed A. Muñoz is a sociologist and an associate professor in the Department of Criminal Justice at the University of Wyoming, where he also directs the Chicano Studies Program. His research focuses on the Latina/o experience in the Midwestern and inter–Rocky Mountain regions of the United States. Previous publications primarily examine Latinas/os and the criminal justice system.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio2-0092055X11430638">
<p>Angela M. Jaime (Pit River and Maidu) is an associate professor in the Department of Educational Studies and American Indian Studies at the University of Wyoming. Her work focuses on American Indian education, social justice, and multicultural education.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio3-0092055X11430638">
<p>Deborah L. McGriff is an associate professor in the Professional Studies Department, Counselor Education program and an adjunct with African American and Diaspora Studies at the University of Wyoming. Her current research interests include multicultural competency development and training for counselors, racial and ethnic identity development for children and adolescents, and attachment in counseling and parenting.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="bio4-0092055X11430638">
<p>Adrian H. Molina is a Jurist Doctor, poet, hip-hop artist, philosopher, historian, and futurist. He teaches Media Justice Studies, Hip-Hop Studies, and Chicano Studies at the high school and college level. He has spoken and performed at youth events, conferences, cultural festivals, and colleges across the country and served as music supervisor for <italic>Papers the Movie</italic>, a documentary about undocumented youth.</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>1</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>40</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>34</fpage>
<lpage>49</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© American Sociological Association 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">American Sociological Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>In recent years, academic programs have increasingly documented student learning. For many, this practice of measuring and analyzing student learning outcomes continues as an elusive endeavor fraught with resentment and misgiving. This article describes the development of a student learning assessment plan for the University of Wyoming’s Chicano Studies Program. An initial program assessment facilitated the development of a faculty agreed-upon mission, goals, and learning outcomes. A summative course embedded assessment strategy provides direct evidence for determining student learning achievement. Student exit interviews provide additional evidence suggesting that Chicana/o Studies curricula help in cultivating a critical cultural thinking framework oriented toward social justice and activism. Current anti-immigrant and anti-Latina/o sentiments provide the context for a discussion of the study’s implications.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>program assessment</kwd>
<kwd>learning outcomes</kwd>
<kwd>student engagement</kwd>
<kwd>diversity</kwd>
<kwd>interdisciplinary courses</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Chicana/o Studies programs and curricula developed from the civil unrest of the 1950s, 1960s, and 1970s. These academic programs that center on the U.S. Chicana/o socioeconomic, historical, and cultural experience were part of an overall civil rights movement that sought redress for more than a century of individual prejudice and institutionalized discrimination directed toward the Chicano community (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0092055X11430638">Muñoz 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0092055X11430638">Ortega 2007</xref>). Now almost 50 years since the beginning of these programs, staunch opponents still characterize Chicana/Latino Studies as anti-American, chauvinistic, and separatist (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0092055X11430638">Fox News 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0092055X11430638">Huffington Post 2010</xref>).</p>
<p>Since the 1980s, more and more academic programs at institutions of higher learning are assessing student learning for accountability. The publically perceived and actual crisis in higher education during this period pushed accrediting associations and state legislatures to demand improved accountability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0092055X11430638">Cameron et al. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0092055X11430638">Moriarty and Garrett 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0092055X11430638">Suskie 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0092055X11430638">Tobin and Gebo 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0092055X11430638">Weiss 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0092055X11430638">Weiss et al. 2002</xref>). Today, assessment of student learning has taken on many forms and is described as a continuous method of (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0092055X11430638">Suskie 2004</xref>:3):</p>
<list id="list1-0092055X11430638" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>establishing clear, measurable expected outcomes of student learning;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>ensuring that students have sufficient opportunities to achieve those outcomes;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>systematically gathering, analyzing, and interpreting evidence to determine how well student learning matches our expectations; and</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>using the resulting information to understand and improve student learning.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>The assessment of student learning became a major goal of the University of Wyoming’s Academic Plan II 2004–2009 and subsequently for all of its academic programs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0092055X11430638">UW Office of Academic Affairs 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>This article describes how the University of Wyoming Chicano Studies Program faculty, with collaborative assistance from American Indian Studies and African American Studies colleagues, developed a feasible assessment cycle for student learning that has proved valuable for a variety of programmatic purposes. An initial program assessment clearly delineated the unit’s mission and goals and revamped the curriculum, which provided the basis for the assessment of student learning. A summative course embedded assessment strategy provided direct evidence for the task of measuring and analyzing six higher-order learning outcomes geared toward promoting critical thinking and social praxis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0092055X11430638">Jennings, Rienzi, and Lyda 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0092055X11430638">Moriarty and Garrett 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0092055X11430638">Peat 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0092055X11430638">Suskie 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0092055X11430638">Zamudio, Rios, and Jaime 2008</xref>). Additional exit interview data with Chicano Studies Program students (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0092055X11430638">Suskie 2004</xref>) reinforce findings suggesting that non-Eurocentric academic programs and curricula can go a long way in cultivating a critical cultural thinking framework that promotes activism and social justice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0092055X11430638">Zamudio et al. 2008</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section1-0092055X11430638">
<title>Chicano Studies at The University of Wyoming</title>
<p>The University of Wyoming’s Chicano Studies Program began its formal existence in the 1998–1999 academic year with the appointment of a full-time director responsible for developing and implementing a minor curriculum. Chicano Studies, rather than Latino Studies, became the academic unit’s name given the relatively large proportional population of Mexican Americans in the state. In addition, the historical events of the Chicano Movement were not so distant for the many students, staff, and faculty who for decades pushed for the unit’s founding. A combination of tenured and tenure-track faculty (<italic>n</italic> = 3) with joint teaching responsibilities in Chicano Studies and a primary tenure home department teaches the majority of curricular courses. A fluid pool of temporary lecturers funded by a variety of university, college, and departmental sources (<italic>n</italic> ≈ 2 to 5 annually) delivers additional instructional support.</p>
<p>A parallel review process is in place for formal faculty members who receive tenure and promotion through their home departments. While this better ensures the proper evaluation of teaching, research, and service efforts of Chicano Studies faculty, scholarly efforts in the home department typically receive more attention and reward. In any case, dual responsibilities make it difficult for faculty to negotiate a proper balance in their teaching, research, and service duties that satisfy both review committees.</p>
<p>Limited faculty resources do not preclude this College of Arts and Sciences academic unit from any upper-administration mandates, including the assessment of student learning. In fact, it has been a requirement since the 2003–2004 school year for each University of Wyoming academic unit to devote a section of its annual report to assessment of student learning activities. The Office of Academic Affairs’ assessment of student learning committee evaluates a unit’s assessment progress and subsequently provides feedback to college deans. While no formal sanctions are in place, a perception exists for many that failure to comply in a genuine manner can have informal consequences such as less serious consideration in the reallocation of instructional and/or noninstructional resources. This could be the case more so for smaller academic units viewed with less scholarly stature.</p>
<p>Inadequate faculty resources also hinder the implementation of a minor curriculum on a regular rotational basis. Not surprising, this hinders the growth of Chicano Studies Program minors, with the number never having exceeded 10 in any one semester since the program’s existence. However, the majority of Chicano Studies courses fulfill cultural context and diversity requirements for the institution’s University Studies Program (general requirements), and thus a variety of student majors from all of the university’s seven colleges enroll in courses to the limits. Students overwhelmingly are white, young, and from rural, socially conservative backgrounds. It is safe to say that this is their first real exposure to a non-Eurocentric subject matter, which tends to produce among some students within the classroom environment a certain level of uncertainty at best and resentment at worst. Instances of negative body language, combative dialogue, and/or course drops occur varying in intensity and range from semester to semester. However, most of these sentiments and behaviors lessen as the semester proceeds and students digest course materials.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0092055X11430638">
<title>Activisim, Social Justice, and Critical Cultural Thinking</title>
<sec id="section3-0092055X11430638">
<title>Establishing Student Learning Outcomes</title>
<p>Departmental administrative tasks are difficult endeavors under normal circumstances given varied faculty interests, a finite set of resources, and the time-honored tradition of self-governance. Not surprising then, faculty often are suspicious of and resistant to higher-level administrative mandates such as the assessment of student learning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0092055X11430638">Cameron et al. 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0092055X11430638">Macias 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0092055X11430638">Mindiola 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0092055X11430638">Moriarty and Garret 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0092055X11430638">Pizzaro 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0092055X11430638">Suskie 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0092055X11430638">Weiss 2002</xref>). Even so, faculty can benefit from assessment activities by coming together to discuss what and why they teach and to discuss their standards and expectations. Faculty also can benefit when they discuss and realize how an interrelated and coherent course curriculum is vital for student success. Finally, faculty can benefit from positive student learning assessment results as they offer additional evidence of teaching excellence. The articulation of these benefits works to promote a culture of assessment among the small, patchwork Chicano Studies faculty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0092055X11430638">Suskie 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>Another potential pitfall easily avoided is starting from scratch (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0092055X11430638">Suskie 2004</xref>). A cursory examination of nationally recognized Chicano/Latino Studies Web sites provided little guidance for the assessment of student learning. Many departments and programs, however, had well-articulated missions and goals. This proved to be the case as well when turning to the National Association for Chicana and Chicano Studies (NACCS) Web site, the discipline’s professional organization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0092055X11430638">National Association for Chicana and Chicano Studies 1972</xref>). Nevertheless, evident from this initial investigation was the need to differentiate program assessment from student learning assessment.</p>
<sec id="section4-0092055X11430638">
<title>Mission and goals</title>
<p>Program assessment involves a detailed review of current departmental curricular and noncurricular resources for their fit with the mission and goals of the department. Specific student learning outcomes then should follow from the overall mission and goals of the department, which in turn should align with college and university missions and goals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0092055X11430638">Suskie 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0092055X11430638">Tobin and Gebo 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>Student learning assessment competitive grant funding allowed the Chicano Studies faculty to convene off campus for a program assessment retreat. Since student activism and community advocacy were and are hallmarks for ethnic studies and women’s studies programs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0092055X11430638">Davidson 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0092055X11430638">Ginsberg 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0092055X11430638">Kidwell and Velie 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0092055X11430638">Soldatenko 2009</xref>), it was decided that outreach should be plainly evident in the program’s mission and goals. To better align with the university’s mission and goals, the program connected to several of the institution’s areas of distinction and challenges highlighted in APII (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0092055X11430638">UW Office of Academic Affairs 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>The interdisciplinary faculty felt confident in the contributions they could make to three of the six university’s areas of distinction:</p>
<list id="list2-0092055X11430638" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>cultural endeavors, the arts, and the humanities;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>history and culture of the region;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>professions and issues critical to the region.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Of the eight issues that challenged the institution, the faculty identified four that they could help ameliorate:</p>
<list id="list3-0092055X11430638" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>the learning environment (freshman interest groups);</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>diversity, internationalization, and access (study abroad);</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>structure of the curriculum (University Studies Program requirements);</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>outreach, extension, and community service (service learning).</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>With this in mind, the primary mission of the UW Chicano Studies Program is to create a high-quality teaching, research, and service program that makes available to students, the university community, the people of the state, and the broader national audience substantive knowledge about the historical cultural, political, and socioeconomic development of Chicanas/os. The six goals of the program are to provide accurate education about Chicanas/os; serve the educational needs of the state’s Mexican American population; disseminate information at local, state, and national venues; enhance Chicana/o student recruitment; advance and support Chicana/o research; and build partnerships at the University of Wyoming and throughout the state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0092055X11430638">UW Chicano Studies Program 2005b</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0092055X11430638">
<title>Instructional resources and curriculum</title>
<p>A second task addressed during this program assessment retreat was the mismatch between available instructional resources and the minor degree curriculum. Taking into consideration their own strengths and interests along with historical developments in the field of Chicana and Chicano Studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0092055X11430638">Córdova 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0092055X11430638">García 1997</xref>), the faculty created a new minor curriculum. The common core consists of 12 credit hours, which include Introduction to Chicano Studies, and then three credit hours, or one course, each from a list of courses in three agreed-upon core areas—history/social science, culture/humanities, and gender. An additional six credit hours of Chicano Studies electives from a list of noncore courses, and any of the core courses not used to fulfill each three-hour core requirement, completed the 18 hours required for a College of Arts and Sciences minor.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0092055X11430638">
<title>Student learning outcomes</title>
<p>With a well-defined mission, attainable goals, and a revised curriculum, the Chicano Studies faculty next took on the task of assessing student learning. A second competitive grant facilitated an off-campus retreat focusing on developing student learning outcomes. In a collaborative spirit, invited faculty from the American Indian Studies and African American Studies programs participated in the discussions. Their volunteer participation proved helpful not only with developing student learning outcomes but also during later stages of the process when volunteers served as independent readers for the actual assessment of student learning.</p>
<p>Also invited and offering additional insight into the process was the Office of Academic Affairs assessment coordinator. Her presence helped confirm a sense of institutional transparency and collaboration from the top, which helped curb varying levels of skepticism and mistrust (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0092055X11430638">Suskie 2004</xref>). Her comments included an assortment of do’s and don’ts about assessment and its significance for the university. In the final analysis, she made it clear that this was the opportunity for an open and honest faculty dialogue about what students should come away with after matriculating through the Chicano Studies curriculum.</p>
<p>Social justice education, another hallmark of ethnic studies and women’s studies academic programs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0092055X11430638">Davidson 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0092055X11430638">Ginsberg 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0092055X11430638">Kidwell and Velie 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0092055X11430638">Soldatenko 2009</xref>), became the guiding principle for student learning outcomes. Students taking Chicano Studies courses would broaden their knowledge base through a non-Eurocentric curriculum. This then could help cultivate critical thinking skills beneficial for activism and social justice. Consequently, borrowed and expanded concepts from a soon-to-be published article provided the basis for a critical cultural thinking framework necessary for analyzing, challenging, and dismantling individual and institutional oppressions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0092055X11430638">Zamudio et al. 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>Initial discussions of emergent student learning outcomes by Chicano Studies Program stakeholders indicated a lack of clarity and purpose. Hence, a “What Every Chicano Studies Minor Should Know” statement introduced the list of student learning outcomes (see <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-0092055X11430638">Appendix A</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0092055X11430638">UW Chicano Studies Program 2005a</xref>). Short narrative definitions and accompanying examples clarified specific student learning outcomes’ respective purposes and goals. The faculty approved revised student learning outcomes in the spring 2006 semester.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-0092055X11430638">
<title>Assessing Student Learning Outcomes</title>
<sec id="section8-0092055X11430638">
<title>Ensuring Opportunities to Achieve Outcomes</title>
<p>Upon completion of revisions, affiliated program faculty provided a project assistant with syllabi for core and noncore courses taught on a regular basis. The project assistant met individually with Chicano Studies faculty members if there were any questions about the course’s purpose, goals, or assignments. After these discussions, the project assistant mapped specific student learning outcomes onto specific courses for potential evaluation through selected assignments (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0092055X11430638">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0092055X11430638" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption><p>UW Chicano Studies Curriculum/Student Learning Outcomes Matrix, 2006</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0092055X11430638" xlink:href="10.1177_0092055X11430638-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="center"/>
<col align="center"/>
<col align="center"/>
<col align="center"/>
<col align="center"/>
<col align="center"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Course</th>
<th align="center">Organic</th>
<th align="center">Relational</th>
<th align="center">Historic</th>
<th align="center">Power</th>
<th align="center">Intersectionality</th>
<th align="center">Aesthetics</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1030: Social Justice</td>
<td>D, J</td>
<td>J, E</td>
<td>E</td>
<td>S</td>
<td>D, J</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1100: Intro</td>
<td>P, D</td>
<td>P, D</td>
<td>RP, P</td>
<td>S, P</td>
<td>P, D</td>
<td>M, PT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2070: Origins to 1900</td>
<td/>
<td>J, D</td>
<td>E</td>
<td/>
<td>E, J</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2360: Mex-American Lit</td>
<td>D</td>
<td>P, BR</td>
<td>P, D</td>
<td>D</td>
<td>D, P</td>
<td>D, P, BR</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3080: Southwest Spanish</td>
<td>D</td>
<td/>
<td>P, E</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>D, PT, E</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3200: Perspectives</td>
<td>N/A</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3800: Sociology</td>
<td>D</td>
<td>E, RP</td>
<td>E, RP</td>
<td/>
<td>D</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4470: Chicano Folklore</td>
<td>P</td>
<td>D, P</td>
<td>RP</td>
<td/>
<td>D</td>
<td>D, P</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4485: Latino Diaspora</td>
<td>S, D</td>
<td>E, D</td>
<td>E, J</td>
<td/>
<td>J, D</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4496: History of Mexico</td>
<td/>
<td>E, BR</td>
<td>E, BR</td>
<td/>
<td>E</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4675: Women of Color</td>
<td>D, J</td>
<td>RP, J</td>
<td>RP</td>
<td>PT, D</td>
<td>RP, J</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4990: Latina/o Education</td>
<td>N/A</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0092055X11430638">
<p>Assessment methods: BR = book review; CP = cultural or artistic performance; D = discussion; E = exam; J = journal; M = mural project; RP = research paper; P = paper (short reaction paper); PJ = project; PT = presentation; S = service learning; Q = quiz; N/A = not available.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0092055X11430638">
<title>Systematically Gathering, Analyzing, and Interpreting Evidence</title>
<p>Taking into consideration the program’s limited resources, the faculty devised and implemented a feasible assessment process to provide useful ongoing feedback for necessary curricular adjustments and future resource planning. Faculty members chose a direct summative evaluation embedded in the course for the task of evaluating their higher-order learning outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0092055X11430638">Jennings et al. 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0092055X11430638">Moriarty and Garrett 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0092055X11430638">Peat 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0092055X11430638">Suskie 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>Direct proof of learning is concrete, observable, clear evidence of what students have or have not learned. Higher-order learning entails the development primarily of thinking and problem-solving skills (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0092055X11430638">Suskie 2004</xref>). Summative assessment transpires after the completion of a class or program and is used for documenting and presenting student learning outcomes to internal and/or external stakeholders. Embedded assessments entrenched into the regular course requirements supply a twofold function of individual student assessment and academic program assessment.</p>
<p>The process entailed staggering the assessment of two student learning outcomes per semester over a three-semester period. Each semester, appraisal of a selected learning outcome occurred through an upper- and a lower-division course with an agreed-upon assignment/activity relevant to the outcome and using a simple holistic rubric. A simple holistic rubric is a short narrative description of the type of work identifiable and acceptable for a particular learning outcome (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0092055X11430638">Appendix B</xref>). This entails using a qualitative analysis that is more flexible and naturalistic in searching for recurring patterns and themes. The goal is not precision in measurement but rather truthful information about what students have learned (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0092055X11430638">Moriarty and Garrett 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0092055X11430638">Suskie 2004</xref>). With the accompanying descriptive narrative and example for each particular outcome as their guide, independent readers determined whether students’ work from selected assignments demonstrated sufficient evidence for the outcome’s realization. Readers oftentimes added comments to substantiate their evaluations.</p>
<p>Student learning assessment occurred after the semester was over and independent from the instructor’s individual assessment of a student’s work. To ensure anonymity and confidentiality, the Chicano Studies office manager removed students’ names and any other potential identifiers from assignments. We now turn to the assessment of student learning outcomes in the chronological order assessed. Discussions demonstrate a potential hazard, the mismatch between selected assignments and student learning outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0092055X11430638">Suskie 2004</xref>).</p>
<p><italic>Assessment of organic insight</italic> took place after the fall 2006 offering of CHST 1100: Introduction to Chicano Studies. A relatively large number of upper-division students enroll in this lower-division course to fulfill their University Studies cultural context and diversity requirements. As can be seen from the rubric in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0092055X11430638">Appendix B</xref>, organic insight involves the development of a contextual framework for understanding one’s own and others’ experiences in relation to the Chicana/o experience. The additional explanation for organic insight informs readers that by engaging in complex discussions about the diversity of the U.S. experience, students will gain an understanding of how their racialized, cultured, gendered, classed, familial, and nonfamilial backgrounds have shaped their experiences and perceptions of the world and in relation to the Chicana/o experience. The example provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0092055X11430638">Appendix B</xref> dealing with Chicano high school dropout rates could be one of many possible articulations in students’ work.</p>
<p>To illustrate, an end of the semester reflection essay assignment asked students, “Explain how your experience in CHST 1100 has impacted the way you understand history, culture, politics, and social processes.” The reflection essay aligns very well with the organic insight definition. After evaluating 26 individual essays, the independent reader concluded, “The students were very positive about their learning in the CHST 1100 class. They expressed many positive impacts on their own lives as well as the constant exposure to new knowledge and perspectives.” One student reflected about:</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>the eye-opening content taught in the class . . . . Of course, not knowing anything about Chicano culture I had a negative stereotype in my mind about how all Chicanos were. I think in my mind I had a picture painted of all Chicanos as gang banger homies. This negative stereotype that I had affected how I acted towards some of my Mexican coworkers. I now realize that I had no right to treat some of them how I did.</p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p>This lack of knowledge about much of the Chicana/o experience in U.S. society was a common thread throughout the essays and a source of frustration for many students.</p>
<p><italic>Assessment of Chicano aesthetics</italic> also occurred after the fall 2006 semester. This learning outcome entails an appreciation and awareness of the aesthetics evident in Chicano art, music, theater, literature, and other artistic expressions. More specifically, students will gain an empathy and appreciation for the artistic beauty evident in expressions of the Chicano experience. This includes expressions of life, death, cultural identity, familial experiences, and political struggle, among other things. An example would be to understand the development, significance, and function of differing elements of graffiti and muralist art in communities throughout the nation.</p>
<p>An upper-division course, CHST 4470: Chicano Folklore, provided materials for evaluation. Like CHST 1100, the course regularly fills due to its University Studies Program cultural context and diversity designations. A final project for which students selected a topic from any of the assigned course readings for a more in-depth analysis was used to assess the outcome. A portfolio format assignment organized and documented students’ research processes and findings.</p>
<p>Once again, it became clear that the assignment matched up closely with the learning outcome. Evaluation of 15 projects produced this response from the independent reader: “The students did a very good job linking what they had read and discussed in class to the various topics that they researched. I believe that the five course goals outlined in the course syllabus were met. I enjoyed reading the papers.” The independent reader’s comments on one paper describe the impact of using multimedia in developing persuasive arguments:</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>Interesting imagery in the PowerPoint slides—powerful—great discussion on how the Virgin of Guadalupe is used to socialize women into the role of “good woman, wife, mother and nurturer.” The presentation of the contemporary images casting her in a more active role challenges the historical role.</p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p><italic>Assessment of historical perspective</italic> transpired after the spring 2007 semester and was the first learning outcome not convincingly realized. Historical perspective requires the development of a critical historical viewpoint for understanding how struggles around social, economic, and political forces have shaped the traditional and contemporary Chicano Diaspora. More specifically, students will be acquainted with how particular conditions during certain historical moments such as Spanish colonization, Manifest Destiny, slavery, the U.S.–Mexico War, industrialization, nativist movements, and globalization have worked to hold Chicanas/os in disadvantaged social, economic, and political positions. For example, students will be able to articulate how past and present economic and political forces in the United States and Mexico have produced the waxing and waning for Mexican immigrant labor in the United States for well over 100 years.</p>
<p>The lower-division course CHST 2370: Chicano History, Origins to 1900, is a USP cultural context and diversity course, and like CHST 1100, it regularly fills with both lower- and upper-division students. Evaluation of a unit exam essay indicated that a good number of students did show an understanding of how history had helped shape the contemporary Chicano Diaspora. Yet there was concern from the independent reader about the appropriateness of the assignment for this particular outcome:</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>I struggled a bit in that the assessment rubric does not yield itself well to the assignment. Had I applied it “strictly,” the students would not have fared well. I am talking specifically about the part that speaks of “traditional and contemporary Chicano Diaspora,” as the assignment did not mention that this should be a part of the discussion.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, several students were able to develop persuasive historical arguments, using the early Spanish racial caste system and 19th-century U.S. racial policies to address the social, political, and economic impact of proposed immigration reforms on immigrant and nonimmigrant Chicanas/os.</p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Only 17 of the 27 (63 percent) papers analyzed sufficiently met the historical perspective outcome. This demonstrates the value of developing clear assignment instructions for students and, in turn, for the student learning assessment process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0092055X11430638">Suskie 2004</xref>).</p>
<p><italic>Assessment of relational awareness</italic> occurred after the spring 2007 semester as well. This outcome requires the development of a theoretical framework for understanding how institutional social structures influence individuals, families, and communities and, in turn, how individuals, families, and communities affect social structures through resistance, social agency, and change. More specifically, students will gain a comprehension of how large political, cultural, and social organizations create political policies and government initiatives and how such organizations and initiatives affect Chicanas/os. Equally important, students will become familiar with how Chicanos have responded to and transformed institutional organizations and policies through civil protest, political organization, and ideological resistance. For example, students will be able to discuss the historical exploitation of migrant farm workers, which eventually resulted in the ongoing struggle for farm workers’ rights that continues to be an inspiration for the contemporary Chicana/o civil rights movement.</p>
<p>A case history assignment from a dual undergraduate- and graduate-level Curriculum and Education seminar, EDCI 5870: Chicanas/Latinos and Education, cross-listed as CHST 4990: Special Topics, analyzed this learning outcome. The assignment required students to interview a Latina/Chicano who had “successfully” navigated, or who was currently navigating, the U.S. K-12 educational system. The instructor, together with his students, constructed a list of interview questions for the case history related to the theories and research they had discussed in class. As the independent reader states:</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>The assignment was very well suited to the student learning outcome. . . . In all 10 case studies of Latina/o K-12 educational experiences, there was a firm grounding of theory and research. . . . Students easily connected what they had learned in class to the “not one size fits all” educational experiences of Latinos/as. . . . I particularly enjoyed reading the stories of individual and family agency and, as well, school and community programs that played a part in educational success stories. . . . Most compelling were several student reflections vowing to incorporate what they had learned from these success stories into their professional futures. . . . For example, “I was able to learn a lot from Maria and I plan to use this valuable information she has given me in my own classroom when I become a teacher.”</p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p><italic>Assessment of power for social change</italic> ensued after the fall 2007 semester and became the second learning outcome not compellingly attained. Power for social change involves the development of a critical consciousness for a social praxis that combats oppressive racist ideologies and social structures that perpetuate individual and institutional inequalities. In particular, a critical consciousness can help students become engaged citizens who actively question the status quo and who work toward ideals and principles that they believe are relevant and worthwhile for society. For example, through service learning projects (i.e., substance use peer mentoring, community gardens, scholarship fundraising, etc.) students can gain an understanding of various roles that they can play, both personally and professionally, in battling all forms of discrimination and exploitation.</p>
<p>The lower-division CHST 1030: Social Justice in the 21st Century course provided evaluation materials for this learning outcome. The course is cross-listed with the African American and Diaspora Studies Program, the American Studies Program, the American Indian Studies Program, and the Gender and Women’s Studies Program. It is a University Studies intellectual community and diversity course and serves as the anchor course for the Social Justice in the 21st Century Freshman Interest Group. With service learning as a major course requirement, the course appears appropriate enough to evaluate an outcome that calls for social praxis and civic engagement.</p>
<p>However, the course’s instructional rotation from year to year between the respective interdisciplinary program directors can limit effective communication about the assessment of specific course goals and, even more so, the assessment of Chicano student learning outcomes. This possibility can worsen when the director is a new faculty member adjusting not only to a new course preparation but also to campus and community life. This became evident in the assessment of power for social change. As the reader states:</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>Support for the power for social change student learning outcome was mixed. . . . The selected assignment does not align well with the student learning outcome. First, what is meant by the development of a critical consciousness? Is it merely becoming aware of social, economic, and political injustice? Or does the development of a critical consciousness require that one actively engage in some sort of social praxis that works to rise above societal inequalities?</p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p>The fourth of five unit essays used to assess power for social change came from an assignment that required students to write a 1- to 2-page analysis of a “Current Debates” or “Narrative Portrait” reading from the class textbook. The assignment provided no additional instructions and produced the following appraisal:</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>Student responses to assigned readings were oftentimes mere summaries of main arguments with little critical analysis. Perhaps a restructuring of the assignment asking students to provide a potential solution to the articles main problem would produce a move toward a critical consciousness that includes praxis, knowingly or unknowingly, on an individual and/or structural basis?</p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p>The reader goes on to state:</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>After reading an article focusing on anti-Catholic sentiments, one student reflects about her ongoing interethnic relationship, an individual act that could be characterized as resisting “oppressive racist ideologies.”</p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p>The student writes:</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>For the past six months, I’ve been dating a man who is half-Hispanic. When we started dating, I was shocked by some of the fears he had. He was afraid that my parents wouldn’t like him because of his ethnicity. When I wanted to introduce him to my grandparents, he was afraid if they saw the cross tattooed on his arm, they wouldn’t like him.</p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p>The reader goes on to comment:</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>Another student, after making a deft comparison of the violence and discrimination directed towards Muslim Americans after 9/11 to that directed toward Japanese after Pearl Harbor, writes that education, an institutional structure, should be used as a tool for social justice.</p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p>The student writes:</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>I also believe that once Americans got over the shock of the attacks, more should have been done to educate our country that Middle Eastern Americans are people just like the rest of us and deserve to be respected in the same way.</p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Overall, half of the papers (9 of 18) were sufficient for the power for social change learning outcome. In the future, evaluation of student journals reflecting on their service learning accomplishments could be a better source of data. What’s more, it is important to inform non-Chicano Studies instructors about assessment activities particularly when courses are cross-listed with other programs and selected for student learning assessment.</p>
<p><italic>Assessment of intersectionality</italic> after the fall 2007 semester ended the first iteration of student learning outcomes appraisals. Intersectionality demands gaining an awareness of the intersection of race, ethnicity, class, gender, and sexual orientation as it plays out organically, relationally, historically, and politically. Students will understand better the vastly different experiences that various individuals will have, as well as the social, political, and cultural conditions that create these varied experiences. For example, students will be able to articulate the possible differences in experience between a wealthy, light-skinned, Cuban-American heterosexual male whose family fled from Cuba during Fidel Castro’s revolution versus those of a young, impoverished, very dark-skinned homosexual female who migrated to the United States from Mexico.</p>
<p>Unit exam essays from CHST 4675: U.S. Women of Color provided data to assess this learning outcome. Twelve of the 13 papers evaluated met the required rubric criterion. The independent reader provides overall thoughts:</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>I think the students did a pretty good with this in-class essay exam question, particularly since it was one of three essay questions they had to address in the 1½ hour time limit. . . . I did select the easiest question, at least for me, to use in the assessment of intersectionality. . . . A basic, you know, what intersectionality is or not question. This was accomplished through an analysis of the development of multiracial feminism, its impact on individuals, and its theoretical importance. . . . Only one student seemed confused, and my favorite line about the matrix of domination surfaced after a telling description of a Chicana woman serving time for a drug-related conviction. “This is not Lindsey Lohan’s 82 hours in jail for two DUIs.”</p></disp-quote>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0092055X11430638">
<title>Using Information to Improve Student Learning</title>
<p>Analyses of student’s coursework from reflection essays, project portfolios, unit exam essays, and case histories indicated the realization of four of the six Chicano Studies student learning outcomes—organic insight, aesthetics, relational awareness, and intersectionality. The student learning outcomes “historical perspective” and “power for social change” did not fare as well. In both cases, independent readers reasoned that selected assignments used for assessment were unclear in their instruction to students and that this lack of clarity produced essays with less than convincing support for the learning outcomes in question.</p>
<p>In the next iteration of appraising student learning outcomes, the faculty should make it a priority to reevaluate these learning outcomes in the same classes after adjusting assignments and/or developing new assignments that better fit respective learning outcome rubrics. The ongoing debate surrounding immigration reform can provide another opportunity for students to historically analyze this contemporary civil rights issue that will continue to be at the forefront of societal debate. Additionally, service-learning projects organized around this topic could better assess a student’s development of a critical consciousness and its importance for social praxis and influential societal transformation.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0092055X11430638">
<title>Estudios Chicana/O Cultivating Critical Cultural Thinking</title>
<p>Indirect supplementary evidence of student learning can further guide the next iteration of assessment, at both the programmatic and individual levels. Indirect evidence offers indications that students are most likely learning, but the support is less obvious and compelling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0092055X11430638">Suskie 2004</xref>). To this end, the director held informal exit interviews at the end of the 2007, 2008, and 2009 semesters. The sample population consisted of graduating Chicano Studies minors and graduating nonminors who had enrolled in more than one Chicano Studies course. In the years mentioned, the number of potential participants in the population ranged from five to seven individuals. Recruitment involved an informal e-mail request to potential participants inviting them to share their views of the program over lunch paid by the program. Even though the population consisted of Latinas/os and non-Latinos/as, lunch interviews consisted of three to one Latina participant(s) from year to year, both Chicano Studies minors and nonminors.</p>
<p>There are two reasons that can help explain the disproportionate sample. Interviews took place at the end of semesters when many students leave for home as soon as they can. In addition, Latinas at the University of Wyoming are highly visible in membership and leadership roles in the two most recognized Latina/o campus student organizations, Movimiento Estudiantíl Chicano de Aztlán (MEChA) and Sigma Lambda Gamma National Sorority, Inc. Moreover, many of the participants worked closely with the Chicano Studies Program faculty and staff on collaborative co-curricular events such as Hispanic Heritage Month and Semana Primavera (Spring Week), to name a few. While their decision to participate may have been out of a sense of loyalty to the program, their casual conversations about the strengths and weaknesses of the program indicate that Chicano Studies helped hone their acquired skills and leadership abilities.</p>
<p>In general, the students had high praise for the faculty and the curriculum. Their comments suggested that the faculty’s varied research and teaching expertise helped to broaden their knowledge about Chicana/o history, culture, and socioeconomic condition. Many voiced how the curriculum helped them better understand their own life experiences and family history <italic>(historical perspective)</italic>. Almost invariably comments arose about reaffirmed pride in their cultural identity with each course completed <italic>(organic insight)</italic>. One student felt that the faculty were the most beneficial aspect of the program due to their dedication and commitment to assist her in developing her potential both in and out of the classroom:</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>You could talk to them and they would understand what you were concerned about, and they would provide advice. They would write letters of support for opportunities they usually identified for you. Most of all, they helped me understand more about my family’s history here in this state—from my abuelo’s Bracero experience in the 1940s, to my parents IRCA experience in the 1980s, to my research agenda and social activism here on campus <italic>(historical perspective, organic insight, relational awareness)</italic>. Now I have to pass all this knowledge on to not only my family, but to others who have misperceptions of who we really are <italic>(power for social change)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p>
<p>With regard to what can be improved, students voiced a desire for a broader curriculum that they realized could only come about with increased faculty resources in disciplines outside of the traditional core of sociology, English, and history. More cultural studies, legal studies, health sciences, business, and research methods courses were high on the students’ wish list. Students also felt that a more inclusive curriculum concerning other Latino ethnic groups could make the university more competitive in attracting Latina/o students and faculty <italic>(intersectionality, relational awareness)</italic>.</p>
<p>When asked if they felt their Chicano Studies minor would benefit them in the end, volunteers responded positively. One student voiced that her Chicano Studies courses improved her “cultural competency,” which is becoming a skill increasingly desired by employers in many service-related professions <italic>(aesthetics)</italic>. Another student did not give direct credit to her Chicano Studies curriculum but did state that she felt she was in her current position due to the fact of her Mexican ancestry and bilingual speaking ability <italic>(relational awareness, organic insight)</italic>. Another commented that the research skills introduced to her in Chicano Studies courses would prove invaluable for her future work in the community <italic>(power for social change)</italic>.</p>
<p>Even so, many believed an Ethnic Studies major would be most beneficial as students would be able to make better connections about different people’s histories and struggles <italic>(historical perspective, intersectionality)</italic>. This would allow more effective coalition building that then could ensure better, meaningful, and resilient social, economic, and political justice <italic>(power for social change)</italic>. This sentiment came about strongest among those who also had taken courses in African American Studies, American Indian Studies, and International Studies.</p>
<p>Another indicator of critical cultural thinking emerged when the director came across a local newspaper article and picture in his files. The director recalled participating in the small but vocal campus demonstration in support of proimmigration reform held almost a month before the national May 1, 2006, “A Day Without Immigrants” boycott and rally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0092055X11430638">Hajela 2006</xref>). The director turned to one of his former students to determine the organizers of this seemingly impromptu rally on the University of Wyoming campus in Laramie. Her e-mail response follows (A. Magaña, personal communication, July 23, 2010):</p>
<p>
<disp-quote><p>The idea behind organizing the first immigration rally was more of a reaction and frustration with the fact that our families and our histories were being attacked as Latinos across the US. At the time, I viewed it more as an attack on immigrants from Mexico, like my parents and family members, but as you may have seen in the picture from the first immigration rally one of the women is from the reservation. We began looking at anti-immigrant attacks as attacks on all indigenous peoples <italic>(organic insight, historical perspective)</italic>.</p>
<p>It was a small-scale event at the University of Wyoming and the organizing group consisted of women who were both members of MEChA and Sigma Lambda Gamma National Sorority, Inc. We wanted to make sure that our campus and community knew that we were also in support of immigrants’ rights and that our contributions both to our communities and the University at large should be valued <italic>(relational awareness, power for social change)</italic>. I think by this point, it’s fair to say, that we had all taken Chicano Studies courses and/or American Indian Studies courses and we had a much better understanding of our region’s history and its relation to Mexico <italic>(intersectionality).</italic></p>
<p>We have always had the support of the Chicano Studies Department and the Latino and Native American faculty on campus. In many ways, it is because of these professors and the knowledge we gained in their classes that we were able to be successful and to also become civically engaged in demanding just change.</p>
<p>These women and I continue to use those same skills and knowledge to further social justice causes of our own personal interest. Perhaps at the time I didn’t think about it as becoming civically engaged, yet I was a young educated Latina who refused to let another system forget her Latino, Indigenous, African, and working class peoples contributions to a country that was just as much hers as it was to the pilgrims who landed years ago <italic>(power for social change)</italic>.</p></disp-quote>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-0092055X11430638">
<title>Discussion and Conclusion</title>
<p>Assessment work is tedious and challenging, particularly for a small academic program with part-time faculty and staff and a limited budget. Nevertheless, assessment plans should be based on commonsense principles, and faculty can and should take reasonable steps to ensure that students are actually learning what the faculty expects them to learn (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0092055X11430638">Suskie 2004</xref>). We believe that our work adds to the national discussion on assessment of student learning in general and for Chicana/Latino Studies in particular (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0092055X11430638">Guerrero 2006</xref>). What’s more, our method can serve as a model for other academic programs with similar instructional and budgetary constraints and by larger academic units either solely or in combination with other assessment strategies.</p>
<p>Off-campus retreats helped in nurturing a culture of assessment among the UW Chicano Studies faculty and facilitated their engagement in program and student learning assessment. From this followed a set of activist program goals and social justice–oriented learning outcomes appropriate not only for Chicano Studies but for other related disciplines as well. For example, learning outcomes described here are comparable to what highly regarded sociologists rank as four of the top five important learning outcomes for sociology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0092055X11430638">Persell 2010</xref>:334–35; numerical ordering and material in parentheses ours)—(1) show the relevance and reality of structural factors in social life <italic>(relational awareness, power for social change)</italic>; (2) place an issue in a larger context <italic>(aesthetics, historical perspective)</italic>; (3) identify and offer explanations for social inequality <italic>(organic insight, intersectionality)</italic>; . . . and (5) compare and contrast one’s own context with those in other parts of the United States and world <italic>(aesthetics, organic insight, intersectionality)</italic>.</p>
<p>In addition, continuous program and student learning assessment does have many benefits. An unexpected outcome from this process was newfound levels of local, regional, and national notoriety for the program. This has proved invaluable in recent years by providing an external network of colleagues to provide advice on other programmatic issues including curricular development, noncurricular programs and events, and external tenure and promotion reviews. Positive assessment results from individual faculty courses have supplemented evidence of excellence in teaching for successful tenure and promotion packets. Many Chicano Studies Program students have gone on to graduate school and/or successful professional careers.</p>
<p>Assessment findings from direct and indirect data presented here indicate that the University of Wyoming Chicano Studies faculty is experiencing success in achieving their desired student learning outcomes. Two caveats necessitate explanation. Independent readers did not note instances of possible hostility and/or resistance to course content in selected assignments that one might expect given some students’ negative sentiments toward course content mentioned earlier. It is possible that students’ assigned work for a letter grade in part is driving the positive outcome observed from the data. Hence, the faculty should collect supplementary assessment data for increased assurance that students are developing a critical cultural thinking framework that promotes social activism and justice. The implementation of short semester-end assessment surveys in all Chicano Studies courses can help in this endeavor. Likewise, a more diverse exit interview sample needs consideration. Offering invitations to appropriate individuals for their participation in exit interviews at midsemester both can help increase diversity and the number of participants.</p>
<p>Regardless, continued assessment activity can help build the justification for the growth of a Chicano Studies major at the University of Wyoming. In addition to another iteration of direct evaluation of student learning outcomes and informal exit interviews, future assessment activities will include an alumni survey facilitated through social networking Web sites and in conjunction with the newly established University of Wyoming Multicultural Alumni Committee. Alumni surveys also can help in future planning efforts such as the feasibility of an expanded U.S. Latino Diaspora Studies Program. New and expanded Chicano/Latina Studies Programs can go a long way in offsetting current anti-Latino sentiments in general and anti-Latino immigrant sentiments in particular.</p>
<p>Finally, as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0092055X11430638">Hohm (2008</xref>:137) points out, higher-level administrators tend to appreciate an academic program that teaches “many students; values and incorporates diversity; produces research aimed at ameliorating societal problems; and is involved in interdisciplinary and multidisciplinary projects.” Also important for the institutional success of academic programs is the alignment of its mission with the mission of the college and university. Examination of institutions of higher education missions, goals, and objectives almost invariably reveals the need for cultivating critical thinking skills among their students for a productive, innovative, and engaged citizenry. We believe we have shown that ethnic studies curricula such as that of the University of Wyoming Chicano Studies Program can do much for the cultivation of critical cultural thinking.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<app-group>
<app id="app1-0092055X11430638">
<title>Appendix A: Chicano Studies Student Learning Outcomes, Chicano Studies Program, University of Wyoming</title>
<sec id="section13-0092055X11430638">
<title>What Every Chicano Studies Minor Should Know</title>
<p>Chicano Studies courses emphasize perspectives that are historical and contemporary, theoretical and practical, and critical and aesthetic. These perspectives help to develop an understanding of oppression and resistance at the individual, institutional, and ideological levels.</p>
<p>Upon completion of the University of Wyoming Chicano Studies minor curriculum, students will have an awareness and appreciation for the Chicana/o experience, particularly as the Chicano experience is expressed in the following concepts and principles of organic insight, relational awareness, historical perspective, power for social change, intersectionality, and aesthetics.</p>
<sec id="section14-0092055X11430638">
<title>Organic insight: the development of a contextual framework for understanding one’s own and others’ experiences in relation to the Chicana/o experience</title>
<p>By engaging in complex discussions about the diversity of the U.S. experience, students will gain an understanding of how their racialized, cultured, gendered, classed, familial, and nonfamilial backgrounds have shaped their experiences and perceptions of the world and in relation to the Chicana/o experience. For example, students will be able to articulate various social, economic, political, and cultural factors for disproportionately high Chicano high school dropout rates and possible solutions to this problem.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0092055X11430638">
<title>Relational awareness: the development of a theoretical framework for understanding how institutional social structures affect individuals, families, and communities and, in turn, how individuals, families, and communities affect social structures through resistance, social agency, and change</title>
<p>Students will gain a comprehension of how large political, cultural, and social organizations are created through political policies and government initiatives and how such policies and organizations affect Chicanas/os. In turn, students will become familiar with how Chicanos have responded to and transformed institutional policies and organizations through civil protest, political organization, and ideological resistance. For example, students will be able to discuss the historical exploitation of migrant farm workers, which eventually resulted in the ongoing struggle for farm workers’ rights that continues to be an inspiration for the contemporary Chicana/o civil rights movement.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0092055X11430638">
<title>Historical perspective: the development of a critical historical viewpoint for understanding how struggles around social, economic, and political forces have shaped the traditional and contemporary Chicano Diaspora</title>
<p>Students will be acquainted with how particular conditions during certain historical moments such as Spanish colonization, Manifest Destiny, slavery, the U.S.–Mexico War, industrialization, nativist Appendix A: (continued)movements, and globalization have worked to hold Chicanas/os in disadvantaged social, economic, and political positions. For example, students will be able to articulate how past and present economic and political forces in the United States and Mexico have produced the waxing and waning for Mexican immigrant labor in the United States for well over 100 years.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0092055X11430638">
<title>Power for social change: the development of a critical consciousness for a social praxis that combats oppressive racist ideologies and social structures that perpetuate individual and institutional inequalities</title>
<p>A critical consciousness can help students become engaged citizens who actively question the status quo and who work toward ideals and principles that they believe are relevant and worthwhile for society. For example, through service learning projects (i.e., substance use peer mentoring, community gardens, scholarship fundraising, etc.) students can gain an understanding of various roles that they can play, both personally and professionally, in battling all forms of discrimination and exploitation.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-0092055X11430638">
<title>Intersectionality: gaining an awareness of the intersection of race, ethnicity, class, gender, and sexual orientation as it plays out organically, relationally, historically, and politically</title>
<p>Students will be able to understand the vastly different experiences that various individuals will have as well as the social, political, and cultural conditions that create their experiences. For example, students will be able to articulate the possible differences in experience between a wealthy, light-skinned, Cuban-American heterosexual male whose family fled from Cuba during Fidel Castro’s revolution versus those of a young, impoverished, very dark-skinned homosexual female who migrated to the United States from Mexico.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0092055X11430638">
<title>Chicano aesthetics: the development of an appreciation and awareness of the aesthetics evident in Chicano art, music, theater, literature, and other artistic expressions</title>
<p>Students will gain an empathy and appreciation for the artistic beauty evident in expressions of the Chicano experience, including but not limited to life, death, cultural identity, familial experiences, and political struggle. For example, students will come to understand the development, significance, and function of differing elements of graffiti and muralist art in communities throughout the nation.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0092055X11430638" position="float">
<label>Appendix B:</label>
<caption><p>Organic Insight Rubric</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0092055X11430638" xlink:href="10.1177_0092055X11430638-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">The assignment shows the development of a contextual framework for understanding one’s own and others’ experiences in relation to the Chicana/o experience. By engaging in complex discussions about the diversity of the U.S. experience, students will gain an understanding of how their racialized, cultured, gendered, classed, familial, and nonfamilial backgrounds have shaped their experiences and perceptions of the world and in relation to the Chicana/o experience.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="3">For example, students will be able to articulate various social, economic, political, and cultural factors for disproportionately high Chicano high school dropout rates and possible solutions to this problem.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>One’s own experiences</td>
<td>Other’s experiences</td>
<td>Relation to the Chicano experience</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p><bold>Comments:</bold></p>
</sec>
</sec>
</app>
</app-group>
<ack><p>The authors thank the three anonymous reviewers and the editor for their helpful suggestions and comments.</p></ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p>The reviewers for this manuscript were, in alphabetical order, Jeanne Ballantine, Peter Callero, and Alicia Suarez.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>Jeanne</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>Phillip</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stavenhagen-Helgren</surname><given-names>Tina</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kobritz</surname><given-names>Barbara</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2002</year>. “<article-title>Assessment as Critical Praxis: A Community College Experience</article-title>.” <source>Teaching Sociology</source> <volume>30</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>414</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Córdova</surname><given-names>Teresa</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1993</year>. <source>Chicana Voices: Intersections of Class, Race, and Gender</source>. <publisher-loc>Albuquerque, NM</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of New Mexico Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>Jeanette R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2010</year>. <source>African American Studies</source>. <publisher-loc>Edinburgh, Scotland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>FOX News</collab>. <year>2010</year>. “<article-title>Arizona Legislature Passes Bill to Curb ‘Chauvinism’ in Ethnic Studies Programs</article-title>.” <source>FOXNews.com</source>, <month>April</month> <day>30</day>. <access-date>Retrieved June 13, 2010</access-date> (<comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2010/04/30/arizona-legislature-passes-banning-ethnic-studies-programs/">http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2010/04/30/arizona-legislature-passes-banning-ethnic-studies-programs/</ext-link></comment>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>García</surname><given-names>Alma M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1997</year>. <source>Chicana Feminist Thought: The Basic Historical Writings</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ginsberg</surname><given-names>Alice E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2008</year>. <source>The Evolution of American Women’s Studies: Reflections on Triumphs, Controversies, and Change</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guerrero</surname><given-names>Carlos</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2006</year>. “<article-title>Student Learning Outcomes</article-title>.” <source>Noticias de NACCS: National Association for Chicana and Chicano Studies Newsletter</source> <volume>34</volume>(<issue>3</issue>). <access-date>Retrieved July 23, 2010</access-date> (<comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.naccs.org/naccs/Noticias_de_NACCS_Archives_EN.asp?SnID=368457997">http://www.naccs.org/naccs/Noticias_de_NACCS_Archives_EN.asp?SnID=368457997</ext-link></comment>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hajela</surname><given-names>Deepti</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2006</year>. “<article-title>Demonstrations Fill the Streets: Pro-Immigration Demonstrations Take Place across the Nation Demanding Citizenship</article-title>.” <source>Laramie Boomerang</source>, <month>April</month> <day>11</day>, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>, <fpage>5</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hohm</surname><given-names>Charles F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2008</year>. “<article-title>Thirty Five Years of Viewing Sociology as an External Program Reviewer: A Dean’s Perspective on How Administrators View Sociology</article-title>.” <source>The American Sociologist</source> <volume>39</volume>(<issue>2-3</issue>):<fpage>130</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>Huffington Post</collab>. <year>2010</year>. “<article-title>Arizona Ethnic Studies Classes Banned, Teachers with Accents Can No Longer Teach English</article-title>.” <source>Huffington Post</source>, <month>April</month> <day>30</day>. <access-date>Retrieved June 13, 2010</access-date> (<comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2010/04/30/arizona-ethnic-studies-cl_n_558731.html">http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2010/04/30/arizona-ethnic-studies-cl_n_558731.html</ext-link></comment>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>Patricia K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rienzi</surname><given-names>Beth</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lyda</surname><given-names>Laramee</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2006</year>. “<article-title>Assessing Student Learning: A Case Study</article-title>.” <source>Teaching Sociology</source> <volume>34</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>286</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kidwell</surname><given-names>Clara Sue</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Velie</surname><given-names>Alan</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2005</year>. <source>Native American Studies</source>. <publisher-loc>Lincoln, NE</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Nebraska Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Macias</surname><given-names>Reynaldo</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2005</year>. “<article-title>‘El Grito en Aztlán’: Voice and Presence in Chicana/o Studies</article-title>.” <source>International Journal of Qualitative Studies in Education</source> <volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mindiola</surname><given-names>Tatcho</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2005</year>. “<article-title>Chicano Studies: On the Margins or Part of the Academy?</article-title>” <source>International Journal of Qualitative Studies in Education</source> <volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moriarty</surname><given-names>Laura J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garrett</surname><given-names>Jennifer Jenkins</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2008</year>. “<article-title>Criminal Justice Assessment: Staying Ahead of the Bullet</article-title>.” <source>Criminal Justice Studies</source> <volume>21</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Muñoz</surname><given-names>Carlos</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>
</person-group> <year>2007</year>. <source>Youth, Identity, Power: The Chicano Movement</source>. <edition>Revised and expanded edition.</edition> <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Verso</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>National Association for Chicana and Chicano Studies</collab>. <year>1972</year>. “<article-title>Mission Statement</article-title>.” <access-date>Retrieved June 16, 2010</access-date> (<comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.naccs.org/naccs/Mission_EN.asp?SnID=1129349989">http://www.naccs.org/naccs/Mission_EN.asp?SnID=1129349989</ext-link></comment>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>Carlos</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2007</year>. “<article-title>Introduction: Chicano Studies as a Discipline</article-title>.” Pp. <fpage>vii</fpage>–<lpage>xv</lpage> in <source>Chicana/o Studies: Survey and Analysis</source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Bixler-Márquez</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>C. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <edition>3rd ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>Dubuque, IA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Kendall Hunt</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peat</surname><given-names>Barbara</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2008</year>. “<article-title>Assessment and Shoes—It’s All about Fit: A Case Study of a Multi-Method, Multi-Level Approach</article-title>.” <source>Criminal Justice Studies</source> <volume>21</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>253</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Persell</surname><given-names>Caroline Hodges</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2010</year>. “<article-title>How Sociological Leaders Rank Learning Goals for Introductory Sociology</article-title>.” <source>Teaching Sociology</source> <volume>38</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>330</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pizzaro</surname><given-names>Marcos</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2004</year>. “<article-title>Searching for Curanderas: A Quest to Revive Chicana/o Studies</article-title>.” <source>Journal of Latinos and Education</source> <volume>3</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Soldatenko</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <source>Chicano Studies: The Genesis of a Discipline</source>. <publisher-loc>Tucson, AZ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Arizona Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Suskie</surname><given-names>Linda</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2004</year>. <source>Assessing Student Learning: A Common Sense Guide</source>. <publisher-loc>Bolton, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Anker</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tobin</surname><given-names>Kimberly</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gebo</surname><given-names>Erika</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2008</year>. “<article-title>Assessing Student Learning and Departmental Effectiveness through an Undergraduate Comprehensive Exam</article-title>.” <source>Criminal Justice Studies</source> <volume>21</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>UW Chicano Studies Program</collab>. <year>2005a</year>. “<article-title>Assessment of Student Learning</article-title>.” <publisher-loc>Laramie, WY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Wyoming</publisher-name>. <access-date>Retrieved July 14, 2011</access-date> (<comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uwyo.edu/chicanostudies/studentlearning-outcomes/index.html">http://www.uwyo.edu/chicanostudies/studentlearning-outcomes/index.html</ext-link></comment>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>UW Chicano Studies Program</collab>. <year>2005b</year>. “<article-title>Mission Statement and Goals</article-title>.” <publisher-loc>Laramie, WY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Wyoming</publisher-name>. <access-date>Retrieved July 14, 2011</access-date> (<comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uwyo.edu/chicanostudies/mission-statement-goals/index.html">http://www.uwyo.edu/chicanostudies/mission-statement-goals/index.html</ext-link></comment>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab>UW Office of Academic Affairs</collab>. <year>2009</year>. <source>Taking Stock: Reflections on a Decade of Academic Planning</source>. <publisher-loc>Laramie, WY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Wyoming</publisher-name>. <access-date>Retrieved June 15, 2010</access-date> (<comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://uwadmnweb.uwyo.edu/acadaffairs/Univ_Plan/ReportCard_2008.pdf">http://uwadmnweb.uwyo.edu/acadaffairs/Univ_Plan/ReportCard_2008.pdf</ext-link></comment>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>Gregory L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2002</year>. “<article-title>The Current Status of Assessment in Sociology Departments</article-title>.” <source>Teaching Sociology</source> <volume>30</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>391</fpage>–<lpage>402</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>Gregory L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cosby</surname><given-names>Janet R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Habel</surname><given-names>Shelly K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>Chad M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>Carolee</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2002</year>. “<article-title>Improving the Assessment of Student Learning: Advancing a Research Agenda in Sociology</article-title>.” <source>Teaching Sociology</source> <volume>30</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0092055X11430638">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zamudio</surname><given-names>Margaret</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rios</surname><given-names>Francisco A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jaime</surname><given-names>Angela M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>2008</year>. “<article-title>Thinking Critically about Difference: Analytical Tools for the 21st Century</article-title>.” <source>Equity &amp; Excellence in Education</source> <volume>41</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>