<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review" xml:lang="EN">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EHQ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spehq</journal-id>
<journal-title>European History Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0265-6914</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7110</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0265691413478542j</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0265691413478542j</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>C Scott Dixon, <italic>Protestants: A History from Wittenberg to Pennsylvania 1517–1740</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Atherstone</surname><given-names>Andrew</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>43</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>349</fpage>
<lpage>351</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec19-0265691413478542j"><title>C Scott Dixon, <italic>Protestants: A History from Wittenberg to Pennsylvania 1517–1740</italic>, Wiley-Blackwell: Oxford, 2010; 269 pp.; 9781405150842, £75.00 (hbk)</title>
<sec id="sec20-0265691413478542j"><title><bold>Reviewed by:</bold> Andrew Atherstone, <italic>Wycliffe Hall, Oxford, UK</italic></title>
<p>Despite its misleadingly broad title, Scott Dixon’s history of early Protestantism is not a general introduction but a closely argued and innovative interpretation, approached through the narrow lens of order and authority. His central thesis is that Protestantism is best understood not by its external conflict against Roman Catholicism, but by its own internal struggle between gospel and law, or freedom and constraint. Who are the authentic Christians? How is the true church gathered? What should Protestant society look like? Embracing all these questions, Dixon maintains, is the overarching tension between liberty and godly order. His concern in this volume is sociological not theological, an investigation of public religion. Dixon leads his readers with agility off the beaten track, supplying an extensive array of local case studies from Europe and North America to illustrate his wider arguments. The chronological and geographical diversity of his material, in transatlantic perspective, is a key strength in this sustained analysis.</p>
<p>Martin Luther in the 1520s and William Penn in the 1680s act as bookends in Dixon’s narrative. He shows that the spontaneity and theological freedom of the early Reformation was brought to an abrupt end by the Peasants’ War and the millenarian antics of Thomas Müntzer, which turned Luther’s movement by reaction into ‘a crusade for order’ (35). As soon as the Protestants of Wittenberg and Zurich gained power, they sought to restrain the religious enthusiasts on whom they had once relied. Although the priesthood of all believers was widely taught as a spiritual reality, the social distinctions between pastor and parishioner remained as entrenched as ever. In Protestant kingdoms the Bible could be read in the vernacular by the ploughman, but was still only to be interpreted by a few properly trained clerics, often doctrinaire and disciplinarian. Evangelical communes celebrated their freedom from the Roman yoke as an act of emancipation and deliverance from Babylonian captivity, but in practice it was ‘one part liberation and one part oppression’ (67). Dixon’s stimulating proposal is that the history of Protestantism is the evolving story of attempts to resolve this inner contradiction. At the end of the seventeenth century William Penn faced the same dilemma as Luther: ‘liberty without obedience is confusion, and obedience without liberty is slavery’ (221). Penn’s vision was a colony in the New World free of confessional boundaries, a refuge for Quakers suffering under the re-imposition of order in Restoration England. Dixon suggests that the Quaker emphasis upon direct revelation through the Holy Spirit, ‘the ingrafted word’ available to every person, was the voice of German radicalism reborn. Yet Penn knew that to do away with order in his utopian city of Philadelphia would bring chaos. This tension was not easily resolved.</p>
<p>The triumph of reformation order ushered in ‘the confessional age’, roughly between the Peace of Augsburg (1555) and the Peace of Westphalia (1648), when doctrinal confessions and catechisms were abundant and theological latitude was severely restricted. Protestants had their magisterium, no less than Roman Catholics. Yet the surprising resurgence of the radical tradition, driven by German Pietism, brought marginalized and persecuted Protestant communities back to the centre at the expense of the old magisterial paradigm. Their concern for Christian renewal brought an emphasis upon godliness rather than orthodoxy, spiritual gifts rather than liturgical office, and personal faith rather than ecclesiastical institutions. Bible study groups and other ‘conventicles’ supplanted church services, even providing the sacrament of the Lord’s Supper without clerical authority. Distinctions between pastors and laity began to evaporate, so that women found roles as prophets and theologians with large regional followings.</p>
<p>Dixon argues that the rise of the evangelical movement from the 1730s must be understood within the context of these debates over order and freedom. George Whitefield and the Wesley brothers brought together a unique synthesis of English Puritanism and German Pietism. Here Dixon’s monograph dovetails well with the recent historiography on the origins of evangelicalism and the extent to which it was a new phenomenon with Protestantism (see Michael Haykin and Kenneth Stewart, eds, <italic>The Emergence of Evangelicalism: Exploring Historical Continuities</italic>, 2008). Although Dixon stops short of pursuing his analysis much into the eighteenth century, he concludes persuasively that evangelicalism had been ‘two centuries in the making’ (228) and that this peculiarly modern brand of Protestant religion was the <italic>dénouement</italic> of the theological tensions which had been simmering beneath the surface ever since Luther launched his crusade.</p>
</sec>
</sec>

</body>
</article>