<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DEM</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spdem</journal-id>
<journal-title>Dementia</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1471-3012</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-2684</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1471301211419018</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1471301211419018</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>How older women who live alone with dementia make sense of their experiences: An interpretative phenomenological analysis</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Frazer</surname><given-names>Soraya M.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1471301211419018">Solihull Mental Health Foundation Trust, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Oyebode</surname><given-names>Jan R.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1471301211419018"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff2-1471301211419018">The University of Birmingham, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Cleary</surname><given-names>Adam</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff3-1471301211419018">Solihull Mental Health Foundation Trust, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1471301211419018">Jan R. Oyebode, School of Psychology, University of Birmingham, Edgbaston, Birmingham B15 2TT, UK Email: <email>j.r.oyebode@bham.ac.uk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>11</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>677</fpage>
<lpage>693</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2011 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This paper investigates the subjective experiences of older women living alone with Alzheimer’s disease, vascular or mixed dementia. Eight women were interviewed to explore how they managed their identities and coped with day-to-day living, in the absence of a significant co-resident other who might reflect them back to themselves. Through interpretative phenomenological analysis themes emerged about loss, embodiment, adapting, awareness, safety, relationships, exclusion and loneliness. Memory loss had the most significant impact through loss of independence. However, the women were actively engaged in re-constructing their sense of self, using a variety of coping strategies. Relationships with friends, neighbours and attendance at memory clubs were important. A search for meaningful relationships was apparent, conflicting with feeling vulnerable and a consequent desire for self protection.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Alzheimer’s</kwd>
<kwd>dementia</kwd>
<kwd>living alone</kwd>
<kwd>sense of self</kwd>
<kwd>women</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1471301211419018">Alzheimer’s Society (2000)</xref> estimates that one third of people with dementia live alone. Their report, <italic>Home Alone</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1471301211419018">Alzheimer’s Society, 1994</xref>) predicted that the number of people with dementia living alone in the UK would almost double by 2011 to reach an estimated 245,000. A key recommendation was the need to focus on this group in order to provide information for planning services. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1471301211419018">Webber, Fox &amp; Brunette (1994)</xref> found people with dementia who lived alone were more likely to be female, older and poorer. In comparison to people with dementia living with others, they were less likely to use hospital, day centre or nursing home care or see physicians on a regular basis. It has been found that those who are unmarried and living alone with no friends are at a higher risk of developing dementia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1471301211419018">Fratiglioni, Wang, Ericsson, Maytan &amp; Winblad, 2000</xref>) and that individuals living alone are diagnosed with dementia at an earlier stage than those living with others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1471301211419018">Sibley et al., 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>Social experiences are vital in shaping a person’s subjective experience of life, especially in relation to an individual’s sense of self as he or she ages. However, sense of self is threatened by dementia because it attacks long past, as well as recent, memories. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1471301211419018">Mills &amp; Coleman (1994)</xref> state that much can be done to preserve a coherent sense of self by encouragement to those with dementia to recall their story; however, a point occurs when a person’s story must be sustained by others, meaning that people with dementia therefore rely on others to remind them of their past selves and to reflect them back to themselves on a day-to-day basis. This presents obvious difficulties for people who live alone, rendering them especially vulnerable to erosion of sense of self. The importance of relationships with others in maintaining personhood has been extensively explored by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1471301211419018">Kitwood (1997)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1471301211419018">Kitwood and Bredin (1992)</xref>, and others (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1471301211419018">Cotrell &amp; Schulz, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1471301211419018">Snyder, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1471301211419018">Harris, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1471301211419018">Sabat, Fath, Moghaddam and Harre’s (1999)</xref> tripartite conception of self is a social constructionist model, whereby Self 1 is the self of personal identity expressed through the indexical ‘I’. It is not reliant on others for its existence, and hence should not be damaged by dementia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1471301211419018">Sabat, 2001</xref>). Recent research by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1471301211419018">Clare, Rowlands, Bruce and Downs (2008)</xref>, demonstrating retained awareness of the self in persons with severe dementia, has supported this assertion. Self 2 comprises the person’s attributes, and beliefs about those attributes, and is divided into the restricted Self 2 (those attributes and beliefs held at any one time), and the unrestricted Self 2 (those attributes and beliefs which are stable throughout the lifespan). Self 3 is the social presentation of selfhood, or persona. A person can be a friend, neighbour, spouse, or parent, and have different personae associated with each of these social relationships. Sabat and colleagues suggest that it is in the attempts to construct and produce a Self 3 that we may find evidence for assaults on the self-esteem of the person with AD. The individual maintains a worthy public persona (Self 3) by reaffirming their life to others, by maintaining relationships with others, and by referring back to aspects of his or her former personae in an earlier social world, thereby maintaining pride and integrity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1471301211419018">Sabat et al., 1999</xref>). Without another person to participate in the construction of Self 3, the person’s attributes and beliefs about those attributes (i.e. Self 2) may become harder to sustain.</p>
<p>It is clear from research to date that although studies have been undertaken to explore the personal experiences of individuals with dementia, little has been undertaken to explore how individuals who live in the absence of an other manage their identities and cope with dementia. This study sought to explore how women who live alone with dementia see themselves and how they cope in their day-to-day lives, in the absence of someone a) to reflect their identities back to them, and b) to help them with day-to-day living.</p>
<sec id="sec1-1471301211419018" sec-type="methods"><title>Method</title>
<sec id="sec2-1471301211419018"><title>Design</title>
<p>Interpretative phenomenological analysis (IPA) was used as a methodological approach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1471301211419018">Smith, 1996</xref>). IPA is concerned with how individuals construe, make sense of, and talk about their experiences, aiming to capture the quality and texture of individuals' experiences and understand the meanings the experience has for them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1471301211419018">Smith, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1471301211419018">Willig, 2008</xref>). It views meanings of participants as social constructions, not objective truths and requires the interviewer to be reflexive, in attending to his or her own personal and professional reactions to the experiences of participants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1471301211419018">Smith &amp; Osborn, 2008</xref>). IPA is based on idiographic analysis which means it examines objects of interest in considerable detail, thus requiring relatively small sample sizes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-1471301211419018" sec-type="subjects"><title>Participants</title>
<p>Eight women with a diagnosis of Alzheimer’s Disease (AD) and/or mixed vascular dementia and AD were interviewed (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1471301211419018">Table 1</xref>). Inclusion criteria were that they lived alone, were proficient in English, willing and able to talk about themselves and give informed consent and, without any major psychiatric problems, apart from possible reactive depression or anxiety as a result of their diagnosis. The Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1471301211419018">Folstein, Folstein, &amp; McHugh, 1975</xref>) was recorded for all participants. At the time of referral, three had scores in the mild range of cognitive impairment (MMSE 20−26) and five were within the moderate to severe range (MMSE 10−19).
<table-wrap id="table1-1471301211419018" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Participants’ demographic details</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1471301211419018" xlink:href="10.1177_1471301211419018-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead align="left">
<tr><th>Participant</th>
<th>Age</th>
<th>MMSE score</th>
<th>Marital status</th>
<th>Previous occupation</th>
<th>Diagnosis</th>
<th>Previous co-resident</th></tr></thead>
<tbody align="left">
<tr>
<td>Ruby</td>
<td>87</td>
<td>26/30</td>
<td>Widowed</td>
<td>Housewife?</td>
<td>AD</td>
<td>Husband</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Alice</td>
<td>82</td>
<td>24/30</td>
<td>Single</td>
<td>Medical professional</td>
<td>AD</td>
<td>Mother</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Emily</td>
<td>75</td>
<td>17/30</td>
<td>Widowed</td>
<td>Housewife?</td>
<td>AD</td>
<td>Husband</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Grace</td>
<td>75</td>
<td>19/30</td>
<td>Divorced</td>
<td>Factory worker</td>
<td>Multi-infarct dementia</td>
<td>Children</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Vera</td>
<td>83</td>
<td>18/30</td>
<td>Widowed</td>
<td>Factory worker</td>
<td>Mixed multi-infarct dementia</td>
<td>Husband</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Florence</td>
<td>95</td>
<td>14/30</td>
<td>Widowed</td>
<td>Housewife</td>
<td>AD</td>
<td>Husband</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Hilda</td>
<td>79</td>
<td>24/30</td>
<td>Widowed</td>
<td>Housewife (husband in army)</td>
<td>Mild dementia</td>
<td>Husband</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Lilly</td>
<td>89</td>
<td>18/30</td>
<td>Widowed</td>
<td>Pharmacy assistant</td>
<td>AD</td>
<td>Husband</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec4-1471301211419018" sec-type="methods"><title>Procedure</title>
<p>After obtaining appropriate ethical approval, I (Frazer) recruited and took informed consent from participants from a mental health service for older people in a major urban city in the UK. I then undertook, and recorded, approximately hour-long interviews with each participant using a semi-structured interview guide. The interview gave the women the opportunity to talk about the impact of their memory problems, past and present views of themselves, their relationships with others, coping strategies, and how they manage living alone.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-1471301211419018"><title>Analysis</title>
<p>The first stage of analysis involved reading and re-reading, and close line by line, phenomenological coding of the experiential claims, concerns and understandings of each participant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1471301211419018">Larkin, Watts, &amp; Clifton, 2006</xref>). In the second stage (interpretative level) a ‘dialogue’ was created between myself, the coded data and psychological knowledge about what it might mean for participants to have their concerns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1471301211419018">Larkin et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1471301211419018">Smith, 2004</xref>). I then compiled a list of emerging themes for each transcript which I clustered into groups. From these I identified main themes and compiled a table of master themes. Fellow IPA researchers and co-authors also analysed parts of transcripts to ensure credibility and trustworthiness. Supervision enabled me to develop ideas and look at the data from different angles, ensuring trustworthiness and transferability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1471301211419018">Lincoln &amp; Guba, 1985</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-1471301211419018" sec-type="results"><title>Results and discussion</title>
<p>We identified four overarching themes: 1) Living with a changing sense of self; 2) A fluctuating awareness of memory problems; 3) Seeking sanctuary versus risking danger; and 4) Being with others − connection versus disconnection. We will discuss each in turn, reflect upon the process as appropriate, and end with a conclusion.</p>
<sec id="sec7-1471301211419018"><title>Theme 1. Living with a changing sense of self</title>
<p><italic>Loss of past self.</italic> Participants described a number of losses during their lives. For most who had been married the death of their husbands was described as their biggest loss:
<disp-quote>
<p>I came in in the morning with a cup of tea for him and found him gone! That was a bit of a shock − you say daft things though, his arm was hanging down and I said, ‘What have I done to deserve this?’ and daft things, and went back in the kitchen and drank his tea! [laughs] (Emily)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>This was recounted less than a minute into the interview and the way the story is retold, illustrates how Emily uses humour to protect herself from the shock then, and pain now, and also minimises it in her language. Saying it so soon implies it is very important to her to convey a Self 2 (life long attributes) with being married being a core part of her identity. Humour was used by most participants as a way of coping with psychic pain. Hilda initially found the loss of her husband too painful to talk about, though later said:
<disp-quote>
<p>… nobody could replace him … I sometimes sit here and think, I used to/erm would he have got married again, you know, and somehow I don’t think he would either, that’s how close we were, you know [pause] I mean when he was really ill, I was ill, suffering with him [coughs] and he was the same. (Hilda)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Hilda indicates the closeness of their relationship and devotion they had for each other. She coughs as she recalls how ill he was, indicating how much she empathized and identified with him. Most who had been bereaved of their husbands, appeared in a state of mourning, lamenting their deaths and idealising the past and their roles as wives.</p>
<p>Hilda was a carer for her husband, so with his death her role as carer had been removed from her identity.</p>
<p>Alice had never married and the central part of her identity was that of professional, thus loss of this role through retirement was the most significant threat to her identity:
<disp-quote>
<p>… I was one of the top [medical professionals] if you know what I mean, I was on a committee, executive committee, attended meetings in London, responsible for organising this and that, and was quite an important person .... I was one of the top people, and as I say, I lectured a lot and was invited to Australia, read papers there and taught in an Australian school for some time, so I was very, very keen on my profession. (Alice)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Alice’s identity as a successful career woman is apparent from the above extract. In recounting this Alice is able to sustain and support her restricted Self 2 – embodying the attributes she believes she had. It is interesting to note her professional role was in the ‘caring profession’ and she described an attachment to her former patients. Retirement from her professional role results in fewer people who can offer the cooperation for her to construct a Self 3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1471301211419018">Sabat et al., 1999</xref>). Someone such as Alice who has taken pride for many years in her professional role, can no longer take pride in this to the same extent as she is not treated with the deference that would signal social recognition of her accomplishments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1471301211419018">Sabat et al., 1999</xref>), hence the need in her narrative to emphasize her past achievements in order to preserve her self esteem.</p>
<p>Loss of role as mother became apparent in those women with limited contact with their children. Many talked of them being far away and difficult to get to, and this seemed to exacerbate their feelings of loss of role as mother and nurturer, also contributing to feelings of loneliness and social isolation.</p>
<p>Loss of independence through decreased mobility and declining confidence had a huge impact on participants’ lives. For example not being able to drive any more appeared to dramatically reduce participants’ social lives and ability to be self reliant. The ability to make their own decisions and look after themselves was hugely important for these women, to feel they had some control over their lives and maintain attributes they viewed as important (Self 2).</p>
<p>Much of the above appears to be about erosion of Self 2, with some participants less able to build and re-build Self 3, due to lack of contact with husbands, children, friends and work contacts who knew their Self 2 attributes and could have reflected them back.</p>
<p><italic>Living with an unwanted self.</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1471301211419018">Hughes (2001)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1471301211419018">Aquilina &amp; Hughes (2006)</xref> argue we are situated-embodied-agents. We are persons because we are situated (in a variety of contexts), embodied and agentive (we do things). In the context of dementia, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1471301211419018">Kontos (2004)</xref> argues that selfhood persists even with severe dementia, because it is an embodied dimension of human existence. The embodied self was seen to be in a state of flux in participants’ accounts, as the women describe ageing both physically and psychologically.</p>
<p>Physical disintegration of the body was a factor voiced mostly in terms of the impact this had upon the participants’ mobility and consequent freedom and independence. Structural disintegration of the ageing body was a part of the felt and seen experience of living with a changing sense of self. If there was a disparity between chronological age and the felt experience of ageing, this created a conflict, as in Emily, who talked of her body still feeling young, even with a ‘lopsided’ breast.</p>
<p>Participants interacted meaningfully with the world through their embodied way of ‘being-in-the-world’. Many had physical ailments which impacted upon their lives, and seemed to hold a more prominent position in their conscious awareness than psychological pain or neurological ageing. Emily’s removed breast (due to cancer), Hilda’s diabetes, Alice’s partial deafness and Florence’s ageing skin were more readily brought to our interviews than the more painful threat of losing their minds. Florence states:
<disp-quote>
<p>… well I do try and wear three-quarter-length things because of all these marks,’cos I’ve got them all over my legs as you can see [shows me her legs] (Florence) L810</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Even at 95 years-old, Florence is concerned about the physical appearance of her ageing body by trying to cover up her damaged skin. However she is happy to show me, suggesting she sees me as a health professional who knows about medical conditions, or as someone who may be able to help her – this seems to be more acceptable than discussing memory problems.</p>
<p>Alongside the physical disintegration of the seen body, was the physical disintegration of the unseen body − the ageing mind and brain cells of dementia. Here the dichotomously constructed concepts of mind and body merge and overlap as participants sought to understand the lived experience of having dementia:
<disp-quote>
<p>… so I know all about acetylcholine and cholinesterase! [laughs] which I gather I am lacking in my brain!/’cos they think its something to do with acetylcholine?/yes they’ve gone a bit peculiar [both laugh] so I’m not daft as far as anatomical brain things are! (Alice)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Alice uses her medical knowledge to try to understand what is happening to her, whilst letting us know memory decline does not mean she is stupid. Loss of intelligence would be a major threat to Alice’s identity, so the laughing protects her from the pain of awareness and of loss of role from doctor to patient.</p>
<p><italic>Adapting to a new self.</italic> Participants adapted to a changing self through various routes. Some used acceptance, either reducing expectations or seeing themselves as having had a good life (Florence, Hilda, Ruby, Grace). Others saw themselves as fighting against adversity (Alice, Hilda, Grace). Some felt the self would continue through others after their death through passing on their values, skills, or genes. Strength in fighting against adversity and ‘putting on a brave face’ were seen in all participants to differing extents − an aspect of Self 2 they wanted to convey. Alice talked of people with strong characters, and felt she could cope with every circumstance that cropped up. Most participants talked of coping – ‘but I’m still coping, you know’ (Ruby), and ‘keeping going’. Hilda described coping with forgetting: ‘I always think “what day is it today?” [laughs] because every day is the same! So I try to make it different and I get dressed and go out!’ (Hilda)</p>
<p>The above illustrates participants actively involved in managing threats to their identities. Some used religion or had values they had lived their lives by, which they fell back on in times of stress as sources of comfort:
<disp-quote>
<p>Oh yes, they come sometimes [neighbours to help], yes I don’t really have no problem in that direction you know, I have to say really, God was good and kind to me because I see people with problems. (Grace)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Grace saw herself as lucky because she could always find help, feeling God guided her through her life, whilst being one of many participants who used downward comparison to appreciate the life she has. The influence of cultural factors should be considered when trying to understand the subjective experiences of heterogeneous groups of people (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1471301211419018">Downs, 2000</xref>). As Grace emigrated here from Jamaica, her attitude to life is flavoured by her cultural background – her expectations from life, in terms of material matters, were not great as compared to some participants, and her culture seems to have had a great influence on the person she is:
<disp-quote>
<p>I just felt as if, time and all is sit down and rest myself, so I don’t really bother now, yeah and my memory is bad for putting down something and I can’t find it, so when I put down anything now, I don’t even write it down, I say ‘well I’ll find it sometime!’, I say, ‘I’ve got too much junk in the house anyway!’ I have to laugh, but would worry some people, don’t really bother me. (Grace)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Here Grace describes having led a long life and wanting to rest. If she can’t find something she does not bother to hunt for it, but accepts this by thinking it may turn up later. If it doesn’t, she rationalises losing it by rendering it unimportant. This is an active coping mechanism emerging from a solid sense of who she is and a lack of anxiety about the unknown. Her belief in God takes the pressure off worrying about existential issues, enabling her to fully live in the present without undue anxiety.</p>
<p>One way of dealing with the threat of loss of identity, and future death was to have a sense of continuity of the self through others or generativity (an investment in benefiting the next generation) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1471301211419018">Erikson, 1963</xref>). Participants talked of passing on values or skills to others. Grace spoke of passing on her dressmaking skills and sewing machine to her daughter; Ruby talked of the transmission of values inherited from her grandmother and passed on to her children, helping them cope with identity changes and losses:
<disp-quote>
<p>I always try to see the best in people you know − well everybody’s got their little dark spots, but I try to see the best in people, well I suppose it’s more or less second nature, the way I was brought up, I can’t remember my mother actually saying it to me, but I think she was much the same and my grandma, they always had a nice attitude to people. Think my children are much the same as well. (Ruby)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Ruby lived her life by her core values, and this seemed to help her cope with dementia. Highly generative adults reconstruct the past and anticipate the future as variations on a prototypical commitment story. Alice (the only participant without children) had made her will and decided who she wanted to inherit her money. She talked of wanting to control her funds, perhaps symbolising her fight against diminishing control and eventual death, and her desire to live on through her nieces, nephews and ex-patients:
<disp-quote>
<p>A woman came over and said ‘Oh Miss X, how lovely to see you!’, and this happens a lot, and I’ve been retired for twenty years for heavens sake! So it really, I mean it’s very heartwarming when people do that/ ‘and Peter’s 41 now’ I mean I remember him when he was a little boy! (Alice)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>For Alice, knowing she made a significant positive impact upon thousands of children though her professional role means she will always be remembered by them. As an ex-academic she also wanted to be remembered through participating in this research. The prospect of having her words published meant Alice would live on after her death. Being engaged in this research also meant she could maintain the restricted Self 2 (i.e. through a continuation of her past job role) and Self 3 (presenting as a knowledgeable academic person) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1471301211419018">Sabat et al., 1999</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-1471301211419018"><title>Theme 2. A fluctuating awareness of memory problems</title>
<p><italic>Living with a declining memory.</italic> Participants used coping mechanisms such as writing ‘to do’ lists, writing on calendars, humour and fighting against decline, through to memory improvement strategies such as playing word games and through attending memory clubs. They spoke of the importance of these strategies and the camaraderie of being with others at the memory club.</p>
<p>Some participants took active control of their memory problems, used strategies such as humour to cope, and fought against the decline thereby protecting their self-esteem:
<disp-quote>
<p>… it’s not too bad. I make a note, and when I’m travelling I’ve always got a list, so if I do have to change trains, I’ve got where I’ve got to change and how long for and things like that, erm, the one daughter says, ‘as long as mum’s got her list, it doesn’t matter if it’s that long [shows with hands small distance] or that long [long distance with hands], she’s happy’ [laughs] (Ruby)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>This illustrates how Ruby takes control of her dementia by minimising its impact, and she makes light of the strategies she uses to manage her journeys by laughing. She uses strategies to ensure dementia does not limit her freedom and this reassures her she can still accomplish complex tasks such as changing trains, enabling her to lead a more active and fulfilling life. An important part of her identity is to be seen as coping and strong, as she led rambling groups for 11 years, prior to diminished mobility due to severe arthritis. She uses her daughter’s talk to validate her ability to cope, and it also tells us something of the quality of their relationship, in that her daughter is supportive but feels her mother can cope with complex circumstances, perhaps an indication of the old restricted Self 2 being continued in the current restricted Self 2.</p>
<p>Many participants were in the midst of a struggle in becoming aware of their memory problems and then heroically fighting against the decline, whilst also being aware of a sense of futility; feeling childish and stupid for not being able to do simple things:
<disp-quote>
<p>It’s very peculiar, you can’t/this is what is worrying me that I am definitely losing my memory, and I try, I can read the newspaper, the pieces I want to read, but I’ve found a book, and I thought I’m going to try and read some of that, to see if I can remember what it’s about, so far, I haven’t got very far, but I’m reading the words, it sounds a bit daft, I know the words but I’ve got to read them/and I go over the road and I say to John when he comes home, ‘What’s so and so John?’, and he’ll say, ‘Oh mother’ and then he’ll sort me out, but it’s silly things that I can’t remember, but they make your life up, you know, and I mean you can’t just forget the little things …. (Emily)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>This is a poignant account of Emily’s fight against memory decline − she knows she is losing her memory and is puzzled by its impact. She starts by saying she can’t do things she used to, but blocks herself and talks of the worry of decline. She wants to battle against decline by training her memory through reading, but it is a difficult and slow process, and she feels stupid because of this. She then goes on to say her son helps her, both using humour to cope with the painful awareness of her memory decline. The narrative suggests a role reversal in him helping her, and her feeling small because of this. She indicates frustration at forgetting ‘the little things’, which may be little to other people, but are hugely significant to her. ‘Fighting it’ appears to be a common phenomenon in individuals coping with Alzheimer’s disease, as also found by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1471301211419018">Clare (2002)</xref>.</p>
<p>Shame about forgetting was experienced by several participants, resulting in a desire to cover-up from others in order to protect their self-esteem:
<disp-quote>
<p>… one day, I <italic>completely</italic> forgot about it! And when I came down, the phone was going, she said, ‘Didn’t you want a dinner today?’ and I said, ‘Oh yes I’ve had one’, she said, ‘Who’ve you had it off?’, so I said, ‘I’ve been over the road!’ but I said ‘I’m ever so sorry but I forgot!’, she said, ‘Well would you like it?’, I said, ‘Yes please’, and he brought it back for me, they are ever such nice men [laughs] I felt ever such a fool …. (Emily)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Feeling stupid about forgetting led to Emily attempting to cover it up, but she was then exposed when probed, so reluctantly admitted it. She felt infantilised – like a little girl admitting she had been naughty and had done something wrong, but then felt grateful they did not chastise her, bringing her dinner back. Her vulnerability is apparent, in forgetting when she had eaten, and being ashamed of being exposed as a fool and liar, a humiliating event, also to relive. Shame in forgetting in persons with dementia has also been discussed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1471301211419018">Cheston (2005)</xref>. This story illustrates the importance of others in helping participants to process ‘mistakes’, and their resultant self-evaluations. It was painful enough for Emily to realize she had made a mistake and try to cover up, but if the response had been to ridicule her, this would have increased the threat to her personal identity, perhaps leading to further retreats into the self to avoid further humiliation. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1471301211419018">Keady and Nolan (1995a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1471301211419018">1995b</xref>) also found individuals with AD try to cover up forgetting. This illustrates the importance of others in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1471301211419018">Sabat et al.’s (1999)</xref> Self 3 (self reflected back from others) and how vulnerable it is to damage from others.</p>
<p><italic>Dementia as loss of control of the mind.</italic> Fear of losing control of the mind was experienced by most participants though only explicitly mentioned by some:
<disp-quote>
<p>Dementia is a very emotive word <italic>anyhow</italic>, erm, you feel that you haven’t got control of your mental processes, and for someone who’s highly trained, this is a <italic>shock</italic>, and you wonder what is going to <italic>happen!</italic>, and you are looking into the future, and particularly with my dear friend who is in this home […] to see what has happened to her, it really sort of worried me as you can imagine, and I was wondering whether I was going to lose my reason. (Alice)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Alice dives in to talk about dementia (the only participant who used the terminology), expressing her fear of losing her mind. She uses the second person to distance herself from the pain of it actually being something she has. This is particularly painful, as she describes herself as ‘highly trained’, suggesting loss of mind is a particularly severe threat to her identity. As a professional, childless woman who had never married, her intellect was central to her identity. She identifies with her friend who has dementia as a fellow professional, and indicates that looking at her is like looking into her own future.</p>
<p><italic>Denial versus despair.</italic> A major source of conflict surrounded admission of memory problems and/or dementia to themselves, and the desire to defend against acknowledging this, as a way of coping. Most participants gave reasons other than dementia for forgetting, often blaming relatives, for getting, for example, hospital appointment dates wrong, or other health problems, such as mishearing:
<disp-quote>
<p>I think it exacerbates any problems that you may have. You see, if I don’t remember something, which is what my dementia is all about isn’t it, it may be that I haven’t heard properly, and if I say, ‘Would you repeat that?’ people will think/there are two aspects of looking at that, either she’s dotty because she’s got dementia, or she hasn’t heard, and often <italic>I</italic> feel it’s because I haven’t heard. (Alice)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Here Alice minimises the severity of dementia by emphasising the extent of her deafness because that is less of a threat to her identity. Her concern is about being misunderstood and categorised as something she is not. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1471301211419018">McAdams (1998)</xref> suggests defence mechanisms help ensure that presentations of the self to an audience through a life story appear in a socially appropriate and self-serving manner; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1471301211419018">Freud (1923)</xref> argued they protect us from knowing the unbearable parts of ourselves. Certainly, participants seemed to move between the poles of denial of problems to acknowledgement, then shame and despair at the realisation of this, which seemed to occur when coping mechanisms broke down:
<disp-quote>
<p>… unless it was written down and they didn’t keep reminding me, I think it would just disappear … well if I had completely forgotten and they hadn’t reminded me, I would get all tightened up you know [makes twisting movement by stomach] that I’d made a mistake/yes I’d feel stupid, I get all keyed up inside and I could shout at everybody! (Lilly)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>In the above, Lilly shows her vulnerability in needing reminding. The twisting movements suggest difficulty in naming her emotion, but she confesses that making a mistake made her feel tense, stupid and frustrated. She then laughs to hide the shame and feelings of helplessness provoked by her inability to remember. This mixture of emotions was a common response to forgetting, though most used denial more actively, with only the occasional seepage when awareness was brought to the surface due to mishaps or ‘mistakes’. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1471301211419018">Oyebode, Motala, Hardy and Oliver (2009)</xref> also found minimisation and excuses other than memory loss to be common coping strategies.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-1471301211419018"><title>Theme 3. Seeking sanctuary versus risking danger</title>
<p><italic>Staying close to home to feel safe.</italic> Although some women were prevented from venturing far from their homes due to obvious physical limitations, others talked of other reasons for not wanting to travel far from home:
<disp-quote>
<p>That’s what I’m frightened about that I might go somewhere and then you can’t get back – I know it sounds a bit stupid like/like you see on films, but I don’t want to be like that. (Emily)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Here Emily seems to express loss of confidence due to the threat and impact of a diminishing memory; however most participants found it hard to admit this explicitly, perhaps as a defence against the fear of death, pride, and not wanting to appear weak and helpless.</p>
<p>The accounts suggest a need to retreat to a place of safety (the home), which could also represent a retreat into the self. This need may arise from a perceived threat to the self which is both internal and external − the internal threat is the experience of forgetting, combined with the external threat emerging as a result of this. This is illustrated by Grace who talked of being worried about being taken advantage of:
<disp-quote>
<p>… and I was mad at her really but then I know now she wouldn’t do that again, you see because, she means well but you see it’s the danger, people who don’t know and they might go around and they come and break into my house and I see that one and I say, ‘This was the one!’ − they are going to say, ‘Well your memory is no good’. (Grace)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Here Grace describes how she felt when her daughter told her that her memory was bad in front of others. She speaks of feeling vulnerable about people outside of her family knowing she has memory problems in case they exploit her. This illustrates how someone with dementia can feel threatened by being seen as less credible, in this instance as a witness, than someone without memory problems.</p>
<p>An underlying fear in all participants’ interviews was of losing control, probably rooted in popular ideas of dementia as someone ‘losing control’ of their mind. Consequently the need for a safe place, which provides a refuge from worrying about the future, arises.</p>
<p><italic>Coping alone.</italic> Some participants talked of finding living alone hard to cope with:
<disp-quote>
<p>I just about manage, I won’t do anything that I don’t feel capable of. I mean I can manage the few finances that I have, like the mortgage I suppose,’cos it isn’t/yes it is paid for! (Lilly)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>This illustrates how Lilly wants to reassure herself and let others know she can manage, but is aware she cannot manage the things she used to. She forgets whether she still has a mortgage or not, leading to more self-doubt about her competence at looking after herself. The struggle to cope then leads to conflicts about whether to move into a nursing home:
<disp-quote>
<p>Sometimes I think, ‘Oh shall I go into a home?’, but I don’t know whether I would settle in a home. (Lilly)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Going into a residential home was seen as ‘giving-up’, and associated with the loss of freedom that participants had whilst living independently. The ‘not-settling’ implies a feeling that one is expected to conform in a residential home, suggesting that for Lilly this would imply giving up aspects of her personhood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1471301211419018">Kitwood, 1993</xref>).</p>
<p>Ruby suggests her childhood as an only child made it easier for her to cope with living alone, but reveals vulnerability again:
<disp-quote>
<p>Well I never feel really alone, as you can see it’s quite busy here [looking out of the window] I know quite a lot of people, I know a lot by sight and quite a few by name, and I feel living here, I could shout out of the window and yell [laughs] for help if I needed it. (Ruby)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Neighbours were mentioned as important in helping participants in practical and emotional ways (see, for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1471301211419018">Walker &amp; Hiller, 2007</xref>). Both Alice and Emily had relatives living in adjacent blocks of flats, who helped them and with whom they had good relationships, and Vera and Florence had carers coming into their homes to help and talked of them as providing companionship. Most participants spoke of feeling they could rely on neighbours if they were in need. However some spoke of feeling lonely:
<disp-quote>
<p>I mean I’ve got my son over there, and people here, but yes, I do feel very lonely, and when you go out,’cos I just want to go out, but you’ve got to come <italic>back</italic> and then sometimes I feel really, really down when I come back. (Emily)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Other participants (Lilly, Hilda) also spoke of the importance of getting out of the house to prevent feelings of loneliness. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1471301211419018">Cattan, Newell, Bond and White (2003)</xref> argue that the quality of social networks influences negative emotions. Some participants’ social relationships did feel unrewarding (Emily), but also the amount of contact could account for feelings of loneliness.</p>
<p><italic>Threat of change.</italic> Emily worried about being evicted, which was tied up with anxiety about the possibility of losing her mind, and then being forced to go into a residential home against her will:
<disp-quote>
<p>I don’t know why, but somebody wants to move me out of here, but I don’t want to move, and she [warden] said, ‘You’re up to date with your rent, you’re clean, you’re tidy and you are no trouble to anybody, why should you leave?’ but I kept thinking, they think I’m going a bit stupid in my head, and they’ll put me in/’cos they’ve put one lady in/but I don’t wanna be in/I don’t wanna go in a home, I like it here. (Emily)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>This illustrates the conflict between an increasing awareness of a declining memory, and the anticipated impact of this on her housing, which represented a place of safety or sanctuary. Living with memory loss had real-world practical implications that were more than just a sense of not being able to remember something. It was as though participants felt they had become stigmatised for having memory problems, then perceived as ‘mad’ and a threat to other residents, and so had to be even more ‘well-behaved’ than other residents in order to keep their homes.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-1471301211419018"><title>Theme 4. Being with others: Connection versus disconnection</title>
<p><italic>Need to belong</italic>
<disp-quote>
<p>I <italic>love</italic> company, I always have done, you know, that’s why I joined that pensioner’s club on a Thursday, and which is quite nice,’cos now with the nice weather coming we have <italic>coach</italic> trips. … I always go out every day, or else I think I wouldn’t use my mouth, you know? If you don’t talk to anybody, just to the co-op up there, I don’t/I walk into [nearby shops] [pause] I don’t get stuck in and miserable and morbid and things like that, I don’t do that, that’s not me. (Hilda)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>This illustrates how Hilda counters the painful feelings she experiences when alone in the house through seeking company and being part of a group. Several of the women spoke of the experience of <italic>doing things together</italic>, echoing the travel and adventure they had in their earlier lives. Alice talked of her need to be with others when she describes her social group:
<disp-quote>
<p>We’ve disbanded from the WI’cos we can’t meet anymore, but we call ourselves the ****** and we meet once a month, we’re quite a collection of people, and we take it in turns to organize where we are going for lunch and things, so that’s quite a good casual event and so on, and then I’ve got other friends as well so I’m not short of friends at all. (Alice)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Meeting with like-minded people was important for most participants although only Alice mentioned being a member of a group other than a pensioners/memory club. Alice saw herself as interesting, as she describes the others in the group, and there is a sense of identification and seeking empowerment through this collective identity. The ‘disbanding’ suggests an activist, fighting spirit with a strong internal locus of control.</p>
<p>Alice, Ruby and Hilda’s descriptions of their relationships with others indicated the search for kindred spirits. Hilda described having one close friend who she would share private thoughts with, and Ruby described a brief encounter with a man she met in China following the death of her husband:
<disp-quote>
<p>… and people were dancing! [both laugh] ballroom dancing! In a paved area of the park and there was about a six lane road to cross, anyway I got straight over there and erm, I was standing there tapping my feet and a man asked me if I danced, and I said ‘Yes’, he said ‘Slow foxtrot?’ and I said ‘Yes’ and erm, it was lovely, I never saw him again, you know, and he said ‘I’m here most days’ and erm, I didn’t ever see him again, anyway it doesn’t matter .… (Ruby)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Here Ruby describes a desire for a (romantic) relationship with someone like-minded following the loss of her husband. She describes the need for intimacy that can be achieved through doing (dance) or ‘flow’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1471301211419018">Csiksentmihalyi, 1975</xref>), which goes beyond superficial ‘chit-chat’. She also expresses her disappointment that the relationship could not develop, then consoles herself by disregarding its importance (and her need). Older people are generally thought of as asexual, yet both Ruby and Hilda’s descriptions indicate passionate feelings being suppressed when Hilda describes her relationship with her deceased husband − ‘ … God we were close’ − illustrating an intense nostalgia and wish for an intimate relationship. Hilda’s desire for meaningful relationships is further illustrated in her comment: ‘ … if I held back and didn’t tell you what I really think, it’s not worth the time is it?’ This suggests a desire for honesty and wanting to be known, conflicting with the need for superficiality to protect herself. Her description of herself as ‘reserved’ reflects a need to want to be known deeply, rather than be simplified and pre-judged as an ‘old woman’. Hilda, Ruby, Alice and Emily mostly clearly indicated a desire to be seen as complex, as if their identity was bound up with an ‘unrestricted’ Self 2 that embodied a wide range of attributes, alongside a fear that others would see a Self 3 that was only a ‘dotty old woman’; and with this an internal conflict between wanting to be known (as complex) versus not wanting to be known (for fear of being perceived as demented).</p>
<p><italic>Privacy.</italic> Although members of various clubs, most participants described their relationships within these as fairly superficial: ‘It’s companionship, and we chat and talk, and erm, there are quizzes’ (Lilly). They appeared to seek to ‘jolly each other along’, not wanting to face the reality of their declining memories, through a collective need to protect themselves. Both Hilda and Emily’s desire to protect their privacy, perhaps indicated a sense of shame and vulnerability about having memory difficulties:
<disp-quote>
<p>Well I think that’s how it should be, you don’t want every Tom, Dick and Harry knowing all your/I’m not that kind of person, I’m reserved I think. (Hilda)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Joining a memory club appears to be a reluctant admission of failure, partly because of its impact on Self 3, since their membership is an open acknowledgement of a change in the restricted Self 2, indicating to others that having memory loss is now part of the person’s identity. Having said this, the women all spoke positively about the memory clubs, in ways that indicated they were of vital importance − in reducing their social isolation and giving a connection with other women who had similar experiences of memory problems. Even if problems were not explicitly shared, they were collectively felt. From their discourse it seemed there was a conflict between wanting-to-be-known, alongside <italic>not</italic>-wanting-to-be-known. The wanting-to-be-known part represented the wish to regain the self that was lost in the past (attachment to their old selves, husbands; unrestricted Self 2) or even to regain selfhood in the present through being in control.</p>
<p><italic>Exclusion.</italic> Participants talked in different ways of feeling excluded by others and society. Some had limited contact with others apart from visits from relatives or carers, and contact at memory/pensioners clubs. Although most had regular contact with at least one relative, Hilda and Emily seemed emotionally cut off from most of their children. Some felt their children were too busy to help or spend time with them:
<disp-quote>
<p>I had to do <italic>everything</italic> myself, I know my daughter, she did try, but she’s always busy and I don’t like to trouble them, and the other one she has moved to [far away]! You see, that was a big surprise to me, but you see it’s their life, what can you do? (Hilda)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Here a sense of abandonment, feeling a burden on others, and resentment about this, and for her daughter moving on with her life and leaving her behind are apparent. Social isolation led to feelings of vulnerability about coping alone. Florence described how her neighbour had been put into a nursing home, and no-one had told her:
<disp-quote>
<p>She won’t come back but as I say the flat is still empty and every time I hear a noise, I go out and see if there is anyone there, because they never came and told me you know!/we were quite good friends. (Florence)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Florence felt angry that her neighbour’s family failed to inform her of the move, indicating a feeling of them both being <italic>invisible</italic> as people, as though the impact of the move on their friendship was not important enough to consider. Florence’s frustration is apparent, along with her futile attempts to make contact again. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1471301211419018">Sabat (1999)</xref> states AD sufferers are often cut off from many activities that define their social worlds and as a consequence suffer a loss of self-esteem as a result of a lack of opportunities in which aspects of the self can be expressed.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec11-1471301211419018" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>The majority of women in this study were widowed and many mourned the loss of their husbands and past selves as wives, professionals, mothers and independent adults. Participants sought to emphasise aspects of the unrestricted Self 2 that might not be obvious on first acquaintance, such as their creativity, resourcefulness, adventurousness or strength, i.e. those stable attributes held across the lifespan, while mourning for the past restricted Self 2 that was embodied in (now lost) roles</p>
<p>The impact of memory loss on independence seemed to have a very significant impact on most of the women’s lives; this appearing to be tied up with ageing and bodily decline − for example in preventing going out due to fear of not remembering how to get home, or loss of driving licence. Many of the women fought against admitting the impact of memory loss as if to deny and ward off the threat of erosion of Self 2.</p>
<p>However many were also actively involved in reappraising who they were and continued to develop their relationships with others. Friends, neighbours and social clubs such as memory clubs formed a focal point for socialization. In these relationships there was a certain tension between an apparent wish to present an authentic Self 3 which acknowledged decline in memory with the inherent risk of being judged as just a silly old woman, and a wish to present a more socially acceptable capable Self 3 that would be better respected.</p>
<p>All of the women had people in their lives with whom they had frequent contact, with friends appearing to take a more prominent role in their lives than family members, perhaps due to the camaraderie of being with others like themselves who might reflect Self 3 back in a more understanding and sympathetic light than those who were younger and fitter. Some were lonely and isolated and craved company but preferred to fight on alone in the safe haven of a residential home rather than face a move to a home that would deprive them of personhood and involve presentation of a Self 3 who had ‘given in’. A search for meaningful relationships was apparent from the women’s talk and a desire to be known deeply rather than be written off as old women. This conflicted with feeling vulnerable and a desire to protect themselves from memory loss, others and possibly death.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-1471301211419018"><title>Clinical and research implications</title>
<p>This research highlights the importance of understanding the position of older women living alone, with cognitive impairments. There was a sense of some of these women particularly those without family support, being ‘lost in the system’, with very little outside contact, apart from occasional contact at memory or pensioners’ clubs which were seen as a life-line.</p>
<p>The experience of shame of having memory problems and the need to cover these up highlights the importance of positive social interactions with others, and, since parts of our identities are constructed from our interactions with others, it also highlights the importance of maintaining personhood. This was paradoxically evidenced by participants coming alive during the interviews and having the desire and ability to talk with depth, animation and richness about their inner worlds and personal experiences, with the hope of being deeply understood rather than superficially judged.</p>
<p>This research indicates that the experience of dementia puts additional strains on ageing individuals, which is compounded by the practical and emotional experience of living alone. Ageing, living alone and the experience of dementia can produce barriers to individuals being able to get out of the house and into the community, access resources and cope with day-to-day living. It also makes it more difficult for these individuals to have access to others in order to form meaningful relationships, and hence continue to construct and reappraise their identities. This highlights the importance of services engaging with marginalized and disempowered individuals such as these women, perhaps to enable them to form connections with others of their generation, through supporting them in forming community groups where they could be encouraged to express themselves creatively and explore their identities, or just <italic>be</italic> with others; and to raise the profile of older people with dementia, thereby raising the public’s awareness of the personal experience of dementia and dispelling some of the shame.</p>
<p>Longitudinal qualitative studies could help us discover more about how individuals cope with the progression of dementia, thereby enabling us to work better clinically with such individuals. Maintaining research relationships over longer time-scales, would provide a sense of containment for participants whilst providing information about the dynamics of selfhood which could benefit future generations of older adults living alone with dementia.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Alzheimer’s Society</collab>. (<year>1994</year>). <source>Home alone: Living alone with dementia</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Alzheimer’s Society</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="web"><collab>Alzheimer’s Society</collab> (<year>2000</year>). <source>Living alone: Advice leaflet</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <comment>Alzheimer’s Society. Retrieved November 6, 2007 from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.alzheimers.org.uk">http://www.alzheimers.org.uk</ext-link></comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aquilina</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The return of the living dead: Agency lost and found?</article-title> In <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Louw</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabat</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (eds.) <source>Dementia: Mind, meaning, and the person</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Open University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cattan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Newell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Alleviating social isolation and loneliness among older people</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Mental Health Promotion</source>, <volume>5</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>20</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheston</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Shame and avoidance: Issues of remembering and forgetting with people with dementia</article-title>. <source>The Magazine for Family Therapy and Systemic Practice</source>, <volume>77</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clare</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>We’ll fight as long as we can: Coping with the onset of Alzheimer’s disease</article-title>. <source>Aging and Mental Health</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>148</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clare</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowlands</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Downs</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>‘I don’t do it like I used to do’: A grounded theory approach to conceptualizing awareness in people with moderate to severe dementia living in long-term care</article-title>. <source>Social Science and Medicine</source>, <volume>66</volume>, <fpage>2366</fpage>–<lpage>2377</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cotrell</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>The perspective of the patient with Alzheimer’s disease: A neglected dimension of dementia research</article-title>. <source>Gerontologist</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Csikszentmihalyi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>). <article-title>Play and intrinsic rewards</article-title>. <source>Journal of Humanistic Psychology</source>, <volume>15</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Downs</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Dementia in a socio-cultural context: An idea whose time has come</article-title>. <source>Ageing and Society</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>239</fpage>–<lpage>375</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erikson</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1963</year>). <source>Childhood and Society</source>, <edition>2nd edn</edition>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Norton</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Folstein</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Folstein</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>McHugh</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>). <article-title>Mini-mental state: A practical method for grading the cognitive state of patients for the clinician</article-title>. <source>Journal of Psychiatric Research</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>198</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fratiglioni</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.-X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ericsson</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maytan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Winblad</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Influence of social network on occurrence of dementia: A community based longitudinal study</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>, <volume>355</volume>, <fpage>1315</fpage>–<lpage>1319</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1923</year>). <source>The ego and the id</source>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Strachey</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1961</year>) <source>The standard edition of the complete works of Sigmund Freud</source> (<volume>Vol. 19</volume>). <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hogarth Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>P. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Pathways to the person: The subjective experience of Alzheimer’s disease</source>. <publisher-loc>Baltimore</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>View of the person with dementia</article-title>. <source>Journal of Medical Ethics</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>86</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Louw</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabat</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Dementia: Mind, meaning, and the person</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Open University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keady</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995a</year>). <article-title>IMMEL: Assessing coping responses in the early stages of dementia</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Nursing</source>, <volume>4</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>341</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keady</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995b</year>). <article-title>IMMEL2: Working to augment coping responses in early dementia</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Nursing</source>, <volume>4</volume>(<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>381</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitwood</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Towards a theory of dementia care: the interpersonal process</article-title>. <source>Aging and Society</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitwood</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>Dementia reconsidered: The person comes first</source>. <publisher-loc>Buckingham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Open University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitwood</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bredin</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Towards a theory of dementia care: Personhood and well-being</article-title>. <source>Ageing and Society</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>269</fpage>–<lpage>287</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kontos</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Ethnographic reflections on selfhood, embodiment and Alzheimer’s disease</article-title>. <source>Ageing and Society</source>, <volume>24</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>829</fpage>–<lpage>849</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clifton</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Giving voice and making sense in interpretative phenomenological analysis</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Research in Psychology</source>, <volume>3</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>102</fpage>–<lpage>120</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lincoln</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guba</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <source>Naturalistic Inquiry</source>. <publisher-loc>California</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McAdams</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>The role of defense in the life story</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality</source>, <volume>66</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>1125</fpage>–<lpage>1146</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Nostalgic memories in dementia: A case study</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Aging and Human Development</source>, <volume>38</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>219</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oyebode</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Motala</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Coping with challenges to memory in people with mild to moderate Alzheimer’s disease: Observation of behaviour in response to analogues of everyday situations</article-title>. <source>Aging and Mental Health</source>, <volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sabat</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <source>The experience of Alzheimer’s disease: Life through a tangled veil</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sabat</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fath</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moghaddam</surname><given-names>F. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harre</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Maintenance of self-esteem: Lessons from the culture of Alzheimer’s sufferers</article-title>. <source>Culture and Psychology</source>, <volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sibley</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacKnight</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rockwood</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisk</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guzman</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The effect of the living situation on the severity of dementia at diagnosis</article-title>. <source>Dementia and Geriatric Cognitive Disorders</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>40</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Beyond the divide between cognition and discourse: Using interpretative phenomenological analysis in health psychology</article-title>. <source>Psychology and Health</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>261</fpage>–<lpage>271</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Reflecting on the development of interpretative phenomenological analysis and its contribution to qualitative research in psychology</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Research in Psychology</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>39</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Osborn</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Interpretative Phenomenological Analysis</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (Eds.), <source>Qualitative psychology: A practical guide to research methods</source>, <edition>2nd edn</edition>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage Publications</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <source>Speaking our minds: Personal reflections from individuals with Alzheimer’s</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>W.H. Freeman</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiller</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Places and health: A qualitative study to explore how older women living alone perceive the social and physical dimensions of their neighbourhoods</article-title>. <source>Social Science and Medicine</source>, <volume>65</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>1154</fpage>–<lpage>1165</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Webber</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunette</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Living alone with Alzheimer’s disease: Effects on health and social service utilization patterns</article-title>. <source>The Gerontologist</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>721</fpage>–<lpage>723</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1471301211419018"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willig</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Introducing Qualitative Research in Psychology</source>, <edition>2nd edn</edition>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage Publications</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<bio>
<p><bold>Soraya Frazer,</bold> BSc (Hons), MSc, ClinPsyD, PG Cert., is a Chartered Clinical Psychologist working for Birmingham and Solihull Mental Health Foundation Trust in Adult Mental Health. Her interests include identity, existential issues, psychoanalysis and qualitative research.</p>
<p><bold>Jan R. Oyebode,</bold> BA (Hons), M Psychol (Clinical), PhD, is a consultant clinical psychologist specialising in work with older people. She is Senior Lecturer and Director of the Clinical Psychology Doctorate Course at the University of Birmingham and also spends one day a week in clinical practice within Birmingham and Solihull Mental Health Trust, UK. Her particular interests are in psychological adaptation to late life events including dementia and bereavement.</p>
<p><bold>Adam Cleary,</bold> BSc (Hons), ClinPsyD, is a Clinical Psychologist specializing in work with older people within Birmingham and Solihull Mental Health Foundation Trust, UK and Honorary Lecturer on the Clinical Psychology Doctorate Course at the University of Birmingham. His particular interests include community psychology and attachment in late life.</p></bio>
</back>
</article>