<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ASM</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spasm</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Assessment</journal-id>
<journal-title>Assessment</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1073-1911</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3489</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1073191113486183</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1073191113486183</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Special Issue on the Personality Inventory for <italic>DSM-5</italic></subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Psychometric Properties of the Personality Inventory for <italic>DSM-5</italic> in an APA <italic>DSM-5</italic> Field Trial Sample</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Quilty</surname><given-names>Lena C.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1073191113486183">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1073191113486183">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ayearst</surname><given-names>Lindsay</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1073191113486183">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Chmielewski</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1073191113486183">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Pollock</surname><given-names>Bruce G.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1073191113486183">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1073191113486183">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Bagby</surname><given-names>R. Michael</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1073191113486183">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1073191113486183">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1073191113486183"><label>1</label>Campbell Family Mental Health Research Institute, Centre for Addiction and Mental Health, Toronto, Ontario, Canada</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1073191113486183"><label>2</label>University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1073191113486183"><label>3</label>Southern Methodist University, Dallas, TX, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1073191113486183">R. Michael Bagby, Departments of Psychology and Psychiatry, University of Toronto, Research Science Bldg, SY-124 (Scarborough Campus), 1265 Military Trail, Toronto, Ontario M1C 1A4, Canada. Email: <email>rmbagby@utsc.utoronto.ca</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>20</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>362</fpage>
<lpage>369</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Section 3 of the fifth edition of the <italic>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</italic> (<italic>DSM-5</italic>) includes a hybrid model of personality pathology, in which dimensional personality traits are used to derive one of seven categorical personality disorder diagnoses. The Personality Inventory for DSM-5 (PID-5) was developed by the <italic>DSM-5</italic> Personality and Personality Disorders workgroup and their consultants to produce a freely available instrument to assess the personality traits within this new system. To date, the psychometric properties of the PID-5 have been evaluated primarily in undergraduate student and community adult samples. In the current investigation, we extend this line of research to a psychiatric patient sample who participated in the APA <italic>DSM-5</italic> Field Trial (Centre for Addiction and Mental Health site). A total of 201 psychiatric patients (102 men, 99 women) completed the PID-5 and the Revised NEO Personality Inventory (NEO PI-R). The internal consistencies of the PID-5 domain and facet trait scales were acceptable. Results supported the unidimensional structure of all trait scales but one, and the convergence between the PID-5 and analogous NEO PI-R scales. Evidence for discriminant validity was mixed. Overall, the current investigation provides support for the psychometric properties of this diagnostic instrument in psychiatric samples.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>personality</kwd>
<kwd>assessment</kwd>
<kwd><italic>DSM-5</italic></kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The approaching publication of the fifth edition of the <italic>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</italic> (<italic>DSM-5</italic>) has occasioned extensive research into the assessment and clinical utility of dimensional personality traits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1073191113486183">Krueger et al., 2011</xref>). In response to the well-established limitations of the categorical personality disorders codified in the fourth edition of the <italic>DSM</italic> (<italic>DSM-IV</italic>), the <italic>DSM-5</italic> Personality and Personality Disorders workgroup proposed a substantial revision to the diagnosis of personality pathology. This proposal included a hybrid model in which a categorical diagnosis of personality disorder is derived on the basis of dimensional, pathological personality traits as well as personality impairment. Workgroup members and consultants developed a freely available instrument for the assessment of the dimensional personality traits within this model—the <italic>Personality Inventory for the DSM-5</italic> (PID-5; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1073191113486183">Krueger, Derringer, Markon, Watson, &amp; Skodol, 2012</xref>)—which has demonstrated initial promise in undergraduate student and community adult samples (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1073191113486183">Ashton, Lee, deVries, Hendrickse, &amp; Born, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1073191113486183">Hopwood, Thomas, Markon, Wright, &amp; Krueger, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1073191113486183">Wright, Thomas, et al., 2012</xref>). The current investigation contributes to this line of investigation from an applied perspective, in a focused evaluation of the psychometric properties of the <italic>PID-5</italic> required for use within a clinical setting.</p>
<p>As outlined in Section 3 of the <italic>DSM-5</italic>, 25 dimensional “lower-order” personality facet traits are used to derive one of seven possible personality disorder diagnoses: schizotypal, antisocial, borderline, narcissistic, avoidant, obsessive–compulsive, and trait-specified. These 25 traits are proposed to reside within one or more five “higher-order” personality domains: negative affect, detachment, psychoticism, antagonism, and disinhibition. These domains resemble those found in established models of personality pathology such as the Personality Psychopathology–Five (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1073191113486183">Harkness &amp; McNulty, 1994</xref>) and/or measures of pathological personality such as the Dimensional Assessment of Personality Pathology–Basic Questionnaire (DAPP-BQ; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1073191113486183">Livesley, Jang, &amp; Vernon, 1998</xref>) and the Schedule for Nonadaptive and Adaptive Personality (SNAP; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1073191113486183">Clark, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1073191113486183">Clark, Simms, Wu, &amp; Casillas, in press</xref>). The domain and facet traits of the <italic>DSM-5</italic> model were empirically derived from a larger set of 37 traits, identified by the <italic>DSM-5</italic> Personality and Personality Disorders workgroup as a comprehensive collection of indicators of personality pathology. The convergence between the resultant <italic>DSM-5</italic> proposal and accumulated empirical research in dimensional personality lends credence to the robustness and validity of its constituent traits (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1073191113486183">Harkness, Finn, McNulty, &amp; Shields, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1073191113486183">Samuel &amp; Widiger, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>The PID-5 has demonstrated acceptable to good psychometric properties in the published literature to date. The hierarchical structure of the PID-5 maps well onto extant models of personality and psychopathology, providing evidence for the construct validity of this measure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1073191113486183">Wright et al., 2012</xref>). Furthermore, the traits of the PID-5 have been linked with traits of prominent models of personality, demonstrating the convergent and discriminant validity of scale scores (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1073191113486183">Ashton et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1073191113486183">Wright, Pincus, et al., 2012</xref>). Finally, and perhaps most important from a clinical perspective, the PID-5 scales account for a substantial amount of variance in <italic>DSM-IV</italic> personality disorder severity and are linked to <italic>DSM-IV</italic> personality disorders as designed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1073191113486183">Hopwood et al., 2012</xref>). Taken together, these investigations provide initial support for the PID-5 as a measure of the dimensional model of personality proposed for use in the <italic>DSM-5</italic>.</p>
<p>The current investigation joins several other investigations in this special issue to address the limitations of the existing psychometric support for the PID-5. Of critical importance, the properties of the PID-5 have yet to be evaluated in a psychiatric sample (cf., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1073191113486183">Watson, Stasik, Ro, &amp; Clark, 2013</xref>), which we believe is necessary prior to its use in clinical settings. Furthermore, the associations between the traits of the PID-5 and the Five Factor Model of personality have yet to be examined empirically (cf., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1073191113486183">De Fruyt et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1073191113486183">Thomas et al., 2013</xref>). The <italic>DSM-5</italic> Personality and Personality Disorders workgroup argued that the traits of this widely used model do not capture pathological traits of clinical relevance in an optimal or comprehensive way. In particular, traits associated with paranoid, schizotypal, and schizoid personality are absent or inadequately represented by scales assessing Openness to Experience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1073191113486183">Tackett, Silberschmidt, Krueger, &amp; Sponheim, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1073191113486183">Watson, Clark, &amp; Chmielewski, 2008</xref>). It is important to explore such associations in a sample likely to exhibit a range of such symptoms. We focus on these particular areas of need, to begin the research required to fully evaluate the validity of the proposed diagnostic scheme.</p>
<sec id="section1-1073191113486183">
<title>The Current Investigation</title>
<p>Our objective in the current investigation was to evaluate the psychometric properties of the PID-5 domain and facet scales with a psychiatric patient sample. In contrast to earlier investigations (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1073191113486183">Ashton et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1073191113486183">Hopwood et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1073191113486183">Wright et al., 2012</xref>), we evaluated the psychometric properties of the domain scales as calculated according to most recent guidelines, wherein each domain represents the average of three facet scales: Negative Affect is the average of the Emotional Lability, Anxiousness, and Separation Insecurity facet scales; Detachment of Withdrawal, Anhedonia, and Intimacy Avoidance; Antagonism of Manipulativeness, Deceitfulness, and Grandiosity; Disinhibition of Irresponsibility, Impulsivity, and Distractibility; and Psychoticism of Unusual Beliefs and Experiences, Eccentricity, and Perceptual Dysregulation. We hypothesized that the PID-5 domain and facet scales will exhibit adequate internal consistency and unidimensional structure, consistent with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1073191113486183">Krueger et al. (2012)</xref>. We further hypothesized that the PID-5 facet scales will be positively associated due to saturation with general personality pathology and distress, but that the PID-5 facet scales within a domain will exhibit greater associations with each other than with facet scales of other domains. We also hypothesized that the PID-5 domain and facet scales will be moderately to strongly associated with thematically correspondent Revised NEO Personality Inventory (NEO PI-R) domain and facet scales, with the exception of the PID-5 Psychoticism domain and the Openness-to-Experience domain, which are likely to exhibit at best a weak association.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1073191113486183" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<sec id="section3-1073191113486183">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>The sample included 201 outpatients (102 men, 99 women) who had previously participated in the APA <italic>DSM-5</italic> Field Trial at the Centre for Addiction and Mental Health (CAMH) in Toronto, Canada. Participants ranged in age from 19 to 73 years (<italic>M</italic> = 41.37, <italic>SD</italic> = 13.67). Current Axis I diagnoses included schizophrenia (<italic>n</italic> = 42), schizoaffective disorder (<italic>n</italic> = 36), attenuated psychosis (<italic>n</italic> = 14), personality disorder (<italic>n</italic> = 69), and other psychiatric diagnoses (<italic>n</italic> = 40) including mood, anxiety, substance use, impulse control, and pervasive developmental disorders.</p>
<p>All participants were required to meet the following criteria: (a) to endorse or exhibit current psychiatric symptoms, (b) to be 18 years of age or older, and (c) to be able to consent and complete the study protocol in English (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1073191113486183">Clarke et al., 2013</xref>, for a full description of study procedures). Clinicians (provincially licensed psychiatrists or registered clinical psychologists at the CAMH site) recruited to participate in the <italic>DSM-5</italic> Field Trial screened all consecutive patients for field trial eligibility, and informed all eligible patients of the opportunity to participate in the trial; interested patients were subsequently contacted by research staff to learn more about the protocol and to schedule research visits. Clinicians screened a total of 1,185 unique patients. Of these, 273 consented to participate and 242 were employed in trial analyses (see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1073191113486183">Narrow et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1073191113486183">Regier et al., 2013</xref>). Participants of the current investigation attended an additional assessment session, including the measures described below.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1073191113486183">
<title>Measures</title>
<sec id="section5-1073191113486183">
<title>Personality Inventory for the <italic>DSM-5</italic></title>
<p>The PID-5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1073191113486183">Krueger et al., 2012</xref>) is a 220-item inventory newly developed to assess the pathological personality dimensions of the proposed hybrid model of personality pathology. This measure asks participants to rate statements on a 4-point Likert-type scale from 0 (<italic>Very False or Often False</italic>) to 3 (<italic>Very True or Often True</italic>). The PID-5 yields scale scores for five domain and 25 facet scale scores.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1073191113486183">
<title>Revised NEO Personality Inventory</title>
<p>The NEO PI-R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1073191113486183">Costa &amp; McCrae, 1992</xref>) is a 240-item self-report measure frequently used to assess five higher-order domain traits and 30 lower-order facet traits of the Five Factor Model of personality. This measure asks participants to rate statements on a 5-point Likert-type scale from 1 (<italic>Strongly disagree</italic>) to 5 (<italic>Strongly agree</italic>). The NEO PI-R has been demonstrated to be a reliable and valid measure of the Five Factor Model traits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1073191113486183">Costa &amp; McCrae, 1992</xref>), including within clinical populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1073191113486183">Bagby et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1073191113486183">Costa, Bagby, Herbst, &amp; McCrae, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1073191113486183">De Fruyt, Van Leeuwen, Bagby, Rolland, &amp; Rouillon, 2006</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1073191113486183">
<title>Statistical Analysis</title>
<p>To estimate the internal consistencies of the PID-5 domain trait scales, we calculated McDonald’s omega (ω) within a latent variable framework (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1073191113486183">McDonald, 1970</xref>). McDonald’s ω is particularly suited to estimating the reliability of a composite score (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1073191113486183">Gignac, Bates, &amp; Jang, 2007</xref>, for an application). To evaluate the internal consistencies of the PID-5 facet trait scales, we calculated Cronbach’s α coefficient and the average item correlation (AIC). The AIC statistic was used to supplement Cronbach’s α, as the AIC is less influenced by scale length.</p>
<p>To evaluate factor structure, we conducted a series of parallel analyses and Velicer’s minimum average partial (MAP) tests to determine how many factors to extract for each domain and facet scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1073191113486183">O’Connor, 2000</xref>). Parallel analysis involves the comparison of eigenvalues from a factor analysis of the actual data with eigenvalues from a factor analysis of a random dataset; the number of factors to retain is based on the number of actual data eigenvalues greater in size than random data eigenvalues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1073191113486183">Horn, 1965</xref>). This empirical method is well suited to the current context due to the ability to generate random permutations of the existing data set, which maintain the same distributional properties as the original. We used 1,000 randomly generated permutations of the existing data set and compared actual data eigenvalues with the 95th percentile eigenvalues in the random data. Velicer’s MAP test involves a series of principal components analyses of the data, extracting an increasing number of principal components. These components are partialed from the correlations between variables. The number of factors to extract is the number of components that generated the lowest average squared partial correlation, which represent the systematic variance in the data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1073191113486183">Velicer, 1976</xref>). For scales with more than one factor according to both indices, factor analyses were then conducted within MPlus 4.2, using a robust maximum-likelihood estimator and treating items as categorical (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1073191113486183">Muthén &amp; Muthén, 1998-2006</xref>).</p>
<p>To evaluate convergent validity, we examined the associations of the PID-5 facet scales within and across each domain. Furthermore, we examined the associations between the PID-5 domain and facet scales and the analogous NEO PI-R domain scale. Finally, we examined the unique association of the NEO PI-R facet scales with the analogous PID-5 domain scales. To accomplish this, five linear regression models were evaluated, with each PID-5 domain scale serving as the criterion variable in separate models in turn. NEO PI-R facet scales of the analogous NEO PI-R domain were entered simultaneously as predictor variables. For example, the PID-5 Negative Affect domain scale was modeled as a criterion variable and the NEO PI-R Anxiety, Angry Hostility, Depression, Self-Consciousness, Impulsivity, and Vulnerability facet scales as predictor variables in the first model. Although Openness-to-Experience has been demonstrated to be distinct from Psychoticism and related traits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1073191113486183">Tackett et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1073191113486183">Watson et al., 2008</xref>), this regression was included as well to explore Five Factor Model facet trait associations with this domain.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1073191113486183" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The mean, standard deviation, and range of the PID-5 domain scales were as follows: Negative Affect <italic>M</italic> = 1.35, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.75, range = 0.00 to 2.95; Detachment <italic>M</italic> = 1.26, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.64, range = 0.00 to 2.85; Psychoticism <italic>M</italic> = 0.94, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.64, range = 0.00 to 2.51; Antagonism <italic>M</italic> = 0.66, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.56, range = 0.00 to 2.80; Disinhibition <italic>M</italic> = 0.99, <italic>SD</italic> = 0.63, range = 0.00 to 2.88. The mean, standard deviation, and range of the PID-5 facet scales are displayed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1073191113486183">Table 1</xref>. To facilitate comparison, the mean and standard deviation of the PID-5 facet scales from the representative sample described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1073191113486183">Krueger et al. (2012)</xref> are also displayed. Anxiousness and Depressivity were markedly elevated in the current sample as compared with Krueger et al. (<italic>d</italic>s .81 and .85, respectively). Other facet scales elevated as compared to this representative sample at a medium effect size include Anhedonia, Distractibility, Emotional Lability, Intimacy Avoidance, Perceptual Dysregulation, Perseveration, Suspiciousness, Unusual Beliefs and Perceptions, and Withdrawal (<italic>d</italic>s .52 to .72). Grandiosity and Manipulativeness were in fact lower in the current sample, albeit with small effect sizes.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1073191113486183" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Descriptive Data for PID-5 Facet Trait Scales.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1073191113486183" xlink:href="10.1177_1073191113486183-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Domains/Facets</th>
<th align="center">α</th>
<th align="center">AIC</th>
<th align="center">Range</th>
<th align="center"><italic>M</italic> (<italic>SD</italic>)</th>
<th align="center"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1073191113486183">Krueger et al. (2012)</xref>, <italic>M</italic> (<italic>SD</italic>)</th>
<th align="center"><italic>d</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Anhedonia</td>
<td>.89</td>
<td>.51</td>
<td>0.00-3.00</td>
<td>1.38 (0.79)</td>
<td>0.89 (0.64)</td>
<td>.69</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Anxiousness</td>
<td>.93</td>
<td>.60</td>
<td>0.00-3.00</td>
<td>1.67 (0.88)</td>
<td>1.02 (0.73)</td>
<td>.81</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Attention Seeking</td>
<td>.90</td>
<td>.52</td>
<td>0.00-3.00</td>
<td>0.83 (0.74)</td>
<td>0.81 (0.65)</td>
<td>.03</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Callousness</td>
<td>.87</td>
<td>.34</td>
<td>0.00-2.29</td>
<td>0.47 (0.47)</td>
<td>0.40 (0.50)</td>
<td>.14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Deceitfulness</td>
<td>.90</td>
<td>.47</td>
<td>0.00-2.80</td>
<td>0.66 (0.66)</td>
<td>0.52 (0.54)</td>
<td>.24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Depressivity</td>
<td>.96</td>
<td>.63</td>
<td>0.00-3.00</td>
<td>1.17 (0.89)</td>
<td>0.53 (0.62)</td>
<td>.85</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Distractibility</td>
<td>.91</td>
<td>.52</td>
<td>0.00-3.00</td>
<td>1.31 (0.81)</td>
<td>0.82 (0.69)</td>
<td>.66</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Eccentricity</td>
<td>.95</td>
<td>.60</td>
<td>0.00-2.92</td>
<td>1.16 (0.83)</td>
<td>0.82 (0.76)</td>
<td>.43</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Emotional Lability</td>
<td>.91</td>
<td>.59</td>
<td>0.00-3.00</td>
<td>1.38 (0.88)</td>
<td>0.94 (0.74)</td>
<td>.55</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Grandiosity</td>
<td>.75</td>
<td>.33</td>
<td>0.00-3.00</td>
<td>0.66 (0.60)</td>
<td>0.82 (0.58)</td>
<td>−.27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hostility</td>
<td>.88</td>
<td>.43</td>
<td>0.00-2.90</td>
<td>1.07 (0.71)</td>
<td>0.91 (0.67)</td>
<td>.23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Impulsivity</td>
<td>.89</td>
<td>.57</td>
<td>0.00-3.00</td>
<td>1.00 (0.79)</td>
<td>0.77 (0.57)</td>
<td>.34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Intimacy Avoidance</td>
<td>.87</td>
<td>.51</td>
<td>0.00-3.00</td>
<td>1.07 (0.85)</td>
<td>0.61 (0.65)</td>
<td>.62</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Irresponsibility</td>
<td>.82</td>
<td>.40</td>
<td>0.00-2.86</td>
<td>0.66 (0.63)</td>
<td>0.39 (0.49)</td>
<td>.49</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Manipulativeness</td>
<td>.85</td>
<td>.54</td>
<td>0.00-3.00</td>
<td>0.66 (0.69)</td>
<td>0.80 (0.67)</td>
<td>.21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Perceptual Dysregulation</td>
<td>.86</td>
<td>.34</td>
<td>0.00-2.58</td>
<td>0.83 (0.62)</td>
<td>0.44 (0.48)</td>
<td>.72</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Perseveration</td>
<td>.88</td>
<td>.44</td>
<td>0.00-2.86</td>
<td>1.18 (0.72)</td>
<td>0.82 (0.62)</td>
<td>.54</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Restricted Affectivity</td>
<td>.82</td>
<td>.40</td>
<td>0.00-3.00</td>
<td>0.92 (0.69)</td>
<td>0.97 (0.56)</td>
<td>−.08</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rigid Perfectionism</td>
<td>.91</td>
<td>.51</td>
<td>0.00-3.00</td>
<td>1.10 (0.76)</td>
<td>1.05 (0.68)</td>
<td>.07</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Risk Taking</td>
<td>.87</td>
<td>.33</td>
<td>0.00-2.71</td>
<td>1.06 (0.57)</td>
<td>1.05 (0.66)</td>
<td>.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Separation Insecurity</td>
<td>.89</td>
<td>.54</td>
<td>0.00-3.00</td>
<td>1.00 (0.84)</td>
<td>0.80 (0.68)</td>
<td>.27</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Submissiveness</td>
<td>.79</td>
<td>.49</td>
<td>0.00-3.00</td>
<td>1.29 (0.75)</td>
<td>1.17 (0.66)</td>
<td>.17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Suspiciousness</td>
<td>.72</td>
<td>.27</td>
<td>0.00-3.00</td>
<td>1.26 (0.62)</td>
<td>0.95 (0.58)</td>
<td>.52</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Unusual Beliefs &amp; Perceptions</td>
<td>.85</td>
<td>.41</td>
<td>0.00-2.63</td>
<td>0.84 (0.72)</td>
<td>0.64 (0.63)</td>
<td>.30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Withdrawal</td>
<td>.92</td>
<td>.55</td>
<td>0.00-3.00</td>
<td>1.33 (0.81)</td>
<td>1.01 (0.72)</td>
<td>.42</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1073191113486183">
<p><italic>Note</italic>. AIC = average interitem correlation.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section9-1073191113486183">
<title>Reliability</title>
<p>The internal consistencies of the PID-5 domain trait scales were as follows: Negative Affect ω = .84; Detachment ω = .75; Psychoticism ω = .87; Antagonism ω = .83; and Disinhibition ω = .80. Cronbach’s α and AIC values of the PID-5 facet trait scales are displayed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1073191113486183">Table 1</xref>. All facet scales demonstrated Cronbach’s α values greater than .70; Callousness, Grandiosity, Perceptual Dysregulation, Risk Taking, and Suspiciousness exhibited AIC values below .40 (mean α = .87, mean AIC = .47).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1073191113486183">
<title>Factor Structure</title>
<p>Both parallel analyses and MAP tests supported a one-factor structure for each of the domain scales. Parallel analyses supported a one-factor solution for all facet scales but Risk Taking. For this scale, the first three eigenvalues from the actual data were 5.49, 2.06, and 0.96; the corresponding first three 95th percentile random data eigenvalues were 1.59, 1.44, and 1.34, suggesting the retention of two components for rotation to solution. MAP tests supported a one-factor solution for all facet scales but Depressivity (average partial correlation = .0315), Hostility (average partial correlation = .0381), and Risk Taking as well (average partial correlation = .0197). Exploratory factor analysis of Risk Taking items revealed that seven of eight positively keyed items scored strongly on the first component (mean factor loading .67, range .50 to .82) and minimally on the second (mean factor loading .07, range −.10 to .37). In contrast, all negatively keyed items scored strongly on the second component (mean factor loading .60, range .50 to .81) and minimally on the second (mean factor loading .01, range −.30 to .21). Thus, the Risk Taking facet scale appears to exhibit a method effect reflecting item keying.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1073191113486183">
<title>Convergent and Discriminant Validity</title>
<p>The univariate associations among the PID-5 facet scales, and between the PID-5 facet and domain scales, are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1073191113486183">Table 2</xref>. Facet scales within each domain were strongly correlated: mean <italic>r</italic> = .41 for Negative Affect; mean <italic>r</italic> = .42 for Detachment; mean <italic>r</italic> = .53 for Antagonism; mean <italic>r</italic> = .39 for Disinhibition; and mean <italic>r</italic> = .68 for Psychoticism. Facet scales across domains were also significantly associated, although to a lesser degree: mean <italic>r</italic> = .36 for Negative Affect; mean <italic>r</italic> = .30 for Detachment; mean <italic>r</italic> = .29 for Antagonism; mean <italic>r</italic> = .35 for Disinhibition; and mean <italic>r</italic> = .38 for Psychoticism. There was considerable range in discriminant associations, however. For example, within Negative Affect, Anxiousness was strongly associated with Anhedonia (Detachment) at <italic>r</italic> = .72, whereas Submissiveness was not significantly associated with Risk Taking (Disinhibition) at <italic>r</italic> = −.05. All domain scales were significantly positively associated, <italic>r</italic>s ranging from .18 to .69 (mean <italic>r</italic> = .46).</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1073191113486183" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Univariate Associations Between PID-5 Domain and Facet Trait Scales.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1073191113486183" xlink:href="10.1177_1073191113486183-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">1</th>
<th align="center">2</th>
<th align="center">3</th>
<th align="center">4</th>
<th align="center">5</th>
<th align="center">6</th>
<th align="center">7</th>
<th align="center">8</th>
<th align="center">9</th>
<th align="center">10</th>
<th align="center">11</th>
<th align="center">12</th>
<th align="center">13</th>
<th align="center">14</th>
<th align="center">15</th>
<th align="center">16</th>
<th align="center">17</th>
<th align="center">18</th>
<th align="center">19</th>
<th align="center">20</th>
<th align="center">21</th>
<th align="center">22</th>
<th align="center">23</th>
<th align="center">24</th>
<th/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> 1</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2</td>
<td>.72</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 3</td>
<td>−.01</td>
<td>.21</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 4</td>
<td>.27</td>
<td>.16</td>
<td>.29</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 5</td>
<td>.20</td>
<td>.26</td>
<td>.58</td>
<td>.63</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 6</td>
<td>.84</td>
<td>.80</td>
<td>.16</td>
<td>.34</td>
<td>.33</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 7</td>
<td>.58</td>
<td>.65</td>
<td>.33</td>
<td>.28</td>
<td>.44</td>
<td>.61</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 8</td>
<td>.45</td>
<td>.58</td>
<td>.34</td>
<td>.36</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td>.53</td>
<td>.60</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 9</td>
<td>.56</td>
<td>.74</td>
<td>.35</td>
<td>.18</td>
<td>.33</td>
<td>.67</td>
<td>.62</td>
<td>.48</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10</td>
<td>−.03</td>
<td>.12</td>
<td>.52</td>
<td>.41</td>
<td>.49</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>.21</td>
<td>.37</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11</td>
<td>.49</td>
<td>.58</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td>.57</td>
<td>.54</td>
<td>.62</td>
<td>.57</td>
<td>.48</td>
<td>.63</td>
<td>.34</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12</td>
<td>.20</td>
<td>.39</td>
<td>.49</td>
<td>.36</td>
<td>.54</td>
<td>.36</td>
<td>.53</td>
<td>.45</td>
<td>.53</td>
<td>.30</td>
<td>.58</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>13</td>
<td>.18</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td>−.06</td>
<td>.15</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td>.12</td>
<td>.16</td>
<td>.15</td>
<td>−.05</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>−.07</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14</td>
<td>.34</td>
<td>.38</td>
<td>.44</td>
<td>.52</td>
<td>.67</td>
<td>.49</td>
<td>.62</td>
<td>.47</td>
<td>.45</td>
<td>.29</td>
<td>.58</td>
<td>.58</td>
<td>.14</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td>.16</td>
<td>.59</td>
<td>.48</td>
<td>.79</td>
<td>.22</td>
<td>.29</td>
<td>.32</td>
<td>.21</td>
<td>.49</td>
<td>.40</td>
<td>.43</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>.56</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>16</td>
<td>.45</td>
<td>.59</td>
<td>.36</td>
<td>.34</td>
<td>.45</td>
<td>.56</td>
<td>.54</td>
<td>.71</td>
<td>.48</td>
<td>.34</td>
<td>.44</td>
<td>.44</td>
<td>.22</td>
<td>.47</td>
<td>.38</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>17</td>
<td>.56</td>
<td>.69</td>
<td>.38</td>
<td>.27</td>
<td>.41</td>
<td>.59</td>
<td>.72</td>
<td>.59</td>
<td>.59</td>
<td>.31</td>
<td>.55</td>
<td>.45</td>
<td>.13</td>
<td>.48</td>
<td>.29</td>
<td>.58</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>18</td>
<td>.29</td>
<td>.13</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td>.43</td>
<td>.37</td>
<td>.23</td>
<td>.24</td>
<td>.43</td>
<td>−.09</td>
<td>.29</td>
<td>.21</td>
<td>.09</td>
<td>.38</td>
<td>.30</td>
<td>.34</td>
<td>.39</td>
<td>.25</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>19</td>
<td>.40</td>
<td>.46</td>
<td>.30</td>
<td>.30</td>
<td>.34</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td>.50</td>
<td>.46</td>
<td>.37</td>
<td>.53</td>
<td>.31</td>
<td>.14</td>
<td>.25</td>
<td>.32</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td>.62</td>
<td>.25</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20</td>
<td>−.07</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>.41</td>
<td>.34</td>
<td>.36</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>.20</td>
<td>.27</td>
<td>.18</td>
<td>.30</td>
<td>.30</td>
<td>.52</td>
<td>−.11</td>
<td>.32</td>
<td>.37</td>
<td>.20</td>
<td>.14</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td>.19</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>21</td>
<td>.41</td>
<td>.56</td>
<td>.44</td>
<td>.18</td>
<td>.39</td>
<td>.56</td>
<td>.51</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td>.59</td>
<td>.23</td>
<td>.53</td>
<td>.49</td>
<td>−.12</td>
<td>.46</td>
<td>.36</td>
<td>.46</td>
<td>.49</td>
<td>.04</td>
<td>.31</td>
<td>.16</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>22</td>
<td>.33</td>
<td>.44</td>
<td>.23</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td>.20</td>
<td>.43</td>
<td>.40</td>
<td>.35</td>
<td>.41</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td>.23</td>
<td>.28</td>
<td>.14</td>
<td>.30</td>
<td>.19</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td>.38</td>
<td>.15</td>
<td>.21</td>
<td>−.05</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>23</td>
<td>.48</td>
<td>.66</td>
<td>.29</td>
<td>.32</td>
<td>.35</td>
<td>.57</td>
<td>.48</td>
<td>.56</td>
<td>.55</td>
<td>.28</td>
<td>.61</td>
<td>.45</td>
<td>.04</td>
<td>.38</td>
<td>.25</td>
<td>.49</td>
<td>.48</td>
<td>.16</td>
<td>.43</td>
<td>.26</td>
<td>.54</td>
<td>.40</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>24</td>
<td>.21</td>
<td>.33</td>
<td>.27</td>
<td>.24</td>
<td>.32</td>
<td>.29</td>
<td>.32</td>
<td>.66</td>
<td>.23</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td>.20</td>
<td>.31</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>.30</td>
<td>.32</td>
<td>.69</td>
<td>.34</td>
<td>.31</td>
<td>.30</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>.24</td>
<td>.29</td>
<td>.38</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25</td>
<td>.60</td>
<td>.46</td>
<td>−.02</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td>.28</td>
<td>.52</td>
<td>.46</td>
<td>.49</td>
<td>.25</td>
<td>.18</td>
<td>.38</td>
<td>.18</td>
<td>.46</td>
<td>.37</td>
<td>.16</td>
<td>.50</td>
<td>.44</td>
<td>.58</td>
<td>.33</td>
<td>−.02</td>
<td>.22</td>
<td>.29</td>
<td>.39</td>
<td>.31</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NA</td>
<td>.65</td>
<td>.89</td>
<td>.38</td>
<td>.20</td>
<td>.37</td>
<td>.78</td>
<td>.69</td>
<td>.67</td>
<td>.90</td>
<td>.17</td>
<td>.67</td>
<td>.54</td>
<td>−.03</td>
<td>.50</td>
<td>.28</td>
<td>.59</td>
<td>.68</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.47</td>
<td>.15</td>
<td>.82</td>
<td>.48</td>
<td>.67</td>
<td>.31</td>
<td>.36</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>DE</td>
<td>.75</td>
<td>.54</td>
<td>−.04</td>
<td>.36</td>
<td>.24</td>
<td>.62</td>
<td>.51</td>
<td>.46</td>
<td>.32</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td>.37</td>
<td>.12</td>
<td>.72</td>
<td>.36</td>
<td>.12</td>
<td>.50</td>
<td>.48</td>
<td>.53</td>
<td>.37</td>
<td>−.09</td>
<td>.21</td>
<td>.32</td>
<td>.38</td>
<td>.27</td>
<td>.88</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AN</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>.21</td>
<td>.67</td>
<td>.60</td>
<td>.90</td>
<td>.23</td>
<td>.37</td>
<td>.43</td>
<td>.25</td>
<td>.76</td>
<td>.50</td>
<td>.50</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td>.60</td>
<td>.90</td>
<td>.46</td>
<td>.40</td>
<td>.39</td>
<td>.40</td>
<td>.40</td>
<td>.38</td>
<td>.20</td>
<td>.34</td>
<td>.41</td>
<td>.24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>DI</td>
<td>.45</td>
<td>.57</td>
<td>.49</td>
<td>.45</td>
<td>.64</td>
<td>.58</td>
<td>.86</td>
<td>.60</td>
<td>.64</td>
<td>.31</td>
<td>.68</td>
<td>.84</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td>.84</td>
<td>.50</td>
<td>.57</td>
<td>.66</td>
<td>.24</td>
<td>.39</td>
<td>.41</td>
<td>.58</td>
<td>.39</td>
<td>.52</td>
<td>.37</td>
<td>.39</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PS</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td>.56</td>
<td>.36</td>
<td>.35</td>
<td>.45</td>
<td>.52</td>
<td>.55</td>
<td>.90</td>
<td>.44</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td>.45</td>
<td>.18</td>
<td>.47</td>
<td>.38</td>
<td>.88</td>
<td>.57</td>
<td>.43</td>
<td>.46</td>
<td>.22</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td>.39</td>
<td>.54</td>
<td>.88</td>
<td>.49</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-1073191113486183">
<p><italic>Note</italic>. All correlations ≥ |.16| are significant at <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05, all correlations ≥ |.20| are significant at <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. 1 = Anhedonia, 2 = Anxiousness, 3 = Attention Seeking, 4 = Callousness, 5 = Deceitfulness, 6 = Depressivity, 7 = Distractibility, 8 = Eccentricity, 9 = Emotional Lability, 10 = Grandiosity, 11 = Hostility, 12 = Impulsivity, 13 = Intimacy Avoidance, 14 = Irresponsibility, 15 = Manipulativeness, 16 = Perceptual Dysregulation, 17 = Perseveration, 18 = Restricted Affectivity, 19 = Rigid Perfectionism, 20 = Risk Taking, 21 = Separation Insecurity, 22 = Submissiveness, 23 = Suspiciousness, 24 = Unusual Beliefs and Experiences, 25 = Withdrawal; NA = Negative Affect, DE = Detachment, AN = Antagonism, DI = Disinhibition, PS = Psychoticism. Correlations between domain scales and the facet scales used in their calculation in gray.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The univariate associations between the PID-5 facet and domain scales and NEO PI-R domain scales are displayed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1073191113486183">Table 3</xref>. The pattern of results was consistent with expectations. Neuroticism, Extraversion, Agreeableness, and Conscientiousness were moderately to strongly associated with the correspondent PID-5 domain scales and the facet scales used to calculate them (in boldface in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1073191113486183">Table 3</xref> to facilitate review). Overall, Neuroticism demonstrated the greatest overall association with the PID-5 facets (mean <italic>r</italic> = .39), followed by Agreeableness (mean <italic>r</italic> = −.33) and Conscientiousness (mean <italic>r</italic> = −.32), reflecting the emotional distress and social and behavioral dysregulation typifying personality pathology. Of note, Openness-to-Experience was minimally associated with all the PID-5 scales with the exception of Risk Taking (<italic>r</italic> = .32).</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1073191113486183" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Univariate Associations Between PID-5 Domain and Facet Trait Scales and NEO PI-R Domain Scales.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1073191113486183" xlink:href="10.1177_1073191113486183-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Domains/facets</th>
<th align="center">N</th>
<th align="center">E</th>
<th align="center">O</th>
<th align="center">A</th>
<th align="center">C</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Negative affect</td>
<td><bold>.81</bold></td>
<td>−.24</td>
<td>.08</td>
<td>−.26</td>
<td>−.52</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Detachment</td>
<td>.49</td>
<td>−<bold>.71</bold></td>
<td>−.21</td>
<td>−.22</td>
<td>−.37</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Psychoticism</td>
<td>.39</td>
<td>−.24</td>
<td>.02</td>
<td>−.30</td>
<td>−.30</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Antagonism</td>
<td>.13</td>
<td>.14</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>−<bold>.60</bold></td>
<td>−.22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Disinhibition</td>
<td>.59</td>
<td>−.10</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>−.43</td>
<td>−<bold>.68</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Anhedonia</td>
<td>.70</td>
<td>−<bold>.66</bold></td>
<td>−.11</td>
<td>−.22</td>
<td>−.45</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Anxiousness</td>
<td><bold>.82</bold></td>
<td>−.42</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>−.23</td>
<td>−.46</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Attention Seeking</td>
<td>.19</td>
<td>.38</td>
<td>.18</td>
<td>−.39</td>
<td>−.20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Callousness</td>
<td>.17</td>
<td>−.16</td>
<td>−.06</td>
<td>−.61</td>
<td>−.24</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Deceitfulness</td>
<td>.26</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td>−<bold>.58</bold></td>
<td>−.39</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Depressivity</td>
<td>.78</td>
<td>−.49</td>
<td>−.04</td>
<td>−.26</td>
<td>−.52</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Distractibility</td>
<td>.62</td>
<td>−.29</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td>−.29</td>
<td>−<bold>.60</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Eccentricity</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td>−.26</td>
<td>.06</td>
<td>−.33</td>
<td>−.34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Emotional Lability</td>
<td><bold>.73</bold></td>
<td>−.16</td>
<td>.14</td>
<td>−.19</td>
<td>−.46</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Grandiosity</td>
<td>−.04</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>.05</td>
<td>−<bold>.48</bold></td>
<td>.06</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hostility</td>
<td>.63</td>
<td>−.16</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td>−.58</td>
<td>−.46</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Impulsivity</td>
<td>.43</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td>−.40</td>
<td>−<bold>.51</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Intimacy Avoidance</td>
<td>.07</td>
<td>−<bold>.34</bold></td>
<td>−.19</td>
<td>−.02</td>
<td>−.11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Irresponsibility</td>
<td>.44</td>
<td>−.05</td>
<td>.01</td>
<td>−.43</td>
<td>−<bold>.61</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Manipulativeness</td>
<td>.11</td>
<td>.18</td>
<td>.10</td>
<td>−<bold>.47</bold></td>
<td>−.20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Perceptual Dysregulation</td>
<td>.43</td>
<td>−.24</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td>−.26</td>
<td>−.31</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Perseveration</td>
<td>.60</td>
<td>−.26</td>
<td>.16</td>
<td>−.30</td>
<td>−.40</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Restricted Affectivity</td>
<td>.04</td>
<td>−.37</td>
<td>−.16</td>
<td>−.29</td>
<td>−.15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rigid Perfectionism</td>
<td>.34</td>
<td>−.13</td>
<td>.21</td>
<td>−.32</td>
<td>.02</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Risk Taking</td>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.33</td>
<td>.32</td>
<td>−.37</td>
<td>−.13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Separation Insecurity</td>
<td><bold>.55</bold></td>
<td>−.04</td>
<td>.00</td>
<td>−.26</td>
<td>−.42</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Submissiveness</td>
<td>.41</td>
<td>−.17</td>
<td>−.12</td>
<td>−.03</td>
<td>−.29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Suspiciousness</td>
<td>.58</td>
<td>−.22</td>
<td>−.01</td>
<td>−.47</td>
<td>−.35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Unusual Beliefs &amp; Perceptions</td>
<td>.17</td>
<td>−.12</td>
<td>−.02</td>
<td>−.20</td>
<td>−.13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Withdrawal</td>
<td>.39</td>
<td>−<bold>.67</bold></td>
<td>−.19</td>
<td>−.28</td>
<td>−.32</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn3-1073191113486183">
<p><italic>Note</italic>. All correlations |.16| are significant at <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05, all correlations |.20| are significant at <italic>p</italic> &lt; .01. N = Neuroticism, E = Extraversion, O = Openness to Experience, A = Agreeableness, C = Conscientiousness.</p></fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The results of the linear regression analyses are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1073191113486183">Table 4</xref>. NEO PI-R facet scales accounted for more than 50% of the variance in the analogous PID-5 domain scale for all domains but Psychoticism. Negative Affect was positively predicted by Anxiety and Angry Hostility. Detachment was negatively predicted by Warmth, Gregariousness, Assertiveness, and Positive Emotions. Antagonism was negatively predicted by Straightforwardness and Modesty. Disinhibition was positively predicted by Achievement Striving and negatively by Dutifulness, Self-discipline, and Deliberation. Finally, Psychoticism was positive predicted by Fantasy and negatively by Actions and Values.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-1073191113486183" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Linear Regression Analyses of the NEO PI-R Facets Predicting PID-5 Domains.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1073191113486183" xlink:href="10.1177_1073191113486183-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Criterion/predictors</th>
<th align="center"><italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></th>
<th align="center"><italic>F</italic></th>
<th align="center">β</th>
<th align="center"><italic>t</italic></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Negative Affect</td>
<td>.67</td>
<td>62.30<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1073191113486183">**</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Anxiety</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.39</td>
<td>4.96<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1073191113486183">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Angry hostility</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.22</td>
<td>3.75<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1073191113486183">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Depression</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.09</td>
<td>1.05</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Self-consciousness</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.07</td>
<td>1.06</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Impulsiveness</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.04</td>
<td>.80</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Vulnerability</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.14</td>
<td>1.92</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Detachment</td>
<td>.56</td>
<td>38.84<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1073191113486183">**</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Warmth</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.21</td>
<td>2.94<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1073191113486183">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Gregariousness</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.31</td>
<td>4.42<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1073191113486183">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Assertiveness</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.14</td>
<td>2.50<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1073191113486183">*</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Activity</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.09</td>
<td>1.54</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Excitement-seeking</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.09</td>
<td>1.49</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Positive emotions</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.26</td>
<td>4.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1073191113486183">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Psychoticism</td>
<td>.25</td>
<td>10.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1073191113486183">**</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Fantasy</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.36</td>
<td>5.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1073191113486183">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Aesthetics</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.01</td>
<td>.11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Feelings</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.04</td>
<td>.52</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Actions</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.29</td>
<td>4.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1073191113486183">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Ideas</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.13</td>
<td>1.70</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Values</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.25</td>
<td>3.73<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1073191113486183">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Antagonism</td>
<td>.52</td>
<td>33.37<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1073191113486183">**</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Trust</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.07</td>
<td>1.11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Straightforwardness</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.55</td>
<td>7.82<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1073191113486183">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Altruism</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.03</td>
<td>.52</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Compliance</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.05</td>
<td>.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Modesty</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.24</td>
<td>3.98<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1073191113486183">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Tender-mindedness</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.04</td>
<td>.64</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Disinhibition</td>
<td>.56</td>
<td>39.94<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1073191113486183">**</xref></td>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Competence</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.10</td>
<td>1.29</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Order</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.01</td>
<td>.22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Dutifulness</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.19</td>
<td>2.69<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1073191113486183">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Achievement striving</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>.22</td>
<td>3.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1073191113486183">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Self-discipline</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.45</td>
<td>5.83<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1073191113486183">**</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Deliberation</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>−.31</td>
<td>4.80<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-1073191113486183">**</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-1073191113486183">
<p><italic>Note</italic>.*<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. **<italic>p</italic> &lt; .01.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1073191113486183" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>These results contribute to a growing body of evidence supporting the validity of the trait model and clinical tool proposed by the <italic>DSM-5</italic> Personality and Personality Disorders workgroup. As anticipated, the majority of trait scales were elevated in the current clinical sample as compared with the representative sample of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1073191113486183">Krueger et al. (2012)</xref>; the decreased severity of Grandiosity and Manipulativeness may be related to the Axis I disorders characterizing the current sample. Domain and facet scales demonstrated acceptable levels of internal consistency, and factor analyses supported a unidimensional structure for all scales but one, supporting the interpretation of a single summary score. The impact of the method effect of the Risk Taking facet scale on measurement accuracy and validity requires further investigation, however.</p>
<p>The PID-5 facet scales within domains were strongly associated, although significant associations were also observed among facets across domains, consistent with our hypothesis that scales would be associated due to their saturation with personality pathology and associated distress, as well as with the strong secondary loadings evidenced in previous research (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1073191113486183">Krueger et al., 2012</xref>). The moderate associations between domain scales were also in line with these hypotheses and previous literature. The PID-5 domain and facet scales were also strongly associated with analogous NEO PI-R domain scales, supporting the convergent validity of these scales. Evidence for the discriminant validity of the PID-5 domain and facet scales was mixed, however. Disinhibition domain and associated facet scales were strongly associated with Neuroticism scores, and Negative Affect scales similarly with Conscientiousness; such patterns of association are captured in hierarchical models such as outlined by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1073191113486183">Wright et al. (2012)</xref>. Numerous facets were associated with more than one NEO PI-R domain scale to a similar degree. In some cases (e.g., Unusual Beliefs and Perceptions scale) this may indicate the lack of available scales appropriate to gauge convergent and discriminant validity in the NEO PI-R; however, in others (e.g., Risk Taking) this may further indicate shortcomings in these forms of validity in these PID-5 scales.</p>
<p>The <italic>PID-5</italic> domain scale associations with NEO PI-R facet scales provide further characterization of domains according to this novel scoring algorithm. Of note, Openness to Experience was minimally associated with all the PID-5 scales with the exception of Risk Taking (<italic>r</italic> = .32). NEO PI-R Openness facet scales accounted for a quarter of the variance in the PID-5 Psychoticism scale, which was uniquely associated with Fantasy in the positive direction, and Actions and Values in the negative direction. Thus, the trait domain associated with oddity, eccentricity, and peculiarity is clearly more consistent with the content domain of psychoticism as conceptualized by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1073191113486183">Harkness and McNulty (1994)</xref>, as compared with the imaginativeness and exploration typifying openness/intellect—as well as the unsympathetic, nonconforming trait domain of the same name described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1073191113486183">Eysenck, Eysenck, and Barrett (1985)</xref>.</p>
<p>Previous investigations have provided critical evidence for the validity of this measure and model. The current investigation contributes to this line of research in being one of the first tests of the PID-5 in a psychiatric sample. This psychiatric sample exhibited a broad range of Axis I and II symptoms, as reflected by the range of psychiatric conditions including a significant proportion of patients meeting criteria for personality disorder diagnoses (34.3%). In this context, results generally supported the internal consistency, factor structure, and convergent validity of most of the PID-5 domain and facet scales in a clinical setting. Previous investigations have explored the hierarchical structure of the facet scales, which speaks to the validity of this measure via its convergence with established hierarchical models of personality (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1073191113486183">Anderson et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1073191113486183">Ashton et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1073191113486183">Wright et al., 2012</xref>). The current investigation maintained a more translational focus on the psychometric properties that may permit clinicians to confidently and knowledgeably interpret scale scores, with a nuanced understanding of how those scores are linked with a popular model of personality. Continued research such as that of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1073191113486183">Hopwood, Schade, Krueger, Wright, and Markon (in press)</xref>, who demonstrated specific dysfunctional beliefs tied to the PID-5 personality domains, will further contribute to the evaluation of the clinical utility of the PID-5 traits, in psychological treatment as well as assessment.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We are indebted to all patients and clinicians for the time and effort they dedicated to their involvement in this research.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: The operating costs of this research were supported by the CAMH Foundation.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sellbom</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bagby</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Quilty</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Veltri</surname><given-names>C. O.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Markon</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>On the convergence between PSY-5 domains and PID-5 domains and facets: Implications for assessment of DSM-5 personality traits</article-title>. <source>Assessment</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>286</fpage>-<lpage>294</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ashton</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hendrickse</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Born</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The maladaptive personality traits of the Personality Inventory for DSM-5 (PID-5) in relation to the HEXACO personality factors and schizotypy/dissociation</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality Disorders</source>, <volume>26</volume>, <fpage>641</fpage>-<lpage>659</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bagby</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>P. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCrae</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Livesley</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Levitan</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>L. T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Replicating the five factor model of personality in a psychiatric sample</article-title>. <source>Personality and Individual Differences</source>, <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>1135</fpage>-<lpage>1139</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <source>Manual for the schedule for nonadaptive and adaptive personality</source>. <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Simms</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Casillas</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (in press). <source>Manual for the schedule for nonadaptive and adaptive personality– 2nd edition (SNAP-2)</source>. <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Narrow</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Regier</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuramoto</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kupfer</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuhl</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kraemer</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>DSM-5 field trials in the United States and Canada, Part I: Study design, sampling strategy, implementation, and analytic approaches</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Psychiatry</source>, <volume>170</volume>, <fpage>43</fpage>-<lpage>58</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>P. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bagby</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Herbst</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCrae</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Personality self-reports are concurrently reliable and valid during acute depressive episodes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Affective Disorders</source>, <volume>89</volume>, <fpage>45</fpage>-<lpage>55</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>P. T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCrae</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <source>Revised NEO Personality Inventory (NEO-PI-R) and NEO Five-Factor Inventory professional manual</source>. <publisher-loc>Odessa, FL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Psychological Assessment Resources</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>De Fruyt</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Clercq</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>De Bolle</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wille</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Markon</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>General and maladaptive traits in a five-factor framework for DSM-5 in a university student sample</article-title>. <source>Assessment</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>295</fpage>-<lpage>307</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>De Fruyt</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bagby</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rolland</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rouillon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group>. (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Assessing and interpreting personality change and continuity in patients treated for major depression</article-title>. <source>Psychological Assessment</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>71</fpage>-<lpage>80</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Eysenck</surname><given-names>S. B. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eysenck</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>A revised version of the Psychoticism Scale</article-title>. <source>Personality and Individual Differences</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>21</fpage>-<lpage>29</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gignac</surname><given-names>G. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>T. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Implications relevant to CFA model misfit, reliability, and the five-factor model as measured by the NEO-FFI</article-title>. <source>Personality and Individual Differences</source>, <volume>43</volume>, <fpage>1051</fpage>-<lpage>1062</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Harkness</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Finn</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McNulty</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The personality Psychopathology-Five (PSY-5): Recent constructive replication and assessment literature review</article-title>. <source>Psychological Assessment</source>, <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>432</fpage>-<lpage>443</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Harkness</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McNulty</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>The Personality Psychopathology Five (PSY-5): Issues from the pages of a diagnostic manual instead of a dictionary</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Strack</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lorr</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Differentiating normal and abnormal personality</source> (pp. <fpage>291</fpage>-<lpage>315</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hopwood</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schade</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>A. G. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Markon</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (in press). <article-title>Connecting DSM-5 personality traits and pathological beliefs: Toward a unifying model</article-title>. <source>Journal of Psychopathology and Behavioral Assessment</source>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hopwood</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Markon</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>A. G. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title><italic>DSM-5</italic> personality traits and <italic>DSM-IV</italic> personality disorders</article-title>. <source>Journal of Abnormal Psychology</source>, <volume>121</volume>, <fpage>424</fpage>-<lpage>432</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1965</year>). <article-title>A rationale and test for the number of factors in factor analysis</article-title>. <source>Psychometrika</source>, <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>179</fpage>-<lpage>185</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Derringer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Markon</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Skodol</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Initial construction of a maladaptive personality trait model and inventory for <italic>DSM-5</italic></article-title>. <source>Psychological Medicine</source>, <volume>42</volume>, <fpage>1879</fpage>-<lpage>1890</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>N. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Markon</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Derringer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Livesley</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Deriving an empirical structure of personality pathology for DSM-5</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality Disorders</source>, <volume>25</volume>, <fpage>170</fpage>-<lpage>191</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Livesley</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vernon</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Phenotypic and genetic structure of traits delineating personality disorder</article-title>. <source>Archives of General Psychiatry</source>, <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>941</fpage>-<lpage>948</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1970</year>). <article-title>The theoretical foundations of principal factor analysis, canonical factor analysis, and alpha factor analysis</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Statistical and Mathematical Psychology</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>21</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Muthén</surname><given-names>L. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muthén</surname><given-names>B. O.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998-2006</year>). <source>Mplus user’s guide</source> (<edition>4th ed.</edition>). <publisher-loc>Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Muthén &amp; Muthén</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Narrow</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuramoto</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kraemer</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kupfer</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greiner</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Regier</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>DSM-5 field trials in the United States and Canada, Part III: Development and reliability testing of a cross-cutting symptom assessment for DSM-5</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Psychiatry</source>, <volume>170</volume>, <fpage>71</fpage>-<lpage>82</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>O’Connor</surname><given-names>B. P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>SPSS, SAS, and MATLAB programs for determining the number of components using parallel analysis and Velicer’s MAP test</article-title>. <source>Behavior Research Methods, Instruments, &amp; Computers</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>396</fpage>-<lpage>402</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Regier</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Narrow</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kraemer</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuramoto</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kuhl</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kupfer</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>DSM-5 field trials in the United States and Canada, Part II: Test-retest reliability of selected categorical diagnoses</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Psychiatry</source>, <volume>170</volume>, <fpage>59</fpage>-<lpage>70</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Samuel</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Widiger</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>A meta-analytic review of the relationships between the five-factor model and DSM-IV-TR personality disorders: A facet level analysis</article-title>. <source>Clinical Psychology Review</source>, <volume>28</volume>, <fpage>1326</fpage>-<lpage>1342</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tackett</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Silberschmidt</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sponheim</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>A dimensional model of personality disorder: Incorporating <italic>DSM</italic> Cluster A characteristics</article-title>. <source>Journal of Abnormal Psychology</source>, <volume>117</volume>, <fpage>454</fpage>-<lpage>459</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yalch</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>A. G. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Markon</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hopwood</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The convergent structure of DSM-5 personality trait facets and five-factor model trait domains</article-title>. <source>Assessment</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>308</fpage>-<lpage>311</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Velicer</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1976</year>). <article-title>Determining the number of components from the matrix of partial correlations</article-title>. <source>Psychometrika</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>321</fpage>-<lpage>327</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chmielewski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Structures of personality and their relevance to psychopathology: II. Further articulation of a comprehensive unified trait structure</article-title>. <source>Journal of Personality</source>, <volume>76</volume>, <fpage>1545</fpage>-<lpage>1586</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stasik</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ro</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Integrating normal and pathological personality: Relating the <italic>DSM-5</italic> trait dimensional model to general traits of personality</article-title>. <source>Assessment</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>312</fpage>-<lpage>326</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>A. G. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pincus</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hopwood</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Markon</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>An interpersonal analysis of pathological personality traits in DSM-5</article-title>. <source>Assessment</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>263</fpage>-<lpage>275</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1073191113486183">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>A. G. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hopwood</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Markon</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pincus</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The hierarchical structure of DSM-5 pathological personality traits</article-title>. <source>Journal of Abnormal Psychology</source>, <volume>121</volume>, <fpage>951</fpage>-<lpage>957</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>