<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AJS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">amjsports</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Sports Med</journal-id>
<journal-title>The American Journal of Sports Medicine</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0363-5465</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-3365</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0363546513479771</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0363546513479771</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Knee</subject>
</subj-group>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll">
<subject>22</subject>
<subject>40</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Effect of Evidence and Changes in Reimbursement on the Rate of Arthroscopy for Osteoarthritis</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0363546513479771">*</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546513479771">†</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Moschetti</surname><given-names>Wayne</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, MS</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546513479771">†</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>Brook</given-names></name>
<degrees>PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546513479771">†</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0363546513479771">‡</xref>
</contrib> <contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Tomek</surname><given-names>Ivan</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, FRCSC</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0363546513479771">†</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0363546513479771">§</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Finlayson</surname><given-names>Samuel</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, MPH</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0363546513479771">§</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0363546513479771">‖</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0363546513479771"><label>†</label>Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center, Lebanon, New Hampshire</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0363546513479771"><label>‡</label>Geisel School of Medicine at Dartmouth, Hanover, New Hampshire</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0363546513479771"><label>§</label>Dartmouth Institute for Health Policy and Clinical Practice, Lebanon, New Hampshire</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0363546513479771"><label>‖</label>Center for Surgery and Public Health, Brigham and Women’s Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts</aff>
<aff id="aff5-0363546513479771">Investigation performed at Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center, Lebanon, New Hampshire</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0363546513479771"><label>*</label>Robert Holmes, MD, Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center, 1 Medical Center Drive Lebanon, NH 03756 (e-mail: <email>Robert.E.Holmes@Hitchcock.org</email>).</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>41</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>1039</fpage>
<lpage>1043</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2013 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">American Orthopaedic Society for Sports Medicine</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-0363546513479771">
<title>Background:</title>
<p>The efficacy of arthroscopic debridement or lavage for knee osteoarthritis (OA) was cast into doubt after publication of several randomized controlled trials beginning in 2002.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0363546513479771">
<title>Purpose:</title>
<p>The authors set out to determine whether evidence of ineffectiveness, along with subsequent changes in reimbursement, were followed by changes in utilization rates of arthroscopy for patients with OA.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0363546513479771">
<title>Study Design:</title>
<p>Cohort study (prevalence); Level of evidence, 2.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0363546513479771">
<title>Methods:</title>
<p>The Florida State Ambulatory Surgery Database was used to examine population-based rates of knee arthroscopy from 2000 to 2008 for patients with and without the diagnosis of OA; data were stratified between public and private payers. These trends were compared with patients who underwent arthroscopy for other diagnoses and were also compared with patients whose arthritis was not the primary indication for surgery.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0363546513479771">
<title>Results:</title>
<p>A 39% decrease in the adjusted population-based rate of knee arthroscopy for OA was observed, from 12.2 per 100,000 adults in 2000 (95% CI, 9.9-14.4) to 7.7 per 100,000 adults in 2008 (95% CI, 6.7-8.6). The overall rate among individuals with a primary diagnosis of OA significantly decreased for both public (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) and private insurance (<italic>P</italic> = .001) and the rate of this decrease was similar between the two insurance types (<italic>P</italic> = .610). Although the unadjusted rates for all knee arthroscopy increased over the study period, the rate of increase was slowed in the years following the publication of several randomized controlled trials and subsequent changes in reimbursement. The average effect on arthroscopy rates attributed to these events was a reduction in 12 per 100,000 private arthroscopies (95% CI, –16.3 to 40.6; <italic>P</italic> = .404) and 35.7 per 100,000 publicly insured arthroscopies (95% CI, 15.0-56.4; <italic>P</italic> = .001).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-0363546513479771">
<title>Conclusion:</title>
<p>Evidence of the lack of efficacy of arthroscopy for knee OA, along with changes in reimbursement, preceded a significant decline in the population-based rates of this procedure in both publicly and privately insured patients in Florida.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>osteoarthritis</kwd>
<kwd>arthroscopy</kwd>
<kwd>placebo</kwd>
<kwd>evidence-based medicine</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Osteoarthritis (OA) is the most common form of arthritis, affecting more than 27 million people in the United States.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0363546513479771">15</xref></sup> Arthroscopy of the knee is one of the most common surgical procedures performed in the country, with approximately 956,000 procedures performed in 2006<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0363546513479771">19</xref></sup> at an average cost of US$5000 per procedure.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0363546513479771">17</xref></sup> Before the 2002 randomized controlled trial by Moseley et al,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0363546513479771">17</xref></sup> arthroscopic surgery with or without knee lavage was believed to help those suffering from severe OA who had failed medical management. Uncontrolled studies suggested that roughly half of patients reported relief of knee pain after arthroscopy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0363546513479771">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0363546513479771"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0363546513479771">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0363546513479771">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0363546513479771">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0363546513479771">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0363546513479771">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0363546513479771">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0363546513479771">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0363546513479771">21</xref></sup></p>
<p>Moseley et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0363546513479771">17</xref></sup> demonstrated no significant difference in patient self-reported knee pain between groups randomized to arthroscopic debridement, arthroscopic lavage, or placebo surgery. This level 1 evidence suggests that knee arthroscopy for OA is no more effective than sham surgery at improving pain and functional outcomes. The Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services (CMS) subsequently made a national coverage decision June 10, 2004, to stop reimbursement for arthroscopy procedures in patients with OA as the primary indication for surgery.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0363546513479771">1</xref></sup> Knee arthroscopy for other diagnoses, including meniscus tear, ligament injury, and loose body removal, continues to be reimbursed.</p>
<p>Previous studies have not examined whether population-based rates for this procedure have decreased after publication of the increasing body of evidence suggesting lack of efficacy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0363546513479771">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0363546513479771">14</xref></sup> The purpose of this study was to examine whether there was a change in the overall population-based rate of knee arthroscopy among those with OA after the publication of the Moseley et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0363546513479771">17</xref></sup> study.</p>
<sec id="section7-0363546513479771" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<p>We examined Florida’s State Ambulatory Surgery Database (SASD), an annual registry encompassing all ambulatory surgical admissions, for the years 2000 through 2008. The SASD is maintained by the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality as part of the Health Care Utilization Project (HCUP). These data provide patient-level discharge information that can be used to examine the cost and quality of health services, patterns of medical practice, access to health care programs, and treatment outcomes. To report the rates of arthroscopy procedures, we used age- and sex-stratified population denominators, available from the US Census Bureau.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0363546513479771">22</xref></sup></p>
<p>Current Procedural Terminology (CPT) codes were used to identify all patients who underwent knee arthroscopy. In the SASD there are up to 10 CPT fields for each encounter; we searched all of these fields to identify those undergoing knee arthroscopy (see Appendix 1, available in the online version of this article at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ajsm.sagepub.com/supplemental">http://ajsm.sagepub.com/supplemental</ext-link>). Codes for bilateral procedures are not available in SASD.</p>
<p>We classified patients into 3 non–mutually exclusive, clinically relevant groups based on the <italic>International Classification of Diseases, 9th Revision, Clinical Modification</italic> (<italic>ICD-9-CM</italic>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0363546513479771">18</xref></sup> The 3 groups were (1) those with a primary diagnosis of OA as defined by a primary <italic>ICD-9-CM</italic> diagnosis of 715.xx; (2) those without any diagnosis of OA; and (3) all patients undergoing knee arthroscopy, without regard to diagnosis.</p>
<sec id="section8-0363546513479771">
<title>Covariates</title>
<p>Changes in population characteristics over time had the potential to influence the observed trends. To account for these changes we included variables for age, sex, insurance type, and comorbidity. Insurance was broadly classified as “public” or “private” using the primary payer information included in the SASD. Public insurance included Medicare, Medicaid, and workers’ compensation; private insurance included health maintenance organizations and commercial insurance. We used the enhanced version of the Charlson index by Quan et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0363546513479771">20</xref></sup> to account for comorbidity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0363546513479771">
<title>Statistical Analysis</title>
<p>Poisson regression was used to model the population rates of knee arthroscopy and to assess changes after the publication of the Moseley et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0363546513479771">17</xref></sup> study (“post-Moseley change”). Poisson regression is an appropriate method for modeling count data because it avoids taking on negative values that might be encountered in ordinary least squares methods, it can easily be used to report incidence rate ratios (IRRs), and it allows for the creation of absolute event counts. We aggregated arthroscopy counts into a quarterly time-series, along with corresponding distributions for age, sex, insurance, and comorbidity. The mean rate of knee arthroscopy was then modeled with an offset for the log population size. We then tested for discontinuity in the regression coefficient before and after the Moseley study (ie, before and after June 2002) while controlling for age, sex, comorbidity, and insurance. Because insurance modifies the effect on rates and volume of arthroscopy, we included an interaction term between the indicator variable for the post-Moseley change and the type of insurance. Next, we included a grouped-linear parameter for the calendar year during the pre-Mosley period because a policy effect estimator may be biased if there is a temporal trend in the data that is independent of the policy question.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0363546513479771">8</xref></sup> Including this parameter removes the temporal trends and provides an unbiased estimate of the policy effect. Finally, we controlled for seasonal variations in the observed rates for Florida by including a categorical indicator for quarter. All analyses were performed using STATA version 11 (College Station, TX) with hypothesis testing at an alpha level of .05.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0363546513479771">
<title>Institutional Review Board Status</title>
<p>The study protocol was approved by the Committee for the Protection of Human Subjects. A waiver of patient consent was granted because the study involved solely an analysis of preexisting deidentified data.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0363546513479771" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The baseline characteristics in regards to age, sex, race, comorbidity index, and primary payer information for patients undergoing knee arthroscopy in Florida are outlined in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0363546513479771">Table 1</xref>. For all diagnoses, patients were overwhelmingly white, had no comorbidity, and were privately insured. The average age during the pre-Moseley period for those with primary OA who underwent arthroscopy was 58.3 years compared with 56.7 in the post-Moseley period (<italic>P</italic> &lt; .001). Without regard to diagnosis, there was a slight increase in mean age between the pre- and post-Moseley period, from 52.6 to 53.4 years.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0363546513479771" position="float">
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Baseline Characteristics of Patients Undergoing Knee Arthroscopy Before and After 2002 in Florida<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn1-0363546513479771"><italic>a</italic></xref></sup></p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0363546513479771" xlink:href="10.1177_0363546513479771-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center" colspan="2">Primary OA<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">No OA<hr/></th>
<th align="center" colspan="2">All Arthroscopy<hr/></th>
</tr>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="center">Pre (n = 4019)</th>
<th align="center">Post (n = 6974)</th>
<th align="center">Pre (n = 82,075)</th>
<th align="center">Post (n = 257,154)</th>
<th align="center">Pre (n = 101,857)</th>
<th align="center">Post (n = 310,536)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Age, y, mean (SD)</td>
<td>58.3 (12.9)</td>
<td>56.7 (12.8)</td>
<td>51.0 (14.9)</td>
<td>52.3 (14.4)</td>
<td>52.6 (14.9)</td>
<td>53.4 (14.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sex, % male</td>
<td>43.5</td>
<td>43.2</td>
<td>55.6</td>
<td>53.8</td>
<td>53.6</td>
<td>52.2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Race, n (%)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> White</td>
<td>3301 (84.5)</td>
<td>5637 (82.5)</td>
<td>65,154 (81.9)</td>
<td>203,264 (80.9)</td>
<td>81,675 (82.6)</td>
<td>246,724 (81.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Black</td>
<td>338 (8.7)</td>
<td>639 (9.4)</td>
<td>5512 (6.9)</td>
<td>17,539 (7.0)</td>
<td>6924 (7.0)</td>
<td>21,787 (7.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Hispanic</td>
<td>160 (4.1)</td>
<td>374 (5.5)</td>
<td>6522 (8.2)</td>
<td>21,790 (8.7)</td>
<td>7416 (7.5)</td>
<td>25,108 (8.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Asian/Pacific Islander</td>
<td>13 (0.3)</td>
<td>28 (0.4)</td>
<td>248 (0.3)</td>
<td>1203 (0.5)</td>
<td>303 (0.3)</td>
<td>1416 (0.5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Native American</td>
<td>9 (0.2)</td>
<td>14 (0.2)</td>
<td>224 (0.3)</td>
<td>313 (0.1)</td>
<td>255 (0.3)</td>
<td>382 (0.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>84 (2.2)</td>
<td>140 (2.0)</td>
<td>1889 (2.4)</td>
<td>7229 (2.9)</td>
<td>2297 (2.3)</td>
<td>8416 (2.8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Charlson index score (%)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 0</td>
<td>3741 (93.1)</td>
<td>6284 (90.1)</td>
<td>78,709 (95.9)</td>
<td>242,962 (94.5)</td>
<td>97,195 (95.4)</td>
<td>290,801 (93.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 1</td>
<td>252 (6.3)</td>
<td>578 (8.3)</td>
<td>3106 (3.8)</td>
<td>12,517 (4.9)</td>
<td>4305 (4.2)</td>
<td>17,305 (5.6)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2</td>
<td>26 (0.6)</td>
<td>112 (1.6)</td>
<td>260 (0.3)</td>
<td>1675 (0.7)</td>
<td>357 (0.4)</td>
<td>2430 (0.8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Primary payer, n (%)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Medicare</td>
<td>1340 (33.3)</td>
<td>1950 (28.0)</td>
<td>16,774 (20.4)</td>
<td>53,571 (20.8)</td>
<td>23,769 (23.3)</td>
<td>70,801 (22.8)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Medicaid</td>
<td>103 (2.6)</td>
<td>144 (2.1)</td>
<td>1589 (1.9)</td>
<td>3401 (1.3)</td>
<td>1933 (1.9)</td>
<td>4187 (1.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Private insurance</td>
<td>2122 (52.8)</td>
<td>4097 (58.8)</td>
<td>48,922 (59.6)</td>
<td>159,385 (62.0)</td>
<td>59,312 (58.2)</td>
<td>189,577 (62.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Self-pay</td>
<td>39 (1.0)</td>
<td>59 (0.8)</td>
<td>1390 (1.7)</td>
<td>3784 (1.5)</td>
<td>1579 (1.6)</td>
<td>4176 (1.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> No charge</td>
<td>3 (0.1)</td>
<td>14 (0.2)</td>
<td>207 (0.3)</td>
<td>553 (0.2)</td>
<td>230 (0.2)</td>
<td>637 (0.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Other</td>
<td>412 (10.3)</td>
<td>708 (10.2)</td>
<td>13,193 (16.1)</td>
<td>36,294 (14.1)</td>
<td>15,034 (14.8)</td>
<td>40,980 (13.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Payer type, n (%)</td>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Public</td>
<td>2164 (53.8)</td>
<td>4172 (59.8)</td>
<td>50,519 (61.6)</td>
<td>163,888 (63.7)</td>
<td>61,121 (60.0)</td>
<td>194,568 (62.7)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Private</td>
<td>1855 (46.2)</td>
<td>2802 (40.2)</td>
<td>31,556 (38.4)</td>
<td>93,266 (36.3)</td>
<td>40,736 (40.0)</td>
<td>115,968 (37.3)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0363546513479771">
<label>a</label>
<p>Based on the primary diagnosis of osteoarthritis (OA), those without OA, and all those undergoing arthroscopy regardless of diagnosis. Data from the Healthcare and Utilization Project (HCUP) database. Pre, before the Moseley et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0363546513479771">17</xref></sup> (2002) study; post, after 2002.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section12-0363546513479771">
<title>Rates and Volumes for Knee Arthroscopy</title>
<p>The annual volume of knee arthroscopy associated with a primary diagnosis of OA in Florida decreased from 1453 cases in 2000 to 885 cases in 2008, a 39% decrease. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0363546513479771">Figure 1</xref> shows quarterly procedure rates and volumes stratified by insurance type.) This corresponds to a 39% decrease in the adjusted population-based rate of knee arthroscopy for OA, from 12.2 per 100,000 adults in 2000 (95% confidence interval [CI], 9.9-14.4) to 7.7 per 100,000 adults in 2008 (95% CI, 6.7-8.6). The changes in the adjusted rates of knee arthroscopy for OA from pre- to post-Moseley periods (ie, the post-Moseley change) were similar between public and private insurances. After adjustment for age, sex, insurance type, and comorbidity, the marginal change observed after the Moseley publication on knee arthroscopy rates for OA was a reduction by 6.6 per 100,000 adults (<italic>P</italic> = .001; 95% CI, 2.6-10.6), or in absolute terms, a decrease of 118 arthroscopies for OA per year (95% CI, 98-138).</p>
<fig id="fig1-0363546513479771" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Rates and volume of knee arthroscopy for osteoarthritis in Florida by insurance status before and after the Moseley et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0363546513479771">17</xref></sup> study (2002). Source: Florida State Ambulatory Surgery Database (SASD) 2000-2008; data adjusted for age, sex, comorbidity, and seasonality.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546513479771-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>During the same years, the volume of knee arthroscopy without regard to diagnosis increased from 37,834 in 2000 to 51,224 in 2008 (a 35.4% increase). For privately insured patients, this corresponded to a 23.0% increase in the adjusted rates of knee arthroscopy, rising from 382 per 100,000 in 2000 (95% CI, 366-397) to 470 per 100,000 adults in 2008 (95% CI, 461-480) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0363546513479771">Figure 2</xref>). The adjusted population-based rate among publicly insured patients increased 10.3%, from 253 per 100,000 in 2000 (95% CI, 242-265) to 279 per 100,000 in 2008 (95% CI, 271-287). Although the overall rates of knee arthroscopy continued to increase, the rate of increase was slower in the post-Moseley years compared with the pre-Moseley period (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0363546513479771">Figure 2</xref>) and was even slower among publicly insured patients compared with privately insured patients (<italic>P</italic> = .001). The average effect on arthroscopy rates after the Moseley publication was a reduction in 12 per 100,000 private arthroscopies (<italic>P</italic> = .404; 95% CI, –16.3 to 40.6) and 35.7 per 100,000 publicly insured arthroscopies (95% CI, 15.0-56.4; <italic>P</italic> = .001). In absolute terms, this is an estimated reduction of 296 publicly insured arthroscopies (95% CI, 244-348) and 131 privately insured arthroscopies (95% CI, 129-350) per year.</p>
<fig id="fig2-0363546513479771" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Age- and sex-adjusted rates and volume of knee arthroscopy in Florida for all diagnoses before and after Moseley et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0363546513479771">17</xref></sup> study (2002). Source: Florida State Ambulatory Surgery Database (SASD) 2000-2008.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546513479771-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Among those without any diagnosis of OA, the volume of knee arthroscopy increased from 30,788 in 2000 to 42,769 in 2008 (a 38.9% increase.) This corresponds to a 25.2% increase in the adjusted population-based rate of knee arthroscopy among private insurance companies, from 318 per 100,000 adults in 2000 (95% CI, 304-333) to 398 per 100,000 adults in 2008 (95% CI, 389-406), and a 14.2% increase for public insurance companies, from 198 to 225 per 100,000 adults from 2000 to 2008, respectively. Despite the increase in the overall rates of knee arthroscopy between 2000 and 2008 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0363546513479771">Figure 2</xref>), there was no evidence that the rate of increase for non-OA diagnoses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0363546513479771">Figure 3</xref>) was any greater than its trend predicted for the post-Moseley years.</p>
<fig id="fig3-0363546513479771" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Rates and volume of knee arthroscopy among patients without osteoarthritis in Florida before and after Moseley et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0363546513479771">17</xref></sup> study (2002). Source: Florida State Ambulatory Surgery Database (SASD) 2000-2008; data adjusted for age, sex, comorbidity, and seasonality.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0363546513479771-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0363546513479771" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Despite an overall increase in the population-based rate and volume of arthroscopic procedures of the knee in Florida, we found that for a primary diagnosis of OA, these rates significantly declined after the Moseley et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0363546513479771">17</xref></sup> publication and the subsequent changes in reimbursement. Interestingly, the rate of procedures for a primary diagnosis of OA was relatively small compared with other knee diagnoses.</p>
<p>The trends observed suggest that the Moseley study, along with reimbursement changes, may have affected the rate of arthroscopy for OA, and that a shift in coding secondary to reimbursement changes does not appear to account for the decline in arthroscopy rates for OA. It does not appear that code shifting had much if any effect on the rates of arthroscopy for OA patients. Although the proportions of arthroscopies coded for the diagnosis of derangement of the posterior horn of the medial meniscus, tear of the lateral meniscus, other and unspecified derangement of medial meniscus, and derangement of the lateral meniscus (potential OA replacement diagnoses) all increased over the time period studied, they were increasing before the study. In fact, it appears that the rate of increase of these codes actually decreased after the Moseley study was published (see Appendix 2, available online). A possible explanation for the increase in overall rates of arthroscopy is the greater availability of highly sensitive imaging studies, specifically MRI, and the number of orthopaedic surgeons with training in arthroscopy.</p>
<p>Not only does the quality of scientific evidence in the literature vary widely, but delays in the implementation of research findings and failure to dismiss ineffective interventions also affect the appropriateness of clinical practice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0363546513479771">10</xref></sup> Furthermore, willingness to accept evidence that promotes an intervention may be greater than willingness to accept evidence for the cessation of a procedure. Surgical specialists must often practice in the absence of high-quality evidence because randomized controlled trials in orthopaedic surgery are limited by the difficulties in recruitment of participants and because sham surgery (true placebo) is considered by some unethical. A 2005 review of published evidence for shoulder surgery revealed that from 1992 to 2002, only 19 papers (3.1%) in mainstream orthopaedics journals described randomized controlled trials, and 538 (88.2%) were single-center case series (level 4 studies), which offer a much lower level of evidence.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0363546513479771">11</xref></sup> However, a recent cross-sectional survey of orthopaedic surgeons found broad support for large clinical trials and suggested that they have the potential to change practice.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0363546513479771">7</xref></sup> Survey respondents expressed willingness to adopt alternative surgical approaches if they felt that the evidence was compelling and sound. Evidence for this willingness is seen in a study performed at the University of California, Los Angeles that evaluated the response of surgeons to published evidence by examining rates of extensive surgery to treat idiopathic clubfoot. The investigators found a dramatic decline in the rate of surgery from 1996 to 2006 after dissemination of sound evidence for a nonsurgical approach (casting).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0363546513479771">24</xref></sup></p>
<p>Although some have criticized the Moseley trial on methodological grounds, subsequent evidence has corroborated the trials’ findings.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0363546513479771">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0363546513479771">13</xref></sup> Near the same time that the Moseley study was published, a Canadian evaluation of 14,391 arthroscopic knee debridement procedures for OA found that almost 10% of patients underwent total knee replacement within 1 year. Rates of arthroscopy were particularly high in patients aged 70 or older, and it was suggested that debridement may be overused in elderly patients in Canada.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0363546513479771">23</xref></sup> A more recent trial randomized OA patients to receive optimal physical and medical therapy plus arthroscopy compared with physical and medical therapy alone. The authors concluded arthroscopic surgery did not confer any additional benefit to optimized physical and medical therapy.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0363546513479771">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0363546513479771">13</xref></sup> These studies all seem to support the idea that arthroscopy for OA of the knee is likely not an efficacious treatment in the vast majority of cases. The results of our analysis suggest that these trials may have had an important influence on clinical decision making and utilization.</p>
<sec id="section14-0363546513479771">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>The HCUP data allow observation of population data for all ambulatory procedures for a given year. Although comprehensive in breadth, these data lack detailed clinical information and provide very little information about the outcomes of surgery. In addition, our use of HCUP assumes that the data set is a complete representation of the population and that the data were collected and recorded correctly. Although these are potential limitations, the HCUP database has been in existence for more than 20 years and is broadly considered a reliable source of claims data. Furthermore, <italic>ICD-9</italic> codes in administrative data are used for billing purposes and are therefore subject to audits.</p>
<p>We also acknowledge the limitation that unmeasured factors may account for some of the change in the rates that we observed. The model of the rates that we present are adjusted for patient age, sex, and comorbidities; quarterly seasonality; and the trend in procedure rate before Moseley.</p>
<p>Our analysis used data from Florida because of its large and diverse population. Since we only evaluated Florida data, our results may not generalize to other areas of the United States. However, our use of age- and sex-adjusted rates along with statistical adjustment for seasonality tempered the effect of many potential confounders, making the results more likely to be applicable to other regions of the country.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-0363546513479771">
<title>Implications</title>
<p>The results of this study suggest that rates of knee arthroscopy for OA in Florida decreased from 2000 to 2008. These changes followed the publication of level 1 evidence suggesting ineffectiveness of the procedure as well as modifications in Medicare reimbursement in response to this evidence. These results suggest that many patients may have been spared potential surgical and anesthesia complications related to a procedure that likely would have offered them negligible benefit. Although arthroscopy for OA patients has decreased since the Moseley study, it is important to note that arthroscopy for OA constituted a small proportion of total arthroscopies, and the overall population-based rate of arthroscopy continued to rise throughout the years analyzed.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<p>The authors declared that they have no conflicts of interest in the authorship and publication of this contribution.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0363546513479771">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<source>Arthroscopic Lavage and Arthroscopic Debridement for the Osteoarthritic Knee, Medicare National Coverage Determinations Manual</source>. Chapter 1: Coverage Determination. <publisher-loc>Washington, CD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department of Health &amp; Human Services (DHHS) Center for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services (CMS)</publisher-name>; <month>June</month> <day>10</day>, <year>2004</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0363546513479771">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Baumgaertner</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>WD</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Vittori</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maurer</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Arthroscopic debridement of the arthritic knee</article-title>. <source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>253</volume>:<fpage>197</fpage>-<lpage>202</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0363546513479771">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bert</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maschka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The arthroscopic treatment of unicompartmental gonarthrosis: a five-year follow-up study of abrasion arthroplasty plus arthroscopic debridement and arthroscopic debridement alone</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>25</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0363546513479771">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heilman</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gsell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wallick</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Tidal irrigation as treatment for knee osteoarthritis: a sham-controlled, randomized, double-blinded evaluation</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>100</fpage>-<lpage>108</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0363546513479771">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schulzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Arthroscopic surgery for osteoarthritis of the knee</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>347</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>1717</fpage>-<lpage>1719</lpage>; author reply <fpage>1717</fpage>-<lpage>1719</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0363546513479771">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feller</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Therapeutic arthroscopy for knee osteoarthritis: time to reconsider?</article-title> <source>Med J Aust</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>179</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>-<lpage>180</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0363546513479771">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dijkman</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kooistra</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pemberton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sprague</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bhandari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Can orthopedic trials change practice?</article-title> <source>Acta Orthop</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>122</fpage>-<lpage>125</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0363546513479771">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>French</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heagerty</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of longitudinal data to evaluate a policy change</article-title>. <source>Stat Med</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>24</issue>):<fpage>5005</fpage>-<lpage>5025</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0363546513479771">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Esformes</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Arthroscopic treatment of degenerative joint disease of the knee</article-title>. <source>Orthopedics</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1317</fpage>-<lpage>1321</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0363546513479771">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haines</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Implementing findings of research</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>308</volume>(<issue>6942</issue>):<fpage>1488</fpage>-<lpage>1492</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0363546513479771">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Harvie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chennagiri</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The use of outcome scores in surgery of the shoulder</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>87</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>151</fpage>-<lpage>154</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0363546513479771">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ike</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rothschild</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Tidal irrigation versus conservative medical management in patients with osteoarthritis of the knee: a prospective randomized study. Tidal Irrigation Cooperating Group</article-title>. <source>J Rheumatol</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>772</fpage>-<lpage>779</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0363546513479771">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Arthroscopic surgery for osteoarthritis of the knee</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>347</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>1717</fpage>-<lpage>1719</lpage>; author reply <fpage>1717</fpage>-<lpage>1719</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0363546513479771">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kirkley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Birmingham</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Litchfield</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A randomized trial of arthroscopic surgery for osteoarthritis of the knee</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>359</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1097</fpage>-<lpage>1107</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0363546513479771">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Felson</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Helmick</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Estimates of the prevalence of arthritis and other rheumatic conditions in the United States, part II</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>26</fpage>-<lpage>35</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0363546513479771">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Livesley</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Doherty</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Needoff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moulton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Arthroscopic lavage of osteoarthritic knees</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>73</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>922</fpage>-<lpage>926</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0363546513479771">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moseley</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Malley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>A controlled trial of arthroscopic surgery for osteoarthritis of the knee</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>347</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>81</fpage>-<lpage>88</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0363546513479771">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="book"><collab>National Center for Health Statistics (NCHS), Centers for Medicare &amp; Medicaid Services (CMS)</collab>. <source>The International Classification of Diseases, 9th Revision, Clinical Modification (ICD-9-CM)</source>. <edition>6th ed</edition>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0363546513479771">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Owings</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kozak</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Ambulatory and inpatient procedures in the United States, 1996</article-title>. <source>Vital Health Stat 13</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>139</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>119</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0363546513479771">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sundararajan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Halfon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Coding algorithms for defining comorbidities in ICD-9-CM and ICD-10 administrative data</article-title>. <source>Med Care</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>43</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1130</fpage>-<lpage>1139</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0363546513479771">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rand</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Role of arthroscopy in osteoarthritis of the knee</article-title>. <source>Arthroscopy</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>358</fpage>-<lpage>363</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0363546513479771">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab>US Census Bureau</collab>. <article-title>Table 1. Annual estimates of the resident population for the United States, Regions, States, and Puerto Rico: April 1, 2000, to July 1, 2009 (NST-EST2009-01)</article-title>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0363546513479771">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wai</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kreder</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Arthroscopic debridement of the knee for osteoarthritis in patients fifty years of age or older: utilization and outcomes in the Province of Ontario</article-title>. <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>84</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>17</fpage>-<lpage>22</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0363546513479771">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zionts</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hitchcock</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maewal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ebramzadeh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Has the rate of extensive surgery to treat idiopathic clubfoot declined in the United States?</article-title> <source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>92</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>882</fpage>-<lpage>889</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>