<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ACR</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spacr</journal-id>
         <journal-title>Acta Radiologica</journal-title>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">0284-1851</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">1600-0455</issn>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
            <publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
         </publisher>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0284185113475607</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0284185113475607</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Breast</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Incidental detection of clinically unexpected breast lesions by computed tomography</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Monzawa</surname>
                  <given-names>Shuichi</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
               <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Washio</surname>
                  <given-names>Tetsuo</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Yasuoka</surname>
                  <given-names>Rie</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Mitsuo</surname>
                  <given-names>Manabu</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kadotani</surname>
                  <given-names>Yoichi</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hanioka</surname>
                  <given-names>Keisuke</given-names>
               </name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4">4</xref>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <aff id="af1">
            <label>1</label>
            <institution xlink:type="simple">Akashi Municipal Hospital, Department of Radiology</institution>, <addr-line>Akashi City, Hyogo</addr-line>
         </aff>
         <aff id="af2">
            <label>2</label>
            <institution xlink:type="simple">Shinko Hospital, Department of Radiology</institution>, <addr-line>Kobe city, Hyogo</addr-line>
         </aff>
         <aff id="af3">
            <label>3</label>
            <institution xlink:type="simple">Akashi Municipal Hospital, Department of Surgery</institution>, <addr-line>Akashi City, Hyogo</addr-line>
         </aff>
         <aff id="af4">
            <label>4</label>
            <institution xlink:type="simple">Akashi Municipal Hospital, Department of Pathology</institution>, <addr-line>Akashi City, Hyogo, 673-8558</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country>
         </aff>
         <author-notes>
            <corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to: Shuichi Monzawa. Email: <email xlink:type="simple">monzawas@cpost.plala.or.jp</email>
            </corresp>
         </author-notes>
         <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
            <month>5</month>
            <year>2013</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>54</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <fpage>374</fpage>
         <lpage>379</lpage>
         <history>
            <date date-type="received">
               <day>7</day>
               <month>7</month>
               <year>2012</year>
            </date>
            <date date-type="accepted">
               <day>27</day>
               <month>11</month>
               <year>2012</year>
            </date>
         </history>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2013 The Foundation Acta Radiologica</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder content-type="sage">The Foundation Acta Radiologica</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <abstract>
            <sec>
               <title>Background</title>
               <p>Increased use of computed tomography (CT) has resulted in greater detection of incidental breast lesions unrelated to the primary diagnostic inquiry.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
               <title>Purpose</title>
               <p>To investigate the morphology and clinical significance of breast abnormalities detected incidentally by conventional CT.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
               <title>Material and Methods</title>
               <p>A total of 2945 female patients underwent CT examinations of the body, including the chest, from May 2006 to April 2010. Two radiologists interpreted these CT scans independently and pointed out a mass or non-mass-like lesion as abnormalities in the breast. Patients who incidentally showed breast lesions on CT scans were identified by a computer-based search of the diagnostic reports and were enrolled in this study. The morphology and enhancement patterns of CT-detected breast lesions were evaluated according to BI-RADS-MRI.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
               <title>Results</title>
               <p>In total, 32 clinically unexpected abnormal breast lesions were found in 31 (1.1%) patients. Twenty-nine of the 32 lesions were detected by contrast-enhanced CT and three by unenhanced CT. Ten breast cancers were found in 10 patients (0.34%), which yielded the prevalence for malignancy of 31% (10/32). Invasive ductal carcinomas accounted for eight lesions, while two were ductal carcinomas <italic>in situ</italic> (DCIS). Nine lesions were depicted as a mass and one DCIS was a non-mass-like lesion. Good morphological predictors of breast cancers for a mass were an irregular shape, a lobulated shape, and an irregular margin. Benign lesions accounted for 22 lesions from 21 patients (0.71%). Of these, 13 lesions in 13 patients were depicted as a mass and nine lesions in nine patients as a non-mass-like lesion.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
               <title>Conclusion</title>
               <p>Unexpected breast lesions can be identified as a mass or non-mass-like lesion on conventional chest CT scans. Among these, breast cancers that are not clinically apparent occur with considerable prevalence. We suggest that careful interpretation of the breast should be a routine part of CT examinations.</p>
            </sec>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group>
            <title>Keywords</title>
            <kwd>CT</kwd>
            <kwd>breast cancer</kwd>
            <kwd>breast</kwd>
            <kwd>incidental lesion</kwd>
            <kwd>unexpected lesion</kwd>
            <kwd>incidentaloma</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="s1">
         <title/>
         <p>In recent years, the development of multidetector-row computed tomography (MDCT) has dramatically improved acquisition speed, and spatial resolution. The clinical application of MDCT has been extended to all diagnostic areas, and its increased use has resulted in greater detection of incidental findings unrelated to the primary diagnostic inquiry. Breast lesions, including cancers, can be identified incidentally in conventional chest computed tomography (CT), for which the breast was not the primary focus. Following the installation of MDCT scanners at our institution, the number of CT-detected breast lesions increased and breast cancers have been identified.</p>
         <p>Breast dynamic magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) has been established as a valid tool for the diagnosis of breast cancers. CT is not used widely for the evaluation of breast lesions because of the drawback of radiation exposure. However, dedicated breast MDCT also provides comparable spatial and contrast resolution and cross-sectional capability. Furthermore, it can identify imaging features suggestive of breast cancers or benign lesions and help to differentiate breast lesions found by mammography and/or ultrasonography (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C2">2</xref>).</p>
         <p>Several studies have evaluated the appearance and clinical significance of incidental CT-detected breast lesions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C3">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C10">10</xref>). In the present study, we evaluated the detection rate of breast lesions on a patient-by-patient basis, which a few studies have reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C10">10</xref>). We describe the morphological features of the lesions primarily according to breast imaging reporting and data system (BI-RADS)-MRI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C11">11</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
         <title>Material and Methods</title>
         <p>The study was approved by our institutional review board and, according to institutional policy, informed consent was not required from any patient whose records were included in the study. Between May 2006 and April 2010, 6308 body MDCT examinations, including the chest, were performed for a wide range of clinical indications in 2945 female patients in our institution; major indications for chest examinations were lung cancer or metastatic lung tumors, including 2641 unenhanced CT, 3187 contrast-enhanced CT, 354 dynamic CT, and 126 miscellaneous contrast-enhanced studies.</p>
         <p>A 64-row MDCT (Aquillion 64; Toshiba medical system, Otawara, Japan) was used with imaging parameters of 120 kVp, 300 mA, tube rotation time of 0.5 s, helical pitch of 27, and 5-mm-thick contiguous sections. Three types of non-ionic iodinated contrast media prefilled in a syringe (100 or 150 mL, 240 or 300 or 350 mg I/mL) were used at the dose of 450–750 mg I per body weight kg for contrast-enhanced studies. In the 3187 contrast-enhanced CT examinations, the contrast medium was administered intravenously at a rate of 1.5 mL/s, with scanning starting 100 s after the initiation of the injection. Most of the 354 dynamic studies were performed focusing on the abdomen. After the abdomen was scanned on early phase with intravenous administration of a contrast medium at a rate of 3–4 mL/s, the chest was scanned on late phase with a 70-s delay. The 126 miscellaneous studies were performed in an early phase, with intravenous administration of the contrast medium at a rate of 3–4 mL/s to survey pulmonary embolism or thoracic aortic diseases.</p>
         <p>One of two well-experienced board-certified radiologists (SM, TW) interpreted the CT scans independently in daily practice and recorded the diagnostic reports. The principal CT criteria for diagnosis of abnormal findings in the breast were primarily based on BI-RADS-MRI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C11">11</xref>), including a mass with a smooth or irregular margin and a non-mass-like lesion corresponding to localized enhancement that lacked a mass effect and looked like enhancing breast parenchyma. We surveyed the diagnostic reports using a computer-based search and identified patients whose reports indicated the presence of a breast lesion. Patients with a known breast lesion discovered initially by mammography and/or ultrasonography and/or MRI were excluded. Patients who had undergone breast surgery 5 or more years ago and had no known recurrent diseases were included. Most of the CT-detected breast lesions were evaluated with mammography and/or ultrasonography. The diagnosis was made based on the findings of mammography or ultrasonography and the histopathologic results of mastectomy, biopsy, and aspiration cytology. If a final diagnosis could not been made, the final diagnostic outcome was determined on the basis of the findings of the lesions on CT performed for the follow-up of their primary disease for 2 or more years.</p>
         <p>One radiologist (SM) blinded to the final diagnostic outcomes reviewed the CT scans of the incidental CT-detected breast lesions and recorded the CT findings, including the number of lesions, size, morphology, distribution, and enhancement patterns for a mass and non-mass-like lesion based on BI-RADS-MRI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C11">11</xref>). The positive predictive value (PPV) for malignancy was calculated for each of the individual CT findings. Assessment categories were also determined based on BI-RADS-MRI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C11">11</xref>). Assessment categories of 4 and 5 were considered as malignant (positive), and categories 2 and 3 as benign (negative), and the sensitivity, specificity, PPV, negative predictive value, positive likelihood ratio, and negative likelihood ratio for malignancy were calculated on a lesion-by-lesion basis to evaluate the diagnostic performance of CT. A positive likelihood ratio &gt; 5 and negative likelihood ratio &lt; 0.2 were considered useful to rule diagnoses in or out, respectively.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s3" sec-type="results">
         <title>Results</title>
         <p>The survey showed that 32 incidental CT-detected breast lesions were identified in 31 (1.1%) of the 2945 patients. In a single patient, two lesions were identified metachronously. Patient history revealed that 24 patients had various malignancies simultaneously or previously. These malignancies included large intestinal cancer in 11 patients, breast cancer in six, renal cell cancer in four, and other malignancies in three. The remaining seven patients had various chronic inflammatory diseases or trauma. Twenty-five of the 32 lesions were identified by contrast-enhanced CT, four by late-phase CT of dynamic studies, and three by unenhanced CT. The CT findings of masses are summarized in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="AR-475607TB1">1</xref> and those of non-mass-like lesions in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="AR-475607TB2">2</xref>.
<table-wrap id="AR-475607TB1" position="float">
               <label>Table 1</label>
               <caption>
                  <p>The morphology and enhancement patterns of masses on CT</p>
               </caption>
               <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <colgroup span="1">
                     <col align="left" span="1"/>
                     <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                     <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                  </colgroup>
                  <thead>
                     <tr>
                        <th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Masses</th>
                        <th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Breast cancers</th>
                        <th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Benign lesions</th>
                     </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Shape</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Round</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Oval</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Lobulated</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Irregular</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Margin</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Smooth</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Irregular</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Spiculated</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Internal enhancement characteristics</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Homogeneous</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Heterogeneous</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Rim enhancement</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Dark internal septations</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Enhancing internal septations</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Central</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Fat tissue</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                     </tr>
                  </tbody>
               </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <table-wrap id="AR-475607TB2" position="float">
               <label>Table 2</label>
               <caption>
                  <p>The morphology and enhancement patterns of non-mass-like lesions on CT</p>
               </caption>
               <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <colgroup span="1">
                     <col align="left" span="1"/>
                     <col align="left" span="1"/>
                     <col align="left" span="1"/>
                  </colgroup>
                  <thead>
                     <tr>
                        <th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-mass-like lesions</th>
                        <th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Breast cancers</th>
                        <th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Benign lesions</th>
                     </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Distribution</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Focal area</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Linear</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Ductal</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Segmental</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Regional</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Multiple regions</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Diffuse</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Internal enhancement characteristics</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Homogeneous</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Heterogeneous</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Stippled</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Clumped</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"> Reticular</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">–</td>
                     </tr>
                  </tbody>
               </table>
            </table-wrap>
         </p>
         <p>Breast cancer was noted in 10 lesions in 10 (0.34%) of the 2945 patients. Six lesions in six of the 10 patients were evaluated with mammography. One lesion was depicted as a mass with an irregular margin, one as a mass with spicules and calcifications, one as focal asymmetry, one as architectural distortion, and two as calcifications. Four lesions in four patients were not examined by mammography. All 10 lesions in the 10 patients were evaluated with ultrasonography and were depicted as a mass. Partial or total mastectomy was performed in these patients and the diagnosis was confirmed. The prevalence in the incidental CT-detected lesions was 32% (10/32). They consisted of solitary tumors, eight lesions were invasive ductal carcinoma (IDC) and two were ductal carcinoma <italic>in situ</italic> (DCIS). In total, nine lesions (eight IDC and one DCIS) were depicted as a mass in the size range of 10–24 (mean 17) mm on CT scans. A 15-mm-sized IDC was detected by unenhanced CT (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="AR-475607F1">1</xref>). No masses with a spiculated margin were identified. A single DCIS was depicted as a 21-mm-wide non-mass-like lesion (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="AR-475607F2">2</xref>). This lesion showed a segmental distribution and a homogeneous internal enhancement pattern. No fine calcifications were visualized on CT in the 10 patients with breast cancer. CT findings of masses with higher PPV values for malignancy were an irregular shape (PPV, 0.80), a lobulated shape (PPV, 0.60), and an irregular margin (PPV, 0.58).
<fig id="AR-475607F1" position="float">
               <label>Fig. 1</label>
               <caption>
                  <p>A 76-year-old woman with IDC of the right breast. Chest CT was performed to examine the abnormal shadow seen on a chest radiograph, which was diagnosed as non-tuberculous mycobacteria. Unenhanced CT scan shows a mass (arrow) of an irregular shape and margin in the upper-outer quadrant of the right breast, which was estimated as category 4</p>
               </caption>
               <graphic position="float" xlink:href="10.1177_0284185113475607-fig1.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="AR-475607F2" position="float">
               <label>Fig. 2</label>
               <caption>
                  <p>A 67-year-old woman with DCIS of the right breast. Chest CT was performed for postoperative follow-up of left breast cancer that had been operated on 8 years before. (a) Contrast-enhanced CT scan shows non-mass-like enhancement (arrow) with a segmental distribution and homogeneous internal enhancement pattern in the upper-outer quadrant of the right breast, which was estimated as category 4. (b) Photomicrograph (hematoxylin-eosin stain, original magnification × 1) of the surgical specimen shows a non-invasive tumor (arrows) with high-grade atypia</p>
               </caption>
               <graphic position="float" xlink:href="10.1177_0284185113475607-fig2.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
         </p>
         <p>A total of 22 benign lesions were identified in 21 (0.71%) of the 2945 patients. Sixteen lesions in 16 of the 21 patients were evaluated with mammography. Three lesions in three patients were depicted as a mass, one lesion in one patient as a focal asymmetry with calcifications, whereas 12 lesions in 12 patients were not visualized. Six lesions in five patients were not examined by mammography. Nineteen lesions in 18 patients were evaluated with ultrasonography. Nine lesions in nine patients were depicted as a mass, whereas 10 lesions in nine patients were not visualized. Three lesions in three patients were not examined by ultrasonography. Biopsy or aspiration cytology under ultrasound guidance was performed for six lesions in six patients. One lesion was diagnosed as mammary duct ectasia, one as intraductal papilloma, and four as benign lesions. Two lesions in two patients were diagnosed as hamartoma and old fibroadenoma based on typical mammographic or ultrasonographic findings. The remaining 14 lesions in 13 patients were considered benign because they disappeared or showed no interval changes on follow-up CT examinations over a period of 2 or more years. Thirteen lesions in 13 patients were depicted as a mass in the size range of 5–70 mm (mean, 15 mm) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="AR-475607F3">3</xref>). Nine lesions in nine patients were identified as non-mass-like lesions in the size range of 6–38 mm (mean, 18 mm). It was expected that benign lesions would yield CT findings with lower PPV values for malignancy. In our series, the benign lesions often showed a round shape (PPV, 0.17), an oval shape (PPV, 0.17), a smooth margin (PPV, 0.20), and homogeneous enhancement (PPV, 0.35) in masses, and focal area (PPV, 0), regional distribution (PPV, 0), and homogeneous enhancement (PPV, 0.20) in non-mass-like lesions.
<fig id="AR-475607F3" position="float">
               <label>Fig. 3</label>
               <caption>
                  <p>A 76-year-old woman with intraductal papilloma of the right breast. Chest CT was performed for postoperative follow-up of rectal cancer that had been operated on 4 years before. (a) Contrast-enhanced CT scan shows a mass (arrow) of a lobulated shape and irregular margin in the upper-outer quadrant of the right breast, which was estimated as category 4. (b) Early phase image of dynamic MRI shows a mass (arrow) of an oval shape and smooth margin in the right breast. A plateau pattern was seen on delayed phase in time intensity curve analysis (not shown). The lesion was diagnosed as intraductal papilloma because it revealed benign findings on fine-needle aspiration cytology, and no remarkable interval changes on follow-up MRI studies</p>
               </caption>
               <graphic position="float" xlink:href="10.1177_0284185113475607-fig3.tif" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
         </p>
         <p>In the retrospective evaluation of BI-RADS assessment category, for masses, one of nine breast cancers was classified as category 5 and eight as category 4, and seven of 13 benign lesions were classified as category 4, five as category 3, and one as category 2. For non-mass-like lesions, one breast cancer was classified as category 4, and one of nine benign lesions was classified as category 4 and the remaining eight as category 3. The overall diagnostic performance of CT drawn from these scores is shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="AR-475607TB3">3</xref>. All breast cancers were assessed as category 4 or 5, and there were no false-negatives for malignancy. However, eight of 22 benign lesions were assessed as category 4 and resulted in false-positives; they included seven mass lesions and one non-mass-like lesion. The sensitivity, specificity, PPV, negative predictive value, positive likelihood ratio, and negative likelihood ratio (95% confidence interval, lower-upper limit) were 1.00 (0.66–1.00), 0.64 (0.41–0.82), 0.56 (0.31–0.78), 1.00 (0.73–1.00), 2.75 (1.58–4.78), and 0.00 (0.00–incalculable), respectively.
<table-wrap id="AR-475607TB3" position="float">
               <label>Table 3</label>
               <caption>
                  <p>Diagnostic performance of CT</p>
               </caption>
               <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <colgroup span="1">
                     <col align="left" span="1"/>
                     <col align="left" span="1"/>
                     <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                     <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                     <col align="char" char="." span="1"/>
                  </colgroup>
                  <thead>
                     <tr>
                        <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                        <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                        <th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Pathology</th>
                        <th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</th>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                        <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                        <th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Breast cancers</th>
                        <th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Benign lesions</th>
                        <th colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                     </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CT</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Breast cancers</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Benign lesions</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td>
                     </tr>
                     <tr>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td>
                        <td colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td>
                     </tr>
                  </tbody>
               </table>
            </table-wrap>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s4" sec-type="discussion">
         <title>Discussion</title>
         <p>In the present study, 10 breast cancers were detected incidentally by conventional unenhanced and contrast-enhanced CT in 10 (0.34%) of 2945 patients over a 4-year period. Limited studies have been reporting the rate of incidental detection of breast cancer calculated on a patient-by-patient basis. Shojaku <italic>et al.</italic> reported a detection rate of 0.3% by unenhanced CT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C6">6</xref>), while Lin <italic>et al</italic>. reported a detection rate of 0.6% by contrast-enhanced CT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C10">10</xref>).</p>
         <p>In our series, nine of the 10 tumors were detected by contrast-enhanced CT. Breast cancers are a relatively hypervascular tumor and are depicted more clearly as an enhanced lesion on contrast-enhanced CT than on unenhanced CT. Contrast-enhanced studies are expected to improve the detectability of breast cancers by CT; therefore, the detection rate may vary with the numbers of unenhanced and contrast-enhanced chest CTs performed at an institution. The prevalence of breast cancers in the incidental CT-detected lesions was 31% (10/32) in our series. Reported prevalences of incidental breast cancers vary from 24% to 57% (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C6">6</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C10">10</xref>). Clinically unexpected breast cancers can be detected even by a conventional CT examination not dedicated for the breast with a considerable detection rate. Given this, attention should also be devoted to the breast during the interpretation of routine chest CT so that a mass or non-mass-like lesion of the breast does not remain unnoticed.</p>
         <p>The detection of breast cancer on unenhanced CT appears to be difficult since breast cancer usually shows attenuation similar to that of the breast parenchyma. However, a tumor of significant size can be detected as a mass even by unenhanced CT, and is depicted as localized soft tissue with different morphology from that of breast parenchyma and an asymmetric appearance of the breasts. Although only one IDC was detected as a mass, 15 mm in size, by unenhanced CT in our series, Shojaku <italic>et al</italic>. reported that unexpected breast cancer was found in 0.3% of patients who underwent unenhanced chest CT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C6">6</xref>), and Swensen <italic>et al.</italic> reported that breast cancer was found in 0.41% of participants who underwent low-dose unenhanced chest CT for lung cancer screening (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C3">3</xref>). Therefore, careful analysis of the breast is necessary even on unenhanced CT.</p>
         <p>Two DCIS were detected as an enhanced lesion on contrast-enhanced CT. Lin <italic>et al</italic>. reported five DCISs among 23 breast lesions (16 malignant) detected incidentally by contrast-enhanced CT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C10">10</xref>), but no other reports of incidental CT-detected DCIS have been published. Contrast-enhanced CT appears to be essential for detection of DCIS. Since DCIS usually appears as a non-mass-like lesion showing subtle morphological changes, DCIS would not be visualized readily on unenhanced CT. The detection of fine calcifications of DCIS by unenhanced CT seems to be difficult as they may be obscured by a partial volume effect because of the insufficient spatial resolution of conventional CT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C7">7</xref>).</p>
         <p>Fourteen lesions were not visualized by ultrasonography and could not be biopsied under ultrasound guidance; therefore, they were evaluated simultaneously with CT when CT was performed for the follow-up of their primary disease. Biopsy under CT or MRI guidance may be an option in these cases; however, it requires special equipments and experience, and can only be performed at a limited number of institutions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C13">13</xref>). Of these 14 lesions, 10 were categorized into category 3 in the retrospective evaluation. These category 3 lesions were a small, round, or oval-shaped mass with a smooth margin or small non-mass-like enhancement of focal area or regional distribution, and they appeared benign. Mammography and ultrasonography are preferable for the follow-up of benign-looking CT-detected lesions like these even if they are invisible on these modalities, however, if patients are scheduled to have CT for the evaluation of their primary disease and they do not desire further follow-up by mammography and/or ultrasonography, follow-up by CT might be admitted as an alternative option.</p>
         <p>In the current study, we obtained many false-positives, and the positive likelihood ratio for malignancy in the retrospective evaluation of diagnostic performance was poor. The 5-mm-section thickness employed in this series of CT scans might be too thick to avoid a partial volume effect and was likely to be suboptimal for the diagnosis of small breast lesions. High spatial resolution imaging with a thinner slice thickness and smaller field of view covering a unilateral breast is now possible with modern MDCT scanners (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C14">14</xref>). Dedicated breast CT examinations with superior spatial resolution may improve diagnostic performance. Perrone <italic>et al</italic>. employed dynamic CT studies with time intensity curve analysis widely used in breast MRI and achieved better specificity for the diagnosis of breast cancers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C2">2</xref>). When a breast lesion is found incidentally on conventional scanning, additional scanning targeting the lesion on late phase might be helpful for differentiation. However, this approach is associated with additional concerns regarding increased radiation exposure.</p>
         <p>The current study had several limitations. Since assessment categories of the CT-detected lesions were determined by a single radiologist retrospectively, the evaluation might be subjective and have low reproducibility. The detectability of a mass may depend upon breast density and a mass may be detected more readily in non-dense breasts with less breast parenchyma. We did not evaluate breast density in the subjects because established CT criteria of breast density were not known. Porter <italic>et al</italic>. showed that CT-detected lesions in non-dense breasts (American College of Radiology [ACR] classification 1 or 2) were likely to be more malignant than lesions in dense breasts (ACR classification 3 or 4) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="AR-475607C7">7</xref>).</p>
         <p>In conclusion, our results showed that conventional chest CT could detect an unexpected breast cancer with a considerable incidence rate. In chest CT examination, survey of the lung is usually the primary focus, and it appears that full attention has not been paid to the breast. We suggest that careful interpretation of the breast should be a routine part of chest CT examination.</p>
         <p>
            <bold>Conflict of interest:</bold> None.</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>REFERENCES</title>
         <ref id="AR-475607C1">
            <label>1</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Inoue</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Sano</surname>
                  <given-names>T</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Watai</surname>
                  <given-names>R</given-names>
               </name>, <etal/>
               <article-title>Dynamic multidetector CT of breast tumors: diagnostic features and comparison with conventional techniques</article-title>. <source>Am J Roentgenol</source>
               <year>2003</year>;<volume>181</volume>:<fpage>679</fpage>–<lpage>86</lpage>
            </citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="AR-475607C2">
            <label>2</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Perrone</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Lo Mele</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Sassi</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
               </name>, <etal/>
               <article-title>MDCT of the breast</article-title>. <source>Am J Roentgenol</source>
               <year>2008</year>;<volume>190</volume>:<fpage>1644</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>
            </citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="AR-475607C3">
            <label>3</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Swensen</surname>
                  <given-names>SJ</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Jett</surname>
                  <given-names>JR</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hartman</surname>
                  <given-names>TE</given-names>
               </name>, <etal/>
               <article-title>Lung cancer screening with CT: Mayo Clinic experience</article-title>. <source>Radiology</source>
               <year>2003</year>;<volume>226</volume>:<fpage>756</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>
            </citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="AR-475607C4">
            <label>4</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Meller</surname>
                  <given-names>MT</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Cox</surname>
                  <given-names>JE</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Callanan</surname>
                  <given-names>KW</given-names>
               </name>. <article-title>Incidental detection of breast lesions with computed tomography</article-title>. <source>Clin Breast Cancer</source>
               <year>2007</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>634</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>
            </citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="AR-475607C5">
            <label>5</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Yi</surname>
                  <given-names>JG</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kim</surname>
                  <given-names>SJ</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Marom</surname>
                  <given-names>EM</given-names>
               </name>, <etal/>
               <article-title>Chest CT of incidental breast lesions</article-title>. <source>J Thorac Imaging</source>
               <year>2008</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>148</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>
            </citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="AR-475607C6">
            <label>6</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Shojaku</surname>
                  <given-names>H</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Seto</surname>
                  <given-names>H</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Iwai</surname>
                  <given-names>H</given-names>
               </name>, <etal/>
               <article-title>Detection of incidental breast tumors by noncontrast spiral computed tomography of the chest</article-title>. <source>Radiat Med</source>
               <year>2008</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>362</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>
            </citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="AR-475607C7">
            <label>7</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Porter</surname>
                  <given-names>G</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Steel</surname>
                  <given-names>J</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Paisley</surname>
                  <given-names>K</given-names>
               </name>, <etal/>
               <article-title>Incidental breast masses detected by computed tomography: are any imaging features predictive of malignancy?</article-title>
               <source>Clin Radiol</source>
               <year>2009</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>
            </citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="AR-475607C8">
            <label>8</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Moyle</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Sonoda</surname>
                  <given-names>L</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Britton</surname>
                  <given-names>P</given-names>
               </name>, <etal/>
               <article-title>Incidental breast lesions detected on CT: what is their significance?</article-title>
               <source>Br J Radiol</source>
               <year>2010</year>;<volume>83</volume>:<fpage>233</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>
            </citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="AR-475607C9">
            <label>9</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hussain</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Gordon-Dixon</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Almusawy</surname>
                  <given-names>H</given-names>
               </name>, <etal/>
               <article-title>The incidence and outcome of incidental breast lesions detected by computed tomography</article-title>. <source>Ann R Coll Surg Engl</source>
               <year>2010</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>124</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>
            </citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="AR-475607C10">
            <label>10</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Lin</surname>
                  <given-names>WC</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Hsu</surname>
                  <given-names>HH</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Li</surname>
                  <given-names>CS</given-names>
               </name>, <etal/>
               <article-title>Incidentally detected enhancing breast lesions on chest computed tomography</article-title>. <source>Korean J Radiol</source>
               <year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>
            </citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="AR-475607C11">
            <label>11</label>
            <citation citation-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
               <collab xlink:type="simple">American College of Radiology.</collab>
               <article-title>ACR BI-RADS MRI</article-title>. In: <source>Breast imaging reporting and data system</source>. <edition>1st edn</edition>. <publisher-loc>Reston, VA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>, <year>2003</year>
            </citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="AR-475607C12">
            <label>12</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Perlet</surname>
                  <given-names>C</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Heywang-Kobrunner</surname>
                  <given-names>SH</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Heinig</surname>
                  <given-names>A</given-names>
               </name>, <etal/>
               <article-title>Magnetic resonance-guided, vacuum-assisted breast biopsy: results from a European multicenter study of 538 lesions</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source>
               <year>2006</year>;<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>982</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>
            </citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="AR-475607C13">
            <label>13</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Mendel</surname>
                  <given-names>JB</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Long</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Slanetz</surname>
                  <given-names>PJ</given-names>
               </name>. <article-title>CT-guided core needle biopsy of breast lesions visible only on MRI</article-title>. <source>Am J Roentgenol</source>
               <year>2007</year>; <volume>189</volume>:<fpage>152</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>
            </citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="AR-475607C14">
            <label>14</label>
            <citation citation-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
               <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Uematsu</surname>
                  <given-names>T</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Yuen</surname>
                  <given-names>S</given-names>
               </name>, <name name-style="western">
                  <surname>Kasami</surname>
                  <given-names>M</given-names>
               </name>, <etal/>
               <article-title>Comparison of magnetic resonance imaging, multidetector row computed tomography, ultrasonography, and mammography for tumor extension of breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source>
               <year>2008</year>;<volume>112</volume>:<fpage>461</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>
            </citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>