<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SEX</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsex</journal-id>
<journal-title>Sexualities</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1363-4607</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7382</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1363460712459308</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1363460712459308</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A fading <italic>Tongzhi</italic> heterotopia: Hong Kong older gay men’s use of spaces</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>Travis SK</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1363460712459308"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1363460712459308">University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1363460712459308">Travis SK Kong, Rm9.17, The ockey Club Tower, Department of Sociology, The University of Hong Kong, Pokfulam Road, Hong Kong. Email: <email>travisk@hku.hk</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<fpage>896</fpage>
<lpage>916</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Modern heteronormativity in Hong Kong has been produced via British colonialism, land developers, and the family, and maintained through post-colonial administration. Together, these factors have resulted in a heterosexual culture of intimacy with rigid public/private distinctions. Homonormativity has emerged with the rise of <italic>tongzhi</italic> (synonym for gay, lesbian, bisexual, and transgendered) space in Hong Kong since the 1990s, but has had the effect of marginalizing certain <italic>tongzhi</italic> along lines of class, age, and the body. Based on the narratives of 14 older (60+) gay men in Hong Kong, this article discusses how they have negotiated same-sex intimacy in everyday sites at two specific times – in their parents’ homes and public toilets in the 1940s–1950s, when homosexuality was a crime and homosexual identity had not yet developed; and in their own homes and within the present-day <italic>tongzhi</italic> world, which presents them with new opportunities and challenges. Using a post-structuralist conception of power/resistance that juxtaposes power and resistance in the same site, this article argues that the private home and public spaces are sites of governmentality/resistance while <italic>tongzhi</italic> spaces are sites of desire/domination, with class and age being important social identifiers of Hong Kong gay men. Through radical use of spaces, a <italic>tongzhi</italic> heterotopia can be created and practised in both hetero-/homo-sexual worlds. This article contributes to the sociology of sexuality by exploring how governmentality via British colonialism (and post-colonialism), land use, and the family shape <italic>tongzhi</italic> bodies and space, exposing the domination of hetero-/homo-normativities in <italic>tongzhi</italic> lives, and highlighting <italic>tongzhi</italic> resistance in Hong Kong.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Colonialism</kwd>
<kwd>‘hetero’-/‘homo’-normativity</kwd>
<kwd>Hong Kong</kwd>
<kwd>older gay men</kwd>
<kwd>public/private</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec1-1363460712459308" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title>
<p>There is a well-established body of literature that examines the complicated relationship between sexuality, space, and place. Early work sought to map visible gay and lesbian spaces, connect sexual politics to the politics of space (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1363460712459308">Levine, 1979</xref>), and show how space is actively produced and heterosexualized through resistance and contestation. While early works focused on the urban lives of middle-class, white, gay men in North American cities, later efforts extended the analysis to the production of lesbian spaces (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-1363460712459308">Valentine, 1993</xref>) and rural queer spaces (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1363460712459308">Kramer, 1995</xref>), and to the UK (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-1363460712459308">Whittle, 1994</xref>), and Europe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1363460712459308">Binnie, 1995</xref>). Inspired by queer theories in the 1990s, scholars have highlighted the hybrid and fluid nature of sexual identities, acknowledging that space is simultaneously sexed, gendered, classed, and racialized, leading to investigations into the multidimensionality and intersectionality of queer lives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1363460712459308">Bell and Valentine, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1363460712459308">Ingram et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1363460712459308">Oswin, 2008</xref>). Discussions have attempted to mark the intersections of sexuality with space, global capitalism, cosmopolitanism, and international migration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1363460712459308">Puar, 2002</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1363460712459308">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>Two issues emerge in this work. First, it draws on Euro-American experiences, which do not reflect the experiences of other cultural contexts including Australia, New Zealand, South Africa, and Latin America. In Asia, a few studies similarly indicate differences, such as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1363460712459308">Lim (2004)</xref> for Singapore, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1363460712459308">Martin (2000)</xref> for Taiwan, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-1363460712459308">Tang (2011)</xref> for Hong Kong. Second, whilst class, gender, and race are recognized as important ‘identity components’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-1363460712459308">Seidman, 1996</xref>: 11) for understanding queer lives, age has largely been neglected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1363460712459308">Plummer, 2010</xref>), with the focus usually being on young and adult queer bodies. Old age is associated with loneliness, social isolation, and mental and physical dysfunction in the heterosexual world, as well as undesirable, unattractive, and even paedophilic characteristics in the homosexual world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1363460712459308">Jones and Pugh, 2005</xref>: 256). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1363460712459308">Pain, Mowl, and Talbot (2000: 379)</xref> argue that ageism, racism, and sexism contribute to the construction of a matrix of oppression. In Hong Kong, the study of ageing has focused overwhelmingly on heterosexual lives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1363460712459308">Chow, 2000</xref>), whilst studies on homosexuality have been predominantly concerned with post-war <italic>tongzhi</italic><sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1363460712459308">2</xref></sup> generations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1363460712459308">Ho, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1363460712459308">Kong, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1363460712459308">Leung, 2008</xref>).</p>
<p>Building on the ‘geographies of sexuality’, this analysis documents the changing nature of public/private and hetero/homo spaces in Hong Kong and argues how gay men make use of spaces for same-sex intimacy under the web of domination governed by British colonialism and post-colonialism, land developers, and the family, using age and class as two major social identifiers. The accounts used in this analysis are based on the oral histories of 14 Hong Kong Chinese men with self-identified same-sex desires, aged 60 or above, who had been living in Hong Kong for more than 40 years.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1363460712459308">3</xref></sup> Post-war Hong Kong in the 1940s and 1950s is chosen for examination because the family home and the public toilet represented two specific sites of the public/private distinction for same-sex love and eroticism at a time when homosexuality was a crime and the <italic>tongzhi</italic> gay identity did not exist. This is then contrasted with contemporary times, where homosexuality has been decriminalized thereby presenting male <italic>tongzhi</italic> with new opportunities and challenges by way of public/private and hetero/homo spaces in Hong Kong.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-1363460712459308"><title>Power, resistance, and the public/private and ‘hetero’-/‘homo’-normativity binaries</title>
<p>This analysis draws from a post-structuralist power-resistance paradigm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1363460712459308">Kong, 2011</xref>: 28–32) that juxtaposes power with resistance in the same space. This enables the deconstruction of public/private and heterosexual/homosexual spaces, thereby allowing for an understanding of hetero-/homo-normativities as sites of domination and resistance. Heteronormativity<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1363460712459308">4</xref></sup> is usually considered the major form of oppression of queer bodies and is ‘more than ideology, or prejudice, or phobia against gays and lesbians; it is produced in almost every aspect of the forms and arrangements of social life’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1363460712459308">Berlant and Warner, 1998</xref>: 554–555). This makes heterosexuality – sexual/erotic or not – appear natural, coherent, and privileged. The heterosexual culture of intimacy, a derivative of heteronormativity, is institutionalized in both the private sphere (e.g. family) and the public sphere (e.g. law, tax, welfare systems), and is celebrated in public rituals (e.g. weddings). This ‘naturalness’ of heteronormative hegemony is a ‘process of power relations in <italic>all</italic> spaces’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-1363460712459308">Valentine, 1993</xref>: 396, emphasis original), making non-normative sexualities (e.g. homosexuality) unintelligible or only appropriate within private spaces.</p>
<p>However, as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1363460712459308">Foucault (1980: 95)</xref> reminds us, ‘(w)here there is power, there is resistance’. Power derives from above and below, and cannot be eliminated, but only resisted or reversed. Public space is a site of domination – of state politics, market exploitation, and the normalization of heteronormativity – and also a site of resistance and opposition. Naturalization of heterosexual intimacy is never fully achieved, as it is constantly being subverted by various practices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-1363460712459308">Valentine, 2002</xref>: 155). Resistance can be overt and direct, as in different strategies against a specific organization such as the state, in changing situations such as in the implementation of new policies, in creating new spaces such as gay ghettoes, and in territorializing public spaces with gay parades, rallies and so on (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1363460712459308">Duncan, 1996</xref>: 139; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1363460712459308">Hubbard, 2001</xref>: 61). However, resistance can also be covert and indirect, especially for the disadvantaged, with ‘tactics’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1363460712459308">De Certeau, 1984</xref>) becoming a form of resistance in the micro-politics of everyday life. Gay men in New York City in the early 20th century developed subcultural codes of dress, speech, and style that were unintelligible and invisible to outsiders but meaningful and visible to other gay men (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1363460712459308">Chauncey, 1994</xref>). Such tactics constitute an ‘art of the weak’ that unsettles the hegemony of heteronormativity and disrupts the public/private dualism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-1363460712459308">Valentine, 2002</xref>: 155).</p>
<p>If public space is both the site of domination and resistance, so too is private space. The home is considered the individual’s castle and the site of resistance to societal domination, capitalist exploitation, and political intervention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1363460712459308">Saunders, 1989</xref>: 184). However, the 1970s feminist slogan ‘the personal is the political’ implies that private space is not free from politics, but is penetrated by power relations through domestic patriarchal sovereignty, familial heteronormativity, and racism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1363460712459308">Duncan, 1996</xref>: 131–135). The home, for most gays and lesbians, is thus a site of resistance to heterosexual society as well as the site of surveillance and regulation by heterosexual family members (especially parents), neighbours, friends, and others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1363460712459308">Johnston and Valentine, 1995</xref>).</p>
<p>If the public/private binary is to be deconstructed, so must the heterosexual/homosexual binary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1363460712459308">Brown, 2009</xref>: 1500; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1363460712459308">Oswin, 2008</xref>: 98). Heterosexual (usually public) space is ‘mainstream’ and ‘dominant’, but it is also resisted and contested through the queer use of gay men and lesbians. Conversely, homosexual space is usually seen as ‘alternative’ and ‘resistant’, but it can also be ‘repressive’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1363460712459308">Hubbard, 2001</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1363460712459308">Duggan (2002)</xref> criticizes the new assimiliationist queer politics in the USA, what she coins homonormativity, which embraces heteronormative assumptions and institutions and promises a ‘demobilized gay constituency and a privatized, depoliticized gay culture anchored in domesticity and consumption’ (2002: 179). This analysis expands this concept to refer to the emerging norms that are being established within the lesbian and gay communities since 2000. By looking at the notion of sexual citizenship under neo-liberalism, lesbians and gay men have slowly transformed themselves from sad, bad, or mad social outcasts to responsible and respectable consumer-citizens who support dominant ideas and norms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1363460712459308">Bell and Binnie, 2000</xref>: Ch.6; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1363460712459308">Richardson, 2001</xref>: 161–163). It is this emerging homosexual subject – the urban, cosmopolitan, civilized, consumerist, that <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1363460712459308">Altman (1997)</xref> calls ‘global gay identity’ – that seems to be establishing a new norm for being homosexual, which simultaneously enhances solidarity and identification for some, while dividing and demarcating those who cannot fully access this ideal, such as the poor, the aged, the non-monogamous, and so forth. Thus homonormativity works along with heteronormativity, by limiting the public space, thereby confining gay men and lesbians to the private sphere whilst privileging (usually middle-class) depoliticized consumer cultures and lifestyles.</p>
<p>To sum up, the site of domination is also the site of resistance, the location of freedom and sexual expression is also the location of restraint and control, and the moment of governmentality is also the moment of subversion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-1363460712459308">Woodhead, 1995</xref>). Public and private spaces are not stable – their boundaries are blurred (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-1363460712459308">Valentine, 2002</xref>: 154). Heterosexual and homosexual spaces are not always in opposition nor inherently more liberated or repressive to one another, their boundaries are fluid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1363460712459308">Brown, 2009</xref>: 1500). The deconstruction of these binaries depends on the political, social, and cultural circumstances of a particular locale, as well as on the ‘identity-components’ applied to the individual.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-1363460712459308"><title>Colonial Hong Kong: The state, capitalist land use and familial heteronormativity</title>
<p>The Confucian patriarchal family system seems to have been the major system of power that regulated homosexual activities in ancient China (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1363460712459308">Kong, 2011</xref>: 151–152). Traditional Chinese masculinity was governed by the Confucian codes of loyalty to the ruler, filiality towards parents and ancestors, and the submission of the younger brother to the older brother (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1363460712459308">Berry and Farquhar, 2006</xref>: 135). The social morality of male sexuality primarily concerned conformity to power hierarchies, within which men had to fulfil social expectations, including marriage and family, and secondarily with the containment of excessive sexuality, as manifested in masturbation, prostitution, and so on (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1363460712459308">Louie, 2003</xref>: 6–7). It is evident that traditional Chinese society had a strong homosocial culture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1363460712459308">Louie, 2002</xref>), a tolerance of men who had same-sex desires (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1363460712459308">Hinsch, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1363460712459308">Ruan and Tsai, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1363460712459308">Samshasha, 1997</xref>) and even men who possessed feminine beauty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-1363460712459308">Song, 2004</xref>). The tales of <italic>yutao</italic> (‘the peach reminder’), <italic>duanxiu</italic> (‘the cut sleeve’), and Lord Long Yang are commonly cited euphemisms among the literati for male homosexuality in Chinese history.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1363460712459308">5</xref></sup> Although male same-sex relations were not seen as a threat to masculinity, they were always in a marginal position, subsumed under the Confucian patriarchal family and the institution of marriage. In other words, heteronormativity in ancient China, with the effect of marginalizing male same-sex relations, was not so much based around exclusive sexual orientation (same-sex desire) or sexual identity (the homosexual), but around the <italic>normalcy</italic> of being a son who must fulfil familial roles and social expectations.</p>
<p>Heteronormativity changed its form when <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1363460712459308">Hong Kong became a British colony (1842–1997)</xref>. Consistent with the colonial government’s overarching ideology of ‘law and order’, buggery<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1363460712459308">6</xref></sup> first became a crime in Hong Kong in 1842 with its colonial founding, and subsequent legislation followed the English common law. The death penalty for buggery was abolished in 1861 in England, and then in 1865 in Hong Kong. The Criminal Law Amendment Act of 1885, dealing with acts of ‘gross indecency’ between males in the UK, was mandated in the colony in 1901. The colonial government, however, did not follow suit with the UK’s Sexual Offence Act of 1967, which decriminalized male homosexual conduct in private. It is believed that such a move would be too ‘liberal’ and ‘radical’ for the population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1363460712459308">Lethbridge, 1976</xref>: 306–310). In other words, from 1842 to 1990 (the year when homosexuality was decriminalized), there was no legal homosexual space in Hong Kong.</p>
<p>Criminalization of homosexuality meant that buggery, whether private or public, consenting or coerced, involving persons of any age, as twosomes or in larger groups – was a punishable offence. Other gay male practices such as ‘gross indecency’ (e.g. fellatio, mutual masturbation) and ‘soliciting’ (any public indication of interest in sex) were also criminalized. Unlike other western locales (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1363460712459308">Chauncey, 1994</xref>: 9; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1363460712459308">Miller, 1995</xref>: 280–281), this was never taken seriously in colonial times in Hong Kong. There were no police plain-clothes entrapments and few attempts were made to regulate homosexual activities and the law against buggery, with an average lower than five cases a year being reported between 1842 and 1975. Both the government and the population tolerated homosexuality as a ‘necessary evil’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1363460712459308">Lethbridge, 1976</xref>: 306–310).</p>
<p>This tolerance of homosexuality can be explained by looking at the relationship between colonial governance and society at the time. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1363460712459308">Lau (1982)</xref> argues that the colonial government in post-war Hong Kong had little intention to intervene with the population, whilst Chinese inhabitants, oriented towards ‘utilitarianistic familism’ (1982: 72–82), relied on the family rather than making demands on the government. This ‘boundary politics’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1363460712459308">Lau, 1982</xref>: 163–172) was carefully played up by both government and populace, serving to differentiate the public space of the British/colonial polity from the private space of Chinese society. The tolerance of homosexuality could be viewed as an example of this functional explanation. However, it has also been argued that colonial governance skilfully picked and promoted Chinese filial piety and utilitarian intentions to manage colonialism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1363460712459308">Law, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1363460712459308">Ong, 1993</xref>). Rather than the ‘inherent nature’ of Chinese culture, these family practices, or what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1363460712459308">Ong (1993:753–62)</xref> calls ‘family biopolitics’, could be seen as the result of strategies used by the state to manage the refugee/immigrant families of post-war Hong Kong. Familial heteronormativity, derived from ‘family biopolitics’, was part of colonial efforts that silenced homosexuality and shifted the site of governance from the state to the family. Modern heteronormativity was articulated through colonial governance, land use, and the family.</p>
<p>Moreover, public housing became a major issue from the 1930s onward. Because of the influx of refugees and immigrants from China, Hong Kong’s population of 625,166 in 1921 more than doubled to 1,639,337 by 1941 and reached 2,360,000 in 1950 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1363460712459308">Faure, 1997</xref>: 149; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1363460712459308">Hong Kong Government, 1952</xref>: 23). Government revenue relied heavily on land sales and taxes as land development played a central role in Hong Kong’s economic development. The colonial government adopted a policy of high land prices, so that half of the population lived in crowded public housing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1363460712459308">Cuthbert, 1995</xref>: 298).</p>
<p>As a result, under British rule, with the conditions of laissez-faire capitalism and a high land-price policy, Hong Kong families, characterized as utilitarianistic familism, developed extraordinary discipline for hard work, fierce competition, and tight control over family members in order to improve family livelihood and wealth. If ‘family biopower’ encodes a series of family practices and ideologies – symbolic, emotional, and utilitarian contractual obligations and mutual support – that regulate economic, productive, and successful Chinese bodies, it also disciplines healthy, reproductive, and heterosexual bodies. Heteronormativity (or in particular familial heteronormativity), articulated as a form of ‘family biopolitics’, functioned to produce the disciplined father, the sacrificing mother, the filial son, and the dutiful daughter in post-war Hong Kong. A child’s – especially a son’s – sense of moral worth requires him to comply with parental wishes to marry, to continue the family bloodline, and to do nothing to harm family status and reputation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1363460712459308">Kong, 2011</xref>: 95–98). How did gay men live in such family biopolitics confined under capitalist land use and British law?</p>
<sec id="sec4-1363460712459308"><title>‘All-in-the-family’</title>
<p>From the end of the Japanese occupation (1945) onwards, the Hong Kong population consisted overwhelmingly of returned immigrants and refugees from Mainland China. Most were working class, settling in Chinese tenement-type buildings, or in squatter homes built on hillsides, on rooftops, or in alleys (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1363460712459308">Rooney, 2003</xref>: 18). In tenement buildings, floors were usually subdivided into small rooms or cubicles (averaging 5.57 sq m), each floor accommodating three or four households, sharing communal kitchen, public latrines, and bathrooms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1363460712459308">Hong Kong Government, 1947</xref>: 54). Family members – immediate family as well as relatives and fictive kin – and neighbours formed a fluid collective living under the same roof. This led to an ‘all-in-the-family’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1363460712459308">Lau, 1982</xref>: 74) notion being adopted by working-class families in the 1940s and 1950s, where mutual assistance and economic exchange, family ownership of property, and utilitarian cooperation, became defining norms of ‘utilitarianistic familism’.</p>
<p>‘Home’ has many meanings –‘shelter’, ‘hearth’, ‘heart’, ‘privacy’, ‘roots’, ‘abode’, and ‘paradise’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-1363460712459308">Somerville, 1992</xref>; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1363460712459308">Gorman-Murray, 2007</xref>). For respondents in this study, cramped, badly ventilated, unhygienic spaces, and quasi-kin communal familial living was their first experience of ‘home’; a site of physical security and emotional and psychological comfort and support. The family home was where they learned to be filial sons and to work hard to contribute to the family economy in close relation with other family members. Their parents taught them frugality, hard work, and compliance to the group – crucial components of the socialization process in the self-sufficient family system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1363460712459308">Salaff, 1981</xref>: 35).</p>
<p>The family home was also the site where heteronormative culture was fostered. Family members usually did not talk about sexuality, or did so mainly in heterosexual terms. No one mentioned homosexuality. The home, under the gaze of other household members, did not permit privacy or cater to the needs of men with same-sex desires. Heternormativity was thus materialized in this site of territorialized power and regulatory practices, not so much from government intervention, but more under surveillance by other household members that silenced these young men’s same-sex desires.</p>
<p>But how could familial heteronormativity be resisted? Most respondents had no idea how to name their same-sex desires. They did not know the word ‘homosexuality’, or hear of the traditional Chinese euphemisms of <italic>yutao</italic>, <italic>duanxiu</italic>, and Lord Long Yang. They discovered their interests in men by playing with their relatives or neighbours. Simon was born in the early 1940s and lived in a tenement cubicle with his mother, who was a ‘second wife’ – his father lived with his ‘first wife’.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-1363460712459308">7</xref></sup> He had some fond memories of this home, where he had first realized same-sex desires:<disp-quote>
<p>It was the time when I learned about this … I didn’t know what it was … I had no idea … didn’t have a name for it … but I liked it … My home had a lot of elder brothers,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-1363460712459308">8</xref></sup> neighbours, a lot of people living together … these elder brothers would play with me … I was not even eighteen and he was my first lover. Whenever I entered the front door, I would pass his cubicle before mine. He was usually studying, but if not he would grab me, and we played in the small corner of the cubicle … nothing serious, mainly hanky-panky.</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>However, these homosexual encounters were usually fleeting and had to be carried out secretly. The boys who played together were usually not gay, just adolescents seeking sexual release. This familial environment urged these young men to discover their same-sex desires, some through writing to pen pals, some reading scant discussions, usually negative media reports about homosexuality, but most through going to public spaces to find other gay men.</p>
<p>After their interactions with other gay men, or even the gay ‘scene’ elsewhere which helped them develop an identity from their same-sex desire, the family home often became a difficult place in which to live. Hiding their same-sex desires and emerging identity became a pressing issue. One way was through argots. Mahjong is a very common Chinese game, but ‘playing mahjong’ came to mean ‘having sex’, and ‘mahjong tile’ referred to the male organ. Public toilets were called ‘gardens’ (later, ‘fish ponds’). ‘Wandering around the garden’ or ‘fishing’ meant ‘cruising’ (US) or ‘cottaging’ (UK). As Simon mentioned during a focus group discussion:<disp-quote>
<p>We lived with many people in the tenement building but shared only one phone. You can’t say going to a ‘public toilet’ to find men! … We have many gardens in Hong Kong … so it is very natural to say that you are going to a garden to see fish  … and you could tell your gay friends you played mahjong last night and got a big mahjong tile!</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Some respondents, however, such as David and Sunny, were less subtle. They were both born in the early 1940s and went out together for over a decade after meeting in their early 20s. Sunny even brought David home:<disp-quote>
<p>I always lived with my family. We even did it in front of our family, it was very dangerous. We did it in the bunk bed: Dad was sleeping next to us and Mum was sleeping on the floor. I don’t know, they never said a word, but they should have known.</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>As in de Certeau’s (1984) discussion of the tactics of introducing alternative meanings within a dominant cultural system, these young gay men did not openly resist domestic heteronormativity; rather, they used covert tactics, referencing argots and making use of the homosocial overcoat, to realize same-sex erotic experiences. As these men got older, however, parents urged them to marry. Marriage usually led to a double life, although some respondents stayed single, and lied to their family throughout their lives. In any case, all had to work within the parameters of familial heteronormativity.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-1363460712459308"><title>The secret garden</title>
<p>The colonial government’s strict control and discrimination policies for the use of public space mainly concerned public hygiene (such as hawker control) and social problems like gambling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-1363460712459308">Too, 2007</xref>: 31–36). In this situation, Hong Kong gay men found space to develop a ‘fishing’ subculture. Before the 1980s, when debate over homosexuality began in Hong Kong, the respondents (especially working-class ones) had not heard of the law governing homosexuality and had no idea that homosexual conduct was a criminal offence. They believed it was a moral issue that would bring shame to the family. Family networks were crucial, and they mainly found work through family members, relatives, or neighbours. There were no exclusive spaces for homosexuals, only one or two Shanghai-style saunas (for presumably heterosexual men), a few hotel cafes catering for mainly the gay and lesbian middle-class and celebrities, and some secret parties. For most gay men, the public space became the major site for finding sex, love, and friendship. They sought privacy in public, as they had little freedom to express their sexuality in the ‘privacy’ of their homes; ‘privacy could only be had in public’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1363460712459308">Chauncey, 1994</xref>: Ch. 7). The cruising ground was thus the site for the redefinition of the public and the private, where there was no freedom to be ‘out’ and no subscription to any identity or community (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1363460712459308">Bell, 1995</xref>: 308).</p>
<p>The respondents ‘found’ other gay men virtually everywhere – walking down streets, on ferries, at street performances, and in railway stations. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1363460712459308">De Certeau (1984: 97)</xref> discusses walking as ‘a process of <italic>appropriation</italic> of the topographical system on the part of the pedestrian’ (emphasis original); ‘queering the street’ can thus be seen as a way to form queer consciousness through wandering, walking, looking, and being looked at. Such ‘acts of operating’ are moments of transgression that destabilize ‘the assumed heteronormativity of urban public space with theatrical displays of queer affection, desire and rage’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1363460712459308">Bell and Binnie, 1998</xref>: 131).</p>
<p>The public toilet was the most common site for ‘fishing’. The design of public toilets at the time permitted easier cruising than those of the present.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-1363460712459308">9</xref></sup> A public toilet usually consisted of two parts: the ‘open’ part, with several urinals or a urinal wall and trough; and the more ‘private’ part, which consisted of squat toilets in two parallel rows over long gutters, partitioned into five or six cubicles with doors. If one stood up, his head would be above the partition. Most respondents had had experiences of ‘fishing’, as Peter (aged 62) discussed in one focus group:<disp-quote>
<p>The look was very important … this is the only way you would know if he was (gay) … You could test the water in the public area where you pretended to pee … or you could go to the more private part … if he was interested in you, he would follow … You could open the door and both of you could masturbate in front of the other. Or if you were brave enough, you could go to his cubicle. Because of the height, one had to squat … or you could pick him up and go elsewhere.</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>‘Fishing’, like walking down a street, became almost a routine. Some would fish for immediate quick sex, but most went to public toilets to meet friends or catch up on gossip, which subsequently led to knowing more men with same-sex desires or even join small gay subcultures. This concept of ‘fishing’, a form of non-normative intimacy, redefines the public and private distinction and challenges normative intimacy. It is public in terms of location but private in terms of the intimate moment participants share. It is criminal intimacy, not just if sex occurs, but also because showing interest in sex publicly is considered ‘soliciting’. But this eroticism outside of the couple form gave these men tremendous pleasure, especially when there was no material gay space for them to go to. Affections formed with strangers and acquaintances could even develop into life-long friendships or partnerships.</p>
<p>This non-normative, even criminal, intimacy bears ‘no necessary relation to domestic space, to kinship, to the couple form, to property, or to the nation’, but it does bear a necessary relation to a ‘counter-public’: ‘an indefinitely accessible world conscious of its subordinate relation’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1363460712459308">Berlant and Warner, 1998</xref>: 558). It was this network of erotic and non-erotic friends – acquaintance, friends, sex partners, lovers, and partners – that provided a loose sense of ‘gay community’, a counter-public, or a heterotopia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1363460712459308">Foucault, 1986</xref>) that nurtured a local gay identity and facilitated sexual and social liaisons.</p>
<p>Modern heteronormativity then was articulated through ‘family biopower’ in post-war Hong Kong, produced under British colonialism (mainly through the law of buggery), capitalist urban land use and the family. The parental family home and the public toilet were two major public/private sites of discipline/desire for (especially working-class) young gay men. Their radical transgression of the boundaries permitted them to create a transient heterotopia in both sites for same-sex love and eroticism.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-1363460712459308"><title>Post-colonial Hong Kong: The state, regulation of public space and the ‘harmonious’ family</title>
<p>Triggered by the death of expatriate police inspector John MacLennan in 1980, the government revised laws governing homosexual conduct, and homosexuality was finally decriminalized in 1990 after lengthy debate.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-1363460712459308">10</xref></sup> Decriminalization had numerous effects. The lengthy debate transformed a deviant sexual conduct from a legal issue into a distinctive social type of ‘homosexual’. This subsequently led to the development of homosexual identities in Hong Kong, including <italic>gei</italic> (gay), <italic>geilo</italic> (gay man), <italic>memba</italic> (member, a.k.a. gay man), <italic>lesi</italic> (lesbian), <italic>TB</italic> (tomboy), <italic>TBG</italic> (tomboy girl), <italic>tungzi</italic>/<italic>tongzhi</italic> (comrade),<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-1363460712459308">11</xref></sup> and others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1363460712459308">Ho, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1363460712459308">Kong, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1363460712459308">Leung, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-1363460712459308">Tang, 2011</xref>). Decriminalization not only protected gay men who engaged in private sexual acts, but also triggered the emergence of local <italic>tongzhi</italic> groups and a pink economy, as well as a more visible and established <italic>tongzhi</italic> subculture.</p>
<p>However, laws concerning homosexuality have not progressed much since Hong Kong was returned to China in 1997. Although the previous age of consent (16 for heterosexuals, 21 for homosexuals) was equalized in 2005, and same-sex partners were included under the domestic violence ordinance after a long battle in 2009, the Equal Opportunity Ordinances does not provide protection based on sexual orientation, and same-sex marriage is not allowed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1363460712459308">Kong, 2011</xref>: 48–51).</p>
<p>With the increasing migrant influx and the blooming post-war baby generations in the 1960s, the colonial government faced the problems of housing, social services and poverty, and so took an active role in developing public housing estates (resettlement estates, low-cost public estates), establishing an infrastructure of new towns, and providing home ownership schemes and loans to the emerging lower middle class. The 1997 Asian financial crisis collapsed property prices and prevented the first Chief Executive of the new Hong Kong Special Administrative Region (SAR) from carrying out his pledge of 85,000 new flats a year. With the population of a small territory (1104 sq km) growing from 3 million in 1960 to 7 million in 2010, the government’s public housing and high land-price policies have restricted the living space of most Hong Kong residents. In 2010, there were 737,900 households living in public rental housing, constituting 31.6% of total household types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1363460712459308">Census and Statistics Department, 2011</xref>: 180). Although Hong Kong people have changed from homeless immigrants to public housing tenants or home-owning citizens, most are still subject to limited choices and conditions in choosing living environments and the financial burden of securing permanent homes.</p>
<p>Moreover, the SAR government has promoted the heterosexual nuclear family as a core value, emphasizing the close and mutually supportive relationships between the married couple and their parents and siblings as an essential part of ‘Chinese culture’ in its policy addresses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1363460712459308">HKSAR, 2011</xref>). The government set up a Family Council in late 2007 to consolidate core family values and harmonious relationships among family members, thereby further institutionalizing familial heteronormativity. The SAR policies that continue to limit the development of <italic>tongzhi</italic> space, and strategic relations with private developers and the family, maintain powerful dominations, which confine the activities of Hong Kong <italic>tongzhi</italic> bodies.</p>
<sec id="sec7-1363460712459308"><title>The home of one’s own</title>
<p>As compared with the past, the living conditions of most respondents are much improved. The working-class informants have moved from tenement building or squatter homes to public estates. Few could afford private flats, even with government assistance. They had been manual workers or low-skilled clerks and are all now retired, some receiving social security allowances. Their family homes are now more spacious and possess basic facilities such as a bedroom, living room with basic furniture, private toilet, bathroom, and kitchen. The communal living space has gone and family life has permitted more privacy. This new familial environment serves as both a site of resistance and surveillance.</p>
<p>Half of the respondents are now living alone, through widowhood, separation or divorce from their wives, or have never married. The other half live with their family members – wives, children, and/or siblings. For those who are living alone, their homes tend to be a place of security, free from surveillance, where they may resist heterosexual norms. They are generally happy with their present, rather simple lives – hanging out with friends, doing <italic>tongzhi</italic> volunteer work, and watching television. The major problem is their health. They all have different degrees of illness, and frequent the hospital. Mr Tang, now 85, lives on his own after his wife passed away 20 years ago. He has fainted several times in his flat, with his children coming to rescue him. Another respondent, who was not so fortunate, died on his own without notice until he was found by neighbours.</p>
<p>For those who live with family members, the privatized family home is a challenge. Living without their wives is easier. Mr Chiu – who died in 2011, at age 75 – separated from his wife and lived with his boyfriend and his son for four years. He never made explicit his relationship with his boyfriend to his son and his son never asked. Living with their wives is more difficult. Couple intimacy is avoided as much as possible, by making excuses such as exhaustion from work, coming home late, or swapping rooms with the children and leaving their wives to stay with the daughters. Mr Lam’s practices are examples of this. Born in 1940 and married in 1972, he has six children. He maintains a good relationship with his wife and children, who currently live with him in a public estate. For him to have a good wife was important for the family, and he had had only fleeting sexual encounters with men. It was at the age of 60, having fulfilled his family duties – conjugal duty to his wife, fatherly duty to his children – that he decide to explore gay romance:<disp-quote>
<p>In the past … I was only concerned about living. I had my family, my wife and kids to raise. I had to fulfil these duties … family meant a man and a woman. After I finished work, I went home and had food, this was happiness … I have always been a very responsible person, my wife trusts me … and my children have all finished their education … that’s when I started to explore this [gay life] … I went to a public toilet and met a man. He brought me to a new world... this was the first time in my life that I felt I fell in love … in my 60s! My heart was thumping when I met him … it’s like a puppy love … I was so happy … but when he asked me to leave my family, I said no, I could not accept this.</p></disp-quote></p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1363460712459308">Salaff (1981)</xref> has aptly described the dutiful ‘working daughter’ of the 1970s, who sacrificed her own self-development, gave up secondary education, and worked in a factory to contribute to the family economy. Likewise, these men sacrificed their own self-development by suppressing their same-sex desires, marrying in order to contribute to the heterosexual family economy. Like the working daughters, they did not really regret their decisions, beginning to explore the gay world later in life. Mr Lam’s ‘puppy love’ was when he met his first boyfriend, but he refused to leave his family and chose familial intimacy over gay romance.</p>
<p>Coming out is always a difficult but life-long process. The notion of individuality, as well as its implicit economic and material affluence of ‘moving out’ to live on one’s own or with one’s same-sex partner, sometimes clashes with the notion of the relational self in the biopolitics of Hong Kong Chinese families (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1363460712459308">Kong, 2011: Ch. 4</xref>). Whether single or married, my respondents negotiated their gay identities in the closet under the parameters of familial heteronormativity. The real opposition is sometimes not so much between homosexuality and heterosexuality, but ‘between those who are willing and able to play traditional family roles and those who are not’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1363460712459308">Berry, 2001</xref>: 219).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-1363460712459308"><title>The new tongzhi space and homonormativity</title>
<p>In accordance with urban renewal and redevelopment, intensified after the SARS crisis in 2003, most public toilets have been renovated. Public toilets are now equipped with individually partitioned urinals and fully partitioned cubicles (walls from floor to ceiling). Most have attendants who clean them. The ‘garden’ has disappeared. Most respondents occasionally go to public toilets, but they now run higher risks than before of police arrest or blackmail by male sex workers.</p>
<p>After the decriminalization of homosexuality in 1991, sites exclusively for <italic>tongzhi</italic> consumption (such as bars, clubs, karaokes, bathhouses, saunas, spas, salons, boutiques, cafés, bookshops) have burgeoned in Hong Kong. This apparently successful ‘territorialization’ of <italic>tongzhi</italic> spaces and the pink economy has nurtured the new <italic>tongzhi</italic> image of the ‘good consumer citizen’, in contrast with the traditional image of ‘citizen-pervert’, and has provided a significant, positive cultural sense of belonging for <italic>tongzhi</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1363460712459308">Kong, 2011</xref>: Ch. 3). This new <italic>tongzhi</italic> identity, closely associated with consumption, is cosmopolitan in outlook, commercially driven, and conspicuously consumed on the body, and might be considered a derivative of a ‘global queer identity’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1363460712459308">Altman, 1997</xref>). However, rather than promoting solidarity and identification, it also divides those who can access this ideal from those who cannot. The emerging gay world is thus more segregated and less tolerating than previous gay environments, and operates along the lines of class, age, gender, sexuality, race, and body type. Most respondents have had extreme difficulty in accessing this exclusive gay space and complain of high prices and the obsession with youthfulness. Eric, a 60-year-old medical professional, remarks:<disp-quote>
<p>The whole world is … very youth-oriented. If you have youthfulness, you have the world … The gay scene is so youth-oriented that you can’t get into it. If you can’t get into it, what space is left for you?</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>If bars and clubs marginalize gay men in terms of class and age, gay saunas discriminate in terms of age and body shape. Simon’s rejection at a gay sauna was shared by others:<disp-quote>
<p>Ageism! The receptionist at Sauna A said to me once, ‘Oh I am sorry, this sauna operates a membership system.’ I said ‘OK! I would like to join’. But he said, ‘No, the forms have all been filled out, please come another time.’ What an excuse!</p></disp-quote></p>
<p>Although most of these working-class gay men possess well-built bodies from manual labour when they were young, their physical capital has now diminished. As Parco, now 66, states: ‘I used to be very popular, but now, no one approached me, that’s why I stopped going there [to saunas].’</p>
<p>If heteronormativity functions to create a hierarchy of ‘good’ and ‘bad’ citizens by privileging heterosexuals and stigmatizing homosexuals, the new homonormativity not only endorses a depoliticized gay culture anchored in privatized domesticity and consumption (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1363460712459308">Duggan, 2002</xref>: 179), but also creates a hierarchy of queer identities and places. In Hong Kong, this hierarchy of identities and bodies has transnational middle-class Chinese gay men and gay Caucasian expatriates at the top; local-born Hong Kong gay male denizens in the middle; and new mainland Chinese migrants, male sex workers, and other gay subordinates at the bottom, defined according to age, class, gender performance, ethnicity, and body type. <italic>Tongzhi</italic> space is thus stratified – bars and clubs in Central Hong Kong attract predominately middle-class, hip, cool, and ‘in’ young male professionals, whilst Kowloon caters more to working-class gays. Most gay saunas privilege muscular athletic and/or youthful bodies; very few welcome the elderly. Very few <italic>tongzhi</italic> NGOs have put older gay men on their service agendas. Within this new homonormative logic, ‘fishing’ is regarded as cheap, irresponsible, unrespectable, and undesirable, and older gay men are alleged to be self-loathing, closeted, and sad creatures who only ‘fish’ in a seedy underworld.</p>
<p>So how do these men resist homonormativity? A few of them ‘quit’ the gay scene and only socialize with close friends. Most still hang out in those saunas that are tolerant to them, and go for sex tourism in Mainland China or other Asian countries such as Taiwan, Thailand, and Malaysia. Some of them participate in <italic>tongzhi</italic> volunteer work. Simon is such an example:<disp-quote>
<p>I get up five in the morning, go running and get home, have breakfast and go back to sleep. I wake up at noon and make lunch, do some volunteer work in the afternoon and then make dinner for myself in the evening, watching tele and talking to friends … During weekends … I go to Sauna G ... or to Shenzhen for erotic massage … and we would go to Thailand once a year.</p></disp-quote></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-1363460712459308" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>British colonialism (and the later post-colonial governance), together with land developers and the Chinese family, have produced a heteronormative culture of intimacy in Hong Kong. During almost the entire colonial period, homosexuality was criminalized, and since its decriminalization in 1990, legal <italic>tongzhi</italic> space has remained limited. There is no same-sex marriage and Hong Kong’s anti-discrimination laws do not cover sexual orientation. Moreover, the government’s relationship with private land developers, manifested in high land prices, public housing policies, and the regulation of public spaces has confined many people to the private space of their families.</p>
<p>Encouraged by the state, family biopolitics has continued to regulate healthy, productive, heterosexual bodies through both family practices and spatial controls. This ‘utilitarianistic familism’ – that being the collective domestic (and predominant working-class) space of the past and the ‘harmonious family’ and ‘privatized’ family unit of the present – promotes familial heteronormativity, privileging the heterosexual culture of intimacy and marginalizing same-sex desire. The family home, the site of discipline and surveillance, has been a site of tension for Hong Kong gay men, as it obliges them to fulfil the roles and duties of filial sons, the good husband, father, and grandfather. However, the family home is also the site of resistance and subversion, as these gay men derive tactics to resist familial heteronormativity such as using argots to communicate, making use of the homosocial overcoat, and living in a closet. Whether they are living on their own or with family members, they are always overshadowed by the closet, which is not created just by the hetero/homo distinction, but also by family/individual dualism, subsumed under the parameters of familial heteronormativity in the Chinese context.</p>
<p>Public space in the past was less regulated, and the public toilet was a major site for same-sex intimacy and eroticism. The public toilet was, and remains, a site of discipline, desire, and erotic possibility, and was once the major ‘private’ site for realizing same-sex intimacy, especially for working-class gay men. Urban renovation and redevelopment has removed this ‘secret garden’, while the pink economy has allowed <italic>tongzhi</italic> commercial spaces to emerge since decriminalization. However, operating under the logic of homonormativity, this newly established homosexual world serves less to promote solidarity and identification than to foster stratification and discrimination. Homosexual space is not the homogenous space of freedom and liberation, but as both a ‘site of desire’ and a ‘site of power and domination’. Openness always entails exclusion, and in the new hierarchy of gay bodies and spaces, class and age are two salient discriminative social signifiers. Whilst class limits their mobility, age becomes a liability. However, even in this discriminatory homo-space, older gay men still find their ‘ways of operating’, through sex tourism, <italic>tongzhi</italic> volunteer work, and immersing with their close friends.</p>
<p>Hong Kong gay men’s radical use of the family and the public spaces challenges the rigid distinction between public/private embedded in the culture of heteronormative intimacy and reveals the dual nature of these spaces as dominating/subversive and governable/desiring. Their experiences in gay space also lead to serious doubts regarding assumptions that homosexual space is free and liberating, instead revealing the heterogeneous and hierarchical nature of <italic>tongzhi</italic> space. As <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1363460712459308">Brown (2009: 1500)</xref> reminds us, ‘the real potential of queer thinking is to undermine binary understandings of sexuality and gender rather than reinforcing them’. By exposing the dual nature of domination/resistance in the public/private and hetero/homosexual spaces, this study offers a critique to heteronormativity and even homonormativity as an encompassing structure governing queer or <italic>tongzhi</italic> lives. My informants’ accounts of the past and present show this duality. They did not find the past too repressive even though homosexuality was a criminal offence and coming out was almost an impossible choice as they created secretive pleasures in the communal family and public toilets. Although they generally applauded the overall ‘liberalization’ of homosexual spaces since the 1990s with decriminalization and well-established <italic>tongzhi</italic> spaces, they do not find it more liberating because of a tendency toward ageism and favouring the middle-classes. They are neither victims nor heroes, but marginal individuals who live under a complex web of dominations – hetero/homo-normativities – in order to create a <italic>tongzhi</italic> heterotopia, a real site that is ‘represented, contested, and inverted’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1363460712459308">Foucault, 1986</xref>: 24), no matter how fleeting and ephemeral, for love, sex, and intimacy.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec10-1363460712459308"><title>Funding statement</title>
<p>I would like to thank the University of Hong Kong (Small Project Fund, ‘Gay and Grey: Oral History of Hong Kong Gay Elders’, awarded in November 2008) for funding this project.</p>
</sec>
<notes>
<title>Notes</title>
<fn-group>
<fn id="fn1-1363460712459308"><label>1</label><p>For an extensive review, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1363460712459308">Binnie and Valentine (1999)</xref>, and the introduction in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1363460712459308">Browne, Lim and Brown (2007)</xref>.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn2-1363460712459308"><label>2</label><p>‘<italic>Tongzhi</italic>’, literally meaning ‘common will’, is usually translated as ‘comrade’. The term was originally used by Sun Yixian (or Sun Yat-sen), the father of the modern Chinese nation, who encouraged Chinese people to fight against the Qing imperialist regime in the early 20th century. His saying, ‘the revolution has not been successful, comrades should fight for it until the end’, became a famous slogan of the revolution in both the Republican and People’s Republic of China eras. It was appropriated as a synonym for lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender in Hong Kong after the First Gay and Lesbian Film Festival, held in 1991, was referred to as the <italic>Tongzhi</italic> Film Festival by a local gay writer Edward Lam. The queer connotation of the term became very popular in both the gay and straight communities in Hong Kong and Taiwan, and later in the gay community in China. Its popularity may be because of its erasure of sexual connotation, unlike the clinical term ‘homosexual’ or western term ‘gay’, and its affirmation of a ‘positive’ rather than ‘negative’ (e.g. ‘queer’) identity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1363460712459308">Kong, 2011</xref>: 14–15; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1363460712459308">Leung, 2008</xref>: 1–6).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn3-1363460712459308"><label>3</label><p>This article is based on an ongoing oral history project of older gay men in Hong Kong since 2009. Respondents were mainly recruited through gay and AIDS non-governmental organizations and then through the snowball technique. All names appearing in this article are pseudonyms, and minor alterations to the biographies of respondents have been made to protect anonymity and confidentiality. Consent was sought before tape-recording. All interviews and focus groups were transcribed from spoken Cantonese to written Chinese, then quotations were translated into written English. Data analysis involved identifying themes, building codebooks and marking texts. The findings and analysis were compared to others in existing literature. One or two in-depth (2–4 hour) individual semi-structured interviews, and three (3–4 hour) focus groups, were conducted. Respondents were aged 60 to 85; 10 were born into the working class whilst 4 were from middle-class families; 6 had primary education, 4 had secondary education, and 4 had university education.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn4-1363460712459308"><label>4</label><p>There are many concepts that address the social oppression of same-sex desires. The most frequent ones are homophobia, heterosexism, compulsory heterosexuality, and heteronormativity, drawn from different theoretical paradigms with the presupposition of the ‘homosexual’ subject and a broader account of how sexuality is organized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1363460712459308">Adam, 1998: 387</xref>). It has been argued that homophobia is rooted in psychology and refers mostly to anti-homosexual practices and ideologies stemming from fear by prejudiced individuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-1363460712459308">Weinberg, 1973</xref>: 1–21). Heterosexism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1363460712459308">Herek, 1995</xref>: 321; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1363460712459308">Plummer, 1992</xref>: 19) and compulsory heterosexuality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1363460712459308">Rich, 1980</xref>: 648) are more sociological as they view the social oppression of sexual difference as a social system like racism or sexism that is imposed on individuals. Heteronormativity is more than just a psychological phobia, or an unjust social system, it is a preferred structure of understanding and cultural practices that make heterosexuality, sexual/erotic or not, appear to be natural, coherent, privileged, and thus hegemonic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1363460712459308">Berlant and Warner, 1998</xref>: 554–555). Each term has its own advantages and heteronormativity is chosen over others because it highlights a metaculture that governs the lives of the individuals being discussed.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn5-1363460712459308"><label>5</label><p>The stories of <italic>yutao</italic> and <italic>duanxiu</italic> were recorded in <italic>Han Fei Zi</italic> and <italic>Han Shu</italic> respectively. The first story is about a romance between Duke Ling of Wei (534–493 BC) and his male favourite Mi Zixia. Mi Zixia tasted a piece of peach, found it to be sweet, and gave the rest of the peach to the duke. The second story is about the last emperor Ai of the former Han Dynasty (6 BC–AD 1) and his male favourite Dong Xian. While the couple were sleeping together on a couch the emperor was suddenly called to attend to state business. In order not to wake his lover, who was still sleeping, the emperor took his sword and severed his anchored sleeve. So ‘the peach reminder’ (<italic>yutao</italic>) and ‘the cut sleeve’ (<italic>duanxiu</italic>) became euphemisms among the literati for male homosexuality in Chinese history. Addiction or obsession (<italic>pi</italic>) for male same-sex relations is often referred to as ‘<italic>long yang pi</italic>’, which is derived from the same-sex love between Lord Long Yang and the King of Wei in the Warring State period (475–221 BC) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1363460712459308">Hinsch, 1990</xref>: 20–22, 32–33, 52–53; Samshasha, 1997: 39, 43, 67–68; see also <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1363460712459308">Kang, 2009</xref>: 22–33).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn6-1363460712459308"><label>6</label><p>Buggery in English law is a generic term for both sodomy (anal intercourse between two men or between a man and a woman) and bestiality (anal intercourse between a man or a woman and an animal), but has generally been used to mean sodomy between men (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1363460712459308">Lethbridge, 1976</xref>: 300–306).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn7-1363460712459308"><label>7</label><p>Polygamy was widely practised until banned in Hong Kong in 1971.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn8-1363460712459308"><label>8</label><p>‘Elder brother’ means an older young man, not a blood relation.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn9-1363460712459308"><label>9</label><p>See similar discussion in Britain by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1363460712459308">Jeyasingham (2010)</xref>.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn10-1363460712459308"><label>10</label><p>The MacLennan case is significant to Hong Kong <italic>tongzhi</italic> history. Scottish police inspector John MacLennan was charged with acts of gross indecency and then found dead in his apartment in1980. Some observers suggested that his death was a murder and a police cover up, which raised media attention that challenged the justice and integrity of the colonial government. The colonial government responded by appointing a judicial committee (Commission of Inquiry) to investigate the case, and another committee (the Law Reform Committee of Hong Kong) to review laws governing homosexual conduct. The Commission of Inquiry concluded that the case was one of suicide in 1981, with the Law Reform Committee publishing a report in 1983 recommending that homosexuality should be decriminalized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1363460712459308">Chan, 2007</xref>: 38–45; Ho, 1997: Ch. 1; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-1363460712459308">Whitehead, 2001</xref>: 19–34).</p></fn>
<fn id="fn11-1363460712459308"><label>11</label><p>‘Tungzi’ and ‘tongzhi’ are Cantonese and Mandarin Chinese (<italic>pinyin</italic>) Romanization respectively. The two terms bear no difference in meaning. Since <italic>tongzhi</italic> has been used almost exclusively in academic writings and in popular culture in Hong Kong, it is used throughout the text to avoid confusion, even though in daily conversation Hong Kong Cantonese pronounces it as <italic>tungzi</italic>. For the use of the term <italic>tongzhi</italic> please see Note 2.</p></fn></fn-group></notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Theorizing homophobia</article-title>. <source>Sexualities</source> <volume>1</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>387</fpage>–<lpage>404</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Global gaze/global gays</article-title>. <source>GLQ: A Journal of Lesbian and Gay Studies</source> <volume>3</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>436</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Perverse dynamics, sexual citizenship and the transformation of intimacy</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Valentine</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Mapping Desire: Geographies of Sexualities</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>304</fpage>–<lpage>317</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Binnie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Theatres of cruelty, rivers of desire: The erotics of the street</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Fyfe</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Images of the Street: Planning, Identity and Control in Public Space</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>140</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Binnie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>The Sexual Citizen: Queer Politics and Beyond</source>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Polity</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Valentine</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <source>Mapping Desire: Geographies of Sexualities</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berlant</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Sex in public</article-title>. <source>Critical Inquiry</source> <volume>24</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>547</fpage>–<lpage>566</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Asian values, family values: Film, video, and lesbian and gay identities</article-title>. <source>Journal of Homosexuality</source> <volume>40</volume>(<issue>3/4</issue>): <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>231</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Farquhar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>China on Screen: Cinema and Nation</source>, <publisher-loc>Hong Kong</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hong Kong University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Binnie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Trading places: Consumption, sexuality and the production of queer space</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Valentine</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Mapping Desire: Geographies of Sexualities</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>182</fpage>–<lpage>199</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Binnie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Valentine</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Geographies of sexuality: A review of progress</article-title>. <source>Progress in Human Geography</source> <volume>23</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>187</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Thinking beyond heteronormativity: Performative explorations of diverse gay economies</article-title>. <source>Environment and Planning A</source> <volume>41</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1496</fpage>–<lpage>1510</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Geographies of Sexualities: Theory, Practices and Politics</source>, <publisher-loc>Aldershot</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Census and Statistics Department</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Hong Kong Annual Digest of Statistics 2011</source>, <publisher-loc>Hong Kong</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hong Kong Special Administrative Region (SAR), People’s Republic of China</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>PCW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Same-sex marriage/constitutionalism and their centrality to equality rights in Hong Kong: A comparative-socio-legal appraisal</article-title>. <source>The International Journal of Human Rights</source> <volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>33</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chauncey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <source>Gay New York: Gender, Urban Culture, and the Making of the Gay Male World, 1890–1940</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>NWS</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Ageing in Hong Kong</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Philips</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Ageing in the Asia-Pacific Region: Issues, Policies and Future Trends</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>158</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cuthbert</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>The right to the city: Surveillance, private interest and the public domain in Hong Kong</article-title>. <source>Cities</source> <volume>12</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>293</fpage>–<lpage>310</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Certeau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <source>The Practice of Everyday Life</source>, <publisher-loc>(trans. S. Rendall). Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duggan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The new homonormativity: The sexual politics of neoliberalism</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Castronovo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Materializing Democracy: Toward a Revitalized Cultural Politics</source>, <publisher-loc>Durham, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Duke</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>194</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Renegotiating gender and sexuality in public and private spaces</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Bodyspace: Destabilizing Geographies of Gender and Sexuality</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faure</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>A Documentary History of Hong Kong: Society</source>, <publisher-loc>Hong Kong</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hong Kong University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foucault</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>) <source>The History of Sexuality, Volume One: An Introduction (trans. R Hurley)</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Vintage</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foucault</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Of other spaces</article-title>. <source>Diacritics</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>22</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorman-Murray</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Reconfiguring domestic values: Meanings of home for gay men and lesbians</article-title>. <source>Housing, Theory and Society</source> <volume>24</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>246</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herek</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Psychological heterosexism in the United States</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>D’Augelli</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Lesbian, Gay and Bisexual Identities over the Lifespan: Psychological Perspectives</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>321</fpage>–<lpage>346</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hinsch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <source>Passions of the Cut Sleeve: The Male Homosexual Tradition in China</source>, <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>HKSAR (2011) Policy address. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.policyaddress.gov.hk">http://www.policyaddress.gov.hk</ext-link> (accessed 28 September 2012)</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Ho PSY (1997) <italic>Politicising identity: Decriminalisation of homosexuality and the emergence of gay identity in Hong Kong</italic>. Unpublished PhD thesis, University of Essex, UK</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Hong Kong Government</collab> (<year>1947</year>) <source>Annual Report on Hong Kong for the Year 1946</source>, <publisher-loc>Hong Kong</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Government Printer</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><collab>Hong Kong Government</collab> (<year>1952</year>) <source>Hong Kong Annual Report 1951</source>, <publisher-loc>Hong Kong</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Government Printer</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Sex zones: Intimacy, citizenship and public space</article-title>. <source>Sexualities</source> <volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Ingram</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouthillette</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Retter</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Queers in Space: Communities/Public Places/Sites of Resistance</source>, <publisher-loc>Washington DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bay Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeyasingham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Building heteronormativity: The social and material reconstruction of men’s public toilets as spaces of heterosexuality</article-title>. <source>Social &amp; Cultural Geography</source> <volume>11</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>325</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Valentine</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Wherever I lay my girlfriend, that’s my home: The performance and surveillance of lesbian identities in domestic environments</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Valentine</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Mapping Desire: Geographies of Sexualities</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pugh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Ageing gay man: Lessons from the sociology of embodiment</article-title>. <source>Men and Masculinities</source> <volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>248</fpage>–<lpage>260</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>WQ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Obsession: Male Same-Sex Relations in China, 1900–1950</source>, <publisher-loc>Hong Kong</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hong Kong University Press (Queer Asia Series)</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>TSK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>The Chinese Male Homosexualities: Memba, Tongzhi and Golden Boy</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Bachelor farmers and spinsters: Gay and lesbian identities and communities in rural North Dakota</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Valentine</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Mapping Desire: Geographies of Sexualities</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>200</fpage>–<lpage>213</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1982</year>) <source>Society and Politics in Hong Kong</source>, <publisher-loc>Hong Kong</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Chinese University of Hong Kong</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Managerializing colonialism</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Trajectories: Inter-Asia Cultural Studies</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>121</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lethbridge</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>The quare fellow: Homosexuality and the law in Hong Kong</article-title>. <source>Hong Kong Law Journal</source> <volume>6</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>292</fpage>–<lpage>326</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>HHS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Undercurrents: Queer Culture and Postcolonial Hong Kong</source>, <publisher-loc>Hong Kong</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hong Kong University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>Gay ghetto</article-title>. <source>Journal of Homosexuality</source> <volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>363</fpage>–<lpage>377</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Where love dares (not) speak its name: The expression of homosexuality in Singapore</article-title>. <source>Urban Studies</source> <volume>41</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>1759</fpage>–<lpage>1788</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Louie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Theorising Chinese Masculinity: Society and Gender in China</source>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Louie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Chinese, Japanese and global masculine identities</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Louie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Asian Masculinities: The Meaning and Practice of Manhood in China and Japan</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>RoutledgeCurzon</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>From citizenship to queer counterpublic: Reading Taipei’s New Park</article-title>. <source>Communal/Plural</source> <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <source>Out of the Past: Gay and Lesbian History from 1869 to the Present</source>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Vintage</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>On the edge of empires: Flexible citizenship among Chinese in diaspora</article-title>. <source>positions: east asia culture critiques</source> <volume>1</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>745</fpage>–<lpage>778</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oswin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Critical geographies and the uses of sexuality: Deconstructing queer space</article-title>. <source>Progress in Human Geography</source> <volume>32</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>103</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pain</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mowl</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Talbot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Difference and the negotiation of ‘old age’</article-title>. <source>Environment and Planning D: Society and Space</source> <volume>18</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>393</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plummer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Speaking its name: Inventing a lesbian and gay studies</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Plummer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Modern Homosexualities: Fragments of Lesbian and Gay Experience</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plummer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Generational sexualities, subterranean traditions, and the hauntings of the sexual world: Some preliminary remarks</article-title>. <source>Symbolic Interaction</source> <volume>33</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>163</fpage>–<lpage>190</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>A transnational feminist critique of queer tourism</article-title>. <source>Antipode</source> <volume>34</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>935</fpage>–<lpage>946</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>Compulsory heterosexuality and lesbian existence</article-title>. <source>Signs</source> <volume>5</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>631</fpage>–<lpage>660</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Extending citizenship: Cultural citizenship and sexuality</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>Culture and Citizenship</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>153</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rooney</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>At Home with Density</source>, <publisher-loc>Hong Kong</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hong Kong University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr59-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Male homosexuality in the traditional Chinese literature</article-title>. <source>Journal of Homosexuality</source> <volume>14</volume>(<issue>3–4</issue>): <fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr60-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salaff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>) <source>Working Daughters of Hong Kong: Filial Piety or Power in the Family?</source>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr61-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Samshasha (1997) <italic>Zhongguo tongxinglian shilu</italic> [History of Homosexuality in China]. Hong Kong: Rosa Winkel Press [Chinese]</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr62-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>The meaning of ‘home’ in contemporary English culture</article-title>. <source>Housing Studies</source> <volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>177</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr63-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seidman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Queer Theory/Sociology</source>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr64-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Somerville</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Homelessness and the meaning of home: Rooflessness or rootlessness?</article-title> <source>International Journal of Urban and Regional Research</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>529</fpage>–<lpage>539</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr65-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>The Fragile Scholar: Power and Masculinity in Chinese Culture</source>, <publisher-loc>Hong Kong</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hong Kong University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr66-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>DTS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Conditional Spaces: Hong Kong Lesbian Desires and Everyday Life</source>, <publisher-loc>Hong Kong</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hong Kong University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr67-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="other"><comment>Too WT (2007) <italic>A study of private/public space in Hong Kong</italic>. Unpublished PhD thesis, The University of Hong Kong</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr68-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valentine</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>(Hetero)sexing space: Lesbian perceptions and experiences of everyday spaces</article-title>. <source>Environment and Planning D: Society and Space</source> <volume>11</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>395</fpage>–<lpage>413</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr69-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valentine</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Queer bodies and the production of space</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Seidman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Handbook of Lesbian and Gay Studies</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>160</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr70-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1973</year>) <source>Society and the Healthy Homosexual</source>, <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Alyson Publications</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr71-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Hong Kong Murders</source>, <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr72-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whittle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Consuming differences: The collaboration of the gay body with the cultural state</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Whittle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.) <source>The Margins of the City: Gay Men’s Urban Lives</source>, <publisher-loc>Aldershot</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr73-1363460712459308"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woodhead</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>(<year>1995</year>) <article-title>‘Surveillant gays’: HIV, space and the constitution of identities</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Valentine</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (eds) <source>Mapping Desire: Geographies of Sexualities</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<bio>
<p><bold>Travis SK Kong</bold> obtained his PhD from the University of Essex in England and is currently an Associate Professor in Sociology at the University of Hong Kong. He currently teaches sexuality, queer theory, as well as media and cultural studies. His research interests are Chinese homosexuality and masculinity, prostitution in Hong Kong and China, and transnational Chinese sexuality. To date, his articles have appeared in books, encyclopedias, and journals (e.g. <italic>Body &amp; Society</italic>, <italic>Sexualities</italic>, <italic>Deviant Behavior</italic>, <italic>Gender, Work and Organization</italic>, <italic>AIDS Care, The Lancet</italic>)<italic>.</italic> He is the author of <italic>Chinese Male Homosexualities: Memba, Tongzhi and Golden Boy</italic> (2011, Routledge).</p></bio>
</back>
</article>