<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JCM</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjcm</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Composite Materials</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9983</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1530-793X</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0021998311434170</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0021998311434170</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A micromechanics-based mesomodel for unidirectional laminates in compression up to failure</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Feld</surname><given-names>Nicolas</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0021998311434170">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0021998311434170"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Allix</surname><given-names>Olivier</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0021998311434170">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Baranger</surname><given-names>Emmanuel</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0021998311434170">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Guimard</surname><given-names>Jean-Mathieu</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0021998311434170">3</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0021998311434170"><label>1</label>LMT-Cachan. PSA Peugeot-Citroën, Velizy Villacoublay, France</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0021998311434170"><label>2</label>LMT-Cachan, UniverSud Paris, Cachan, France</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0021998311434170"><label>3</label>EADS France, Innovation Works, Mechanical Modelling Team, Suresnes, France</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0021998311434170">Nicolas Feld, LMT-Cachan. PSA Peugeot-Citroën – DRD/DRIA/DSTF/MSMX/MCSP, VV1415, Route de Gisy, 78943 Velizy Villacoublay, France Email: <email>nicolas.feld@mpsa.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>46</volume>
<issue>23</issue>
<fpage>2893</fpage>
<lpage>2909</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This study introduces an enriched description of a mesomodel for laminates in compression. The improvements are based on previous micromechanical studies regarding failure by kinking under combined compression and shear. The homogenization of the micromechanical response is based on an equivalence in recoverable, stored, and dissipated energy. This leads to a modified constitutive relation at the mesoscale which is probabilistic, i.e., parametrized by a measure of the statistical fiber misalignment, and features a nonlinear elastic potential in compression. The identification procedure is precisely detailed and applied on a T300/BSL-914C UD ply. It is shown that, thanks to simple deterministic relations, the mesoscale constitutive behavior is able to closely represent the homogenized ply's response of the underlying microstructure.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Compressive failure</kwd>
<kwd>microbuckling</kwd>
<kwd>modeling</kwd>
<kwd>homogenization</kwd>
<kwd>fragmentation</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Industries wish to extend the use of long-fiber-reinforced composites in order to design structural components which could also act as shock-absorbers. In fact, several experimental studies have shown the ability of such structures to dissipate a large amount of energy when loaded in compression.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0021998311434170">1</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0021998311434170">2</xref> Nevertheless, this is not always the case and, under certain loads, such structures can also break in a brittle manner. The practical challenge is thus to be able to design robust crash-absorbers with appropriate triggers that insure a highly dissipative failure process for a variety of load paths. In the design process, one wishes to perform as much meaningful simulations as possible in order to limit the number of experimental tests. A requirement is therefore to introduce a reliable model that is able to reproduce the basic and local features of the main mechanisms of dissipation under combined compression and shear loads. Two main mechanisms are locally involved in the dissipation process.
<list id="list1-0021998311434170" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Delamination between the plies of the composite.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Fragmentation of the fibers in compression with induced matrix degradation.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>In the study carried out by Guimard et al.,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0021998311434170">3</xref> the rate-dependent behavior of a delamination cohesive zone model in dynamics was studied. This complementary paper is focused on the mesomodeling of the behavior of uni-directional (UD) plies up to failure under combined compressive and shear loads.</p>
<p>Material failure under compression-dominated loads is often due to the microbuckling of the fibers.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0021998311434170">4</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0021998311434170">5</xref> This phenomenon is favored by the induced matrix degradation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0021998311434170">6</xref> and is highly dependent on fiber misalignments.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0021998311434170">7</xref> This competition between geometrical and material instabilities causes the strains to ultimately localize into a characteristic volume of finite width, known as a kink-band. The kinking phenomenon is now well observed and understood: Many experimental studies have attested the influence of various parameters, including the intrinsic waviness of the fibers,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0021998311434170">8</xref><sup>–</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0021998311434170">10</xref> the level hydrostatic pressure,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0021998311434170">11</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0021998311434170">12</xref> the prescribed shear,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0021998311434170">13</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0021998311434170">14</xref> the material constituents and proportions,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0021998311434170">15</xref><sup>–</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0021998311434170">18</xref> and on a more structural level, the effects of thickness/size effects<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0021998311434170">19</xref><sup>–</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0021998311434170">21</xref> and notches/holes.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0021998311434170">22</xref><sup>–</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0021998311434170">24</xref></p>
<p>The situation is not the same with respect to a numerical model expected to deal with components or structural applications. The difficulty is mainly associated to the difference of scales between the basic phenomenon itself (fiber diameter δ<sub><italic>f</italic></sub>  ≃ 7 µm) and the structural components (several centimeters or larger). A possible way to overcome this problem is by bridging the scales through homogenization, with the main difficulty coming from the strong nonlinear effects implied in this case.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0021998311434170">25</xref> A recent review on nonlinear homogenization can be found in Castañeda et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0021998311434170">26</xref></p>
<p>The problem herein is conceptually close to those treated in Ladevèze and Lubineau,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0021998311434170">27</xref> Ladevèze et al.,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0021998311434170">28</xref> and Hild et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0021998311434170">29</xref> for instance. The principle is to seek an energy equivalence between the microstructure and a homogenized model whose expression along with the chosen variables (observable and internal) and their relations have to be identified.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0021998311434170">30</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0021998311434170">31</xref> The main interest of this approach is, when successful, to avoid relying on computational homogenization methods. These imply, on each elementary cell at each time step, to solve independent tangent problems, by averaging the evolution of the state of strains and stresses. These strategies differ mainly by the order of homogenization performed and include the FE2 method<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-0021998311434170">32</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-0021998311434170">33</xref> (first order) and the gradient-enhanced method<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0021998311434170">34</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-0021998311434170">35</xref> (second order). Furthermore, unless coupled with an adapted strategy, such approaches cannot be used when ‘hard’ localization occurs.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-0021998311434170">36</xref></p>
<p>In this study, we propose to enrich a mesoscale model<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0021998311434170">37</xref> with results obtained from a previously established microscopic theory.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0021998311434170">38</xref> As such, and since the microscopic phenomena involved are rather accurately described, the method proposed in Aravas et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0021998311434170">31</xref> is chosen for its simplicity. Also, the focus of the method on energy conservation is in agreement with the context of this study. As a matter of fact, absorbed energies are a critical criterion for the design of composite shock absorbers and the analysis of composite structures for which kinking is not the ultimate fracture process (e.g., quasi-static indentation).</p>
<p>The first part of this article briefly describes the micromodel used as a reference in this study. Its main characteristics, hypotheses, and results are reminded. Next, the ‘target’ mesomodel and its main existing properties are presented as well. The third section is dedicated to the homogenization strategy proposed in this study, preceded by a short literature survey on homogenization techniques for composite material modeling. Then, the identification procedure is applied to a T300/BSL-914C UD ply, and the possibilities and limits of the method are presented in the light of first results.</p>
<sec id="sec1-0021998311434170"><title>Microscopic theory</title>
<p>The micromodel herein used for the simulation of kinking has been originally proposed in Feld et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-0021998311434170">38</xref> Its main hypotheses and results and reminded here. It is a uniaxial microbuckling model based on Budiansky and Fleck's kinking theory,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-0021998311434170">39</xref><sup>–</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0021998311434170">41</xref> extended to multi-axial loads and with an elasto-plastic damageable constitutive behavior for the matrix. Such modifications allow to take into account the effect fiber/matrix debonding and matrix microcracking, which significantly reduce the energy absorbed during the failure process, and that of shear stresses, which are known to have a strong impact on material strength.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-0021998311434170">42</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0021998311434170">43</xref> Additional hypotheses include:
<list id="list2-0021998311434170" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>The representative volume element (RVE) is periodic along a β-inclined direction toward the transverse direction, β being the final angle of the kink-band.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The fibers are elastic, display a known initial waviness ω<sub>0</sub> (defined thereafter by its amplitude on half-wavelength ratio λ<sub>0</sub>), and an Euler–Bernoulli beam-like behavior.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The (thin) matrix has a nonlinear behavior which is driven by the kinematic of the fibers.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Buckling is linearized along the mode favored by the waviness shape (here, mode 1).</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The fibers break when a strain-driven brittle criterion is reached:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0021998311434170"><label>(1)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math1-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq1.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub> is the axial Young modulus of the ply, δ<sub><italic>f</italic></sub> the mean diameter of the fibers, and ω the fibers' rotation. This microscopic criterion – the same as for fiber breaking in tension – generally does not affect the mesoscopic material strength of the ply in compression.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-0021998311434170">44</xref> It does, however, impact the total absorbed energy and final kink-band size.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>This model has been used to simulate the response of a representative volume element Ω made of homogenized fiber–matrix material, loaded in compression σ<sub>11</sub> ≡ <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub>ε<sub>11</sub> and/or shear σ<sub>12</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0021998311434170">Figure 1</xref>). The studies performed have verified a number of existing results and provided the authors with several new ones.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-0021998311434170">45</xref> Those of interest for this study are reminded here.
<fig id="fig1-0021998311434170" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Draft of a RVE representing the material microstructure and loads.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-fig1.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>One important feature of the model is the introduction of an enriched nonlinear behavior for the matrix, featuring shear and transverse damage. It is a critical ingredient for a better prediction of compression strength and absorbed energies. With such modeling, the response of the microstructure to a compressive load displays a snap-back (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0021998311434170">Figure 2(a)</xref>) that requires a continuation method to be properly captured.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-0021998311434170">46</xref><sup>–</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-0021998311434170">48</xref> At the edges of the RVE, the strains can be split into two parts: a linear ‘bulk’ component ε<sub><italic>M</italic></sub> due to linear elastic compression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0021998311434170">Figure 2(b)</xref>); and a nonlinear ‘kinking’ component ε<sub><italic>m</italic></sub> that displays only a snap-through (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0021998311434170">Figure 2(c)</xref>). These verify the strain partition equation:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula2-0021998311434170"><label>(2)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math2-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula2-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq2.tif"/></disp-formula>
From now on, the focus is set on the nonlinear component. As expected from Argon,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0021998311434170">7</xref> fiber waviness strongly affects critical stresses. However, absorbed energies are found less dependent, with the same order of magnitude as scale effects,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-0021998311434170">49</xref> as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0021998311434170">Figure 3(a)</xref>. This can also be deduced from the constitutive response, in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0021998311434170">Figure 3(b)</xref>, which present a lower strength but also a less stiff post-peak behavior as fiber waviness increases. Fiber waviness also affects the initial tangent response, as indicated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0021998311434170">Table 1</xref>.
<fig id="fig2-0021998311434170" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>−σ<sub>11</sub> function of −ε<sub>11</sub> at the edges of a 105-µm wide kink-band, a waviness λ<sub>0</sub> = 0.01, and a shear load σ<sub>12</sub> = 0 MPa (left); linear elastic component (center); nonlinear component (right).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-fig2.tif"/></fig>
<fig id="fig3-0021998311434170" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Compressive stress and absorbed energies function of waviness λ<sub>0</sub> (left); stress–strain response of the microstructure for λ<sub>0</sub> = 0.004 − 0.0105 (right).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-fig3.tif"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="table1-0021998311434170" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Initial tangent <italic>moduli</italic> of the microstructure with or without the elastic part, for fiber waviness λ<sub>0</sub> = 0.001 − 0.01 and elastic modulus <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub> = 130 MPa</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-table1.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead>
<tr><th>λ<sub>0</sub></th>
<th>0.01</th>
<th>0.009</th>
<th>0.008</th>
<th>0.007</th>
<th>0.006</th>
<th>0.005</th>
<th>0.004</th>
<th>0.003</th>
<th>0.002</th>
<th>0.001</th></tr></thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><inline-formula id="ilm1-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math1-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (MPa)</td>
<td>1390</td>
<td>1670</td>
<td>2110</td>
<td>2760</td>
<td>3760</td>
<td>5410</td>
<td>8460</td>
<td>15,030</td>
<td>33,820</td>
<td>135,280</td></tr>
<tr>
<td><inline-formula id="ilm2-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math2-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (MPa)</td>
<td>119</td>
<td>121</td>
<td>123</td>
<td>124</td>
<td>126</td>
<td>127</td>
<td>128</td>
<td>129</td>
<td>129.5</td>
<td>129.9</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>If one considers that the largest relevant waviness (based on observation from Paluch<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0021998311434170">50</xref>) is precipitating failure, an elastoplastic material modeling leads to a significant overestimation of the critical stresses in a compression–shear plane.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-0021998311434170">41</xref> However, with a material modeling taking damage into account, a reasonable correlation between experimental and numerical tests is obtained (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0021998311434170">Figure 4(a)</xref> and other tests by Jelf and Fleck,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0021998311434170">13</xref> Vogler et al.,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0021998311434170">14</xref> Vogler and Kyriakides,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-0021998311434170">43</xref> Allix et al.,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0021998311434170">51</xref> and Hinton et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-0021998311434170">52</xref>). The constitutive response, in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0021998311434170">Figure 4(b)</xref>, presents a lower strength and a slightly smoother peak as shear pre-stress increases.
<fig id="fig4-0021998311434170" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Compression/shear failure plane of a T300/BSL-914C ply with (gray) and without (black) damage (left); stress–strain response of the microstructure under mixed loads (right).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-fig4.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>In order to decide whether the homogenized model should be deterministic or probabilistic, simple numerical test cases have been performed. The numerical setup consists in a unidimensional structure loaded in compression. It is discretized with finite elements of length 105 µm (the size of a kink-band) and obeys to a simplified constitutive law that depends directly on fiber waviness (distributed using statistics from Paluch<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-0021998311434170">50</xref>). The results of the test cases, displayed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0021998311434170">Table 2</xref>, imply that centimeter-long samples are still sensitive to waviness distributions. Since the comparison with experimental results is expected to involve 10-mm long samples, the fiber waviness should be a probabilistic parameter of the homogenized model.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-0021998311434170">53</xref>
<table-wrap id="table2-0021998311434170" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Average and standard deviation of failure stress depending on the structure's length</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-table2.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Specimen length (mm)</td>
<td>1.05</td>
<td>2.1</td>
<td>5.25</td>
<td>10.5</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>52.5</td>
<td>105</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Average Strength (MPa)</td>
<td>2150</td>
<td>1750</td>
<td>1650</td>
<td>1600</td>
<td>1570</td>
<td>1540</td>
<td>1500</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Standard Deviation (MPa)</td>
<td>243</td>
<td>221</td>
<td>182</td>
<td>151</td>
<td>105</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>18</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
<p>All these observations need to be taken into account at mesoscale, which implies a probabilistic model with respect to fiber waviness, a strong coupling with shear under mixed loads, and a nonlinear behavior that takes into account the loss of stiffness, the irreversible strains, and the nonlinear elasticity from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0021998311434170">Figure 2(c)</xref>. The nature of the laws and couplings introduced will depend strongly on the target mesomodel of this study, which is described in the following section.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec2-0021998311434170"><title>Mesomodel fundamentals</title>
<p>In order to perform comparisons between virtual and experimental tests, we wish to include the data provided by this micromodel into a higher scale model: the damage mesomodel for laminates developed at the LMT-Cachan (further referenced shortly as <italic>mesomodel</italic>). It has been introduced in its ‘standard’ version in Ladevèze,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-0021998311434170">37</xref> Allix and Ladevèze,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0021998311434170">54</xref> and Ladevèze and Le Dantec,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0021998311434170">55</xref> and is based on two fundamental hypotheses:
<list id="list3-0021998311434170" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>A laminate's behavior can be derived from that of its elementary constituents: namely, the plies and their interfaces (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0021998311434170">Figure 5</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0021998311434170">1</xref></sup>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0021998311434170"><p><sup>1</sup>In the following, only the ply's behavior will be studied. For more details about the interfaces' behavior, please refer to Allix and Ladevèze,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-0021998311434170">54</xref> Allix et al.,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-0021998311434170">56</xref> Allix and Blanchard,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-0021998311434170">57</xref> and Guimard et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-0021998311434170">58</xref>.</p></fn></p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The degradation state of each ply is constant through-the-thickness.</p></list-item>
</list>
<fig id="fig5-0021998311434170" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Destructuration of a laminate into plies and interfaces.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-fig5.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The degradation state is described using damage variables, each of them being associated with an elementary degradation phenomenon:
<list id="list4-0021998311434170" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p><italic>d</italic> is the influence of diffuse damage due to fiber–matrix debonding and micro-cracking on shear;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>d</italic>′ the influence of the same phenomena on transverse tension; and</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>d</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub> the binary damage representing brittle fiber fracture.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>Let us note: (1) the ideal direction of the fibers, (2) the transverse in-plane direction, and (3) the transverse out-of-plane direction. The plies are transverse isotropic along direction 1. Let us also note σ<sub><italic>ij</italic></sub> the components of the Cauchy stress tensor and <inline-formula id="ilm3-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math3-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="ilm4-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math4-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ij</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula id="ilm5-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math5-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ij</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the undamaged elastic <italic>moduli</italic> and Poisson ratios of the ply. The in-plane specific energy of the ply reads:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula3-0021998311434170"><label>(3)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math3-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable align="right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1 2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>á</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>ñ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>á</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>ñ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>21</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>á</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>ñ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow/></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>á</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>ñ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula3-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq3.tif"/></disp-formula>
with &lt;•&gt; the <italic>positive part</italic> function and <inline-formula id="ilm6-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math6-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> an internal variable describing isotropic inelasticity. The full details of the mesomodel, including damageable and inelastic behavior, are reminded in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec7-0021998311434170">Appendix 1</xref>.</p>
<p>The function <italic>e</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> affects the axial compressive behavior. It has been experimentally identified as a nonlinear elastic form (quadratic with respect to compressive strains) followed by brittle failure in Allix and Ladevèze<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0021998311434170">51</xref> for several composite materials. Here, the aim is to use homogenization to achieve a better approximation of the behavior and dissipated energy up to and beyond the ultimate stress, including when significant shear makes the failure non brittle. The enrichment is expected to replace the function <italic>e</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> and affect the evolution of other internal variables (<italic>d</italic>, <inline-formula id="ilm7-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math7-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, etc.).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec3-0021998311434170"><title>Homogenization strategy</title>
<sec id="sec4-0021998311434170"><title>Homogenization techniques for material modeling</title>
<p>Homogenization techniques have been used for many years as a modeling tool for increasingly complex microstructures. The objective is always the extraction of the minimum amount of relevant information for the modeling of the material at a higher scale. Many theories of continuum materials, particularly when they introduce internal variables,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0021998311434170">59</xref> are based on or can be explained with homogenization, provided the microstructure is well known.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-0021998311434170">60</xref> Due to their highly heterogeneous nature and rather periodic microstructure, nonlinear composites have motivated their share in terms of homogenization studies (starting with Hill's<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-0021998311434170">61</xref>).</p>
<p>Most homogenization techniques put an emphasis on respecting one, several, or preferably all the following energies: the directly recoverable elastic energy, the energy stored inside the material (as residual self-equilibrated stress and compatible strain fields), and the energy dissipated in heat. To represent the variations of these energies, when they exist, internal variables can be introduced: inelasticity is linked to dissipated and sometimes stored energies; while damage is rather linked to an evolution of elastic and dissipated energies. Energy storage is known to be induced by material heterogeneity, which may cause dislocation forests in metals or slip-and-grip situations in other materials, such as rocks or composites. Loss of elastic energy is generally associated with growing or multiplying cracks in the microstructure, which are also favored by material heterogeneity.</p>
<p>Early studies regarding energy storage are due to Taylor and Quinney,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-0021998311434170">62</xref> who investigated the ‘cold work’ of metals. Various experimental techniques have been applied to metals and polymers using this approach to investigate the amount of stored energy.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-0021998311434170">63</xref> The extension to cracked materials, such as concrete and rocks, involving contact with friction is more recent.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0021998311434170">30</xref> In Aravas et al.,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0021998311434170">31</xref> detailed a simple theoretical procedure for recovering the stored energy in a more general case, but only applied it in one dimension. More recently, several authors have extended the basic theories and methods previously proposed to the case of brittle or quasi-brittle materials in two dimensions.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0021998311434170">29</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-0021998311434170">64</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-0021998311434170">65</xref></p>
<p>In Vivier et al.,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-0021998311434170">66</xref> such a strategy has been applied to a numerical test case – as opposed to strictly experimental measurements – in order to validate the approach. Similar procedures have been applied to composite micro-cracked elementary cells,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0021998311434170">27</xref> but only in terms of damage. Finally, Schapery<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-0021998311434170">67</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-0021998311434170">68</xref> has applied a similar strategy to his own visco-elastic kinking theory with matrix cracking in finite strains. The resulting mesoscale model is able to represent the buckling instability with a rather coarse mesh, adapted to mesoscale simulations, using the Abaqus software.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-0021998311434170">69</xref> This strategy has also been successfully adapted to woven laminates, in a finite strains model written at the scale of the tows.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-0021998311434170">70</xref></p>
<p>The micromodel of interest in this study features small strains but large deflexions, damageable elastic-plastic material models, and probabilistic geometrical parameters. It does not feature explicit cracks and/or contact with friction, although more detailed models could. The approach introduced in Aravas et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0021998311434170">31</xref> is therefore adapted to the case at hand, and as will be shown in the following sections, similar equivalences can be written.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec5-0021998311434170"><title>Main hypotheses</title>
<p>The aim of this study is to extract from a <italic>micromodel</italic> relevant homogenized data in order to feed a <italic>mesomodel</italic>. The RVE to be homogenized is the volume of material inside the final kink-band. This choice is motivated by the fact that, during compressive loading, approximately 95% of the energies are concentrated inside the kink-band. This choice of RVE is compatible and may be combined with the one used for the micro–meso bridge for transverse cracking<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0021998311434170">28</xref> in a three-dimensional RVE with large displacements. Let us consider a homogenized mesoscale material in a continuum thermodynamics framework with isothermal transformations and no initial stresses.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-0021998311434170">71</xref> In order to bind its thermodynamics to that of the microstructure, energy equivalences similar to those postulated in Aravas et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0021998311434170">31</xref> are considered: <italic>The recoverable part of the specific energy</italic> Ψ<sup><italic>e</italic></sup>, <italic>the stored part of the specific energy</italic> Ψ<sup><italic>p</italic></sup>, <italic>and the dissipated specific power</italic> Φ <italic>are all respected</italic>:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula4-0021998311434170"><label>(4)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math4-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable align="right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mi>      </mml:mi><mml:mtext>and</mml:mtext><mml:mi>      </mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Ψ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>Ω</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Ω</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Ψ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>μ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mo>Ω</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>   </mml:mi><mml:mtext>and</mml:mtext><mml:mo>Φ</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>Ω</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Ω</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>Φ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>μ</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mo>Ω</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula4-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq4.tif"/></disp-formula>
where .<sub>μ</sub> discriminates a microscopic variable; <inline-formula id="ilm8-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math8-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="ilm9-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math9-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and Φ<sub>μ</sub> are computed inside the RVE Ω using the micromodel as a virtual test sample.</p>
<p>Since the enrichment proposed here deals with axial compression, possibly mixed with shear, only these two loading directions are concerned by this homogenization procedure. The observable variables are the mesostresses in compression σ<sub>11</sub> and shear σ<sub>12</sub>, and the mesostrains in compression ε<sub>11</sub> and shear γ<sub>12</sub>. In order to define which internal variables must complement the observable ones, the micromodel is loaded in pure compression following a cycled path. The results are the one plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0021998311434170">Figure 2</xref>. The last curve presents several types of nonlinearities:
<list id="list5-0021998311434170" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>A loss of stiffness, which can be linked to a damage variable <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Residual strains, which can be linked to inelastic strains <inline-formula id="ilm10-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math10-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Nonlinear unloading paths.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>Each of these nonlinearities requires dedicated modeling and identification. However, not all of them are necessarily linked to an internal variable. For instance, a close examination of energies during decreasing loads indicates that they are indeed elastic, which indicates that they derive from local geometric nonlinearities. Hence, the specific energy potential of the mesoscale material:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula5-0021998311434170"><label>(5)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math5-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:munder><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">D</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula5-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq5.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <bold>D</bold> is a fourth-order damage tensor including <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub>. If we consider that the model features isotropic inelasticity driven by a single effective variable <inline-formula id="ilm11-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math11-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and that the strain partition hypothesis holds, it reads:<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0021998311434170">59</xref>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula6-0021998311434170"><label>(6)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math6-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:munder><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">D</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula6-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq6.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>Since the potential depends on several observable and internal variables that evolve with the load parameter (<inline-formula id="ilm12-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math12-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), partial derivatives cannot always be computed. As for experimental identification procedures,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0021998311434170">29</xref> we rely on unloading paths, where:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula7-0021998311434170"><label>(7)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math7-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:munder><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula7-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq7.tif"/></disp-formula>
and where Ψ<sup><italic>p</italic></sup> can be directly measured when Ψ<sup><italic>e</italic></sup> = 0.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec6-0021998311434170"><title>Mesomodel improvement</title>
<p>The axial component of the elastic potential <inline-formula id="ilm13-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math13-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is obtained by postulating a simplified form of the fibrous microstructure, similar to that of early kink-band models for anisotropic rocks.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-0021998311434170">72</xref> This rheological model introduces a similar nonlinearity – through the angle α – while remaining a very simple system with 1 degree of freedom (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0021998311434170">Figure 6</xref>).
<fig id="fig6-0021998311434170" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Rheological draft illustrating the nonlinearity between σ<sub>11</sub> and ε<sub>11</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-fig6.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The observable variables are σ<sub>11</sub> and ε<sub>11</sub>. Now let us define the potential associated with this rheological model based on its elementary parts. The recoverable elastic energy reads:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula8-0021998311434170"><label>(8)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math8-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula8-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq8.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>k</italic> is the stiffness of the ‘spring’ and σ<sub><italic>r</italic></sub> the backstress inside it. The momentum equilibrium of the rheological model reads:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula9-0021998311434170"><label>(9)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math9-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>tan</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula9-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq9.tif"/></disp-formula>
where α is the rotation of the rheological model, with a value of α<sub>0</sub> when no tension is involved. It is shown in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec8-0021998311434170">Appendix 2</xref> that, for a given state of internal variables, α can be approximated as a nonlinear function of σ<sub>11</sub> only:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula10-0021998311434170"><label>(10)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math10-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>tan</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula10-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq10.tif"/></disp-formula>
So, that on each unloading path, the elastic energy of the model reads:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula11-0021998311434170"><label>(11)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math11-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula11-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq11.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>This nonlinear elastic potential is convex but non-symmetric with respect to σ<sub>11</sub>, as can be seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0021998311434170">Figure 7</xref>. It also yields:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula12-0021998311434170"><label>(12)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math12-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula12-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq12.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula13-0021998311434170"><label>(13)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math13-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable align="right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">︷</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula13-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq13.tif"/></disp-formula>
<fig id="fig7-0021998311434170" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Elastic potential Ψ<sup><italic>e</italic></sup> as a function of the longitudinal stress σ<sub>11</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-fig7.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>In the way the rheological model was defined, <italic>k</italic> plays a similar role as the matrix in the micromodel. Consequently, all material nonlinearities are associated with <italic>k</italic>. The outcome of such a choice, although not obvious yet, is that their evolutions will remain independent of the fiber waviness λ<sub>0</sub>, which is a probabilistic parameter. This is not the case if material nonlinearities rather affect <italic>E</italic><sub>1</sub>. Consequently, the kinking damage <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> is defined such that <italic>k</italic> = <italic>k</italic><sup>0</sup>(1 − <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub>), and the total and inelastic strains ε<sub><italic>r</italic></sub> and <inline-formula id="ilm14-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math14-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, respectively, are defined such that <inline-formula id="ilm15-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math15-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec8-0021998311434170">Appendix 2</xref> for more details). Therefore, Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula8-0021998311434170">8</xref>) also reads:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula14-0021998311434170"><label>(14)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math14-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula14-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq14.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>This form can be introduced in the expression of the in-plane specific energy of the ply.
<disp-formula id="disp-formula15-0021998311434170"><label>(15)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math15-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable align="right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>21</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>á</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>ñ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>á</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>ñ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula15-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq15.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>The thermodynamic force associated with kinking damage <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> is introduced as:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula16-0021998311434170"><label>(16)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math16-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula16-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq16.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
<p>This additional degradation mechanism is intrinsically linked to diffuse damage, since the latter develops in the micromodel during kinking. Therefore, the driving force of kinking damage, <italic>Y</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub>, should involve both <italic>Y</italic><sub><italic>r</italic></sub> and <italic>Y</italic><sub><italic>d</italic></sub>, while the driving force of diffuse damage, <italic>Y</italic>, may need to be adjusted in order to take into account the effect of compression (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec7-0021998311434170">Appendix 1</xref>). No interactions are considered between <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> and <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>f</italic></sub> in this study.</p>
<p>Similarly, <inline-formula id="ilm16-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math16-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is supposed to be driven by the same inelastic process as the rest of the mesomodel, a strong hypothesis that will require verification. Consequently, the least intrusive modification to make would be in the definition of the equivalent stress <inline-formula id="ilm17-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math17-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>eq</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec7-0021998311434170">Appendix 1</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec7-0021998311434170"><title>Numerical identification procedure</title>
<p>These unknowns and hypotheses call for an identification procedure in two steps:
<list id="list6-0021998311434170" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>First, the elastic nonlinearities are identified on small mixed loads using a minimization technique between the response of the micromodel and the form chosen above. The parameters <italic>k</italic><sup>0</sup> and α<sub>0</sub> are identified. This step is repeated for several fiber waviness values, which are presumed to impact the value of α<sub>0</sub> only.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Then, the material nonlinear variables are identified along mixed paths featuring several unloadings. The recoverable energy can be computed on each unloading path, while the stored energy is computed each time the elastic energy drops to zero. The evolution law of <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> as a function of <italic>Y</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub>, and the (updated) expressions of <italic>Y</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub>, <italic>Y</italic>, and <inline-formula id="ilm18-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math18-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>eq</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are identified. This step does not need to be repeated for several fiber waviness values, since their effect has been taken into account already. However, it will be done in this article in order to prove this hypothesis.</p></list-item>
</list></p>
<p>A few limitations of this procedure must be highlighted here. Due to the fundamentally unsymmetrical nature of buckling, mesoscopic shear loads lead to mesoscopic – and not only compatible <italic>microscopic</italic> – shear strains. However, this distortion is not taken into account as a first approximation. Only the degradation of the microstructure is of interest. Also, the consistency of the method can be discussed when strong transformation gradients are involved (e.g. close to the edges).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-0021998311434170">34</xref> Finally, a characteristic length (the scale of the kink-band) has been introduced into a model which already presents another (the thickness of the plies) of the same order of magnitude (<italic>w</italic><sub><italic>kb</italic></sub> ≃ 0.105 mm and <italic>w</italic><sub><italic>ply</italic></sub> ≃ 0.125 mm). Consequently, none of the possible and likely interactions between kinking and thickness effects (e.g. out-of-plane buckling or through-the-thickness kink-band growth) will be captured.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-0021998311434170">73</xref></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec8-0021998311434170"><title>Identification of a T300/BSL-914C UD ply</title>
<p>The kink-band size <italic>w</italic><sub><italic>kb</italic></sub> is taken equal to 105 µm from now on. Since <italic>k</italic><sup>0</sup> represents some kind of material property while α<sub>0</sub> is rather linked to geometric considerations (the initial fiber waviness and a possible additional misalignment with the far-field compressive load due to shear), all statistical variations are supposed to affect only the latter. After minimising the difference between the responses of the micromodel and the approximated law on a surface for values of λ<sub>0</sub> varying from 0.01 to 0.0025 and values of σ<sub>12</sub> ranging from 0 to 40 MPa, we found:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula17-0021998311434170"><label>(17)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math17-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>18</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>360</mml:mn><mml:mtext>MPa</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula17-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq17.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula18-0021998311434170"><label>(18)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math18-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula18-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq18.tif"/></disp-formula>
with <italic>c</italic><sub>α</sub> = 12.4 rd and <italic>c</italic><sub>γ</sub> = 1.07 rd. The projections of the surface of response along (λ<sub>0</sub>, α<sub>0</sub>) and (σ<sub>12</sub>, α<sub>0</sub>) are plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0021998311434170">Figure 8(a) and (b)</xref>, respectively.
<fig id="fig8-0021998311434170" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>α<sub>0</sub> function of λ<sub>0</sub> (left) and σ<sub>12</sub> (right).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-fig8.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The quality of the approximation of the elastic nonlinearities can be measured under compressive loads in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0021998311434170">Figure 9</xref>, which displays three responses for various values of λ<sub>0</sub>. According to their trends, the approximation is particularly good for small loads, which corresponds to the elastic regime of the structure. When loads grow larger, the quality of the approximation worsens, but by then the material nonlinearities will already change the response significantly. Besides, the approximation is most accurate for the highest values of λ<sub>0</sub>, which are precisely the waviness values for which localization – and consequently the highest strains – are expected to occur
<fig id="fig9-0021998311434170" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Responses of the <italic>elastic</italic> microstructure and approximated law for λ<sub>0</sub> = 0.001 − 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-fig9.tif"/></fig>
</p>
<p>The identification of the damage evolution law is first performed without shear loads and considering <italic>Y</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> = <italic>Y</italic><sub><italic>r</italic></sub>. By loading/unloading increasingly the microstructure, the partial derivative of the elastic energy can be computed on each unloading path and the damage value can be deduced knowing the undamaged <italic>moduli</italic>. The results of such a procedure are plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0021998311434170">Figure 10(a)</xref>, in terms of damage variable against thermodynamic force. The identification has been repeated for various values of λ<sub>0</sub> and, as expected, the results seem rather insensitive. The form of law is relatively simple until <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> ≃ 0.3 and reads:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula19-0021998311434170"><label>(19)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math19-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>sup</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula19-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq19.tif"/></disp-formula>
with <italic>Y</italic><sub>κ</sub> = 11.8 MPa. A simple power law can be used when <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> &gt; 0.3, but the rather brutal change in behavior might also indicate a transition between pre-buckling and post-buckling damage development, which has not been investigated more in depth yet.
<fig id="fig10-0021998311434170" position="float"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p><italic>d</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> function of <italic>Y</italic><sub><italic>r</italic></sub> = <italic>Y</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> for λ<sub>0</sub> = 0.01, 0.0075, 0.005, and 0.0025 (left); <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> function of <italic>Y</italic><sub><italic>r</italic></sub> for σ<sub>12</sub> = 10, 20, 30, and 40 MPa (right).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-fig10.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>Once the law is defined, the expression of its driving force under mixed loads remains to be identified. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0021998311434170">Figure 10(b)</xref> suggests the following relation:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula20-0021998311434170"><label>(20)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math20-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula20-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq20.tif"/></disp-formula>
with <italic>b</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub> = 8.</p>
<p>The same holds for <italic>d</italic>. One can verify that, without compressive stresses, the mesoscopic law linking <italic>Y</italic><sub><italic>d</italic></sub> to <italic>d</italic> is exactly the same as the one defined for the material constituents of the micromodel in pure shear (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0021998311434170">Figure 11(a)</xref>). This law has been chosen compatible with the mesomodel on purpose, in order to be identified on standard ±45° tensile tests. Under mixed loads, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0021998311434170">Figure 11(b)</xref> suggests the following coupled form for <italic>Y</italic>:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula21-0021998311434170"><label>(21)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math21-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula21-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq21.tif"/></disp-formula>
with <italic>b</italic><sub><italic>r</italic></sub> = 0.12.
<fig id="fig11-0021998311434170" position="float"><label>Figure 11.</label><caption><p><italic>d</italic> function of <inline-formula id="ilm19-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math19-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as in the mesomodel (left); <italic>d</italic> function of <inline-formula id="ilm20-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math20-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for σ<sub>11</sub> = 0, 100, 200, and 300 MPa (right).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-fig11.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>Once the elastic and damageable components are known, under the strain partition hypothesis, the stored and dissipated energies of the model can be directly identified using the relations <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="disp-formula4-0021998311434170">4</xref>, although their form is relatively constrained due to the hypotheses made earlier. The results in terms of an equivalent <inline-formula id="ilm21-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math21-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>eq</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> stress are plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0021998311434170">Figure 12(a)</xref>. As expected, they are rather unaffected by fiber waviness. The evolution presents an unusual shape that can be approximated with the following equivalent stress:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula22-0021998311434170"><label>(22)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math22-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>eq</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>23</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>31</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>33</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula22-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq22.tif"/></disp-formula>
with <italic>a</italic><sub><italic>r</italic></sub> = 0.25, until an inelasticity saturation threshold is reached:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula23-0021998311434170"><label>(23)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math23-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>·</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mtext>when</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>σ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>σ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>T</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula23-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq23.tif"/></disp-formula>
with σ<sub><italic>T</italic></sub> = 95 MPa. Such a form also reproduces mixed loads where compression is predominant. The threshold then shifts to higher values of <inline-formula id="ilm22-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math22-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>eq</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, since it only depends on σ<sub><italic>r</italic></sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig12-0021998311434170">Figure 12(b)</xref>).
<fig id="fig12-0021998311434170" position="float"><label>Figure 12.</label><caption><p><inline-formula id="ilm23-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math23-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>eq</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> function of <inline-formula id="ilm24-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math24-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for λ<sub>0</sub> = 0.01, 0.0075, 0.005, and 0.0025 (left); and for σ<sub>12</sub> = 0, 10, 20, 30, and 40 MPa (right).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-fig12.tif"/></fig></p>
<p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig13-0021998311434170">Figure 13</xref> also reveals a good reproduction of mixed loads with predominant shear, for which the saturation threshold is never reached. Consequently, the hypothesis of ‘kinking-driven’ inelasticity following the same process as the rest of the mesomodel is verified. The only unexpected ingredient is the inelasticity threshold, but since its criterion is strictly compression-driven, it does not change standard results in other directions.
<fig id="fig13-0021998311434170" position="float"><label>Figure 13.</label><caption><p><inline-formula id="ilm25-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math25-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>eq</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> function of <inline-formula id="ilm26-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math26-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for σ<sub>11</sub> = 0, 100, 200, and 300 MPa.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-fig13.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>The value of each new parameter introduced by this procedure is reminded in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0021998311434170">Table 3</xref>. The validity of all these expressions for large multi-axial loads is subject to caution.
<table-wrap id="table3-0021998311434170" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Summary of the new parameters and values identified with this procedure</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-table3.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides"><thead>
<tr><th>Material parameter</th>
<th>Symbol</th>
<th>Value</th>
<th>Unit</th></tr></thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Rheologic modulus</td>
<td><italic>k</italic><sup>0</sup></td>
<td>18,360</td>
<td>MPa</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Waviness multiplier</td>
<td><italic>c</italic><sub>α</sub></td>
<td>12.4</td>
<td>rd</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Rotation multiplier</td>
<td><italic>c</italic><sub>γ</sub></td>
<td>1.07</td>
<td>rd</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Kinking critical force</td>
<td><italic>Y</italic><sub>κ</sub></td>
<td>13.7</td>
<td>MPa</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Shear/kinking coupling</td>
<td><italic>b</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub></td>
<td>8</td>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Kinking/shear coupling</td>
<td><italic>b</italic><sub><italic>r</italic></sub></td>
<td>0.12</td>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Kinking inelastic coupling</td>
<td><italic>a</italic><sub><italic>r</italic></sub></td>
<td>0.25</td>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Inelastic threshold</td>
<td>σ<sub><italic>T</italic></sub></td>
<td>95</td>
<td>MPa</td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec9-0021998311434170" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title>
<p>With all necessary unknowns of the model identified (<italic>k</italic><sup>0</sup>, the expressions of α<sub>0</sub>, <italic>Y</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub>, <italic>Y</italic>, and <inline-formula id="ilm27-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math27-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>eq</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and the evolution of <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>k</italic></sub>), this method offers a good reproduction of the compressive behavior of the microstructure up to complete failure. It is worth highlighting that <italic>all</italic> the parameters introduced in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0021998311434170">Table 3</xref> are identified with the simple numerical simulations described in the previous sections. No additional experimental tests are required. Further, a number of these parameters may remain valid for any type of laminate, particularly those related to fiber waviness. As a matter of fact, the only information that requires actual experimental measurement is the statistical fiber waviness.</p>
<p>As <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14-0021998311434170">Figure 14(a)</xref> shows, the constitutive law reproduces accurately all the nonlinearities of the micromodel. The error in terms of stored and dissipated energies is of the order of magnitude of the percent. Further, the behavior of the mesomodel in other directions is not affected by the changes (unless when it should, such as when compression is involved). With the addition of the linear elastic component of the strains, the final response can be compared with the monotonic responses obtained by a nonlinear elastic model.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0021998311434170">51</xref> For instance, the compressive stiffness can be expressed as linearly depending on compressive strains using the following relation:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula24-0021998311434170"><label>(24)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math24-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula24-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq24.tif"/></disp-formula>
<fig id="fig14-0021998311434170" position="float"><label>Figure 14.</label><caption><p>Stress–strain constitutive response identified for λ<sub>0</sub> = 0.01 and σ<sub>12</sub> = 0 MPa at the edges of the kink-band (left); comparison of the global monotonic response with Allix et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-0021998311434170">51</xref></sup> (right).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-fig14.tif"/></fig></p>
<p>With a compressive modulus of <inline-formula id="ilm28-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math28-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>120</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> GPa and α<sub><italic>V</italic></sub> = 16 GPa/%, the monotonic responses correlate quite well (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig14-0021998311434170">Figure 14(b)</xref>), although Allix and Vittecoq rather found values of α<sub><italic>V</italic></sub> of 20 GPa/% and higher.</p>
<p>Results are less precise but still quite acceptable when straighter fibers and/or shear loads are involved, as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig15-0021998311434170">Figure 15</xref> show.
<fig id="fig15-0021998311434170" position="float"><label>Figure 15.</label><caption><p>Stress–strain constitutive response identified for λ<sub>0</sub> = 0.005 and σ<sub>12</sub> = 20 MPa (left); for λ<sub>0</sub> = 0.0025 and σ<sub>12</sub> = 30 MPa (right).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-fig15.tif"/></fig></p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec10-0021998311434170" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title>
<p>This article described a procedure to numerically extract an equivalent behavior for a UD laminate failing by kinking. This strategy requires the definition of a characteristic length, which is taken equal to the kink-band width, and of a constitutive model. This model is parametric, driven by the main statistical parameter of the microstructure: the fiber waviness. The development of damage and inelasticity due to compression loadings is taken into account through additional internal variables, and deterministic evolution laws are introduced. Finally, the interactions that naturally arise between compression and shear are also taken into account through coupling parameters. All these are numerically identified, based on energy conservation principles.</p>
<p>At last, the equivalent behavior identified by this procedure can be implemented in the damage mesomodel. The strategy itself is not limited to the material nor the models chosen in this article. As a matter of fact, further studies will focus on the implementation of this behavior in the framework of the <italic>hybrid</italic> model for laminates.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-0021998311434170">74</xref> This three-dimensional ply-scale model features discrete modeling of through-the-thickness cracking and localized delamination. One of the objectives is to perform simulation of plies or even stacks, in order to study the interactions between kinking and other failure modes, particularly splitting which is known to develop alongside kinking in some situations.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-0021998311434170">75</xref> This will also allow to perform structural simulations in a unified framework, compare the results with complex experimental tests,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0021998311434170">24</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-0021998311434170">76</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-0021998311434170">77</xref> and to investigate structural effects identified by other authors (e.g. thickness effects,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0021998311434170">19</xref> compressive stress gradients,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0021998311434170">21</xref> etc).</p>
<p>A few precautions have nevertheless to be taken for the numerical integration of the full constitutive response (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0021998311434170">Figure 2(a)</xref>). Indeed, because of the snap back, the solution of the constitutive law is not always unique for a given state of strains. In an implicit case, a combination of continuation algorithms may be used to follow the solution and the equilibrium path at all time.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-0021998311434170">78</xref> In an explicit framework, the least precaution to take is to accurately compute the released, stored, and dissipated energies during stress jumps.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<sec id="sec11-0021998311434170"><title>Funding</title>
<p>This study has been funded by ANR (Agence Nationale de la Recherche) <italic>VulComp</italic> Phase 1 project, under the grant ANR-2006-MAPR-0022-01.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec12-0021998311434170"><title>Conflict of interest</title>
<p>None declared.</p>
</sec>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickett</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozycki</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Computational methods for predicting impact damage in composite structures</article-title>. <source>Compos Sci Technol</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>2183</fpage>–<lpage>2192</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guillon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivallant</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrau</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Petiot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Thévenet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pechnik</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Étude des mécanismes d'absorption d'énergie dans les structures carbone-époxyde</article-title>. <source>In: Journées Nationales sur les Composites 15</source>. <comment>Paris, Pluralis, 2006, p. 8</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guimard</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Allix</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Pechnik</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Thévenet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization and modeling of rate effects in the dynamic propagation of mode-ii delamination in composite laminates</article-title>. <source>Int J Fract</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>160</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanics of composite strengthening</article-title>. <source>In: Fiber composite materials: papers presented at a seminar of the American Society for Metals, October 17 and 18, Metals Park, Ohio: American Society for Metals, 1964</source>. <comment>1965, pp. 37–75</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>On the shear instability of structures caused by compressive load</article-title>. <source>In: Aircraft design technical meeting</source>. <comment>Los Angeles, CA, 1965, pp. 566–580</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schuerch</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prediction of compression strength in uniaxial boron fiber-metal matrix composite materials</article-title>. <source>AIAA J</source> <year>1966</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>102</fpage>–<lpage>106</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Argon</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fracture of composites</article-title>. <source>In: Treatise on materials science and technology</source>. <comment>Vol. 1, 1972, pp. 79–114</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Piggott</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bainbridge</surname><given-names>DMR</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The compression strength of composites with kinked, misaligned and poorly adhering fibres</article-title>. <source>J Mat Sci</source> <year>1981</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>2831</fpage>–<lpage>2836</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piggott</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of fibre waviness on the mechanical properties of unidirectional fibre composites: a review</article-title>. <source>Compos Sci Technol</source> <year>1995</year>; <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>205</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wisnom</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Compressive failure due to shear instability: Experimental investigation of waviness and correlation with analysis</article-title>. <source>J Reinf Plast Compos</source> <year>1996</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>420</fpage>–<lpage>439</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Deformation of a carbon-epoxy composite under hydrostatic pressure</article-title>. <source>J Mater Sci</source> <year>1975</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1323</fpage>–<lpage>1333</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oguni</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravichandran</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Failure mode transition in unidirectional e-glass/vinylester composites under multiaxial compression</article-title>. <source>J Compos Mater</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>2081</fpage>–<lpage>2097</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jelf</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleck</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Compression failure mechanisms in unidirectional composites</article-title>. <source>J Compos Mater</source> <year>1992</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>2706</fpage>–<lpage>2706</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogler</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>S-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyriakides</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Composite failure under combined compression and shear</article-title>. <source>Int J Solids Struct</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>1765</fpage>–<lpage>1791</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piggott</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Compression strength of carbon, glass and kevlar-49 fibre-reinforced polyester resins</article-title>. <source>J Mater Sci</source> <year>1980</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>2523</fpage>–<lpage>2538</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sohi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>The effect of resin toughness and modulus on compressive failure modes of quasi-isotropic graphite/epoxy laminates</source> <publisher-name>Technical Memorandum 22647, NASA</publisher-name>, <year>1986</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Narayanan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schadler</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanisms of kink-band formation in graphite/epoxy composites: a micromechanical study</article-title>. <source>Compos Sci Technol</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>2201</fpage>–<lpage>2213</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yerramalli</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Waas</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A nondimensional number to classify composite compressive failure</article-title>. <source>J App Mech</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>402</fpage>–<lpage>409</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wisnom</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of specimen size on the bending strength of unidirectional carbon fibre-epoxy</article-title>. <source>Compos Struct</source> <year>1991</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>63</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Soutis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Thickness effect on the compressive strength of t800/924c carbon fibre-epoxy laminates</article-title>. <source>Composites Part A</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>227</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drapier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Grandidier</surname><given-names>J-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Potier-Ferry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A structural approach of plastic microbuckling in long fibre composites: comparison with theoretical and experimental results</article-title>. <source>Int J Solids Struct</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>3877</fpage>–<lpage>3904</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sivashanker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleck</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutcliffe</surname><given-names>MPF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Microbuckle propagation in a unidirectional carbon fibre-epoxy matrix composite</article-title>. <source>Acta Mater</source> <year>1996</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>2581</fpage>–<lpage>2590</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Soutis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Measuring the notched compressive strength of composite laminates: specimen size effects</article-title>. <source>Compos Sci Technol</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>2359</fpage>–<lpage>2359</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gutkin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinho</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>On the transition from sheardriven fibre compressive failure to fibre kinking in notched CFRP laminates under longitudinal compression</article-title>. <source>Compos Sci Technol</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>1223</fpage>–<lpage>1223</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nezamabadi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yvonnet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zahrouni</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Potier-Ferry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A multilevel computational strategy for handling microscopic and macroscopic instabilities</article-title>. <source>Comput Meth Appl Mech Eng</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>198</volume>: <fpage>2099</fpage>–<lpage>2110</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castañeda</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Telega</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gambin</surname><given-names>B</given-names><suffix>(eds)</suffix></name></person-group>. <source>Nonlinear homogenization and its applications to composites, polycrystals and smart materials</source>, <publisher-loc>Dodrecht/Boston</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher-name>, <year>2004</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ladevèze</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lubineau</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>An enhanced mesomodel for laminates based on micromechanics</article-title>. <source>Compos Sci Technol</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>533</fpage>–<lpage>541</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ladevèze</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lubineau</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Towards a bridge between the micro- and mesomechanics of delamination for laminated composites</article-title>. <source>Compos Sci Technol</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>698</fpage>–<lpage>712</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hild</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Burr</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Leckie</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Matrix cracking and debonding of ceramic-matrix composites</article-title>. <source>Int J Solids Struct</source> <year>1996</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>1209</fpage>–<lpage>1220</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrieux</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bamberger</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Marigo</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Un modèle de matériau microfissuré pour les bétons et les roches</article-title>. <source>J Méc Théor Appl</source> <year>1986</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>471</fpage>–<lpage>513</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aravas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Leckie</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>On the calculations of the stored energy of cold work</article-title>. <source>J Eng Mater Technol</source> <year>1990</year>; <volume>112</volume>: <fpage>465</fpage>–<lpage>470</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr32-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feyel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaboche</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fe2 multiscale approach for modelling the elastoviscoplastic behaviour of long fibre sic/ti composite materials</article-title>. <source>Comput Meth Appl Mech Eng</source> <year>2000</year>; <volume>183</volume>: <fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>330</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr33-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feyel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A multilevel finite element method (fe2) to describe the response of highly non-linear structures using generalized continua</article-title>. <source>Comput Meth Appl Mech Eng</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>192</volume>: <fpage>3233</fpage>–<lpage>3244</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr34-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kouznetsova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Geers</surname><given-names>MGD</given-names></name><name><surname>Brekelmans</surname><given-names>WAM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Multi-scale constitutive modelling of heterogeneous materials with a gradient-enhanced computational homogenization scheme</article-title>. <source>Int J Numer Meth Eng</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>1235</fpage>–<lpage>1260</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr35-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kouznetsova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Geers</surname><given-names>MWD</given-names></name><name><surname>Brekelmans</surname><given-names>WAM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Multi-scale secondorder computational homogenization of multi-phase materials: a nested finite element solution strategy</article-title>. <source>Comput Meth Appl Mech Eng</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>193</volume>: <fpage>5525</fpage>–<lpage>5550</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr36-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geers</surname><given-names>MGD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kouznetsova</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name><name><surname>Brekelmans</surname><given-names>WAM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Multi-scale computational homogenization: trends and challenges</article-title>. <source>J Comput Appl Math</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>234</volume>: <fpage>2175</fpage>–<lpage>2182</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr37-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ladevèze</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sur la mécanique de l'endommagement des composites</article-title>. <source>Comptes-rendus des Journées Nationales sur les Composites 5</source>. <comment>Paris, pp. 667–683, Pluralis</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr38-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feld</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Allix</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Baranger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Guimard</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Micro-mechanical prediction of UD laminates behaviour under combined compression up to failure: inuence of matrix degradation</article-title>. <source>J Compos Mater</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>2317</fpage>–<lpage>2333</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr39-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Budiansky</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleck</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Compressive failure of fiber composites</article-title>. <source>J Mech Phys Solids</source> <year>1993</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>183</fpage>–<lpage>211</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr40-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fleck</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Budiansky</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prediction of kink width in compressed fibre composites</article-title>. <source>J App Mech</source> <year>1995</year>; <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>329</fpage>–<lpage>337</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr41-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guimard</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Allix</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Pechnik</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Thévenet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Statistical energy and failure analysis of cfrp compression behavior using a uniaxial microbuckling model</article-title>. <source>J Compos Mater</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>2807</fpage>–<lpage>2828</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr42-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wisnom</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of shear stresses in indirect compression tests of unidirectional carbon fiber/epoxy</article-title>. <source>Am Inst Aeronaut Astronaut J</source> <year>1991</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1692</fpage>–<lpage>1697</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr43-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogler</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyriakides</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>On the initiation and growth of kink bands in fiber composites: Part i. experiments</article-title>. <source>Int J Solids Struct</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>2639</fpage>–<lpage>2682</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr44-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Budiansky</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleck</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Amazigo</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>On kink-band propagation in fiber composites</article-title>. <source>J Mech Phys Solids</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>1637</fpage>–<lpage>1653</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr45-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feld</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Allix</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Baranger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Techniques de modélisation de la fragmentation</source>. <comment>Rapport d'activité, ANR VulComp – Work Package 3.2, 2010</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr46-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wempner</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Discrete approximation related to nonlinear theories of solids</article-title>. <source>Int J Solids Struct</source> <year>1971</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>1581</fpage>–<lpage>1599</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr47-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riks</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The application of Newton's method to the problem of elastic stability</article-title>. <source>ASME Trans Ser E J Appl Mech</source> <year>1972</year>; <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>1060</fpage>–<lpage>1065</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr48-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crisfield</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A fast incremental/iterative solution procedure that handles “snapthrough”</article-title>. <source>Comput Struct</source> <year>1981</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>–<lpage>62</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr49-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Effendi</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrau</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guedra-Desgeorges</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Failure mechanism analysis under compression loading of unidirectional carbon/epoxy composites using micromechanical modelling</article-title>. <source>Compos Struct</source> <year>1995</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr50-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paluch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of geometric imperfections in fibres for unidirectional fibre-reinforced composites</article-title>. <source>La Recherche Aéronaut</source> <year>1994</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>431</fpage>–<lpage>448</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr51-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allix</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ladevèze</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vittecoq</surname> <given-names>É</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Modelling and identification of the mechanical behaviour of composite laminates in compression</article-title>. <source>Compos Sci Technol</source> <year>1994</year>; <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>42</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr52-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hinton</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaddour</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Soden</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Failure criteria in fibre reinforced polymer composites: the world-wide failure exercise</source> <publisher-name>Oxford: Elsevier Science</publisher-name>, <year>2004</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr53-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lamon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Mécanique de la rupture fragile et de l'endommagement: approches statistiques et probabilistes</source> <publisher-name>Études en mécanique des matériaux et des structures, Hermès-Lavoisier</publisher-name>, <year>2007</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr54-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allix</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ladevèze</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Interlaminar interface modelling for the prediction of delamination</article-title>. <source>Compos Struct</source> <year>1992</year>; <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>242</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr55-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ladevèze</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Dantec</surname> <given-names>É</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Damage modeling of the elementary ply for laminated composites</article-title>. <source>Compos Sci Technol</source> <year>1992</year>; <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>267</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr56-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allix</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Feissel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Thévenet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A delay damage mesomodel of laminates under dynamic loading: basic aspects and identification issues</article-title>. <source>Comput Struct</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>1177</fpage>–<lpage>1191</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr57-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allix</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mesomodeling of delamination: towards industrial applications</article-title>. <source>Compos Sci Technol</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>731</fpage>–<lpage>744</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr58-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guimard</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Allix</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Pechnik</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Thévenet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Energetic analysis of fragmentation mechanisms and dynamic delamination modelling in CFRP composites</article-title>. <source>Comput Struct</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>1022</fpage>–<lpage>1032</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr59-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lemaître</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaboche</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Mécanique des Matériaux Solides</source>. <comment>Paris: Dunod, 2nd edn., 1993</comment>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr60-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eshelby</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The determination of the elastic field of an ellipsoidal inclusion, and related problems</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc London Ser A, Math Phys Sci</source> <year>1957</year>; <volume>241</volume>: <fpage>376</fpage>–<lpage>396</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr61-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A self-consistent mechanics of composite materials</article-title>. <source>J Mech Phys Solids</source> <year>1965</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr62-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinney</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The latent energy remaining in a metal after cold working</article-title>. <source>Proc R Soc London Ser A, Math Phys Sci</source> <year>1934</year>; <volume>143</volume>: <fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>326</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr63-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Titchener</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bever</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The stored energy of cold work</article-title>. <source>Prog Metal Phys</source> <year>1958</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>247</fpage>–<lpage>338</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr64-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halm</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dragon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>An anisotropic model of damage and frictional sliding for brittle materials</article-title>. <source>Eur J Mech A Solids</source> <year>1998</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>439</fpage>–<lpage>460</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr65-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pensée</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dormieux</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Micromechanical analysis of anisotropic damage in brittle materials</article-title>. <source>J Eng Mech</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>128</volume>: <fpage>889</fpage>–<lpage>897</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr66-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vivier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Trumel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hild</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>On the stored and dissipated energies in heterogeneous rate-independent systems: theory and simple examples</article-title>. <source>Cont Mech Thermodyn</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>411</fpage>–<lpage>427</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr67-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schapery</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A theory of mechanical behavior of elastic media with growing damage and other changes in structure</article-title>. <source>J Mech Phys Solids</source> <year>1990</year>; <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>215</fpage>–<lpage>253</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr68-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schapery</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prediction of compressive strength and kink bands in composites using a work potential</article-title>. <source>Int J Solids Struct</source> <year>1995</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>739</fpage>–<lpage>765</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr69-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Violette</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Schapery</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Time-dependent compressive strength of unidirectional viscoelastic composite materials</article-title>. <source>Mech Time-Depend Mater</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr70-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Waas</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ambur</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Compressive failure of fiber composites under multi-axial loading</article-title>. <source>J Mech Phys Solids</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>611</fpage>–<lpage>611</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr71-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Germain</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>QS</given-names></name><name><surname>Suquet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Continuum thermodynamics</article-title>. <source>J App Mech</source> <year>1983</year>; <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1010</fpage>–<lpage>1020</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr72-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Research in tectonics: kink bands and brittle deformation</source> <publisher-name>Geological Survey of Canada, gSC Paper 68-52</publisher-name>, <year>1968</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr73-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drapier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Grandidier</surname><given-names>J-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Potier-Ferry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Towards a numerical model of the compressive strength for long fibre composites</article-title>. <source>Eur J Mech A Solids</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>–<lpage>92</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr74-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ladevèze</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lubineau</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Violeau</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A computational damage micromodel of laminated composites</article-title>. <source>Int J Fract</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>137</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr75-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yerramalli</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Waas</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A failure criterion for fiber reinforced polymer composites under combined compression–torsion loading</article-title>. <source>Int J Solids Struct</source> <year>2003</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1139</fpage>–<lpage>1164</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr76-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vittecoq</surname> <given-names>É</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sur le comportement en compression des composites stratifiés carboneépoxy</article-title>. <source>PhD thesis</source> <publisher-name>Université de Paris 6</publisher-name>, <year>1991</year>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr77-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koerber</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Xavier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Camanho</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>High strain rate characterisation of unidirectional carbon-epoxy im7-8552 in transverse compression and in-plane shear using digital image correlation</article-title>. <source>Mech Mat</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>42</volume>: <fpage>1004</fpage>–<lpage>1019</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr78-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gutiérrez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Energy release control for numerical simulations of failure in quasibrittle solids</article-title>. <source>Commun Numer Meth Eng</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.</citation></ref>
<ref id="bibr79-0021998311434170"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le Dantec</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Contribution à la modélisation du comportement mécanique des composites stratifiés</article-title>. <source>PhD thesis</source> <publisher-name>Université Paris 6</publisher-name>, <year>1989</year>.</citation></ref>
</ref-list>
<app-group>
<app id="app1-0021998311434170"><title/>
<sec id="sec13-0021998311434170"><title>Appendix 1</title>
<sec id="sec14-0021998311434170"><title>Mesomodel details</title><p>The in-plane specific energy of the ply reads:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula25-0021998311434170"><label>(25)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math25-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable align="right"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1 2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>á</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>ñ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>á</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>ñ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>21</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>á</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>ñ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right" columnspan="1"><mml:mrow/></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>á</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>ñ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula25-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq25.tif"/></disp-formula>
with 〈.〉 the <italic>positive part</italic> function and <inline-formula id="ilm29-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math29-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> an internal variable governing isotropic inelasticity.</p><p>The thermodynamic forces associated with each damage variable read:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula26-0021998311434170"><label>(26)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math26-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula26-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq26.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula27-0021998311434170"><label>(27)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math27-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>á</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>ñ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula27-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq27.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula28-0021998311434170"><label>(28)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math28-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>á</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>ñ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula28-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq28.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p><p>Since <italic>d</italic> and <italic>d</italic>′ are representing the same mechanisms of degradation, their associated forces are coupled in a single driving force:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula29-0021998311434170"><label>(29)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math29-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula29-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq29.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p><p>Evolution laws can be written with respect to these forces:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula30-0021998311434170"><label>(30)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math30-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>max</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula30-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq30.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula31-0021998311434170"><label>(31)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math31-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula31-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq31.tif"/></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula32-0021998311434170"><label>(32)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math32-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>max</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>á</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>ñ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula32-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq32.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula id="ilm30-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math30-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a thermodynamic force, possibly different in tension than in compression.</p><p>The development of fiber/matrix debonding and microcracking leads to local slipping between the phases of the composite. At the plies' scale, the residual stresses and strains due to these transformations can be seen as material inelasticity. This behavior is best reproduced using ‘effective’ stresses:<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-0021998311434170">59</xref>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula33-0021998311434170"><label>(33)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math33-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:munder><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">K</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">K</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula33-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq33.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <bold>K</bold> is the Hooke tensor of elasticity. Similarly, effective inelastic strains with respect to dissipated energy equivalence are introduced:<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-0021998311434170">55</xref>
<disp-formula id="disp-formula34-0021998311434170"><label>(34)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math34-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mrow><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mrow><mml:mi>·</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>·</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula34-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq34.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p><p>Under the hypotheses of associated plastic flow and standard generalized material, inelasticity is driven by a single isotropic cumulated variable <inline-formula id="ilm31-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math31-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula35-0021998311434170"><label>(35)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math35-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>·</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>·</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula35-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq35.tif"/></disp-formula>
where <italic>g</italic> is the loading surface:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula36-0021998311434170"><label>(36)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math36-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>eq</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>eq</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula36-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq36.tif"/></disp-formula>
with <inline-formula id="ilm32-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math32-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the isotropic hardening associated with <inline-formula id="ilm33-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math33-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula37-0021998311434170"><label>(37)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math37-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula37-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq37.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p><p>Finally, <inline-formula id="ilm34-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math34-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>eq</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is an equivalent stress that reads in-plane:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula38-0021998311434170"><label>(38)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math38-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>eq</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula38-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq38.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p><p>With the above expressions, the plastic multiplier reads:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula39-0021998311434170"><label>(39)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block" id="math39-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>·</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="helvetica">H</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>á</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>·</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>ñ</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula39-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq39.tif"/></disp-formula>
where ℋ is the Heaviside function and <italic>h</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> the hardening modulus. Since <italic>g</italic> only depends on <inline-formula id="ilm35-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math35-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>eq</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="ilm36-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math36-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, the modulus reads:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula40-0021998311434170"><label>(40)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math40-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi/><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>Ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula40-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq40.tif"/></disp-formula>
Hence, the plastic multiplier:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula41-0021998311434170"><label>(41)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math41-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>·</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>'</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>·</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>eq</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula41-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq41.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p><p>All the parameters of the mesomodel have been identified for T300/BSL-914C plies in Le Dantec<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0021998311434170">79</xref> using cycled 0°, ±45°, and ±67.5° tensile tests. The values used in this study are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0021998311434170">Table 4</xref>.
<table-wrap id="table4-0021998311434170" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Summary of the mesomodel in-plane parameters and values<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-0021998311434170">79</xref></p></caption><graphic alternate-form-of="table4-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-table4.tif"/>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead>
<tr><th>Material parameter</th><th>Symbol</th><th>Value</th><th>Unit</th></tr></thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Axial Young's modulus</td>
<td><inline-formula id="ilm37-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math37-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td>
<td>130,000</td>
<td>MPa</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Transverse Young's modulus</td>
<td><inline-formula id="ilm38-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math38-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td>
<td>8500</td>
<td>MPa</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Shear modulus</td>
<td><inline-formula id="ilm39-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math39-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td>
<td>4200</td>
<td>MPa</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Poisson ratio</td>
<td>ν<sub>12</sub></td>
<td>0.4</td>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Shear/transverse coupling</td>
<td><italic>b</italic></td>
<td>0.5</td>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Damage coupling</td>
<td><italic>c</italic></td>
<td>0.8</td>
<td/></tr>
<tr>
<td>Diffuse initiation force</td>
<td><italic>Y</italic><sub>0</sub></td>
<td>0.03</td>
<td>MPa</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Diffuse critical force</td>
<td><italic>Y</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub></td>
<td>8</td>
<td>MPa</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Brittle tension force</td>
<td><italic>Y</italic><sub><italic>t</italic></sub></td>
<td>25</td>
<td>MPa</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Elastic limit</td>
<td><inline-formula id="ilm40-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math40-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>~</mml:mi></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td>
<td>64</td>
<td>MPa</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Hardening modulus</td>
<td><italic>K</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub></td>
<td>1000</td>
<td>MPa</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Hardening power</td>
<td><italic>m</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub></td>
<td>0.54</td>
<td>MPa</td></tr>
<tr>
<td>Inelastic coupling</td>
<td><italic>a</italic></td>
<td>0.5</td>
<td/></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap></p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec15-0021998311434170"><title>Appendix 2</title>
<sec id="sec16-0021998311434170"><title>Rheological model details</title><p>The form of the rheological model with 1 degree of freedom considered is reminded in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig16-0021998311434170">Figure 16</xref>.
<fig id="fig16-0021998311434170" position="float"><label>Figure 16.</label><caption><p>Rheological model sketch.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-fig16.tif"/></fig></p><p>Let us consider the observable variable σ<sub>11</sub>. We want to express the angle α as a function of this variable only. The rheological model presents a non-zero initial value of α, which initially implies:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula42-0021998311434170"><label>(42)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math42-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>kb</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>sin</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula42-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq42.tif"/></disp-formula>
And when the system is loaded:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula43-0021998311434170"><label>(43)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math43-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>kb</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>sin</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula43-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq43.tif"/></disp-formula>
Let us define:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula44-0021998311434170"><label>(44)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math44-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>kb</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext>and</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>ɛ</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>v</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>w</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>kb</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula44-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq44.tif"/></disp-formula>
We have:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula45-0021998311434170"><label>(45)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math45-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>sin</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula45-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq45.tif"/></disp-formula>
Let us consider σ<sub><italic>r</italic></sub>, the dual stress of ε<sub><italic>r</italic></sub>, defined as:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula46-0021998311434170"><label>(46)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math46-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula46-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq46.tif"/></disp-formula>
The momentum equilibrium of the rheological model reads, for any α:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula47-0021998311434170"><label>(47)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math47-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>tan</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula47-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq47.tif"/></disp-formula>
By combining the previous expressions:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula48-0021998311434170"><label>(48)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math48-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>sin</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo/><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>tan</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula48-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq48.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p><p>Hence, for a given state of internal variables (i.e. <inline-formula id="ilm41-0021998311434170"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="mml-math41-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and possible damage affecting <italic>k</italic>), α can be implicitly defined as a function of σ<sub>11</sub>. We define:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula49-0021998311434170"><label>(49)</label><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" id="math49-0021998311434170"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>tan</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula49-0021998311434170" xlink:href="10.1177_0021998311434170-eq49.tif"/></disp-formula>
</p>
</sec>
</sec></app></app-group></back>
</article>