<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CCJ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spccj</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Contemporary Criminal Justice</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1043-9862</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-5406</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1043986212465529</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1043986212465529</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Editors’ Introduction to the Special Issue</article-title>
<subtitle>Contemporary Research on Youth Gangs</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>Kristy N.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name><surname>Esbensen</surname><given-names>Finn-Aage</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>Kristy N.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Esbensen</surname><given-names>Finn-Aage</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>28</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue: Contemporary Research on Youth Gangs</issue-title>
<fpage>386</fpage>
<lpage>388</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 SAGE Publications</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>While gangs in America have existed for over a century, the empirical work on gangs has its roots in Frederick Thrasher’s 1927 study of gangs in Chicago. Thrasher’s influence is evidenced by the fact that it is seemingly impossible to read any gang study (new or old) without it being mentioned in the literature review (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1043986212465529">Brantingham, Tita, Short, and Reid, 2012</xref>). Following Thrasher’s (1927) chronicling of Chicago gangs, interest in and study of this collective form of group behavior and identity flourished, especially during the 1950s and 1960s and again during the past quarter century (1990 – present). Studies of gangs and gang members represent the diversity of methods available to researchers: ranging from descriptive/qualitative case studies of one gang or several gang members to large scale multi-site longitudinal surveys of potentially gang-involved youth. Another approach to studying gangs relies on surveying law enforcement agencies regarding gangs and gang crime, including the annual National Gang Survey conducted in the US (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1043986212465529">Egley &amp; Howell, 2012</xref>). While the stereotypical gang depictions available in popular culture or mainstream media suggest gangs are almost exclusively found in certain locales and represented by only a subset of the population, gang studies, especially those of the past twenty years, paint a different picture. Gangs are found in urban, suburban, and rural locales. Gangs are not monolithic; they come in different sizes and different structures. Gang members are not only ethnic minority males; gang members reflect the demographic composition of their communities. Research has also documented that gangs are not just an American phenomenon; gangs have been identified in nations around the globe (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1043986212465529">Covey, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1043986212465529">Esbensen and Maxson, 2012</xref>). This ever expanding body of gang research has taught us much, ranging from knowledge of risk factors associated with gang membership, the effect of gang joining on subsequent behavior, the trajectory of gang membership, the diversity of gang structures, and promising and not-so-promising responses to gangs. In short, we now know a lot about gangs.</p>
<p>However, the world is changing rapidly. And the world that existed when Thrasher was studying his 1,313 gangs in Chicago is no longer. Technology has made the world smaller. Commerce with countries a half a world away is available with the click of a button. Television broadcasts are being dismissed in lieu of the immediacy of streaming on smart phones and computers. Social media is making instant connections possible. Despite what groundbreaking ideas Thrasher had about the ecology of a neighborhood and the impact on the residents of that community, there was no way for him to predict what technology would do to redefine “community.” The awareness and cultural influence of gangs can no longer be expected to remain only in cities or only amongst certain groups of people or, for that matter, only in America. Policing gangs on the street is no longer sufficient to understanding their behavior or activities, police are now forced to monitor social media sites, blogs, or other web postings. And, more importantly, we have no idea what impact the modern world has on the stability of gangs (as a group) and gang members (i.e., individual trajectories). For these reasons, two trends are evident. First, the scope of gang research must broaden to include new topics, the use of new technologies, and include new potential populations perhaps previously believed to be “sheltered” from gang influence. Second, what we used to “know” needs to be continuously tested, re-tested, and applied to a wider subject base.</p>
<p>The purpose of this special issue on gangs is to truly inform <italic>Contemporary Criminal Justice</italic>, and to investigate new topics and re-address what we think we know about gangs in this ever-changing context. Sela-Shayovitz and Yellin investigate the role of the internet in the lives of gang members. The internet has drastically changed the way everyday business is conducted, and there is no reason to believe that gang members are immune from its influence. Shayovitz and Yellin investigate the role of the web in the social life of gangs and as a method for potentially expanding their criminal enterprises.</p>
<p>Studies in this special issue look to broaden our global understanding of gangs and gang members. Winfree compares the reasons for joining offered by gang members in Germany and Bosnia-Herzegovina. Cross-national gang studies are challenging to conduct, and therefore, have been relatively rare (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1043986212465529">Klein, 2012</xref>). But a group of gang scholars dedicated to espousing the importance of true cross-national gang research have brought about a surge of international comparisons in the past few decades (i.e., the Eurogang Program of Research). Winfree’s piece is not the only article in this volume that has an international perspective. Shayovitz and Yellin conduct their research on gang members in Israel and Rostami, Leinfelt, and Holgersson examine Swedish gangs.</p>
<p>In addition to expanding our global understanding of gangs, Freng, Davis, McCord, and Roussell draw our attention to gang members in America that are often overlooked, namely, American Indian gangs. Freng and colleagues examine the correlates of gang joining in this understudied American population. But, not to become too narrowly focused, two articles in this volume (Esbensen and Carson; Melde, Diem and Drake) use two different national datasets to examine the broader gang picture. Melde et al. utilize the Gang Resistance Education and Training (G.R.E.A.T.) program data collected in the 1990s (i.e., G.R.E.A.T. 1) and Esbensen and Carson utilize the data collected from the second, and most recent, national evaluation of the G.R.E.A.T. program (i.e., G.R.E.A.T. 2). Both datasets include thousands of school-aged participants in cities throughout the United States. Therefore, both offer a broader depiction of gang members.</p>
<p>In an attempt to re-address old issues in a modern context Esbensen and Carson replicate an “old faithful” in the world of gang studies. In 1998, Esbensen and Winfree challenged previously held racial and sex differences in gang members’ involvement in delinquency. Since that time, other work, including those in an international perspective, has supported their conclusions. Their work, still often cited, has not been truly replicated since that time. Esbensen and Carson use a current, national sample of youth to accomplish this task.</p>
<p>Melde, Diem, and Drake tackle an important question in their study investigating the predictors of stable gang membership. Gang research is difficult, in general, for access reasons, sample size constraints, and the variability in gang career. While we know that gang membership is often short and fleeting, much of what we know about differences between short-term and stable gang members is based on anecdotal information. Data to explore this issue are difficult to obtain. This data issue is evident in Melde and collegues’ comparison of stable gang members with those who are not. Even with an initial sample of over 2,000 study participants, they identified only 140 gang members. They then used the panel data from these 140 youths to examine factors associated with the length of gang membership.</p>
<p>Finally, Rostami and colleagues also readdress a gang classic. Using law enforcement data, they seek to determine if the Maxson and Klein (1995) gang typology is relevant to Swedish gangs. International gangs are often described as different or “distinct” from American gangs (regardless of the accuracy of the American gang depiction) (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1043986212465529">Klein’s, 2012</xref>, discussion of the “Eurogang paradox”). Rostami and colleagues offer the American experience as a starting point to understand the complexity and commonality of Swedish gangs.</p>
<p>As the world continues to change, so will gangs. As gangs and gang members change, so must research. This special issue exemplifies researchers’ ongoing attempts to be relevant in this discussion – this international, virtual, and timeless discussion.</p>
<sig-block>
<sig>Kristy N. Matsuda<break/>
Finn-Aage Esbensen<break/>
<italic>University of Missouri - St. Louis</italic>
</sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1043986212465529">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brantingham</surname><given-names>P. Jeffrey</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tita</surname><given-names>George E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Short</surname><given-names>Martin B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>Shannon E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The ecology of gang territorial boundaries</article-title>. <source>Criminology</source>, <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>851</fpage>-<lpage>885</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1043986212465529">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Covey</surname><given-names>Herbert C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Street gangs throughout the world</source>. <publisher-loc>Springfield, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Thomas</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1043986212465529">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Egley</surname><given-names>Arlen</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>
<name><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>James C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <source>Highlights of the 2012 National Youth Gang Survey</source>. <publisher-loc>OJJDP</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Juvenile Justice Fact Sheet</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1043986212465529">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Esbensen</surname><given-names>Finn-Aage</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maxson</surname><given-names>Cheryl L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <source>Youth Gangs in International Perspective: Results from the Eurogang Program of Research</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>:<publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1043986212465529">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>Malcolm</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The next decade of Eurogang Program Research</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Esbensen</surname><given-names>F.A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maxson</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds.) <source>Youth Gangs in International Perspectives: Results from the Eurogang Program of Research</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>