<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EUA</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">speua</journal-id>
<journal-title>Environment and Urbanization Asia</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0975-4253</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">XXXX-XXXX</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage India: New Delhi, India</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/097542531200300114</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_097542531200300114</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Review</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Triumph of the City: How Our Greatest Invention Makes Us Richer, Smarter, Greener, Healthier, and Happier</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>Satmohini Isha S.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-097542531200300114">Senior Research Fellow National Institute of Urban Affairs New Delhi</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>3</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<fpage>251</fpage>
<lpage>253</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Glaeser</surname><given-names>Edward</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>2011</year>. <source>Triumph of the City: How Our Greatest Invention Makes Us Richer, Smarter, Greener, Healthier, and Happier</source>. <publisher-name>The Penguin Press</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>. <edition>First Edition</edition>. ISBN: <isbn>978-1-59420-277-3273</isbn> pp.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 National Institute of Urban Affairs (NIUA)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">National Institute of Urban Affairs</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Cities are an organic creature with the thread of its life strung by a set of fragile yet complex relationships between its various actors. Edward Glaeser, probably the best known urban economist in business today, leads us to believe in the organism called ‘city’ and pointedly discourses why some cities prosper, some stagnate, while some just die.</p>
<p>This book is to understanding city development the way Steven Levitt’s Freakonomics was to understanding economics for so many non-economists, and will be enjoyed by readers irrespective of professional interest in the business of city development. Having said that, the book leaves us wanting for more, especially Asian stakeholders. While the author draws conclusions based on a set of robust data-sets gleamed from North American cities, he supplements these with anecdotal experiences from Asian, African and Latin American cities. That slums of Dharavi (Mumbai), Lagos and Kolkata can be morphed into a gleaming Manhattan or a serene Paris by pure economic interventions sounds wonderful, although slightly heady. This apart, Triumph of the City is indeed a triumph and shatters numerous myths especially on the role cities play in the advancement of the humankind. Peppered with interesting facts and magniloquent arguments, its lucid text makes this 227-page ‘novel’ a pleasurable read.</p>
<p>The book is divided into 10 chapters, each presenting a set of papers which make for blog-like reading. Each chapter presents a set of arguments which remain interwoven throughout other chapters as well. It is a challenge to do a systematic review based on chapters; rather, a review based on principal arguments is felt more likely to do justice. The review is also tailored for purpose of readers of this journal and focuses more on what may be of interest to emerging economies, although the book is predominantly focused on learning from and for American cities.</p>
<p>Achieving higher density in the city through systematic vertical growth is a better way to expand compared to horizontal growth. Glaeser pays tribute to Jane Jacobs, the noted urbanist, who believed that restricting heights and preserving old neighbourhoods would ensure affordability, but challenges her belief from the economic point of view as restrictive development in city core would make it more expensive and exclusive, thus reducing affordability citing Paris as a prime example. The author presents a series of compelling data on how sub-urban sprawl leads to greater costs of providing services, leads to more carbon emissions, and chokes evolution of art and culture. He demonstrates that irrespective of a national economic recession, year-on-year Manhattan continues to demonstrate increasing wage earning returns, continues to employ more waiters per square foot area, and continues to showcase the best of art and culture.</p>
<p>Cities are not full of poor people because cities cause poverty, but because cities attract poor people from rural areas. The ability of a city to attract the poor speaks positively of its economic growth potential. The poor come to cities for jobs as a big city provides for a diversified portfolio of employers, and the sheer variety of jobs and opportunities to hop across jobs allow people to decide what they can do best. The problem of slums is not because the city is overpopulated, but because slum dwellers are often too disconnected from the economic heart of the city. He feels that limiting growth of megacities would cause more hardship than gain, and that urban growth is a great way to reduce rural poverty. He makes an impassioned plea to governments to invest in poor people and not poor places citing many examples where inane attempts at urban renewal make little economic sense and compares this to a bribe to poor people to stay in declining areas.</p>
<p>The challenges posed by slums and urban poverty are acknowledged, and urban infrastructure stress is identified as the key challenge of burgeoning cities. However, the author feels that despite its terrors, urban poverty can offer a path towards prosperity for both the poor and the nation as a whole. While, on one hand, increasing migrants mean worsening quality of infrastructure for the city’s long-time residents, on the other hand, new arrivals get access to infrastructure that they never did in rural areas. The author strongly feels that restricting access of urban infrastructure to a few would not only be inequitable, but unethical as well. He links favelas of Rio and slums of Mumbai and Kolkata today to the nineteenth century American cities indicating that while emerging economy cities have a considerable distance to go before they catch up with their Western counterparts, catch-up they certainly can. However, the governments have an important role to play to ensure that strong policies and investments are available to combat the costs of poverty. Again pointing to American cities, particularly Manhattan and New York, the author highlights the strong financial investments and strong governmental interventions that ensured access to clean water and safe streets. Need for strong urban governance is highlighted and example of Singapore is provided where fewer policy and operational constraints have meant that the government has been able to provide a clean and safe city to its residents.</p>
<p>Human capital, far more than physical capital, contributes to success of cities. Per capita productivity rises sharply if the metropolis is well educated, and not if it is not. The rise of Bangalore and Silicon Valley as global cities is attributed to investments in education. A study of American cities indicates that going to college is associated with an over 80 per cent increase in earnings. Education does not just improve a region’s economic prospects; it also helps create a more just society. Giving the poor education is probably the single most efficient means of helping them become prosperous adults. A case is made for investing in systemic reforms in education where recent research demonstrates that lower-income students stand to gain the most, if not equally, from this. Talented teachers and a good school curriculum are attributed as the two most important ingredients for success of the education system, and thereby the city as a whole.</p>
<p>Cities are incubators of ideas. The origins of Paris, Rotterdam, Chicago and London may have been mundane, but these cities over the past two centuries have provided vast amounts of cultural, economic and political innovation which would not have been possible, or would have taken a millennium longer, in a rural society. Historically, cities have fostered artistic innovations, be it Florence, Vienna or Paris. This is because cities have the ability to get like-minded people together to innovate as they sit face-to-face. In today’s world, information technology and Internet is important but it has been a harbinger of growth only when it has been successfully combined with knowledge gained face-to-face. Cities, and more importantly competition within and between cities, have led to urban citizens making progressive innovations in all fields and towards this end, it is important not to ‘contain’ city growth but to ‘promote’ city growth through various avenues.</p>
<p>Glaeser also talks of the need for smart cities and seeks smarter environmentalism. He criticizes the American style of suburb living as it leads to increased emissions compared to living in taller structures downtown. He focuses on Chinese and Indian cities where he believes tremendous potential exists for future carbon savings by making the city dense, growing vertically instead of horizontally, and providing for a city life based around public transportation systems. At the same time, he calls for smarter environmentalism in cities of developed economies. Smarter environmentalism requires thinking through the inadvertent side effects of different environmental policies and recognizing those that actually do more harm than good. For example, a policy to protect local greens or dilapidated heritage sites in downtown areas may lead to increased fringe expansion, which may mean that more people would drive to work, thus causing more carbon emissions than managing downtown areas would have resulted in. Smart environmentalism embraces incentives, and Ken Livingstone’s congestion charge is hailed as a good practice as it actually forced people to move out of cars into public transport systems.</p>
<p>The author also presents a set of interesting case studies of cities across the world focusing on what attributes made cities such as Tokyo, Singapore, Boston, Milan, Minneapolis, Vancouver, Chicago, Atlanta and New York successful, but readers may have benefited from more case studies of smart cities coming up in China, Mid-East Asia and India.</p>
<p>In this wonderful volume, Glaeser shatters a number of myths on cities and firmly establishes the importance of cities in sustaining economic and spiritual growth of humankind. In fact, he celebrates the growth of cities. Yet, in spite of stating that we must not see cities through its buildings but rather through its citizens, his unemotional view of what cities require to do next makes one ponder on whether growth of cities, especially cities in emerging economies, can be based on pure economic logic.</p>
<sig-block>
<sig>Satmohini Isha S. Ray<break/>
<italic>Senior Research Fellow</italic><break/>
<italic>National Institute of Urban Affairs</italic><break/>
<italic>New Delhi</italic></sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
</article>