<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JMI</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjmi</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Management Inquiry</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1056-4926</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-6542</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1056492612441394</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1056492612441394</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Meet the Person</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Cross-Cultural Knowledge Sharing for Competitive Advantage</article-title>
<subtitle>An Interview With Nigel J. Holden</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>Jeffrey</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1056492612441394">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Vance</surname><given-names>Charles M.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1056492612441394">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1056492612441394"><label>1</label>Loyola Marymount University, Los Angeles, CA, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1056492612441394">Charles M. Vance, Loyola Marymount University, 1 LMU Drive, MS 8385, Los Angeles, CA 90045, USA Email: <email>cvance@lmu.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>10</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>21</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>397</fpage>
<lpage>403</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The contemporary business organization functions in a global economy operating in multiple country environments and with competitive advantage based largely on the ability to develop and manage knowledge. In this interview, Nigel Holden, a prominent expert and contributor to both cross-cultural management and knowledge management, explores his current views of the relationship between the two in the modern multinational company. Calling for a move beyond what he characterizes as a superficial approach for developing a global perspective in Western business education, he focuses on the “art” of cocreating a common cognitive and emotional ground to facilitate sharing of knowledge between individuals and in networks with different cultures in different contexts. In this, he explores the role of tacit knowledge and, particularly, language itself as a knowledge management metaphor and an influence on knowledge transfer. Finally, he elaborates on the challenge of enabling knowledge flows across cultural barriers in international firms.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>cross-cultural</kwd>
<kwd>knowledge management</kwd>
<kwd>international diversification</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1056492612441394" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Dr. Nigel Holden has enjoyed a professional lifetime immersed in both the work environment and study of cross-cultural management issues. He retired from full-time academic life at the end of 2010 but has a visiting research fellowship at the Centre for International Business at the University of Leeds in the United Kingdom. He has held professorships in cross-cultural management in Denmark (1997-2001), Germany (2002-2004), and the United Kingdom (2004-2010), and retains visiting professorships at universities in Austria, Denmark, and Thailand.</p>
<p>Holden holds a bachelor’s degree in modern languages (Salford, 1969), an MA in Russian language and literature (London, 1981), and a PhD in international industrial marketing (Manchester Business School, 1986). In 2008 he was described by the <italic>International Journal of Cross Cultural Management</italic> as having influenced a generation of scholars in North America and Europe with his work on knowledge management combined with his unconventional approach to traditional thinking about cross-national values. Holden has coauthored management books on Japan (1994) and Russia (1998), and his acclaimed “Cross-Cultural Management: A Knowledge Management Perspective” (2002) has appeared in Chinese and Russian versions. In this book, he proposed that our well-worn traditional perspective of cross-cultural management be very productively redesignated as cross-cultural knowledge management. His latest book, coauthored with Martin Glisby, is “Creating Knowledge Advantage: The Tacit Dimensions of International Competition and Cooperation.”</p>
<p>In 2009, Holden was an adviser to the United Nations Industrial Development Organization (UNIDO), and in 2009-2011, he served as a consultant to the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) on knowledge management issues. He was invited in 2010 to join the Advisory Board of the Ikujiro Nonaka Centre for Knowledge Management at IESE Business School in Navarra, Spain. Holden is a management educator and researcher who has widely traveled and has been a frequent keynote speaker at academic conferences in Europe and Asia.</p>
<p>In true cross-cultural knowledge management fashion, in Holden’s research career, he has translated source material for informing our English-dominated world from the following languages: Danish, French, German, Japanese, Polish, and Russian. He is a veritable font of tacit and explicit knowledge on cross-cultural management with its myriad of forms and processes of communication and information exchange across our global village. His fertile ideas, challenging academia’s sacred-cow concepts about culture in our global marketplace, represent very needed and helpful further peelings of the cultural onion. In this interview, we are pleased to elicit from Nigel Holden some insightful points related to the very fruitful admixture of the fields of cross-cultural management and knowledge management.</p>
<speech>
<speaker>Q:</speaker>
<p>Why did you and Martin Glisby write your recent book on creating knowledge advantage? What need did you perceive that drove you forward with this project, other than to promote your fame and fortune?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Holden:</speaker>
<p>Martin and I both feel that the concept of culture that has dominated management education and research for a good 50 years—always focusing on national value systems and differences—is out of kilter with the workings of the modern global knowledge-based economy. For over 10 years I have been suggesting that cross-cultural management should be repositioned as a form of knowledge management. It is pretty obvious—well, to me anyway—that there is some kind of relationship between culture on the ground and tacit knowledge, which is by its very nature context specific. Our book in fact extended that conviction by arguing that each and every kind of cross-cultural interaction produces tacit knowledge—insights, if you like—of greater or lesser significance. But to advance our ideas, our book had to have case studies, which are grounded in tacit knowledge, based on interviews in Europe and Asia with managers from internationally operating companies in various industry sectors. We converted what we learned from them into models and even into unusual propositions about international business practice.</p>
<p>Of course, there’s the fame angle. But it’s not just the content of the book that serves to promote us. The really noteworthy thing is that we are a professor-practitioner team. This combination is really unheard of in international management writing on both sides of the Atlantic. We did everything together—getting funding, conducting interviews in Japan, China, Korea, Denmark, and UK, and sharing the writing. In our own way we are leaders! To promote our fortune? Doubt it.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Q:</speaker>
<p>When most of us teach about the various extant dimensions of international culture, it seems that these dimensions offer only a stereotype of a culture, which nonetheless provides a useful initial framework to allow us to begin to understand the culture, yet we need to continue to test and refine our understanding of the particular culture’s characteristics. However, after reviewing your work we have a distinct sense that our understanding of many of the dimensions themselves is quite superficial, as you’ve described our popular Western conceptualization of the Chinese “guanxi.” Are we often really only promoting shallow stereotypes of stereotyped dimensions?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Holden:</speaker>
<p>I think that’s a good way of putting it. Someone has got to crack this for at least one not entirely obvious reason. The popular but quite superficial approach for developing a global perspective that dominates business education in the West (and therefore unfortunately the widespread executive and management development programs that are closer to actual practice) believes that “cultural intelligence” is the Holy Grail. But this very linear, recipe-oriented, widely held view has missed the point. It’s not about getting yourself accepted by counterparts in foreign business environments. It really has to do with the art—the art, note—of cocreating with those counterparts in context-specific ways common cognitive and emotional ground to facilitate sharing of knowledge, elements of behavior, and even modes of life. You cannot teach this vital art with the Hofstede, Trompenaars, or GLOBE schemes, which are mightily responsible for ensuring that entire countries become abstractions, and their inhabitants stereotypes.</p>
<p>We need better schemes that enable, say, a U.S. executive or student to see things from the other’s point of view. When you can see the world from a new angle, you can acquire a kind of logic for dealing with foreign business partners that resonates with their culture. But this requires of you a willingness to step outside your own comfort zone and to abandon any superior thought that there is nothing to learn from them. If arrogance is part of your cultural baggage, it will always be picked up—like a bad smell—and put people in opposition to you. Then you return to New York and LA, telling everyone how dumb, unfriendly, and completely incompetent were those very people whose respect you lost. If that’s happened in China, the chances are that someone over there has lost face. Some people seem to think that this is momentary feeling of humiliation. It’s better to realize that causing your Chinese colleague to lose face may be tantamount to delivering a lifelong insult. Westerners tend to go overboard about <italic>guanxi</italic>, but no Chinese is going to open up his <italic>guanxi</italic> to you if you caused loss of face. Forget <italic>guanxi</italic>—well, almost—and learn to apply intelligence and tact. That’s the essence of the art I was talking about. The tricky bit for business schools is that you can only really learn it on the spot.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Q:</speaker>
<p>Tacit knowledge is, of course, a slippery concept. Consequently, you employ multiple metaphors for understanding it and do not define it. And, even in your case studies, the term is not generally employed. Do you find that managers can relate to this abstraction and understand it? Can they act on that understanding?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Holden:</speaker>
<p>Only one of the managers we interviewed in Europe and Asia had heard of the term “tacit knowledge.” To the others we described it as “soft knowledge” arising from experience, intuitions, and supporting sense-making. This seemed to be readily understood. But we found that the term tacit knowledge by itself kept suggesting something rather static and detached from business life. We therefore started to refer to it as cross-cultural knowledge sharing. International managers can identify with this expression, because they recognize that this refers to cross-cultural processes in which they actively participate.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Q:</speaker>
<p>The linkage between explicit and tacit knowledge also is extremely murky for many of us. You go so far as to suggest that these two terms may be regarded as a network package. Can you talk a bit about tacit knowledge and this network linkage? Does the idea only gain meaning from its link to explicit knowledge?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Holden:</speaker>
<p>Yes, that linkage is murky. We are saying that knowledge in the world of business practice is assembled by people working in their particular networks for other people working in wholly different networks in all manner of countries. The assembled knowledge is therefore a network package of explicit and tacit elements intended for different operational environments or contexts. So, when it comes to international and cross-cultural business, the art of knowledge management lies in converting a knowledge package, designed in one environment (or culture), into a package that does not merely suit but <italic>resonates with</italic> the network characteristics of the target environment(s). In practice it is impossible to separate the tacit from the explicit for the simple reason that there is always a subjective element in knowledge, so models that like to show tacit knowledge as the unseen bit of a kind of knowledge iceberg are missing the point. The strength of tacit knowledge depends on how it is aligned with explicit knowledge and applied with it.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Q:</speaker>
<p>You have suggested that tacit knowledge can only be truly understood if the surrounding context is understood as well. But, with culture as context, can this knowledge ever truly be communicated to individuals or organizations in a substantially different culture?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Holden:</speaker>
<p>The context is in effect a perceived combination of explicit and tacit elements, but no two people necessarily have the same interpretation of it. When it is a context you are familiar with—your home, yours sports club, your organization—you know the relationship between the two. In a foreign business environment there is a tendency to misjudge the balance between the two. On the spot you make judgments about people and situations. But these judgments are often partial, possibly misinformed and even misguided. Nonetheless, they may end at corporate headquarters as “truth.” But an even greater problem is when the big guys at corporate headquarters have <italic>already</italic> taken a view about how things work in that foreign environment to suit their business plans. This premature assessment builds severe ethnocentrism, which is a major impediment for cross-cultural knowledge transfer processes.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Q:</speaker>
<p>What is the influence of corporate language choice on the flow of tacit knowledge when the language of the organization is not the language of the home country?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Holden:</speaker>
<p>Language filters knowledge. When knowledge in a source language is to be transferred to another, in that process the filtering is haphazard and potentially misleading. When you think about it, most knowledge that is created, shared, and transferred in international business takes place in cross-cultural contexts. When knowledge crosses a language barrier, and that happens literally millions of times a day, not only may the knowledge be distorted, but the actual transfer process may extend the presumed time for completion of a given project. I am not talking of seconds or minutes here, but weeks and months. Just think of international mergers. In other words, inefficient cross-cultural knowledge transfer and sharing can have the unwelcome effects of undermining strategies, deflecting managers’ time and attention, and overrunning budgets. It goes on all the time in international mergers. I call this “management by misanticipation.”</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Q:</speaker>
<p>Language plays a role both as metaphor for knowledge management and as a factor that influences the transfer of knowledge. Can you discuss this important insight further?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Holden:</speaker>
<p>I once wrote that language is “management’s lost continent.” I think that’s still true. Where would managers be without language? Their careers are directly linked to what they do with language and the effect their language behavior has on others. Managers are said to spend 80% of their professional time talking. But there are interesting cross-cultural variations. For example, American managers are said to use language as a means of self-assertion; for their French counterparts language is a kind of intellectual weapon with which to make lucid distinctions; to German managers it is a platform for displaying thorough job knowledge; whilst in China language has to be used in circuitous ways to preserve harmony—at least, that’s the ideal. Such cross-culturally variable styles of communication have a significant effect on how knowledge is shared—or not shared and even misunderstood—among multicultural teams or among international networks. Smart managers are those who always pay attention to different knowledge-sharing styles.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Q:</speaker>
<p>Following Nonaka, the case is often made that, for the Japanese at least, language is superior for the sharing of tacit knowledge and absorbing knowledge from other cultures. Would you elaborate on why you believe language has helped in absorbing knowledge and how its contextual nature helps the process?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Holden:</speaker>
<p>Every language is, as it were, designed to suit the norms and conventions covering social interactions in its corresponding culture. In the case of Japan, we all know that the Japanese people prefer to avoid confrontation. But it goes beyond the lexicon of shimmering courtesies to convey this all-important politeness; the very grammar of the Japanese reflects degrees of politeness according to the situation and social distance between interacting parties. Roy Andrew Miller, a famous U.S. professor of Japanese, reckoned it takes a foreigner 20 years to master these face-saving nuances of the Japanese language.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Q:</speaker>
<p>Within your case study of Denso, is the language piece a hindrance to transfer to non-Japanese (or non-Japanese speaking) parts of the organization? Could it be that the sort of mystical concept like the Denso Spirit does not translate culturally to Western sensibilities, and that it is really never possible to fully understand or appreciate it?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Holden:</speaker>
<p>In large Japanese corporations, which employ hundreds and even thousands of foreigners, the workforce is “secretly” divided into the Japanese part and non-Japanese part. As a foreigner, you can never enter the Japanese world on equivalent membership terms. When it comes to conveying things like the company ethos and practices that are rooted in Japanese organizational behavior, the cultural divide gets complicated. Your Japanese colleagues desperately want you as a foreigner to understand these things, but to also be mystified by them at the same time, which is, of course, an almost impossible balance to strike.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Q:</speaker>
<p>Is there a cultural distance that influences the ability to transfer knowledge? Your position is that every act of knowledge transfer begins with a conversion of tacit knowledge. Is that always true within a common cultural setting? Or within relatively close cultures? Or when the same language is being utilized? Or when it is explicit knowledge being transferred?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Holden:</speaker>
<p>Knowledge is not knowledge unless it is accepted as such by others. Therefore, it must pass from its originator to others. In everyday life the knowledge content (i.e., the nominally explicit element) is transferred through some kind of social interaction. Skills in handling the social interaction are a form of tacit knowledge in its own right, and that knowledge—from the receivers’ point of view—becomes part of the entire knowledge package. This is a seriously misunderstood point, because receivers’ reaction to how the knowledge is transferred colors their attitude towards the knowledge content and its utility in a new context. Firms just don’t get it. They continually fall into the trap of thinking that it’s all about knowledge content.</p>
<p>From 1991 to 2003 the European Commission disbursed seven billion (not million) euros to transfer best management practice to the former USSR. Hundreds of European universities, business schools, and consultancies jumped on the bandwagon. In 2007 the EU’s own auditing body described the results of this massive process of cross-cultural knowledge transfer as poor—a waste of EU taxpayers’ money. Not enough thought went into redesigning the knowledge content <italic>and its tacit envelope</italic> to suit former USSR’s highly complex context.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Q:</speaker>
<p>There are multiple levels of culture—national, regional, company, profession, etc. How do these multiple cultural contexts interact for effective tacit knowledge transfer? Can company and/or professional cultures overcome the limitations of country culture?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Holden:</speaker>
<p>For the transfer at any level of knowledge in general—knowledge with explicit and tacit components—there must be common cognitive ground among senders and receivers. But creating that can be exceedingly difficult for parties who have never met and are communicating by email –in other words, an absolute majority of today’s electronically connected business partners! A prerequisite for this common ground is the creation of a constructive working atmosphere that can transcend the national, regional, company, and professional levels. Such a good, constructive atmosphere, which is by its nature always motivating, spreads like welcome sunshine in an organization. By contrast, think of how many dismal, sunless mergers you know!</p>
<p>If ensuring the transfer of tacit knowledge is of special importance, then you need an atmosphere that nurtures interanimation, which is a kind of mental and psychological force bringing not just minds but also hearts together. In the West we don’t like the idea of talking about heart as the seat of our emotions in our business dealings. It sounds soft and vague—hence unmasculine, hence unmanagerial. I am regularly in Thailand, where the heart is central to all business dealings. Indeed, Thai business (as my Thai colleague tells me) abounds with metaphors to do with the heart.</p>
<p>This distinction brings me to a major point, which is most relevant in the light of the recent Academy of Management conference in San Antonio, where this year’s grand theme was all about bridging the gap between the Western world and Asia. In the West we have a very cerebral view of business knowledge, but in Asian countries business knowledge must, as it were, find a resonance in local hearts. This means that Western knowledge packages for Asia need to be designed to <italic>esteem</italic> local business partners in order to secure the all-important interanimation. But that takes a lot of experience; it can only be theorized in a business school.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Q:</speaker>
<p>Are there any particular professional culture orientations close to us that tend to interfere with international business success?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Holden:</speaker>
<p>I have spent 30 years investigating and writing about cross-cultural interactions in international business. There are two problem cultures that are close to us in the management arena, in my opinion. First, there is the culture of corporate headquarters and in particular that of top management who are perpetual victims of what I will call cross-cultural dazzle. This refers to the persistence of cherished and cozy presuppositions, often based on no personal experience whatsoever, about how foreign business partners and potential customers shall think and shall behave. This kind of attitude, which places too much emphasis on perceived similarities, nurtures blind spots and sustains comfort zones.</p>
<p>The second culture is the one that envelops MBA education, which is so obsessed with viewing economies and markets from strategic vantage points that students are not given worthwhile tools for productively navigating and making sense of the world’s business cultures. As we wrote in our most recent book, MBA education has a way of reducing entire countries to abstractions and their inhabitants to stereotypes. No wonder some Harvard Business School professors, consistent with the rather superficial recipe approach I mentioned earlier, are after what they call a new kind of “cultural intelligence” that helps future business leaders understand foreign business cultures “at a granular, how-to-get-it-done level” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1056492612441394">Datar, Garvin, &amp; Cullen, 2010</xref>).</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Q:</speaker>
<p>Three of your recent book’s case studies involve interactions between Eastern higher context language societies and Western (European) ones. Were these cases chosen because of the cultural distance involved? Does cultural distance heighten the likelihood of difficulty in knowledge transfer?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Holden:</speaker>
<p>The cases were chosen for purely pragmatic reasons. We had good contacts in all four organizations. We approached them about being informants for case studies, and those people facilitated the decisions. It suited us to have two or three cases involving Asian companies. In Asian cultures with their emphasis on face-saving, trust (in their sense of the word), and harmony, it was clear to us that business in countries like Japan and China pay greater attention to knowledge derived from <italic>feelings</italic>—a word that Western business people don’t much care for since it does not fit with the image of the “tough” decision maker idealized in many Western countries.</p>
<p>At risk of overgeneralization, you have to accept that there exists a certain gulf between Western thinking and Eastern thinking. The appreciation of tacit knowledge as an influence in worldviews, innovation, and organization building is split along the classic East–West fault line: the East being flexible in synthesis, the West being very tough in analysis. Japan, the quintessential oriental knowledge management environment, puts tacit knowledge and its knowledge-creating implications at center stage; the West focuses on codified or explicit knowledge transfer and implementation. So in practical terms you have to accept that this cultural distance is a given, and that creating the right kind of common cognitive ground to bridge this cultural distance is going to take a lot of trial and error on both sides.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Q:</speaker>
<p>Regarding your Novo Nordisk case, can you elaborate on how the limited time spent by the teams of facilitators on-site in Novo Nordisk operations works in the transfer of knowledge versus the Novo Nordisk Way of Management (NNWoM) concept? How do they effectively work together?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Holden:</speaker>
<p>The NNWoM has been designed to be applicable to every aspect of Novo Nordisk’s activity wherever the company operates. But it is more than a management code. It creates via the facilitators a platform for building an equal playing field between corporate headquarters and the company’s units, and among the units themselves in more than 80 countries. This cultural alignment platform has the effect of massively reducing the cultural distance within the global firm, whereby headquarters is not a distant, disconnected entity in the corporate stratosphere, but both a beacon and listening post all in one. It has taken years of experimentation to achieve this system, and it is always evolving. It is an outstanding example of loose–tight management admired in <italic>In Search of Excellence.</italic></p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Q:</speaker>
<p>Would you elaborate on your HR observation about the relationship between tacit knowledge and talent management—especially within the technical specialist domains dominated by explicit knowledge? What are the implications for staffing and training in the international business?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Holden:</speaker>
<p>A clear example comes to mind. There is now research in the US and Europe suggesting that expats, when they return from a foreign assignment, find that nobody back at corporate headquarters is remotely interested in what kind of knowledge they have acquired abroad. Yet one of the purposes of sending them to this or that country was to acquire that very knowledge <italic>for competitive advantage!</italic> The enormous knowledge that the expats have accumulated about business in, say, Japan, China, or Brazil simply withers on the vine. It is surely obvious that a lot of this knowledge is tacit and invariably very precious to individuals. Feeling shunned, these executives quit the corporation for another one. This outcome means that the current employer not only loses a talented member of staff but also his or her tacit knowledge. In the 1980s (I don’t know about now) Japanese corporations developed systems for in effect downloading the brains of their expats, whereby returning expats’ tacit knowledge was made explicit, and captured and retained for staff development and training. They were especially interested in know-how for cross-cultural relationship building. In my experience, Western firms value this kind of know-how in principle, but are less good at converting it into an explicit knowledge resource. Novo Nordisk is a good example of a firm that does this tacit knowledge capture and explicit conversion well.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Q:</speaker>
<p>Would you expand a bit on the idea of network knowledge creation? Wouldn’t there be potential for even more contextual blockages here with networks that span organizational boundaries?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Holden:</speaker>
<p>Networks are generally seen as sets of contacts and carriers of information. I see a network as a pathway to resources—customers, revenue, new ideas, people with special talents, political influence, and so forth. The resulting human interactions generate colossal amounts of knowledge, so the network can also be seen as a creator of knowledge. But because this form of knowledge creation does not happen systematically, much less according to any kind of plan, the emerging knowledge tends to be undervalued, accidentally blocked, or even completely neglected. Cross-culturally speaking, corporate headquarters as the network central hub are the true authors of contextual blockages, and as such are unwitting killers of tacit knowledge created in their own international networks.</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Q:</speaker>
<p>Do you think that your work informs the manager in an international company? When all is said and done, what should be done to better facilitate knowledge flows? How do your ideas translate for the manager in the field?</p>
</speech>
<speech>
<speaker>Holden:</speaker>
<p>If things don’t work at the human level in cross-cultural business interactions, the tendency is to attribute clashes and misunderstandings to differences in value systems. This has put businesses and business schools on a false scent for decades. The crucial thing is knowing how to handle knowledge flows across cultural barriers. If you’re no good at that, it can be very costly. For example, mishandling of knowledge flows across cultural barriers will in the long run literally bring an international merger to its knees. This means that the executives in international companies have to think less about knowledge content and more about their and their companies’ style of knowledge sharing. The art lies in recognizing signals and then making sense of them. Easy to say, I know. In simple practical terms the executive should endeavor in his or her cross-cultural business dealings to apply intelligence and tact—tact being a rare ability to size up contexts, deduce what is really important to counterparts, and act accordingly. One thing that is really important is trust, but this concept also varies cross-culturally. Remember that in many countries trust isn’t generated by the power of the brand you represent or the prestige of your corporation. It’s nothing you deserve; it’s what you earn.</p>
</speech>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<bio>
<title>Bios</title>
<p><bold>Jeffrey Gale</bold> is a professor of management and chair of the management department at LMU in Los Angeles where his primary teaching and research are in the areas of strategic management and international strategy. He holds SB and SM degrees from the Sloan School of Management at MIT and a PhD from the Anderson Graduate School of Management at the University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA). In addition, he holds a JD from UCLA and is a member of the California Bar. Prior to joining LMU, he held faculty positions at the University of Washington and the University of Texas at Dallas and has also held visiting appointments at UCLA, Ben-Gurion University in Israel, and Katholieke Universitat in Leuven, Belgium. He has published widely in such journals as <italic>Business in the Contemporary World, European Business and Economic Development, Midwest Review of International Business Research, Policy Studies Journal, Journal of Contemporary Business</italic>, and <italic>Financial Executive</italic> as well as the <italic>Wall Street Journal</italic>. He has been an active consultant on strategy issues for more than two decades and has also served as an outside director in two financial services firms.</p>
<p><bold>Charles M. Vance</bold> is a professor of management and human resources (HR) at Loyola Marymount University (LMU) in Los Angeles, where he has taught at executive, MBA, and undergraduate levels. His research, teaching, and consulting have broadly focused on talent and knowledge management, as well as broader HR issues in the global marketplace. Besides the <italic>Journal of Management Inquiry</italic> (<italic>JMI</italic>), his numerous publications have appeared in such journals as <italic>Academy of Management Learning and Education, Journal of World Business, Human Relations, Journal of Business Ethics</italic>, and <italic>Journal of Small Business Management.</italic> He is coauthor of the current text, <italic>Managing a Global Workforce</italic> (M. E. Sharpe).</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>Reference</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1056492612441394">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Datar</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garvin</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cullen</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Rethinking the MBA: Business education at a crossroads</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Harvard Business Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>