<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">QHR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spqhr</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Qual Health Res</journal-id>
<journal-title>Qualitative Health Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1049-7323</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-7557</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1049732313494119</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1049732313494119</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Thinking Through Every Step: How People With Spinal Cord Injuries Relearn to Walk</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>Meggan M.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049732313494119">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Berkowitz</surname><given-names>Dana</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1049732313494119">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hannold</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1049732313494119">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Velozo</surname><given-names>Craig A.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049732313494119">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Behrman</surname><given-names>Andrea L.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049732313494119">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1049732313494119"><label>1</label>University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1049732313494119"><label>2</label>Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge, Louisiana, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1049732313494119"><label>3</label>Department of Veterans’ Affairs, Gainesville, Florida, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1049732313494119">Meggan M. Jordan, University of Florida Department of Sociology, Criminology, and Law, 3219 Turlington Hall, PO Box 117330, Gainesville, FL 32611, USA. Email: <email>megganjordan@gmail.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>23</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue: Community Care</issue-title>
<fpage>1027</fpage>
<lpage>1041</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>In this article we explore how people with incomplete spinal cord injury (iSCI) create meaning out of their changing bodies as they undergo a therapeutic intervention called locomotor training (LT). Therapeutic interventions like LT are used to promote the recovery of walking ability among individuals with iSCI. The chronological nature of this study—interviews at three points throughout the 12-week intervention—enhances understanding of the recovering self after spinal cord injury. Drawing on a constructivist theoretical framework, we organize data according to three narrative frames. Participants interpreted LT as (a) a physical change that was meaningful because of its social significance, (b) a coping strategy for dealing with the uncertainty of long-term recovery, and (c) a moral strategy to reconstitute the self. We offer findings that lay the conceptual groundwork for generating new knowledge about what is important to people with iSCI as they relearn how to walk.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>constructivism</kwd>
<kwd>disability / disabled persons</kwd>
<kwd>embodiment / bodily experiences</kwd>
<kwd>lived body</kwd>
<kwd>lived experience</kwd>
<kwd>physical therapy</kwd>
<kwd>recovery</kwd>
<kwd>rehabilitation</kwd>
<kwd>spinal cord injury</kwd>
<kwd>symbolic interactionism</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><disp-quote>
<p>What happens to my body happens to my life. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1049732313494119">Frank, 1991</xref>, p. 13)</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Scientific advances in the fields of neuroscience, rehabilitation, and biotechnology have altered our understanding of spinal cord injury. Similarly, the types of injury to the spinal cord have also changed. The diagnosis of incomplete spinal cord injury (iSCI) has become more common as emergency medical care and scientific advances preserve sensory or motor functions below the level of the spinal cord lesion. Additionally, the latest research in spinal cord injury recovery suggests that neural centers that control walking in the body can be activated after repeated practice and training (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1049732313494119">Dietz &amp; Harkema, 2004</xref>). For patients with iSCI, this training—called locomotor training (LT)—has been shown to improve their ability to walk independently, using a treadmill, a body-weight support system, and manual assistance from therapists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1049732313494119">Behrman &amp; Harkema, 2000</xref>). Traditionally, bodily changes during LT are examined from the biomedical perspective of functional mobility. Patients are numerically rated according to criteria such as level of body-weight support required, number of steps taken, walking speed, walking duration, ability to balance, and number of falls.</p>
<p>Groundbreaking research in LT has revealed new knowledge about the nervous system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1049732313494119">Barbeau, Ladouceur, Norman, Pepin &amp; Leroux, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1049732313494119">Edgerton et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1049732313494119">Protas et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-1049732313494119">Wirz, Colombo, &amp; Dietz, 2001</xref>), but less is known about how these scientific advances affect the nexus between a person’s sense of self, his or her body, and his or her everyday surroundings. If medical advancements promise partial recovery from spinal cord injury and rehabilitation interventions aim to improve walking ability, we ask: What do these advancements mean for the ways people with iSCI experience and interpret their embodied selves?</p>
<p>To answer this question, we entered an LT site and asked patients to interpret the meanings of the changes in their bodies. Previous studies have retrospectively examined perceptions of the changed body after iSCI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1049732313494119">Chau et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1049732313494119">Edgerton et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1049732313494119">Hannold, Young, Rittman, &amp; Behrman, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1049732313494119">Nymark et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-1049732313494119">Seymour, 1998</xref>), but few have examined changes occurring during the course of the therapy. We interviewed persons with iSCI (<italic>n</italic> = 5) three times throughout their LT to explore how they told their stories of their changing bodies across a 12-week time period.</p>
<sec id="section1-1049732313494119">
<title>The Context: A New Era for Spinal Cord Injury</title>
<p>Twenty years ago, scientists discovered that an injured spinal cord can recover (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1049732313494119">Barbeau et al., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1049732313494119">Edgerton et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1049732313494119">Harkema et al., 1997</xref>). Incomplete injuries are those in which some muscle movement and feeling are present below the site where the spinal cord injury occurred. Capitalizing on the neuroplasticity of the central nervous system, innovative rehabilitation therapies like LT have been developed to enhance the recovery of walking ability in persons with damage to the cord.</p>
<p>Locomotor training is a type of physical therapy that aims to improve gait velocity, endurance, and functional performance in persons with chronic iSCI. The overall goal for the person undergoing LT is to achieve independent walking at normal speeds without an assistive device (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1049732313494119">Behrman et al., 2005</xref>). This type of training, or intervention, comprises robotically assisting a participant while he or she walks with body-weight support on a treadmill (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1049732313494119">Behrman &amp; Harkema, 2000</xref>). The robotic component of LT involves a gait-driven orthosis that fits over the patient’s legs and is programmed to simulate walking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1049732313494119">Colombo, Joerg, Schreier, &amp; Dietz, 2000</xref>). The orthosis is equipped with a sensor that adjusts based on weak movements generated by the patient’s own body to reproduce motor responses for walking or stepping. LT simulates normal walking speeds and movements as much as possible, and encourages standing, upright posture, coordinated limb movements, independence, and use of unrestrictive assistive devices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1049732313494119">Harkema &amp; Behrman, 2002</xref>). Persons undergoing LT have shown physical and psychosocial benefits that are linked to a renewed sense of identity, and increased confidence and participation in community life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1049732313494119">Behrman et al., 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Despite the promise of new technologies like LT, the experience of spinal cord injury is still fraught with anxieties and ambivalence. To bridge the disconnect between medical advancements and patient experiences, a growing number of researchers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1049732313494119">Angel, Kirkevold, &amp; Pedersen, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1049732313494119">Hammell, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1049732313494119">Kurz, Burke, &amp; Stineman, 2008</xref>) are beginning to focus on “meaningful living” for persons undergoing rehabilitation after injury. Examining patient experiences can reveal meaningful, competent, self-regulated, and satisfying engagement in activities that are consistent with an individual’s sense of self and identity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1049732313494119">Feeney, 2010</xref>). Certainly persons living with spinal cord injury would like researchers to inquire “not only whether the pain they experience is burning or tingling but also about the impact of pain on their lives” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1049732313494119">Hammell, 2010</xref>, p. 1215). The psychosocial impact of the injury is now being considered alongside the plethora of medical and functional problems that follow in the wake of a spinal cord injury (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1049732313494119">Angel, Kirkevold, &amp; Pedersen, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>By attending to the narratives of people relearning how to walk, scholars and practitioners alike can better understand the social ramifications of human resilience. The new era of spinal cord research is ripe for researchers to conceptualize recovery as a matrix of relationships between lived experience, identity, and physical paralysis and the therapies that attempt to lessen it. Our study fits within this new era of research in that we offer a more complete picture of iSCI recovery than clinical or functional principles alone could provide.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1049732313494119">
<title>Theoretical Sensitivity</title>
<p>A symbolic interactionist framework grounded in social constructionism<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1049732313494119">1</xref></sup> informed and guided our research on how people with iSCI experience locomotor therapy. Symbolic interactionists assume that human beings possess the ability to think and imbue their world with meaning. To understand these meanings, sociologists conduct empirical examinations of the relationship of everyday life to everyday knowledge, or how the “[person] on the street” develops, maintains, or transforms his or her reality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1049732313494119">Berger &amp; Luckmann, 1966</xref>). Symbolic interactionism parses through narratives to learn how individuals become cognizant of the practices and attitudes situated in the background of their world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1049732313494119">Habermas, 1981</xref>).</p>
<p>Within the past two decades, symbolic interactionism has become a powerful theoretical tool for understanding the illness experience (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1049732313494119">Charmaz, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1049732313494119">Conrad &amp; Barker, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-1049732313494119">Weitz, 1989</xref>). As medicine paradigmatically shifts toward treating the whole person, illness is not defined simply as a failure in functional mechanics, but a rupture in a person’s ability to negotiate the world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1049732313494119">Leonard, 1994</xref>). Health researchers within the symbolic interactionist tradition have examined how men with spinal cord injury find meaning from physical pain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-1049732313494119">Smith &amp; Sparkes, 2008</xref>), and how people with spinal cord injury frame rehabilitation as a fight for getting on with life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1049732313494119">Angel et al., 2008</xref>). The common objective of constructivist studies is to advance understanding of how patients create meaning from their everyday lives—a crucial component to designing services that meet the needs and preferences of persons with disabilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1049732313494119">Lutz &amp; Bowers, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Different moral, practical, and situational meanings of the self are created when the body relearns how to move after illness. We used the symbolic interactionist perspective to understand how people with iSCI develop their self-images within the context of their interactions with the world during therapy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1049732313494119">Blumer, 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1049732313494119">Mead, 1934</xref>). As critics of the biomedical approach have argued (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-1049732313494119">Rosenfeld &amp; Faircloth, 2004</xref>), a better scientific understanding of the central nervous system does not translate into a better understanding of how the self is healed or transformed. Thus, researchers in the constructivist tradition reveal how the experience of sudden illness or disability is a daily struggle with mundane, everyday tasks.</p>
<p>Radley’s research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-1049732313494119">1989</xref>) on people with coronary heart disease, for example, suggests that the act of relearning everyday tasks after illness is not simply a function of individualized coping, but is instead a socially negotiated process. Moreover, reporting on her ethnography of heart disease, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-1049732313494119">Wheatley (2006)</xref> called the activities carried out after a massive bodily change “reskilling.” Reskilling “requires ongoing efforts to interpret risks and remake the body, to redefine and reinvent the self, and to rearrange social relations and routines” (p. 3). Indeed, reskilling is a symbolically complex process whereby the individual reassesses, regroups, and takes stock of new knowledge about his or her body and the social world.</p>
<p>Although identity reconstruction after disability has been covered widely in the literature on health and illness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1049732313494119">Bury, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1049732313494119">Charmaz, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1049732313494119">Faircloth, Boylstein, Rittman, Young, &amp; Gubrium, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1049732313494119">Kleinman, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1049732313494119">Mattingly &amp; Garro, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-1049732313494119">Reissman, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-1049732313494119">Williams, 1984</xref>), few have applied symbolic interactionism to the process of reskilling, or relearning the body’s basic tasks (like walking), and none have applied it to people with iSCI undergoing locomotor training. In the analysis that follows, we attend to the social processes by which participants assigned meaning to situations, events, others, and themselves as they attempted to move their bodies after spinal cord injury. The meanings that people with iSCI construct are necessary for understanding how these patients conceptualize their sense of disability, recovery, adjustment, reintegration, and embodiment.</p>
<p>In our research we examined how people with iSCI understood an intervention intended to get them “up and walking again” (at least through body-weight support). Using symbolic interactionism as a theoretical lens through which to view the experiences of people with iSCI, we ask the following research question: If medicine can offer partial recovery from spinal cord injury and therapeutic interventions aim to improve walking ability, how do these efforts impact the everyday lives of people with incomplete spinal cord injuries?</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1049732313494119" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<p>Data for this study were gathered in a southern U.S. state from 2007 to 2008 in conjunction with a rehabilitation intervention to promote walking recovery. A state university’s medical institutional review board approved the study in 2007 and reapproved it annually thereafter. We interviewed 5 people with iSCIs throughout a 12-week course of locomotor training to promote walking recovery. Participants were interviewed three times—before therapy, at the midpoint of therapy (6 weeks), and the last day of therapy—for a total of 15 interviews analyzed.</p>
<p>We designed our study to be exploratory in nature. The goal of this study was not to test the outcomes of locomotor training but rather to explore the interplay between transformations of the self and the body for people with iSCI. The application of qualitative research methods enabled us to generate knowledge about this phenomenon. Our strategy for inquiry involved a combination of phenomenological methods, grounded theory analysis, and constructivist theory. Phenomenological methods involve studying a small number of subjects through extensive and prolonged engagement to develop patterns and relationships of meaning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1049732313494119">Moustakas, 1994</xref>). Likewise, phenomenological methods focus on the smallest units of experience that have larger significance for a person’s life, such as walking ability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-1049732313494119">Smith, Larkin, &amp; Flowers, 2009</xref>). Multiple interviews with people undergoing the same activity enhanced analysis and exposed more complex meanings of LT than could be seen in a single time point. The advantage of “small-<italic>N</italic> research” such as ours is the richness observed within the boundaries of a case, allowing us to focus on real-life situations and to analyze experiences and interpretations as they unfold in practice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1049732313494119">Flyvbjerg, 2006</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section4-1049732313494119">
<title>Sample and Recruitment</title>
<p>Participants were recruited through staff at a rehabilitation research center in which ongoing therapeutic interventions with physical therapists were occurring. Staff screened those who met the only study criterion, which was being an active participant in LT (participating in our study was not a requirement for receiving LT therapy, however). The participants were selected based on their willingness to undergo three interviews after their therapy sessions. Given that we were dependent on therapists for recruitment, we could not use theoretical sampling. We obtained informed consent for participation in the study prior to beginning the first interview.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1049732313494119">
<title>Participants</title>
<p>We interviewed 4 men and 1 woman. All participants were White, ranging in age from 45 to 62. Participants were injured as a result of hazardous working conditions, motor vehicle accidents, or bicycle accidents. Time since the injury varied between 1 and 4 years. All injuries were classified as iSCI injuries. All participants were able to perform their activities of daily living to some degree, and 3 had recently acquired car hand controls for driving. An Iraq war veteran, a construction worker, a competitive athlete, and 2 retired police officers were represented.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1049732313494119">2</xref></sup> All 5 traveled from out of town to participate in the training. Two participants arrived at the intervention site in a wheelchair and were using walkers by the end of the 12 weeks; 2 others used wheelchairs throughout the therapy; 1 person rarely used an assistive device. Participants complained of secondary complications of iSCI, such as back pain, lack of bladder control, nerve damage, muscle spasms, blood clots, and lack of sleep. Their goals for the intervention addressed symptomatic (lessening lower back pain), functional (becoming more independent in bathing, showering, and dressing), and expansive (returning to a life of skiing or cross-country travel) concerns.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1049732313494119">
<title>Data Collection</title>
<p>Each interview lasted approximately 1 hour. Interviews were audio recorded and transcribed verbatim. All identifying information was removed in transcription. Pseudonyms are used in this article to protect the participants’ identities. We created three distinct interview guides (see <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-1049732313494119">Appendix A</xref>). During the first interview, participants were asked to talk about their accident, how their life had changed since the event (life activities, job, family, sense of self, social and physical obstacles), goals for therapy, and the importance of these goals to their life at home. The second interview, conducted at the midpoint of their training, was focused on their first day of training, the meaning of the changes in their body, how these changes affected their self-concept, and whether the training so far had met their initial expectations.</p>
<p>The final interview took place on the last day of training. Similar questions from the second interview guide were used, in addition to questions asking participants to reflect on the value of LT to their life, their progress in terms of easier and more difficult aspects of the training, and their assessment of their original goals. The interview questions that were directly rooted in our theoretical framework and provide the scaffolding of this article include: What changes have you seen in your body since our last interview? What do these changes mean to you in your daily life?</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1049732313494119">
<title>Data Analysis</title>
<p>A multidisciplinary team of researchers, comprised of two sociologists, a rehabilitation scientist, an occupational therapist, and a medical anthropologist analyzed the interview data.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1049732313494119">3</xref></sup> Two members of the research team had personal connections to disability: One had muscular dystrophy and another was a cancer survivor. These different perspectives allowed for investigators with different viewpoints to interpret the same data; it is what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1049732313494119">Denzin (1984)</xref> called “investigator triangulation.” Forgoing a single perspective and integrating social psychology, anthropology, and functional outcomes culminated in a richer analysis. Interviewers wrote memos detailing their subjective impressions of the participant’s verbal and nonverbal cues immediately after each interview.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1049732313494119">4</xref></sup> Memos also served as the researchers’ notes for perceived changes between the first, second, and third interviews. This comparison laid the groundwork for developing theoretical connections. We used the NVivo qualitative software package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1049732313494119">QSR International, 2008</xref>) to code and organize the data.</p>
<p>We analyzed the data using a loose adaptation of constructivist grounded theory strategies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1049732313494119">Charmaz, 2006</xref>). We utilized familiar grounded theory techniques such as coding, memoing, and comparative methods to ensure rigor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1049732313494119">Charmaz, 2006</xref>). Our analysis proceeded in three phases. In the initial phase, we coded line by line, giving codes tentative labels that closely matched the participants’ wording; e.g., “getting back [what I lost]” and “my entire life changed.” At this point, we began to develop a loose coding framework, and initial codes were checked using the constant comparative process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1049732313494119">Glaser &amp; Strauss, 1967</xref>) to compare data across participants. When a participant completed three interviews, or a case, we compared data in earlier and later interviews of the same individuals.</p>
<p>Second, we used focused coding to sift through the most significant or frequent initial codes to sort, synthesize, integrate, and organize our data. In this phase we continued the process of creating abstract codes while also making decisions about categorization. Codes with similar themes were housed under more abstract codes, such as “threats to self” for any talk relating to changed identity and roles (both positive and negative). Finally, in the theoretical phase of coding, we organized codes according to a coherent, analytic story, loosely structured around the sections of this article. Although we used these three steps to guide our general coding road map, we admit that the process did not occur in linear, distinct phases; rather, “the picture slowly emerged as a patchwork mosaic” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1049732313494119">Dey, 2003</xref>, p. 86).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1049732313494119">
<title>Findings</title>
<p>Participants in the sample experienced gait improvement in the following areas: endurance, balance, reduced pain, increased strength, and less muscle spasticity. Despite the commonality of these embodied transformations, they had different meanings for each participant. We detail how participants perceived their progress, managed the uncertainty of recovery, and constructed their identity across the 12 weeks of therapy. Because participants’ sense of embodiment was a common thread permeating all narratives, in the analytic story that follows we show how, as <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1049732313494119">Thomas (2002)</xref> observed, the “biological reality of bodies is shaped by and impacts back upon social and environmental practices” (p. 76).</p>
<sec id="section9-1049732313494119">
<title>The Meaning of Movement: Two Stories of Progress</title>
<p>Each participant undergoing LT constructed his or her progress differently. Here we describe two participants’ accounts of their changing bodies from the beginning to the end of their therapy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1049732313494119">Howson, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1049732313494119">Merleau-Ponty, 1958</xref>). We chose these 2 participants because of their different reports of progress: Richard believed that he saw considerable changes in his own body, whereas Lucas characterized his bodily changes as unremarkable. Because participants had very little in common other than a life-changing event that affected their spinal cord, their narratives do not lend themselves to comparison. Instead, we use this descriptive account of two very different experiences in LT to illustrate the individuality and uniqueness that characterized recovery narratives during the training.</p>
<p>Richard, a man in his early 60s, thought he would never walk again after his injury 4 years previously. Through weight training, he developed the use of his arms and hands, and partial use of his legs. He said that his biggest life change was ending his cross-country road trips on a motorcycle. His goal for therapy was “walking normally”—something he viewed as different from “walking fast.” Progress for him materialized in three areas: balance, endurance, and what he called “mechanical walking.” By the second interview, he noted dramatic improvements in all three areas, although he still experienced “toe hits” on the treadmill, which caused him great frustration because he wanted to walk smoothly. These functional abilities translated into meaningful activities in the community. He stated that it was important for him to be able to walk around the mall without feeling tired, and that increased endurance helped him achieve this. By the final interview, he reported that he was able to walk overground from his hotel room to the therapy session without resting. He stated, “Whatever I have to do, I can do it and not get tired anymore; it is a lot like being normal.” This accomplishment was monumental for him in that he could walk without feeling “dead tired,” as he did at the beginning of the intervention.</p>
<p>Lucas, a man in his mid-30s who had lived with the injury for a year, remarked that his biggest life change was the limitation of his interactions with the community. For instance, he could not visit a beach bar with his friends, because he could not wheel on the sand. He set his goals very high at the beginning of the training; he wanted to get on his feet and walk out of the training session by the end. He used phrases like “getting back to normal” and “walking normally,” implying that he saw the intervention as a way to manage the disruption in his life that he experienced by not being able to walk.</p>
<p>By the second interview, he reported that he did not see “that big of an improvement” in his ability to walk, and that he was still coping “with the same crap.” Nevertheless, he said wheelchair transfers and wheeling uphill—activities requiring upper-body strength—seemed easier at that point in the intervention. He reported that this improvement gave him the ability to stand up and hold his balance while using a disability safety bar in the shower. By the third interview, he lamented that he saw no drastic changes in his body (e.g., walking around without an assistive device), but said that the training made it easier for him to move around to complete his activities of daily living. Because of these changes, he made plans to start weight lifting and working out on an exercise bike. He said that the therapy enabled him to get up on his knees and move his body without a struggle, which had a positive impact on his getting a good night’s sleep.</p>
<p>We gain several insights into the recovering self after iSCI through Richard’s and Lucas’ accounts of their changing bodies over the course of 12 weeks in LT. Although they are not long-term-recovery narratives, their stories are snapshots of daily frustrations and accomplishments, illustrating how the management of progress can fluctuate during a short period of time. The men internalized these changes in different ways. Richard believed that his body changed such that the therapy was a major turning point in his life. He remarked,
<disp-quote>
<p>During the past month, I see the end of the tunnel. I see the light there. It is almost done and [I am] reflecting on where I have come to when I first came here to where I am at now.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Because of the changes he witnessed in his body—increased endurance most of all—he ended the intervention on an expansive note: “To get me back into life, I will try doing the things I used to do and enjoy doing.” The intervention made a difference in Richard’s self-concept by expanding possibilities for returning to activities that he previously enjoyed.</p>
<p>Lucas reported more mundane changes that did not appear to greatly alter his perspective on his disability or his future. By claiming that the intervention helped him cope with “the little things in life,” he saw the therapy as more of a warm-up for real recovery than a major turning point. At the beginning, he defined progress as a drastic improvement in walking ability to do the things he wanted to do with his wife, child, or friends. At the end of the intervention, he admitted that he had to lower his expectations for recovery and that this particular intervention was a way to get his body in motion without miraculous results. For him the therapy was not without benefits; LT just delivered them more slowly than he expected. Lucas’ story shows how expectations for progress are constantly negotiated when hopes are initially set very high. Although he witnessed positive outcomes in ease of wheelchair use and ability to transfer his body, these were not up to his standards in how he defined progress. He wanted to play with his child on the playground or have a beer with friends on the beach. Like Richard, Lucas did not want to simply relearn how to walk; he wanted to return to activities that he enjoyed doing before the injury.</p>
<p>Without the certainty of returning to a life of meaningful activities, at minimum LT represented a milestone for returning participants to the sensation—if not the actual promise—of walking. For 3 days a week, participants got up and walked. Whether this routine translated into actual benefits in walking outside the training room varied. Richard’s and Lucas’ differences in age, severity of injury, starting points, and time spent adapting to a new physical habitus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-1049732313494119">Thibodaux, 2005</xref>) shaped their differing attitudes toward their progress in LT. Thus, progress is not a linear concept for persons with iSCI. It is more useful to define progress by the everyday fits and starts, the so-called good days and bad days of daily life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1049732313494119">Charmaz, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1049732313494119">Laskiwski &amp; Morse, 1993</xref>). Nonetheless, the belief that things are progressing, that the body is changing, and that the diagnosis for iSCI is not forever fixed or permanent, are powerful arbitrators between hope and despair (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1049732313494119">Warren &amp; Manderson, 2008</xref>). In this way, the LT intervention is symbolic of a launch pad out of the privacy of the hospital bed and into the public sphere, where potentially life can go on as normal.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1049732313494119">
<title>Managing the Uncertainty of Incomplete Spinal Cord Injury</title>
<p>Researchers have documented that experiencing uncertainty is a persistent characteristic of persons with illness and disability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1049732313494119">Mishel, 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1049732313494119">1999</xref>). People who are ill worry about remission, recurrence, setbacks, exacerbations, and destabilization of health, which prevents them from planning day-to-day events and setting long-term goals. The physiology of iSCI shapes individuals’ attitudes toward long-term recovery. Depending on the location of the injury on the spinal cord, neurological impairments throughout the body can vary from person to person (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1049732313494119">Palmer, Kriegsman, &amp; Palmer, 2000</xref>). The highly personalized nature of the injury is one reason the iSCI recovery and reintegration process does not always follow an orderly pattern (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1049732313494119">Angel et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1049732313494119">Crewe &amp; Zola, 1983</xref>).</p>
<p>Gwen, a woman in her mid-40s who had been living with the injury for 6 months, described the “incomplete” experience:
<disp-quote>
<p>Being incomplete, some people call it both a blessing and a curse. It’s a blessing in the fact that it’s not like “what you see is what you get,” which means being paralyzed from the upper chest down. But the curse is like you don’t know when it’s going to happen, how much you’re going to get back. Some people have my injury and they regain almost everything. And in the [rehabilitation hospital], I saw people that had been injured for longer than me, but they had less return.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Participants realized that uncertainty was a fact of life for this injury, yet felt constrained by their inability to plan for the future. They negotiated the uncertainty of the recovery process in various ways. Some wanted their former lives back and viewed the intervention as their “ticket” to returning to this former life. Others set small-scale goals and reevaluated their priorities in light of setbacks in their therapy experience. All 5 participants dreaded the end of their 12 weeks, expressing sadness that they could not continue. Therapy seemed to give them hope for a more certain future, offering possibilities but not promises.</p>
<p>Spinal cord injuries can present what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1049732313494119">Morse (1997</xref>, p. 28) called “threats to the integrity of the self,” which means that an injury disrupts a person’s life so violently that his or her core identity is compromised or altered in some essential way. Finding comfort in the impermanence of the injury is one way of preserving the self and maintaining a sense of control over the uncontrollable. Some researchers have documented ways patients manage uncertainty to eliminate it (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-1049732313494119">Selder, 1989</xref>), whereas others have proposed that patients integrate the feeling of uncertainty into their everyday lives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1049732313494119">Mishel, 1990</xref>). Our analysis lends support to the latter view, in which people with iSCI shift their values to accommodate new perspectives on life, while their core identities remain intact.</p>
<p>For instance, Earl, a man in his late 40s who had been living with his injury for 6 months, offered the view that the uncertainty of iSCI was not something to be feared, but embraced for its surprises: “I’m glad I got what I got. Because the doctors always told me, ‘You don’t know what will come back. It’s what you want to come back.’ That’s the attitude that I’ve had, and that’s helped me out tremendously.” In a similar vein, the experience of LT helped Richard integrate uncertainty into his life by structuring time so he could make decisions with a clearer head and sharper vision about future possibilities. As for his plans after LT, he said during his third interview,
<disp-quote>
<p>I might even go back to teach. . . . I will cross that bridge when I come to it. I think I am closer to crossing that bridge now than before I got here. I think emotionally I can get back into the flow of society, not just physically, but mentally, whether it is to work or to volunteer my time in the community, or writing. I think I will be more ready to make a decision as to which direction I want to go when I leave here.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Richard drew on the imagery of a bridge to illustrate what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1049732313494119">Becker (1997)</xref> called “living in limbo,” or living in between life chapters. By metaphorically speaking of crossing bridges, or holding off on decisions until after LT, Richard engaged in a biographical reconstruction that was not yet complete. Characterized in this way, uncertainty is a transitory state of being in the world; it is the act of being “suspended in social space” (Becker, p. 119) in which materials are gathered and ideas are considered, yet no permanent structures or edifices are built.</p>
<p>Another strategy participants used to combat uncertainty was to apply experiential knowledge to their new, unfamiliar situation. For example, Gwen saw the immutable aspects of recovery as incompatible with her previous embodied self. During each of the three interviews she dwelled on the uncertain future, yet she also deployed strategies for combating this uncertainty. Attempting to reconcile her training as an athlete with her injury, she described recovery as “fits and starts” instead of a linear progression:
<disp-quote>
<p>I’m used to training as an athlete, [where you] put in a lot of hard work and you get a positive result. And with the spinal cord injury, it’s not like that. It’s almost like you have to wait for the muscles to be ready.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Although her athletic frame of reference was valuable, it was ultimately her Buddhist faith that provided Gwen with a positive certainty about her recovery prospects. Practicing mindfulness prepared her for the mental stamina of “thinking all the time” about her body. She applied this practice to her recovery:
<disp-quote>
<p>As a Buddhist you’re supposed to practice mindfulness . . . and being injured like this, you have to be mindful about everything. You have to rethink. I can remember back to when I was like, “Do I have the strength to turn on the electric toothbrush?” seated in my wheelchair. And it was hard, and I could get it maybe three out of ten times. . . . You have to think through every step. . . . Can I actually just brush my teeth and not worry so much about what are my legs doing?</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Gwen was certain that she would walk again; she just did not know when that day would come. This anxiety over unknown recovery caused Gwen to ask, “How much will I get back and when? Will I max out [stop healing]? How will I know I have reached this point?” She drew on her experiential knowledge as a Buddhist and former athlete to manage her uncertainty as she encountered her new and unfamiliar reality, allowing her to construct a form of practice that was familiar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1049732313494119">Mishel, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-1049732313494119">Selder, 1989</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1049732313494119">
<title>Navigating a Disabled Identity: Physical and Moral Transformations of the Self</title>
<p>In this study we found that participants experienced more than physical outcomes as they progressed through LT. They also processed new perceptions and concepts of self with the aid of comparisons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1049732313494119">Charmaz, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1049732313494119">Noam, 1993</xref>). Participants made sense of their disability in four ways: comparing past and present selves, comparing themselves to others, ranking assistive devices, and assessing their own levels of independence. In other words, participants judged their own progress against other people with similar disabilities and judged their worth according to their perceived independence before the injury. Classifying disability and assistive devices and negotiating help and independence were ways that physical transformation in therapy corresponded to moral transformation of the self. For people with iSCI undergoing LT in particular, their interpretations of therapy assumed a moral dimension as they reconciled old selves to launch new identities.</p>
<sec id="section12-1049732313494119">
<title>Memories of former selves</title>
<p>We found that the old adage “Time heals all wounds” was highly variable for people with iSCI. Participants’ prospects for recovery were shaped by memories of their former selves. For some, talk of “what I was like before the injury” often provoked sorrow and anger; they felt like a reset button had been pushed on their lives. For example, Gwen shared the following:
<disp-quote>
<p>It’s like you’re mourning a loss in terms of what you once could do. And I did get emotional yesterday, shopping at [the grocery store], being so excited that I could do it with a quad-cane, whereas a year ago now, I wouldn’t have even thought about going grocery shopping as being a big deal. So it’s like you can see, like, “Wow, I’ve progressed a lot.” It’s also that kind of looking back, and going, “Yeah, but I’ve lost a lot too.”</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Gwen’s observations intersect with themes of constructing progress and managing uncertainty. Narratives of time in life postinjury move in a recursive loop between remembering the past self and grappling with an uncertain future recovery. These narratives shape the perceptions of progress in the present (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-1049732313494119">Sparkes &amp; Smith, 2003</xref>). Gwen illustrated how past, present, and future were conflated when waiting in the “holding room” of recovery. She suggested that sometimes the only stability of iSCI was the feeling of loss entwined with the accomplishment of survival.</p>
<p>Memories of a former, healthier self destabilized a clean break with illness that recovery implies. The basic storyline of the restitution narrative, or how we tell stories about health in Western culture—“Yesterday I was healthy, today I’m sick, but tomorrow I’ll be healthy again” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1049732313494119">Frank, 1995</xref>, p. 77)—is problematic for people with illness. Our analysis suggests that the restitution narrative is too neat and linear to accurately describe the realities of iSCI. Lucas, for example, struggled with the prospect that “tomorrow, I’ll be healthy again.” He remarked that no matter how much “return” he received from therapy, the memory of his uninjured body would forever haunt him. He offered a metaphor to convey the experience of living in a body that had been permanently altered:
<disp-quote>
<p>Say you broke three of your fingers, but they healed up. But one of them is crooked. There’s no way to get a ring on it. Say it was your wedding ring on your finger. How would you feel about that? Even though your whole body’s normal, except that one finger, what are you going to think about every day? And what are you going to do for the rest of your life when you look at your hands? You’re gonna know that . . . that one finger pissed me off [made me angry] to no end. And that’s how it is.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Lucas’ metaphor gives textured nuance to the idea of recovery. Living with the memory of a former self, with the changed body as a constant trigger for that memory, evokes anger.</p>
<p>Not all participants described themselves as changed in this way. For example, Nelson and Earl distanced themselves from their bodies and the raw emotions that memories could bring to the surface. Earl rejected the idea that the injury had changed his core self in any meaningful way: “I’ve always felt the same. I haven’t changed. Just because my body’s changed doesn’t mean my mindset has changed.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1049732313494119">5</xref></sup> Earl’s sentiments mirror findings from research conducted on men with spinal cord injury who struggled to convince society that “their bodies were changed, but not their minds nor their identities” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1049732313494119">Laskiwski &amp; Morse, 1993</xref>, p. 146). Our analysis reveals the extent to which the prospects for letting go of a former body and self varied among the 5 participants. Ultimately, it is unpredictability—time’s inability to heal and a person’s inability to control results—that makes grappling with life after spinal cord injury all the more challenging.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1049732313494119">
<title>Comparisons to others</title>
<p>We also found that people with iSCI frequently compared themselves to other people with spinal cord injury (or those disabled after an accident as opposed to those who were disabled because of degenerative or congenital conditions). Participants spoke of people who were “totally disabled,” and often reminded the interviewer that they themselves were functioning far higher than this level. Whenever participants compared themselves to others, they usually referenced people whom they had met in rehabilitation hospitals immediately following their injury. Some participants shared that when they woke up in the hospital, they were told that they would never walk again, and others expressed anguish about how they felt when they were told they would be paralyzed from the chest down. Despite these predictions, however, none of the participants in the LT program actually ended up with the diagnosis of complete tetraplegia. Participants were proud that they were more mobile than the doctors had anticipated.</p>
<p>Gwen, a competitive athlete, positioned herself as privileged compared to the people with disabilities she encountered in the hospital: “You’re in a hospital like that, and no matter how much you think your life sucks [is terrible], look at somebody who can’t eat food, has a machine breathing for them. It’s almost like, ‘What am I complaining about?’” She expressed that she never felt like she belonged at the inpatient rehabilitation hospital, describing the culture of that space as catering to those with complete spinal cord injuries. She stressed how the LT study was “much more to what [she] was interested in, which was walking.” Gwen described the LT therapy as a “partnership,” a conception that she contrasted with the controlling environment of inpatient rehabilitation. She appreciated how the therapists allowed her to make her own decisions in the training room, such as whether to loosen or tighten certain straps on the gait orthoses (the robotic legs that fit over the patient’s legs). She excitedly described LT as a “meeting of the minds” in which her athletic experience and their walking expertise resulted in a regimen that did not involve “teaching [her] to sit well in a chair.”</p>
<p>Participants often reaffirmed and challenged differences between people with disabilities—a phenomenon that became apparent when they compared incomplete and complete spinal cord injury. Richard offered an inclusive explanation for the diversity among people with spinal cord injury:
<disp-quote>
<p>It’s like a snowflake. No two snowflakes are alike. It is like that with this injury. You talk to some people with [a spinal cord injury], and they broke their neck at the same exact location as you and they can walk just fine, but they have no use of their hands, their shoulders, and their arms. And then you have other people who have the complete opposite . . . no two injuries are alike. But I am able to empathize with them, because I have a pretty good idea what they are going through. Because regardless of what your injury is, I would say for the first six months, they are all pretty much alike.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Richard alluded to the uniqueness of every injury and how all persons with spinal cord injury struggle with the same issues (up to a point). Richard’s metaphor for spinal cord injury as a “snowflake” was more inclusive than a strict ranking of the body’s functional potential. However, Richard still placed value on bodies that recover faster. According to him, physical similarities decreased between people with spinal cord injury as they regained function at vastly different points along a spectrum of bodily ability.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1049732313494119">
<title>Ranking assistive devices</title>
<p>Participants’ use of assistive devices also changed throughout the intervention and influenced the way they judged their own impairment. Although none who finished therapy abandoned assistive devices altogether, many moved from wheelchairs to walkers to crutches to canes. Participants benchmarked their progress based on a hierarchy of assistive devices. They saw themselves as making progress whenever they moved up the hierarchy, away from using wheelchairs and toward using canes. A powered wheelchair lingered at the bottom of the hierarchy, because loss of arm movement implied total dependence.</p>
<p>Gwen was proud of the fact that she kept her power wheelchair in a dusty corner of her garage. Nurses encouraged her to use the wheelchair because she could go places without getting tired. She resisted this idea and, after consulting her therapists in the LT program, decided to “move up” to a walker with wheels. Although she valued her walker more than the power chair, she still felt ambivalence toward using any assistive device. She described her device as a “little old lady walker”—something she would rather not use, although it helped her walk better on uneven surfaces.</p>
<p>Gwen also remarked that, as a petite woman, the difference between a walker and a wheelchair had subtle repercussions for power and perception. To her, a walker was better than a wheelchair because she regained her height. In the chair, she noted that people literally talked down to her, affecting how other people saw her. Maintaining level eye contact was important to Gwen’s status as a competent adult and her ability to resist infantilization by others in public. That a walker would rank higher than a wheelchair makes sense in the context of her life; it also highlights how an individual’s symbolic definition of progress can stand in complete contrast to existing physician-centered labels. Participants felt the need to justify their choices as they wrestled with these dilemmas throughout the 12 weeks of LT. At the same time, they conjured new images of themselves as they became more aware of how others viewed them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1049732313494119">Cooley, 1902</xref>). Finding the best assistive device was not just about selecting from an array of medical products; it involved a political dance, selecting new images of disability and discarding tired stereotypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1049732313494119">Charmaz &amp; Rosenfeld, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>Participants often looked to LT as a tool, however minor, that might aid in realignment between the body and the self. The strategy of locating one’s status via assistive devices emerged when Lucas managed his expectations for progress in therapy:
<disp-quote>
<p>I’ve only got four weeks left. I’m on the halfway mark now. Yeah, I’ve improved, but not to where my expectations were. I thought I wouldn’t be in a wheelchair at four and a half weeks;<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1049732313494119">6</xref></sup> I thought I’d be on a walker every day and dependent on a walker, and then the next four and a half weeks I’d be on my feet walking like normal. Like with a cane or something. Those were my expectations coming here. But now . . . I’m at the halfway mark and I’m still in my wheelchair, you know?</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Lucas’ language about being in a wheelchair was an important political distinction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1049732313494119">Iezzoni, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr82-1049732313494119">Zola, 1991</xref>). Researchers have noted how the wheelchair has its own ontology to reveal how people incorporate it into their lives. This ontology involves “using” the chair, acting “from” the chair, or, as Lucas stated, being “in the chair” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1049732313494119">Papadimitriou, 2010</xref>). Lucas used a metaphor of confinement to suggest being controlled by the chair rather than controlling it himself as an active wheelchair user. The phrase suggests the beginning stages of the re-embodiment process for adjusting to life as a wheelchair user.</p>
<p>Indeed, Lucas’ antipathy toward the chair makes sense because a wheelchair has complex meanings in our culture: It is a vehicle of freedom and independence, but a symbol that degrades, demotes, and devalues users in public settings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1049732313494119">Papadimitriou, 2010</xref>). For a patient with a spinal cord injury who has been immobile for a long time, however, the wheelchair might become a liberating device at the top of the hierarchy. Hence, the constructions of physical disability and attitudes toward assistive devices are dependent on where people locate themselves in a spectrum of bodily control.</p>
<p>In summary, participants talked frequently of the desire to move up the scale, so to speak, from one assistive device to the next, and as far away from wheelchairs as possible. LT was viewed as the ultimate liberating “device.” Even though the robotic prosthesis was more artificial and imposing than a wheelchair, it allowed people to return to the feeling of walking. Upright walking is a value judgment that constructs our attitudes toward assistive devices, classifies bodies, and privileges independence in our culture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1049732313494119">Cole, 2004</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1049732313494119">
<title>Negotiating help and independence</title>
<p>In addition to constructing progress via comparison to others with spinal cord injury and assistive devices, participants were also heavily invested in the process of negotiating their own help and independence. Independence meant different things to the participants; they mentioned independence in tandem with the ability to defend themselves in public, lift heavy items, pump gas, help with chores at home, and drive themselves to therapy sessions. For all of the participants, a meaningful dimension of their loss of independence was how it changed their interactions and relationships with friends and family (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1049732313494119">Hammell, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1049732313494119">Kleiber, Brock, Lee, Dattilo, &amp; Caldwell, 1995</xref>).</p>
<p>For some, LT supported the ability to present a competent, imposing persona in public. For example, an important goal for Richard was to be able to trust himself with a firearm. By the third interview, he jubilantly expressed that the biggest change in the training was his endurance, which he said helped him “deal with the unexpected.” The therapy gave him so much confidence in his walking that by the last interview, he vowed to go to the shooting range and start carrying a gun again. Stories from the men in the sample are typical of the process by which men with spinal cord injury reappropriate a culturally normative idea of masculine behavior to fit their postinjury identities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1049732313494119">Gerschick &amp; Miller, 1995</xref>). Male participants wrestled with the hegemonic ideal of physical strength that constitutes independence. For the most part, they saw LT as a tool for recovering the independence that they had lost; no one attempted to redefine dependence as a positive quality for a man to possess.</p>
<p>Finally, the LT site itself was a space for reclaiming lost independence. All of the participants traveled long distances to attend the immersive training, voluntarily leaving their families behind. Two stayed in hotels by themselves, 2 drove in from at least an hour away, and 1 traveled across the country but stayed with a relative. Hence, participants revealed a sense of satisfaction for completing a complicated task on their own. Several participants treated the time as if it were a retreat away from a life of dependence. Richard said,
<disp-quote>
<p>My wife could stay here the entire time with me, but I don’t want her to. I want to be on my own; I want to sink or swim. If I sink, then I sink, but I want to do it on my own.</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The training room created a positive space for him, where he could envision his potential for recovery. This finding is similar to other research that revealed how practitioners attempt to “give space to suffering” by actively stopping their professional interventions and allowing people to reach their personal limits and the frustrations that follow (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-1049732313494119">Struhkamp, 2005</xref>).</p>
<p>Ironically, participants characterized the world outside the intervention as more frustrating than the world inside it. Lucas stated that he did not want his family with him during training because it was his time to get better. Likewise, Richard enjoyed LT because his old, familiar environment only reminded him of what he could not do. Participants appreciated their time alone in new surroundings, expressing trepidation about returning to a world where they could be reminded of their weaknesses.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1049732313494119" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>This qualitative, constructivist, and phenomenological study explored the meanings that advancements in therapeutic interventions had for people with incomplete spinal cord injuries. Analyzing the stories of 5 participants currently enrolled in a therapeutic intervention designed to improve walking ability allowed us to draw several broad conclusions about the way such interventions are socially interpreted. First, profound bodily changes after injury made everyday routines problematic for the participants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1049732313494119">Dyck, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-1049732313494119">Smith, 1987</xref>). For people with disabilities, walking is not a heroic obstacle to overcome, but rather part of the daily struggle with mundane tasks through which identity is expressed and confirmed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1049732313494119">Locker, 1983</xref>).</p>
<p>More complicated was the fact that all 5 participants in our study believed firmly in LT’s therapeutic benefits. Specific healing ideologies embedded in LT might explain this fervor. Therapists use LT to take advantage of principles of neuroplasticity, which maintain that nerves can recover and/or regenerate through repetitive use or movement. Accordingly, participants began to restructure their lives around the concept of recovery through walking. Unlike other rehabilitation programs that encourage adaptation to a disability or feeling empowered in a wheelchair, LT has a specific restitution narrative with walking as its central focus. The therapy is prized in that patients actually walk on a treadmill, allowing them to revel in the feeling of inhabiting an upright body. Some have not felt this sensation in years. Just as the cultural uses of walking are metaphors of strength, power, and autonomy, upright posture allows for a presentation of self that can transform the character of lived space (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1049732313494119">Cole, 2004</xref>). For people with iSCI in this study, walking was contextualized by the setbacks and surprises from attempting to reclaim a lost power. Participants were fully invested in returning to the sensation of walking and all the emotions, gestures, and social benefits that accompany it.</p>
<p>Second, our findings reveal how people with iSCI construct their embodied progress through comparing themselves to people with complete spinal cord injury and use their assistive devices as symbols to mirror their progress. Participants lived on the margins between disability and the able-bodied world, dedicated to the possibilities of returning to the activities they enjoyed doing prior to injury. Hoping to return to full activity did not mean living in denial, but it did mean believing that technology (i.e., LT) was on their side, so to speak, to improve their lives. Participants reacted negatively to traditional rehabilitation programs that did not allow them to relearn how to walk, asserting that these therapies overlooked their potential for reclaiming movement and independence.</p>
<p>During the therapy participants lived tethered to a cogent ideology of recovery. Packaged within this were beliefs about their own high standards for healing. Participants prided themselves on completing grueling workouts and believed that LT perfectly matched their goals. In their view, LT was an elite therapy that provided value for those who, like themselves, existed between paralysis and movement. Given that participants conceptualized LT as a therapy for “people interested in walking,” we believe that LT aids in the creation of a unique identity for people with iSCIs.</p>
<p>Third, participants’ independence and its inextricable link to walking was another mode for making sense of a changed world. Participants were more satisfied with their LT experience when it was conceived as a moral transformation—not merely a contest to win as much independence as they could, but as a space to meditate on the possibilities for new selves, reconfiguring independence on their own terms. Fourth, the act of carving out a new identity by comparing one’s own abilities to another person’s creates a power dilemma that LT is ill-equipped to resolve. Our findings highlight the extent to which participants internalized the indexes used by rehabilitation scientists (such as the Index of Activities of Daily Living by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1049732313494119">Katz, Downs, Cash, &amp; Grotz, 1970</xref>). People tend to classify their own level of impairment and measure themselves against ideals and expectations of cultural norms. However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1049732313494119">Deal (2003)</xref> warned that disability classifications, reified through biomedicine, result in the lowest-ranked people becoming “even more vulnerable to the vagaries of social policy without the support of those who should be their comrades and defenders” (p. 907). In other words, the social distance between people with incomplete and complete injuries might be exacerbated by ideologies in LT that narrowly construct bodily ability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-1049732313494119">Wendell, 1996</xref>).</p>
<p>We advance understanding of how people with iSCI talk about their changing bodies in relation to what they know, or how their reality is maintained and legitimized (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1049732313494119">Berger &amp; Luckmann, 1966</xref>). Data indicate that this reality was maintained by reconciling uncertain recovery, finding meaningful social benchmarks for functional progress, and positioning status toward cultural values of independence. Narratives of progress, uncertainty, and disability were the building blocks for long-term-recovery narratives. For some participants, recovery was characterized by identity transformation: accepting their limitations and reformulating their old life into a new one. For others, recovery was functional and mundane: dependent on the day-to-day fluctuations in the body and its ability to maneuver in the community. In a sense, participants undergoing LT found themselves at a crossroads in which passive rehabilitation services were transformed into active, fluid projects on the self.</p>
<sec id="section17-1049732313494119">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>Our findings should be viewed in light of their limitations, the most obvious of which is the small sample size. The participants were unique in that they were highly motivated, persistent, and more than willing to commit to a physically demanding 12-week time period. Conclusions could have been different if we had focused on patients who were unable to commit to these demands (such as those who had dropped out of the intervention or those who rejected the idea of rehabilitation altogether). Different conclusions could also have been reached if we had interviewed people with spinal cord injuries who were not newly disabled, particularly those who could offer a longitudinal view on the positive changes disability had on their lives. Because no data were collected beyond the third interview, we cannot make conclusions about the effects on patients’ lives weeks, months, or years after completion of the therapeutic intervention. Follow-up research is needed to determine if our findings still accurately reflect people’s experiences years after the LT program.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section18-1049732313494119">
<title>Implications for Clinical Practice</title>
<p>The study has practical implications for rehabilitation programs in that we offer data that bolster the need to situate changes within the therapy room for contexts outside of it. If a patient says he or she feels, for example, more tone in his or her feet, this physical experience has a social component that impacts the individual at home or in the community. The tone might mean difficulty using public transportation, sleeping, or doing housework. Patients talk about their bodies cohered to their surroundings, not segregated from them. Hence, progress toward recovery becomes meaningful insofar as people can do the things that are important to them in their everyday lives. Even focusing on a relatively narrow aspect of spinal cord injury rehabilitation—gait—has larger implications beyond the purely functional aspects of walking. Relearning how to walk is linked to forming closer ties with friends, spending less time on personal care, and feeling safer in public.</p>
<p>The question for any new medical advancement in alleviating iSCI should not be, “Does this new therapy restore function for people with spinal cord injury?” The question should be, “How do patients interpret the results from these new therapies?” Capturing the process of creating meaning from physical changes can bridge the gap between the clinician’s measured functional performance and the social meaning of that performance. These findings, however exploratory, can be used to improve patient-centered rehabilitation research and program development.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<app-group>
<app id="app1-1049732313494119">
<title>Appendix A</title>
<sec id="section19-1049732313494119">
<title>Sample Questions From Interview Guides</title>
<p>Interview 1 (Before training/intervention)</p>
<list id="list1-1049732313494119" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Could you tell me about your spinal cord injury (how/when did it happen, what happened after that, rehabilitation)? How has your life changed since the injury?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>What things have been the most problematic for you since your spinal cord injury?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>How do these problems/issues affect you on a daily basis?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>What do you know about locomotor training? What are your concerns about the intervention?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>What do you hope to accomplish through locomotor training? What is the most important change you hope to accomplish through this intervention?</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Interview 2 (Midpoint of training/intervention)</p>
<list id="list2-1049732313494119" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>Describe for me what your first day of locomotor training was like.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>What aspects of the training have been easiest for you? What aspects have you found to be the most difficult?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>What changes have you noticed since the beginning of training? What are you able to do now that you weren’t able to do before starting the training? What changes have been the most important to you so far?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>How has your participation in locomotor training affected the way you feel about yourself? How has it affected your family members?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>What do you hope to accomplish during the rest of your training?</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Interview 3 (End of training/intervention)</p>
<list id="list3-1049732313494119" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>How has your understanding of locomotor training changed since our last interview? What changes have you noticed since our last interview? What changes have been the most important to you during this time period?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>How will you continue to carry over what you have learned and accomplished through training into your daily life?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>How has your participation in locomotor training affected your family members since our last interview?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>What do you value the most about participating in locomotor training? What did you enjoy the most?</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>How have your accomplishments in locomotor training matched your expectations?</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
</app>
</app-group>
<ack>
<p>We thank Jini Hanjian, Mary Joe Roach, Craig Boylstein, and Charles Gattone, who assisted us in the development of this project. We also thank the participants, who patiently answered our questions and warmly opened their homes and hotels to us.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: A Veterans Affairs Rehabilitation Research and Development grant provided the funds to pay project staff, purchase equipment, and develop this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1049732313494119">
<label>1.</label>
<p>We use symbolic interactionism as an umbrella theory to encompass social constructivism more specifically. We understand that constructivism and symbolic interactionism have different theoretical histories, but we use them interchangeably here. To be more precise, whenever the term <italic>constructivist framework</italic> is used, we mean that the participants’ knowledge is the product of social practices. This framework recognizes how credentialed knowledge of biomedicine is, in principle, no different from the everyday common sense knowledge of patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-1049732313494119">Young, 2008</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1049732313494119">
<label>2.</label>
<p>In accordance with institutional review board requirements, general occupation descriptions are intentional. We wish to ensure the confidentiality of participants.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1049732313494119">
<label>3.</label>
<p>Author contributions to this article are as follows: Meggan Jordan collected and analyzed data and wrote the majority of this article; Dana Berkowitz worked on data collection, data analysis, and writing; Elizabeth Hannold offered qualitative methods consultation and data analysis advice; Craig Velozo wrote the original grant for this project; and Andrea Behrman provided the space in which the locomotor training took place.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1049732313494119">
<label>4.</label>
<p>The two sociologists on the team conducted the interviews and wrote the memos.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-1049732313494119">
<label>5.</label>
<p>Notably, Earl was different from other participants in both the content and delivery of his narrative. His answers to interview questions were curt, and he did not open up to us about vulnerabilities or weaknesses. Boundless optimism (“I know I can do it. There ain’t a doubt in my mind. I know I can do it. Ain’t no ‘can’t.’”) was all that he chose to reveal during the interviews.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-1049732313494119">
<label>6.</label>
<p>The participant was a little bit beyond half-way through the program at the time of this interview. He had completed 8 weeks of therapy and had 4 more weeks to go. He was dividing those completed 8 weeks in half, with milestones at 4 weeks (for ending wheelchair use) and 4 weeks (for walking normally). He might have been lumping time together in half-week stages because training days only took place 3 days a week.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Author Biographies</title>
<p><bold>Meggan M. Jordan</bold>, PhD, is a postdoctoral fellow at the University of Florida in Gainesville, Florida, USA.</p>
<p><bold>Dana Berkowitz</bold>, PhD, is an assistant professor at Louisiana State University in Baton Rouge, Louisiana, USA.</p>
<p><bold>Elizabeth Hannold</bold>, PhD, is a rehabilitation health scientist at the Department of Veterans’ Affairs in Gainesville, Florida, USA.</p>
<p><bold>Craig A. Velozo</bold>, PhD, OTR/L, is a professor and associate chair at the University of Florida in Gainesville, Florida, USA.</p>
<p><bold>Andrea L. Behrman</bold>, PT, PhD, FAPTA, is an associate professor at the University of Florida in Gainesville, Florida, USA.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Angel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kirkevold</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Rehabilitation as a fight: A narrative case study of the first year after a spinal cord injury</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Qualitative Studies on Health and Well-being</source>, <volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>28</fpage>-<lpage>38</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17482620802393724</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Angel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kirkevold</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Getting on with life following a spinal cord injury: Regaining meaning through six phases</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Qualitative Studies on Health and Well-being</source>, <volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>39</fpage>-<lpage>50</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17482620802393492</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Barbeau</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ladouceur</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pepin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leroux</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Walking after spinal cord injury: Evaluation, treatment, and functional recovery</article-title>. <source>Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation</source>, <volume>80</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>225</fpage>-<lpage>235</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0003-9993(99)90126-0</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <source>Disrupted lives: How people create meaning in a chaotic world</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Behrman</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harkema</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Locomotor training after human spinal cord injury: A series of case studies</article-title>. <source>Physical Therapy</source>, <volume>80</volume>(<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>688</fpage>-<lpage>700</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2522/ptj.20070315</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Behrman</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lawless-Dixon</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bowden</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Phadke</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harkema</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Locomotor training progression and outcomes after incomplete spinal cord injury</article-title>. <source>Physical Therapy</source>, <volume>85</volume>(<issue>12</issue>), <fpage>1356</fpage>-<lpage>1371</lpage>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.physicaltherapyjournal.com/content/85/12/1356.full">http://www.physicaltherapyjournal.com/content/85/12/1356.full</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Luckmann</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1966</year>). <source>The social construction of reality: A treatise on the sociology of knowledge</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Anchor Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Blumer</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1969</year>). <source>Symbolic Interactionism: Perspective and method</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bury</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>). <article-title>Chronic illness as biographical disruption</article-title>. <source>Sociology of Health &amp; Illness</source>, <volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>167</fpage>-<lpage>182</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1467-9566.ep11339939</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Charmaz</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>Good days, bad days: The self in chronic illness and time</source>. <publisher-loc>New Brunswick, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rutgers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Charmaz</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Stories of suffering: Subjective tales and research narratives</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Health Research</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>362</fpage>-<lpage>382</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/104973239900900306</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Charmaz</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Constructing grounded theory</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Charmaz</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rosenfeld</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Reflections of the body, images of self: Visibility and invisibility in chronic illness and disability</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Waskul</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vannnini</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Body/embodiment: Symbolic interaction and the sociology of the body</source> (pp. <fpage>35</fpage>-<lpage>50</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Burlington, VT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chau</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hegedus</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Praamsma</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tsukada</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Renwick</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Women living with a spinal cord injury: Perceptions about their changed bodies</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Health Research</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>209</fpage>-<lpage>221</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1049732307312391</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>Still lives: Narratives of spinal cord injury</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Joerg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schreier</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dietz</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Treadmill training of paraplegic patients using a robotic orthosis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Rehabilitation Research and Development</source>, <volume>37</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>693</fpage>-<lpage>700</lpage>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11321005">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11321005</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Conrad</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>K. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>The social construction of illness: Key insights and policy implications</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health and Social Behavior</source>, <volume>51</volume>(<supplement>Suppl. 1</supplement>), <fpage>S67</fpage>-<lpage>S79</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0022146510383495</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cooley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1902</year>). <source>Human nature and the social order</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Scribner’s</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Crewe</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zola</surname><given-names>I. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.). (<year>1983</year>). <source>Independent living for physically disabled people</source>. <publisher-loc>Lincoln, NE</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>People with Disabilities Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Disabled people’s attitudes toward other impairment groups: A hierarchy of impairments</article-title>. <source>Disability &amp; Society</source>, <volume>18</volume>(<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>897</fpage>-<lpage>910</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0968759032000127317</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Denzin</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <source>The research act</source>. <publisher-loc>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice Hall</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Grounded theory</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Seale</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gobo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gubrium</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Qualitative research practice</source> (pp. <fpage>80</fpage>-<lpage>93</lpage>). <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dietz</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harkema</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Locomotor activity in spinal cord-injured persons</article-title>. <source>Journal of Applied Physiology</source>, <volume>95</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>1954</fpage>-<lpage>1960</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/japplphysiol.00942.2003</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dyck</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Hidden geographies: The changing lifeworlds of women with multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Social Science &amp; Medicine</source>, <volume>40</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>307</fpage>-<lpage>320</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0277-9536(94)E0091-6</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Edgerton</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hodgson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Prober</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Guzman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>de Leon</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>A physiological basis for the development of rehabilitative strategies for spinally injured patients</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Paraplegia Society</source>, <volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>150</fpage>-<lpage>157</lpage>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/1683668">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/1683668</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Faircloth</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boylstein</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rittman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gubrium</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Sudden illness and biographical flow in narratives of stroke recovery</article-title>. <source>Sociology of Health &amp; Illness</source>, <volume>26</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>242</fpage>-<lpage>261</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-9566.2004.00388.x</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feeney</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>There’s always something that works: Principles and practices of positive support for individuals with traumatic brain injury and problem behaviors</article-title>. <conf-name>Seminars in Speech and Language</conf-name>, <volume>31</volume>(<issue>03</issue>), <fpage>145</fpage>-<lpage>161</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0030-1257531</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Flyvbjerg</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Five misunderstandings about case-study research</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Inquiry</source>, <volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>219</fpage>-<lpage>245</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1077800405284363</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>A. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>At the will of the body: Reflections on illness</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Houghton Mifflin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>A. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <source>The wounded storyteller: Body, illness, and ethics</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gerschick</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Coming to terms: Masculinity and physical disability</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Sabo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Men’s health and illness</source> (pp. <fpage>183</fpage>-<lpage>204</lpage>). <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>B. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1967</year>). <source>The discovery of grounded theory: Strategies for qualitative research</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Aldine</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Habermas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <source>The theory of communicative action</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Beacon Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hammell</surname><given-names>K. R. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Quality of life after spinal cord injury: A meta-synthesis of qualitative findings</article-title>. <source>Spinal Cord</source>, <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>124</fpage>-<lpage>139</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.sc.3101992</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hammell</surname><given-names>K. R. W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Spinal cord injury rehabilitation research: Patient priorities, current deficiencies, and potential directions</article-title>. <source>Disability and Rehabilitation</source>, <volume>32</volume>(<issue>14</issue>), <fpage>1209</fpage>-<lpage>1219</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09638280802627694</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hannold</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rittman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Behrman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Locomotor training: Experiencing the changing body</article-title>. <source>Journal of Rehabilitation Research and Development</source>, <volume>43</volume>(<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>905</fpage>-<lpage>916</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1682/JRRD.2005.07.0122</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Harkema</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Behrman</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Locomotor training principles and practice</source>. <publisher-loc>Los Angeles</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Robomedica</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Harkema</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hurley</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>U. K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Requejo</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dobkin</surname><given-names>B. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Edgerton</surname><given-names>V. R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Human lumbosacral spinal cord interprets loading during stepping</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source>, <volume>77</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>797</fpage>-<lpage>811</lpage>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jn.physiology.org/content/77/2/797.long">http://jn.physiology.org/content/77/2/797.long</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Howson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <source>The body in society: An introduction</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Polity</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Iezzoni</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <source>When walking fails: Mobility problems of adults with chronic conditions</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Downs</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cash</surname><given-names>H. R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grotz</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1970</year>). <article-title>Progress in development of the index of ADL</article-title>. <source>Gerontologist</source>, <volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>, <supplement>Part 1</supplement>), <fpage>20</fpage>-<lpage>30</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/geront/10.1_Part_1.20</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kleiber</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brock</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dattilo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Caldwell</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>The relevance of leisure in an illness experience: Realities of spinal cord injury</article-title>. <source>Journal of Leisure Research</source>, <volume>27</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>283</fpage>-<lpage>299</lpage>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.calvin.edu/~yl33/documents/Relevanceofleisureinanillnessexp95.pdf">http://www.calvin.edu/~yl33/documents/Relevanceofleisureinanillnessexp95.pdf</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kleinman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <source>The illness narratives: Suffering, healing, and the human condition</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basic Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kurz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stineman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Exploring the personal reality of disability and recovery: A tool for empowering the rehabilitation process</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Health Research</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>90</fpage>-<lpage>105</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1049732307309006</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Laskiwski</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morse</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>The spinal cord injured patient: The modification of hope and expressions of despair</article-title>. <source>Canadian Journal of Rehabilitation</source>, <volume>6</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>143</fpage>-<lpage>153</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>A Heideggerian phenomenologic perspective on the concept of a person</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Benner</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Ed.), <source>Interpretive phenomenology</source> (pp. <fpage>43</fpage>-<lpage>64</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Newbury Park, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Locker</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <source>Disability and disadvantage: The consequences of chronic illness</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Tavistock</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bowers</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Disability in everyday life</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Health Research</source>, <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>1037</fpage>-<lpage>1054</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1049732305278631</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Mattingly</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garro</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.). (<year>2000</year>). <source>Narrative and the cultural construction of illness and healing</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mead</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1934</year>). <source>Mind, self, and society</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Merleau-Ponty</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1958</year>). <source>Phenomenology of perception</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mishel</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Uncertainty in illness</article-title>. <source>Journal of Nursing Scholarship</source>, <volume>20</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>225</fpage>-<lpage>232</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1547-5069.1988.tb00082.x</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mishel</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Reconceptualization of the uncertainty in illness theory</article-title>. <source>Image: Journal of Nursing Scholarship</source>, <volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>256</fpage>-<lpage>262</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1547-5069.1990.tb00225.x</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mishel</surname><given-names>M. H.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Uncertainty in chronic illness</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Nursing Research</source>, <volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>269</fpage>-<lpage>294</lpage>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/springer/arnr/1999/00000017/00000001/art00012">http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/springer/arnr/1999/00000017/00000001/art00012</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Morse</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Responding to threats to integrity of self</article-title>. <source>Advances in Nursing Science</source>, <volume>19</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>21</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journals.lww.com/advancesinnursingscience/Abstract/1997/06000/Responding_to_Threats_to_Integrity_of_Self.3.aspx">http://journals.lww.com/advancesinnursingscience/Abstract/1997/06000/Responding_to_Threats_to_Integrity_of_Self.3.aspx</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Moustakas</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <source>Phenomenological research methods</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Noam</surname><given-names>G. G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Normative vulnerabilities of self and their transformations in moral action</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Noam</surname><given-names>G. G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wren</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>The moral self</source> (pp. <fpage>209</fpage>-<lpage>238</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nymark</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>DeForge</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barbeau</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Badour</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bercovitch</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tomas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Body weight support treadmill gait training in the subacute recovery phase of incomplete spinal cord injury</article-title>. <source>Neurorehabilitation and Neural Repair</source>, <volume>12</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>119</fpage>-<lpage>136</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/154596839801200307</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kriegsman</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>J. B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <source>Spinal cord injury: A guide for living</source>. <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Papadimitriou</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Becoming en-wheeled: The situated accomplishment of re-embodiment as a wheelchair user after spinal cord injury</article-title>. <source>Disability &amp; Society</source>, <volume>23</volume>(<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>691</fpage>-<lpage>704</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09687590802469420</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Protas</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Qureshy</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sherwood</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Supported treadmill ambulation training after spinal cord injury: A pilot study</article-title>. <source>Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation</source>, <volume>82</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>825</fpage>-<lpage>831</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/apmr.2001.23198</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>QSR International Pty Ltd</collab>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>NVivo (Version 8) [Computer software]</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Melbourne, Australia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Radley</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Style, discourse and constraint in adjustment to chronic illness</article-title>. <source>Sociology of Health &amp; Illness</source>, <volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>230</fpage>-<lpage>252</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1467-9566.ep11435222</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Riessman</surname><given-names>C. K.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Performing identities in illness narrative: Masculinity and multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Research</source>, <volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>33</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/146879410300300101</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rosenfeld</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Faircloth</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Embodied self and commitment to movement: Constructing the moral self through arthritis narratives</article-title>. <source>Symbolic Interaction</source>, <volume>27</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>507</fpage>-<lpage>529</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1525/si.2004.27.4.507</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="gov">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Selder</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Life transition theory: The resolution of uncertainty</article-title>. <source>Nursing &amp; Health Care</source>, <volume>10</volume>(<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>437</fpage>-<lpage>451</lpage>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/2797502">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/2797502</ext-link></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Remaking the body: Rehabilitation and change</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sparkes</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Changing bodies, changing narratives and the consequences of tellability: A case study of becoming disabled through sport</article-title>. <source>Sociology of Health &amp; Illness</source>, <volume>30</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>217</fpage>-<lpage>236</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-9566.2007.01033.x</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>). <source>The everyday world as problematic: A feminist sociology</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Northeastern Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Flowers</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Interpretive phenomenological analysis: Theory, method, and research</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sparkes</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Men, sport, spinal cord injury and narrative time</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Research</source>, <volume>3</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>295</fpage>-<lpage>320</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1468794103033002</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Struhkamp</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Wordless pain: Dealing with suffering in physical rehabilitation</article-title>. <source>Cultural Studies</source>, <volume>19</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>701</fpage>-<lpage>718</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09502380500365655</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thibodaux</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Habitus and the embodiment of disability through lifestyle</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Occupational Therapy</source>, <volume>59</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>507</fpage>-<lpage>515</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5014/ajot.59.5.507</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The ‘disabled’ body</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Real bodies</source> (pp. <fpage>64</fpage>-<lpage>78</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Basingstoke, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Manderson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Constructing hope: Dis/continuity and the narrative construction of recovery in the rehabilitation unit</article-title>. <source>Journal of Contemporary Ethnography</source>, <volume>37</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>180</fpage>-<lpage>201</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0891241607312493</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weitz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Uncertainty in the lives of persons with AIDS</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health and Social Behavior</source>, <volume>30</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>270</fpage>-<lpage>281</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2136960</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr77-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wendell</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <source>The rejected body: Feminist philosophical reflections on disability</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr78-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wheatley</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Bodies at risk: An ethnography of heart disease</source>. <publisher-loc>Burlington, VT</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr79-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1984</year>). <article-title>The genesis of chronic illness: Narrative re-construction</article-title>. <source>Sociology of Health &amp; Illness</source>, <volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>175</fpage>-<lpage>200</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1467-9566.ep10778250</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr80-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wirz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dietz</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Long term effects of locomotor training in spinal humans</article-title>. <source>Journal of Neurology, Neurosurgery, and Psychiatry</source>, <volume>71</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>93</fpage>-<lpage>96</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jnnp.71.1.93</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr81-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>M. F. D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <source>Bringing knowledge back in: From social constructivism to social realism in the sociology of education</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Taylor &amp; Francis</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr82-1049732313494119">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zola</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Bringing our bodies and ourselves back in: Reflections on a past, present, and future “medical sociology.”</article-title> <source>Journal of Health and Social Behavior</source>, <volume>32</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>16</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2136796</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>