<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RSH</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sprsh</journal-id>
<journal-title>Perspectives in Public Health</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1757-9139</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1757-9147</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1757913912457312</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1757913912457312</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Current Topics and Opinions</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Adult Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD): public health implications</article-title>
</title-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>132</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>209</fpage>
<lpage>210</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© Royal Society for Public Health 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Royal Society for Public Health</copyright-holder>
</permissions></article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p><bold><italic>In 2008 NICE guidance recommended the identification and treatment of Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) in adults. Previously, diagnosis and treatment of this condition had mainly been confined to children and young people. Dr Tamsin Newlove-Delgado and Professor Ken Stein from University of Exeter explain why adult ADHD is important and what the implications are for health improvement, commissioning and providing evidence based services</italic></bold></p>
<p>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) is a neurodevelopmental disorder, with symptoms of inattention, hyperactivity and impulsivity causing significant impairment in functioning. The diagnostic criteria for ADHD currently require that symptoms must have been present before the age of seven years, and be apparent in more than one setting.</p>
<p>There is no single cause; instead the condition appears to result from a complex interaction of genetic and environmental factors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1757913912457312">1</xref></sup> ADHD is estimated to affect 3-5% of children of school age in the UK.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1757913912457312">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1757913912457312">2</xref></sup></p>
<sec id="section1-1757913912457312">
<title>Does ADHD exist in adults?</title>
<p>Few studies have followed up young people with ADHD beyond the age of 25. A meta-analysis of data from follow-up studies suggested that although the rate of persistence of ADHD meeting the full diagnostic criteria at age 25 was only 15%, the persistence of symptoms was much higher at around 40-60%.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1757913912457312">3</xref></sup> Therefore, although the prevalence of ADHD certainly declines with age, a significant proportion of adults have still been found to be affected.</p>
<p>ADHD in adults remains the subject of some debate, given the high rate of co-morbidities and the difficulty in distinguishing normal symptoms from pathological ones. However, in 2008 the National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE) reviewed the evidence on adult ADHD, recommending recognition of the condition and establishment of services for assessment and management, with stimulant medication as the first-line treatment for adults with either moderate or severe levels of impairment.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1757913912457312">2</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1757913912457312">
<title>How many adults might suffer with ADHD?</title>
<p>A meta-analysis of world literature produced a pooled prevalence estimate of 2.5%.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1757913912457312">4</xref></sup> The UK 2007 Adult Psychiatric Morbidity Survey<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1757913912457312">5</xref></sup> used the six item Adult ADHD Self Report Scale (ASRS) to screen the sample for ADHD symptoms. Using this scale 8.2% of adults scored four or more, which was considered to warrant clinical assessment, and 0.6% scored all six, indicating a high likelihood of a positive diagnosis. NICE have estimated the number of men with ADHD at over 300,000 in England, and the number of women at over 80,000,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1757913912457312">6</xref></sup> indicating that there is a considerable population likely to be affected.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1757913912457312">
<title>Impact of adult ADHD</title>
<sec id="section4-1757913912457312">
<title>Higher risk of other psychiatric disorders</title>
<p>Adults with ADHD are at increased risk for other psychiatric disorders. Over a lifetime, it is estimated that over three-quarters of those with ADHD will have a psychiatric co-morbidity;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1757913912457312">7</xref></sup> with depression and anxiety being most common.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1757913912457312">
<title>Substance misuse and smoking</title>
<p>Substance misuse affects up to half of adults with ADHD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1757913912457312">7</xref></sup> A significant proportion of those in contact with substance misuse services also have ADHD symptoms. High rates of smoking (up to 40%) in ADHD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1757913912457312">8</xref></sup> may be explained by genetic influences or self-medication with nicotine: the condition is also linked with earlier initiation of smoking and difficulty in quitting.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1757913912457312">9</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1757913912457312">
<title>Accidents</title>
<p>Studies have reported that adolescents and adults with ADHD are more likely to be involved in road traffic collisions, to be stopped for speeding, and to report losses of concentration and control whilst driving.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1757913912457312">10</xref></sup> Similarly, both children and adults with ADHD appear to have more accidents and injuries in general, possibly due to impulsivity and risk-taking behaviours.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1757913912457312">11</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1757913912457312">
<title>Educational and occupational underachievement</title>
<p>Adults with ADHD experience higher job turnover and more periods of unemployment. A recent European study found they were twice as likely to be unemployed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1757913912457312">12</xref></sup> Their educational and occupational achievements are lower than would be expected given sibling achievements and IQ.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1757913912457312">13</xref></sup> In the US estimated productivity losses due to absenteeism and underperformance have been calculated at $3.7 billion per year.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1757913912457312">14</xref></sup></p>
<p>Unsurprisingly, ADHD in adults is also unequally distributed across society. In the 2007 Adult Psychiatric Morbidity Survey,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1757913912457312">5</xref></sup> a positive screen for the disorder was found to be associated with younger age groups, those not in employment, those with the lowest household income, and among people with low educational attainment. In addition, from young adulthood onwards, people with hyperactivity are at greater risk of antisocial behaviour and arrest; and there is a high prevalence in forensic populations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1757913912457312">15</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1757913912457312">
<title>Evidence based services for adult ADHD</title>
<p>Medication (methylphenidate and atomoxetine in particular) has been shown to be effective in reducing symptoms in adults in a number of randomised controlled trials.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1757913912457312">2</xref></sup> Whilst economic studies in adults are lacking, analysis undertaken by NICE indicated that medication was likely to be cost-effective. There is little high-quality evidence examining psychological interventions for adults, although these may be helpful.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1757913912457312">2</xref></sup> Appropriate provision should include diagnosis and assessment, drug monitoring and psychological treatment services, and robust arrangements for transition from child and adolescent services for young people with ADHD.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1757913912457312">2</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1757913912457312">
<title>What is the role of public health?</title>
<p>Despite the development of services in some areas of the UK, research suggests a significant level of unmet needs. There is likely to be a large number of adults with ADHD who may experience impairing symptoms and could benefit from treatment but are not receiving it. Estimates of the proportion of adults with ADHD currently receiving drug treatment are as low as 1.24%. This may be due to ongoing reservations about prescribing for this group; along with gaps in service provision.</p>
<p>Some examples of potential areas for public health influence and action are:</p>
<list id="list1-1757913912457312" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>research into prevention;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>evaluating health promotion interventions in this population – for example how best to prevent the uptake of smoking, or illicit drug use;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>developing smoking cessation services for adults and young people with ADHD;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>supporting the development of a high quality evidence base for intervention; and</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>jointly commissioning pathways for diagnosis and management across all ages.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Given the breadth of impact of ADHD from childhood onwards, and the inequalities in health that result, there is surely a strong argument for public health to contribute both to prevention and to improving outcomes for this disadvantaged population.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We acknowledge funding from the National Institute for Health Research Collaborations for Leadership in Applied Health Research and Care. The views and opinions expressed in this paper are those of the authors and not necessarily those of the NHS, the NIHR or the Department of Health.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1757913912457312">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Thapar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jefferies</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stergiakouli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>What causes attention deficit hyperactivity disorder?</article-title> <source>Arch Dis Child</source> <year>2011</year>; doi:10.1136/archdischild-2011-300482<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/archdischild-2011-300482</pub-id></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1757913912457312">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence</collab>. <source>Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder: diagnosis and management of ADHD in children, young people and adults. CG72</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1757913912457312">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Faraone</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Biederman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mick</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The age-dependent decline of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder: a meta-analysis of follow-up studies</article-title>. <source>Psychol Med</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>36</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>159</fpage>-<lpage>65</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1757913912457312">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Czobor</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bálint</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mészáros</surname><given-names>Á</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bitter</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and correlates of adult attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder: meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Br J Psychiatry</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>194</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>204</fpage>-<lpage>11</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1757913912457312">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>National Centre for Social Research and Department of Health Sciences, University of Leicester</collab>. <source>Adult psychiatric morbidity in England, 2007: Results of a household survey</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Health and Social Care Information Centre</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1757913912457312">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence</collab>. <source>Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder. Costing report. Implementing NICE guidance</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1757913912457312">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sobanski</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Psychiatric comorbidity in adults with attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD)</article-title>. <source>Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</source> <year>2006</year>; <volume>256</volume>(<issue>0</issue>):<fpage>i26</fpage>-<lpage>i31</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1757913912457312">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pomerleau</surname><given-names>OF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Downey</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stelson</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pomerleau</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cigarette smoking in adult patients diagnosed with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder</article-title>. <source>J Subst Abuse</source> <year>1995</year>; <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>373</fpage>-<lpage>378</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1757913912457312">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Milberger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Biederman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Faraone</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>ADHD is associated with early initiation of cigarette smoking in children and adolescents</article-title>. <source>J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source> <year>1997</year>; <volume>36</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>37</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1757913912457312">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Madaan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Adult attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder and driving: why and how to manage it</article-title>. <source>Curr Psychiatr Rep</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>13</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>345</fpage>-<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1757913912457312">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Swensen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Birnbaum</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamadi</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cremieux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Secnik</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Incidence and costs of accidents among attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder patients</article-title>. <source>J Adolesc Health</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>35</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>346.e1</fpage>-<volume>346.e9</volume>,</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1757913912457312">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>De Zwaan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gruss</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Graap</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glaesmer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>The estimated prevalence and correlates of adult ADHD in a German community sample</article-title>. <source>Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</source> <year>2011</year>: <volume>262</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>79</fpage>-<lpage>86</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1757913912457312">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Biederman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petty</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fried</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schoenfeld</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Educational and occupational underattainment in adults with attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder: a controlled study</article-title>. <source>J. Clin. Psychiatry</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>1217</fpage>–<lpage>1222</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1757913912457312">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Birnbaum</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Secnik</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leong</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Costs of attention deficit–hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) in the US: excess costs of persons with ADHD and their family members in 2000</article-title>. <source>Curr Med Res Opin</source> <year>2005</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>195</fpage>-<lpage>205</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1757913912457312">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ginsberg</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hirvikoski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lindefors</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) among longer-term prison inmates is a prevalent, persistent and disabling disorder</article-title>. <source>BMC Psychiatry</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>10</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>112</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>