<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review" xml:lang="EN">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EHQ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spehq</journal-id>
<journal-title>European History Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0265-6914</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7110</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0265691413478542d</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0265691413478542d</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>RJB Bosworth, <italic>Whispering City: Rome and Its Histories</italic></article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Baxa</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>43</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>340</fpage>
<lpage>341</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013 Reprints and permissions: sagepub.co.uk/journalsPermissions.nav</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec7-0265691413478542d"><title>RJB Bosworth, <italic>Whispering City: Rome and Its Histories</italic>, Yale University Press: New Haven, CT, 2011; xvii + 358 pp., 36 illus.; 9780300114713, £25.00 (hbk)</title>
<sec id="sec8-0265691413478542d"><title><bold>Reviewed by:</bold> Paul Baxa, <italic>Ave Maria University, Florida, USA</italic></title>
<p>In this ambitious work the historian of fascist Italy, Richard Bosworth, seeks to unravel the many histories that are embedded in the Roman cityscape and examine how they have influenced Italian history since the Risorgimento. Following in the footsteps of Gibbon, Freud, and others, Bosworth seeks to identify the various layers of history found in Rome. Unlike them, however, Bosworth refuses to privilege any one of those histories. Rome’s landscape, writes Bosworth, ‘is shifting and multidimensional, a place where historical currents flow, meet, fuse and disperse, with greater or lesser dynamic thrust, sometimes visible, sometimes not, but always giving propulsive charge of some sort to the present as contemporaries seek a path to the future’ (7). Bosworth’s project is to show how the various histories of Rome continue to ‘whisper’, despite attempts by various regimes to impose monolithic meanings on the city.</p>
<p>In order to explore these various histories, Bosworth chooses both well-known and obscure Roman sites such as the Napoleonic Museum, the Victor Emanuel Monument, the Foro Italico (formerly Foro Mussolini), the Villa Torlonia (official residence of the Mussolini family during the <italic>Ventennio</italic>), and the monument to the murdered former Prime Minister Aldo Moro in the Via Caetani. From these particular sites Bosworth proceeds to illuminate their place in Rome’s ‘whirlpool of histories’ (30). Each site represented an attempt to impose an essentialist reading of Roman history – and each failed.</p>
<p><italic>Whispering City</italic> is an impressive work; the product of a master craftsman of history. Bosworth’s achievement is to trace each of the histories and their fate in the turbulent history of modern Italy. Thus we get a superb survey of the city’s Catholic, nationalist and fascist histories and the attempts by the Papacy, the liberal monarchy, and Mussolini’s dictatorship to appropriate the Eternal City. Bosworth provides a vast panorama of Popes, politicians, dictators, kings, mayors and occupiers who attempted to remake Rome in their own image. Although the breadth of the book is sweeping, Bosworth devotes much space to the fascist regime. Those familiar with Bosworth’s body of work will not be surprised that he sees Mussolini’s Rome as a spectacular failure – although it did come close to imposing one historical vision above all others. Ultimately fascist <italic>Romanità</italic> is dismissed by Bosworth as ‘razzmatazz’, consisting of nothing more than ‘pyrotechnics’ and ‘verbiage’ (196–7).</p>
<p><italic>Whispering City</italic> is not without its shortcomings. The text could have used pruning in places, and there are some factual errors. The church of the Santo Cuore Immacolato in Piazza Euclide, for example, was designed by Armando Brasini, not Marcello Piacentini. Also, the telescoping of Italian history onto the Roman stage has the paradoxical effect of pushing the city itself off to the side. Bosworth’s focus is on the macrohistory of the Italian nation and the policies of popes and national leaders. Municipal politics are discussed at times, but these moments are fleeting. Issues like urban planning and housing are mentioned but sporadically. The focus on politics also has the effect of eclipsing the histories examined by artists, film directors and other cultural figures. They too have their personal Romes. Fellini and Pasolini are mentioned, but only briefly. It is regrettable that the Rome of artists could not find more room in Bosworth’s analysis.</p>
<p>Despite these issues, the book is a superb addition to the scholarship on modern Rome. Through his intricate interweaving of Rome’s histories, Bosworth convincingly shows how Rome has been both a millstone and a hope for Italian democracy. Italy’s ‘Roman problem’ is that the Eternal City is often the focus of anti-democratic forces in the nation’s history. Bosworth demonstrates how this problem has been especially acute in the last twenty years since the downfall of the ‘First Republic’ and the rise of Berlusconi. In this period Rome has witnessed the rehabilitation of fascism’s memory, especially through the rise of the so-called ‘anti-anti-fascist’ thesis pioneered by the late historian Renzo De Felice. One of the most poignant illustrations in the book is the street sign dedicated to De Felice near the Villa Torlonia.</p>
<p>Not to end on a despairing note, Bosworth concludes by arguing that if Rome’s competing histories are allowed to co-exist in fruitful dialogue, then democracy in Italy will have a healthy future: ‘As the twenty-first century continues, it is important to insist on the right of each citizen, each resident, each visitor in person or imagination, still to hymn their own Rome and, thereby, democratically contest the meaning of the city’ (291). This book may contribute to such a cause.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
</article>