<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DIS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spdis</journal-id>
<journal-title>Discourse Studies</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1461-4456</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1461-7080</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1461445612450374</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1461445612450374</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>From sequential to affective discourse marker: Hebrew <italic>nu</italic> on Israeli political phone-in radio programs</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Maschler</surname><given-names>Yael</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff1-1461445612450374">University of Haifa, Israel</aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Dori-Hacohen</surname><given-names>Gonen</given-names></name>
<aff id="aff2-1461445612450374">University of Massachusetts, Amherst, USA</aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1461445612450374">Yael Maschler, Department of Hebrew Language, University of Haifa, Mount Carmel 31905, Haifa, Israel. Email: <email>maschler@research.haifa.ac.il</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>14</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>419</fpage>
<lpage>455</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Previous studies of Hebrew <italic>nu</italic> investigate this discourse marker in casual conversation. The current study explores <italic>nu</italic> on Israeli political phone-in radio programs and broadens our knowledge both about the functions and grammaticization processes of discourse markers and about some particularities of Israeli political talk radio. The comparison to casual talk reveals both qualitative and quantitative differences. In casual talk, the main function of <italic>nu</italic> is a sequential one – urging further development of an ongoing topic (69%). In the radiophonic data, the most common role of <italic>nu</italic> is as a keying token (53%), functioning in the affective realm. Furthermore, the talk-radio data show a wider variety of keys constructed by <italic>nu</italic> – which range from joking to sheer contempt – clustering closer towards the latter, in contrast to the case of casual talk, manifesting mostly the joking key. Structurally, whereas sequential functions are generally accomplished by stand-alone <italic>nu</italic>, affective tokens are accompanied by same-speaker talk. The analysis sheds new light on how a sequential token might come to function in the affective realm.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Affect</kwd>
<kwd>discourse markers</kwd>
<kwd>emotion</kwd>
<kwd>grammaticization</kwd>
<kwd>Hebrew conversation</kwd>
<kwd>interactional sociolinguistics</kwd>
<kwd>Israeli phone-in radio talk</kwd>
<kwd>key</kwd>
<kwd>minimal responses</kwd>
<kwd>stance</kwd>
<kwd>urging tokens</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1461445612450374" sec-type="intro">
<title>1. Introduction</title>
<p>Hebrew <italic>nu</italic> is a non-referential item imported in the early days of revival of the Hebrew language, as is the case for many discourse markers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-1461445612450374">Schiffrin, 1987</xref>) in language contact situations (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1461445612450374">Brody, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1461445612450374">Maschler, 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1461445612450374">1994</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1461445612450374">2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1461445612450374">Matras, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1461445612450374">Salmons, 1990</xref>). Even-Shoshan’s dictionary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1461445612450374">2003</xref>) classifies it as an interjection and provides the information that <italic>nu</italic> was ‘imported from the European languages’, which could be understood as mainly Russian (<italic>nu</italic>), Yiddish (<italic>nu</italic>), and possibly Polish (<italic>no</italic>). Even-Shoshan provides the meanings <italic>′efo</italic> (‘therefore’), <italic>hava</italic> (‘let us’), <italic>uvxen</italic> (‘well then’) – all words of rather high register. To these meanings, another dictionary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1461445612450374">Avneyon, 1998</xref>) adds a colloquial use: <italic>milat zeruz</italic> (‘an urging word’) and provides the example: <italic>nu kvar, bo! hasha′a me′uxeret!</italic> (‘<italic>nu</italic> already, come! It’s late!).</p>
<p>Previous studies of this discourse marker (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1461445612450374">Maschler, 1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1461445612450374">2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1461445612450374">2009</xref>) in casual face-to-face conversation among friends and relatives found that the main function of <italic>nu</italic> is urging further development of an ongoing topic (69% of all tokens; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1461445612450374">Maschler, 2009</xref>). The following segment from the Israeli <italic>Survivor</italic> reality TV show is unique in confirming some of the properties of <italic>nu</italic> revealed in those studies:</p>
<p>Excerpt 1: <italic>Survivor</italic> Reality Show<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1461445612450374">1</xref></sup></p>
<graphic id="img1-1461445612450374" position="anchor" xlink:href="10.1177_1461445612450374-img1.tif"/>
<p>In response to Itay’s request that Efrat explain why she views him as <italic>the biggest ‘operator’</italic>, Efrat first confirms the reason supplied by Itay (<italic>′ani haxi shaket</italic>, ‘I’m the most quiet [person around here]’, line 11), and proceeds to begin the second reason (lines 16–18): <italic>shta–yim, ′ani xoshevet Itay ′e–m, shegam batkufa shel Kaniba</italic>, (‘two–, I think Itay uh–m, that also during the Kaniba era,’). Line 18 ends in continuing intonation.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1461445612450374">2</xref></sup> However, Itay does not wait for the continuation but rather hastens Efrat with a token of <italic>nu</italic> (line 19). In response, and possibly under the influence of the existence of an overhearing audience<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1461445612450374">3</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1461445612450374">Goffman, 1981</xref>), Efrat turns around to face him with the negation element <italic>lo</italic> (‘no’, line 20) employed here as a discourse marker (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1461445612450374">Maschler, 1998</xref>) and the metalingual utterance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1461445612450374">Maschler, 1994</xref>) <italic>′ani ′adaber baketsev sheli–, vekshe ′ani ′ertse lehotsi mila–, ′ani ′otsi mila. ′al tagid li nu, ve′al tezarez ′oti</italic>. (‘I’ll speak at my own pace, and when I want to get a word out, I’ll get a word out. don’t say ‘<italic>nu</italic>’ to me, and don’t rush me’) (lines 22, 25, 27, 29–30). Efrat explicitly spells out the function of <italic>nu</italic> as a hastener here, and her utterance attests the impoliteness she associates with it. With the ironic utterances <italic>dabri</italic> (‘speak’), <italic>vaksha</italic> (‘please’), <italic>slixa</italic> (‘excuse me’) and the eye roll (lines 23–24, 26, 28, 31, 34), Itay ridicules Efrat’s dramatic response, attempting to minimize her presentation of him as impolite.</p>
<p>Following the methodology of interactional sociolinguistics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-1461445612450374">Schiffrin, 1994</xref>; e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1461445612450374">Goffman, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1461445612450374">Gumperz, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-1461445612450374">Tannen, 2007 [1989]</xref>), we employ the term ‘impoliteness’ in its everyday sense (rather than as a term in a theory of politeness), stemming from the attempt to control another’s actions (here, hastening an interlocutor). Previous study shows that the majority of <italic>nu</italic> tokens in casual Hebrew conversation do not seem to be interpreted as impolite because in fact they function to encourage the flow of talk rather than obstruct it. Taking the liberty to control the flow of another’s discourse can be perceived as polite in that it is indicative of the audience’s high involvement in the speaker’s talk. ‘By exhibiting their impatience in moving forward in a topic – to the point of attempting to control the flow of another’s discourse via <italic>nu</italic> – hearers show maximal involvement in the talk’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1461445612450374">Maschler, 2009</xref>: 74). In argumentative contexts, however, it was shown that this is not the case, and <italic>nu</italic> is often interpreted as impolite in the sense that it obstructs the continuation of talk, as it did in excerpt 1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1461445612450374">Maschler, 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1461445612450374">2009</xref>). The <italic>Survivor</italic> example documents in the most explicit fashion the impolite aura associated with <italic>nu</italic> in Israelis’ metalinguistic awareness.</p>
<p>In the present study, we extend the investigation of the discourse marker <italic>nu</italic> to a corpus of Israeli political phone-in radio programs. The data come from 100 interactions, over 7.5 hours (458 minutes) of talk, which took place on three different programs on the two leading public stations in Israel (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1461445612450374">Dori-Hacohen, 2009</xref> for more details concerning the database). We show, first of all, that employment of <italic>nu</italic> in this corpus differs both qualitatively and quantitatively compared with its use in casual Hebrew conversation. Furthermore, the exploration reveals additional uses of this discourse marker not commonly found in casual talk, thus expanding our understanding of the functions and structural properties of <italic>nu</italic>.</p>
<p>In considering the various uses of <italic>nu</italic> throughout the database, we will see that some of them are mainly sequential, in the sense that they pertain to the unfolding of the sequence of actions taking place in interaction (as in the <italic>Survivor</italic> excerpt above), whereas others pertain more to the construction of key (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1461445612450374">Hymes, 1986</xref>), emotion, or affect, defined as ‘displayed heightened involvement in conversation’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1461445612450374">Couper-Kuhlen, 2009</xref>: 94). Maschler has studied the question of how it may come about that a particular discourse marker might come to have two such different functions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1461445612450374">2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1461445612450374">2009</xref>). Our study sheds new light on this matter and discusses the implications for grammaticization theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1461445612450374">Hopper, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1461445612450374">Hopper and Traugott, 2003</xref>). Since our corpus is taken from Israeli political talk radio, as an aside, our study points to some functional differences in the employment of <italic>nu</italic> in this context as compared with its employment in casual conversation.</p>
<sec id="section2-1461445612450374">
<title>1.1. Residues of affect in <italic>nu</italic> prior to its borrowing into Hebrew</title>
<p>There has not been much study of <italic>nu</italic> and its equivalents based on naturally occurring discourse in the relevant European languages, but there is some evidence suggesting that it already had both sequential and affective meanings before being imported into Hebrew. For instance, Rosten describes Yiddish <italic>nu</italic> as:
<disp-quote>
<p>. . . the verbal equivalent of a sigh, a frown, a grin, a grunt, or a sneer. It is an expression of amusement or recognition or uncertainty or disapproval. It can be used fondly, acidly, tritely, belligerently. [. . .] It can convey pride, deliver scorn, demand response. (2003 [1968]: 397)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Whereas the last function listed by Rosten pertains more to the sequential realm, all others are affective.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1461445612450374">Kryk (1992)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-1461445612450374">Wierzbicka (1976)</xref> describe a variety of functions for Polish <italic>no</italic>, including the sequential functions of stimulating the hearer to act and encouraging the hearer to continue his/her utterance, as well as some functions which Kryk claims correspond to English <italic>well</italic> or are ‘equivalent to emphatic expressions, such as <italic>this is what I mean/that’s it</italic>, etc.’ and function therefore in the affective realm, for example:
<disp-quote>
<p><italic>Chodzi o analizę języka mówionego</italic>, <bold><italic>no</italic></bold><italic>!</italic></p>
<p>They mean the analysis of spoken language, <bold>that’s it</bold>! (p. 203)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>In an autobiographical novel published in Hebrew in 2004 by a Polish woman born in 1937, who remained in Poland with her parents until 1949, we find the following description of her mother’s condescending attitude towards other post-war Polish Jews who had survived the Holocaust, a description the author constructs in the mother’s voice:
<disp-quote>
<p><italic>kaxa ze haya ′etslenu, haya kavod vehayta rama, lo kmo kol miney ′anashim shexazru xayim mehamilxama ufit′om hem mesaprim kama hayu mexubadim ve′ashirim lifney hamilxama [. . .]. sipurim, sipurim vesipurim</italic>, <bold><italic>la′aga ′ima sheli betuv-lev salxani</italic></bold><italic>: ze haya besax hakol soxer dagim masrixim, ze lo kara sefer ′exad baxayim shelo, lezot ′eyn kultura bixlal, ve′aba shela, ba′ayara, haya mekaneax ′et ha′af bishtey ′etsbe′otav.</italic> <bold><italic>no?</italic></bold> <italic>′eyfo hem ve′eyfo ′anaxnu?</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1461445612450374">Frankel, 2004</xref>: 95)</p>
<p>This is how it was in our family, there was dignity and there were high standards, not like all sorts of people who returned alive from the war and suddenly they tell how dignified and wealthy they used to be before the war, [. . .]. ‘Stories, stories and stories’, my mother would <bold>mock in forgiving kind-heartedness</bold>: ‘this one was just a stinky-fish dealer, that one had never read a book his entire life, this one [FEM] has no culture, and her father, in the village, used to wipe his nose with his two fingers. <bold>no</bold>? Where are they and where are we?’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1461445612450374">Frankel, 2004</xref>: 95, translation and emphasis ours)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Note the strategy of language alternation at the discourse marker in question (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1461445612450374">Brody, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1461445612450374">Maschler, 1988</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1461445612450374">1994</xref>) – Polish <italic>no</italic> as opposed to Hebrew <italic>nu</italic>, conveying the diaspora flavor of the mother’s talk via this affective marker delivering mockery here, as attested by the author’s sentence introducing this constructed dialogue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-1461445612450374">Tannen, 2007 [1989]</xref>). It is precisely the similarity with Hebrew <italic>nu</italic> which enables this author to employ a Polish word in a Hebrew novel.</p>
<p>Although the majority of functions mentioned by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1461445612450374">Grenoble (1998)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1461445612450374">Multisilta (1995)</xref> for Russian <italic>nu</italic> seem to belong in the sequential realm (‘to introduce a new topic, or signal the continuation of a previously established, activated topic’, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1461445612450374">Grenoble, 1998</xref>: 181), Multisilta mentions that 3.5% of all tokens in her database perform an emotive function, but she refrains from illustrating them in her 1995 article.</p>
<p>Both sequential and affective functions, then, seem to have been performed by <italic>nu</italic> in the languages of origin. We are not aware of any research attempting to explain how <italic>nu</italic>/<italic>no</italic> has come to have two such different functions in other languages (for additional studies of <italic>nu</italic> and its equivalents in other European and non-European languages, see note 6). Furthermore, when such particles are borrowed into a new language and culture, although the form of the particle may be taken over, its discourse functions are not always borrowed as well. For instance, judging by the Hebrew spoken by recent Russian immigrants to Israel, there is some evidence of different usage of <italic>nu</italic> in Russian compared to Hebrew. These speakers employ <italic>nu</italic> much more frequently than do Israeli Hebrew speakers, and they often employ <italic>nu</italic> to mitigate an utterance in a manner which is not employed in Hebrew (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1461445612450374">Maschler, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1461445612450374">Mazo and Voloshin, 1999</xref>).</p>
<p>Thus, the borrowed item very often acquires new meanings, tainted by the new language and culture into which it is imported. It is these meanings we seek to uncover in the present study for the Israeli Hebrew context, along with a suggestion concerning how they may have emerged from discourse.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1461445612450374">
<title>2. <italic>Nu</italic> on Israeli political phone-in programs: A quantitative perspective</title>
<p>Because of its perceived impoliteness, we would perhaps not expect to find much employment of <italic>nu</italic> on political phone-in radio programs. Indeed, while the frequency in casual face-to-face talk averages one token approximately every 1.3 minutes, the talk-radio corpus manifests an average of about one token only every 8.6 minutes.</p>
<p>This finding is even more striking when considering the difference in medium between the two corpora. Some studies have found that telephone conversations show a higher rate of minimal responses such as <italic>um, ah, er</italic> because of participants’ need to hold onto the floor and the lack of kinesic features aiding them in this task (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1461445612450374">Ball, 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1461445612450374">Beattie, 1977</xref>). Considering that hastening a speaker could in principle be accomplished kinesically (via an earnest gaze or some head nodding, for example), we might expect more <italic>nu</italic> tokens in <italic>non</italic> face-to-face interaction, yet the radio phone-in interactions actually manifest fewer <italic>nu</italic> tokens.</p>
<p><italic>Nu</italic> was shown to be employed in four functions in the corpus of casual talk: 1) urging further development of an ongoing topic, 2) hastening a non-verbal action, 3) granting permission to perform an action (as a ‘go-ahead’ token; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1461445612450374">Schegloff, 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-1461445612450374">2007</xref>), and 4) as a keying token, coloring the utterance with a tone ranging from joking to provoking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1461445612450374">Maschler, 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1461445612450374">2009</xref>). Not only frequency, but also the distribution of <italic>nu</italic> differs across the two corpora (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1461445612450374">Table 1</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1461445612450374" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Distribution of <italic>nu</italic> tokens across functions in casual conversation versus talk radio.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1461445612450374" xlink:href="10.1177_1461445612450374-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Urging further development of ongoing topic</th>
<th align="left">Hastening non-verbal action</th>
<th align="left">Granting permission to perform action</th>
<th align="left">Keying token</th>
<th align="left">Total</th>
<th align="left">Frequency</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Casual conversation</td>
<td>79 (69%)</td>
<td>6 (5%)</td>
<td>3 (3%)</td>
<td>27 (23%)</td>
<td>115 (100%)</td>
<td>1:1.3 minutes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Talk radio</td>
<td>13 (24%)</td>
<td>1 (2%)</td>
<td>11 (21%)</td>
<td>28 (53%)</td>
<td>53 (100%)</td>
<td>1:8.6 minutes</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>At first glance, it seems that the two corpora manifest the same discourse functions for <italic>nu</italic>. Upon further examination, however, we will see that this is not accurate. One difference which can already be discerned has to do with the second column – hastening a non-verbal action (such as the example provided in Avneyon’s dictionary and cited in the opening of this study). In the corpus of casual talk, participants occasionally hasten each other to perform actions in the extra-lingual world via <italic>nu</italic>. In the particular corpus investigated, this included actions such as tasting some soup, stopping to cough, completing an interaction with another customer at the supermarket, etc. In the radiophonic data, there are no such cases simply because participants are not generally mutually engaged in other actions besides their talk. The one non-verbal action hastened throughout the entire radiophonic database consists of <italic>nu</italic> uttered by a caller who hastens himself to remember a name. This, then, constitutes hastening a cognitive action, which is borderline between a verbal and a non-verbal one (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1461445612450374">Maschler, 2009</xref>). Because this category in the radiophonic corpus consists of only one token, we will not elaborate on it here.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1461445612450374">
<title>3. Sequential functions of <italic>nu</italic></title>
<sec id="section5-1461445612450374">
<title>3.1. Urging further development of ongoing topic</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1461445612450374">Table 1</xref> shows that while in casual conversation the main function of <italic>nu</italic> is urging further development of an ongoing topic (69%), in the radiophonic data only 24% of the tokens function in this role. Examine, for instance, excerpt 2, an interaction in which the caller brings up what is known as Israel’s <italic>demographic problem</italic>, that is, the belief that within about two decades, the majority of Israeli citizens will not be Jewish. The host attempts to get him to suggest solutions to <italic>the demographic problem</italic>:</p>
<p>Excerpt 2: ‘Let’s Say I Were Foreign Minister’, 27.5.05</p>
<graphic id="img2-1461445612450374" position="anchor" xlink:href="10.1177_1461445612450374-img2.tif"/>
<p>Following many digressions up to now in the interaction, the caller opens with <italic>yesh li ra′ayon ′adir!</italic> (‘I’ve got a great idea’, line 284). Once more, he digresses to something else and 20 intonation units later finally begins to elaborate his solution to the problems in the Middle East (lines 305–306). He digresses yet again, this time to a metalingual comment: <italic>ze hatsaga ma she′ani ′omer, ′al taxshov she′ani mitkaven ′axshav birtsinut</italic> (‘it’s a show what I’m saying, don’t think I mean it seriously now’, lines 307–308). At this point, the host loses some of his patience and, employing <italic>nu</italic> in a tone of despair (line 309), hastens him to return to the topic – his proposed solution – which he indeed does at line 310.</p>
<p>Similarly, when the caller continues but digresses yet again, this time to over-elaborate on the foreign ministers who would take part in his solution: <italic>ro..roma pariz london ′amerika rusya, ′ata yodea, kol sarey haxuts</italic>. (‘Ro .. Rome Paris London America Russia, you know,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1461445612450374">4</xref></sup> all foreign ministers.’, lines 316–319), the host responds with the repetition <italic>ken ken ken ken</italic>. (‘yeah yeah yeah yeah.’) in final intonation contour, indicating that this elaboration is unnecessary (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-1461445612450374">Stivers, 2004</xref>). Subsequently, by employing <italic>nu</italic> at line 321, he escalates this indication by hastening the caller’s return to the ongoing topic, which the caller indeed returns to immediately following the hastening.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1461445612450374">
<title>3.2. Granting permission to perform action</title>
<p>As pointed out in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1461445612450374">Maschler (2003)</xref>, as a hastener, <italic>nu</italic> appears as a first pair part of an adjacency pair (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-1461445612450374">Schegloff, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-1461445612450374">Schegloff and Sacks, 1973</xref>), initiating a move further advancing the topic. Thus, in the previous example, for instance, when the host employs <italic>nu</italic> following the caller’s digression elaborating on the foreign ministers (excerpt 2, lines 316–321), this <italic>nu initiates</italic> a return to the ongoing topic, to which the caller <italic>responds</italic> in the subsequent intonation units.</p>
<p>When granting permission to perform an action, on the other hand, <italic>nu</italic> appears as a second pair part – a ‘go-ahead’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1461445612450374">Schegloff, 1990</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-1461445612450374">2007</xref>), as can be seen in line 312 of excerpt 2. At line 310, the caller responds to the host’s hastening <italic>nu</italic> (line 309), abandons his metalingual digression of lines 307–308, and returns to his solution to <italic>the demographic problem</italic>. He describes a hypothetical situation: <italic>naniax shehayu samim ′oti sar haxuts karega?</italic> (‘let’s say they appointed me foreign minister now?’). In the absence of response to this utterance ending in rising question intonation and followed by a slightly longer pause, the caller, in pursuit of response, adds an additional question: <italic>′ata yodea ma hayiti ′ose?</italic> (‘you know what I’d do?’, line 311). This question – a first pair part – receives a <italic>nu</italic> response from the host (line 312), an action allowing the speaker to elaborate, which he indeed does in the following lines.</p>
<p>As can be seen from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1461445612450374">Table 1</xref>, the frequency of this type of <italic>nu</italic> rises from 3% in the casual conversation corpus to 21% in the radiophonic data. This has to do with the fact that such <italic>nu</italic> tokens tend to follow metalingual announcements of performing some action in the discourse realm: for example, <italic>′az ′agid lexa ma bo′er</italic> (‘so I’ll tell you what’s so urgent’, see excerpt 3 below), <italic>′ani ′agid lexa lama</italic> (‘I’ll tell you why’), <italic>bo ′agid lexa</italic> (‘come I’ll tell you’), <italic>takshiv</italic>(‘listen’), <italic>lama ′ani sho′el ′otxa ′et ze</italic> (‘why do I ask you this’), <italic>bo ′od davar</italic> (‘come another thing’), <italic>ten li rak lehashmia lexa .. rak lehagid lexa ′et hadavar haze ve′ani gomer</italic> (‘let me just sound you .. just tell you this thing and I’m done’). Such metalingual announcements (a special type of <italic>pre-</italic>’s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1461445612450374">Schegloff, 1980</xref>)) are common in non-narrative, argumentative discourse, but much less so in narrative discourse. Narratives are not very common in the talk-radio corpus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1461445612450374">Hacohen, 2007</xref>), whereas they constitute a significant portion of the casual conversation database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1461445612450374">Maschler, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>As pointed out in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1461445612450374">Maschler (2003)</xref>, this ‘go-ahead’ <italic>nu</italic> is quite similar to Finnish <italic>no</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-1461445612450374">Sorjonen, 2002</xref>). In Finnish, however, two different particles have emerged – Finno-Ugric <italic>nii(n)</italic>, urging further development of a topic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-1461445612450374">Sorjonen, 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-1461445612450374">2002</xref>), and <italic>no</italic>, a ‘go-ahead’. In Hebrew, a single utterance, <italic>nu</italic>, performs both functions.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1461445612450374">5</xref></sup> Interestingly, both Finnish <italic>no</italic> and Hebrew <italic>nu</italic> probably originate from the same Germanic source (related to German <italic>nun</italic> (‘now’)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1461445612450374">6</xref></sup>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1461445612450374">
<title>4. Constructing the roles of ‘host’ and ‘caller’ via <italic>nu</italic></title>
<p>So far, all radiophonic <italic>nu</italic> tokens we have seen were employed by the host. Indeed, callers employ <italic>nu</italic> at a significantly lower rate, as can be seen from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1461445612450374">Table 2</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1461445612450374" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Distribution of <italic>nu</italic> tokens across hosts and callers.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1461445612450374" xlink:href="10.1177_1461445612450374-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Urging further development of topic</th>
<th align="left">Hastening non-verbal action</th>
<th align="left">Granting permission to perform action</th>
<th align="left">Keying token</th>
<th align="left">Total</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Total</td>
<td>13 (100%)</td>
<td>1 (100%)</td>
<td>11 (100%)</td>
<td>28 (100%)</td>
<td>53 (100%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hosts</td>
<td>11 (85%)</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>6 (55%)</td>
<td>24 (86%)</td>
<td>41 (77%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Callers</td>
<td>2 (15%)</td>
<td>1 (100%)</td>
<td>5 (45%)</td>
<td>4 (14%)</td>
<td>12 (23%)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>We see that hosts employ <italic>nu</italic> for urging further development of a topic almost six times more often than callers. Indeed, ensuring a lively development of topics is one of a host’s main roles in such programs. Not only would hastening a host be considered impolite for a caller; keeping time and maintaining interest for the audience are not among a caller’s responsibilities. Thus we see that <italic>nu</italic> is employed in a way that constructs the difference between the roles of ‘caller’ and ‘host’ on these programs.</p>
<sec id="section8-1461445612450374">
<title>4.1. Callers’ employment of nu as a ‘go-ahead’</title>
<p>In order to understand the relatively high rate of callers’ employment of <italic>nu</italic> for granting permission (45% as opposed to 15% in the first column of <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1461445612450374">Table 2</xref> and 14% in the fourth), let us examine excerpt 3, an interaction which took place on the eve of general elections in both Israel and the Palestinian Authority in early 2006, following the Israeli evacuation of the Gaza Strip. The Israeli prime minister at the time, Ariel Sharon, had had a stroke. The caller here addresses the acting prime minister:</p>
<p>Excerpt 3: ‘What’s So Urgent?’ 18.1.06</p>
<graphic id="img3-1461445612450374" position="anchor" xlink:href="10.1177_1461445612450374-img3.tif"/>
<p>The caller ends his plea to the acting prime minister <italic>to postpone everything</italic> (i.e. any further unilateral Israeli concessions) with the utterance <italic>ma bo′er!</italic> (‘what’s so urgent!’, line 151). The host, who had already attempted a response at line 152 (lines 154–155), attempts another response to the second <italic>ma bo′er</italic> (lines 159, 161), again to no avail. Only upon the caller’s third <italic>ma bo′er</italic> does the host succeed in getting the floor, and this – by treating the caller’s utterance literally, as a question: <italic>′az ′agid lexa ma bo′er.</italic> (‘so I’ll tell you what’s so urgent.’, line 165). To this <italic>pre-</italic>, the caller responds with <italic>nu</italic> (line 167), overlapping the beginning of the host’s ′<italic>ata rotse lishmoa</italic>? (‘you wanna hear?’, line 166).</p>
<p>An interlocutor’s signaling that the speaker continue with his/her action can be accomplished with varying degrees of enthusiasm on the part of the interlocutor concerning the speaker’s continuation. Thus, we begin to see the affective hues which often accompany this sequential token – a topic which will be further elaborated in section 5. Earlier research has shown that the sequential functions of <italic>nu</italic> can be described along a continuum of ‘degree of encouragement to proceed with action’ from ‘most encouraging’ to ‘least encouraging’: urging one to perform the action, hastening it, granting permission, allowing, allowing reluctantly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1461445612450374">Maschler, 2003</xref>). While hastening an action is mainly a host’s responsibility, granting permission to perform a conversational action may become – at least in Israel – a caller’s task, and, as we see in lines 152–156, the caller may choose not to grant it. With the <italic>nu</italic> of line 167, the caller indeed finally grants permission for the action announced by <italic>′az ′agid lexa ma bo′er.</italic> (‘so I’ll tell you what’s so urgent.’, line 165), but he does so rather reluctantly. His reluctance is evident in his blocking the action until the host’s third attempt at it. Furthermore, the host’s elaborate institutional response following this token of <italic>nu</italic> shows that the caller’s reluctance is not lost on the host: <italic>′ata rotse lishmoa? ′ata sha′alta. /′az/ ten lanu, na′ane lexa. bishvil ma ′ani po?</italic> (‘you wanna hear? you asked. /so/ let us, we’ll answer you. what am I here for?’, lines 166–171). A person enthusiastic to hear an explanation is in no need for such an introduction.</p>
<p>We are not claiming that the caller’s reluctance is accomplished <italic>only</italic> via the <italic>nu</italic> token here. Clearly, it is also accomplished by the various accompanying strategies discussed in the previous paragraph. We would like to suggest, however, that when a go-ahead token is recurrently performed in contexts involving reluctance, over time, the result may be that reluctance becomes strongly associated with the token itself (more on this below).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1461445612450374">
<title>5. Keying <italic>nu</italic></title>
<p>The reluctance of the <italic>nu</italic> token in the previous example (excerpt 3, line 167) <italic>accompanies</italic> its sequential function. We will now develop the argument that over time, certain recurring affects accompanying sequential <italic>nu</italic> have become dissociated from its sequential functions, so that certain <italic>nu</italic> tokens have come to function only affectively, as keying tokens, with a greatly diminished sequential quality.</p>
<p>The main function of <italic>nu</italic> in the talk-radio data is not in the sequential realm, but rather as a keying token. While this function is manifested by less than a fourth of all casual talk cases (23%), in the radio programs over half the tokens (53%) are employed in this manner.</p>
<p>Earlier study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1461445612450374">Maschler, 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1461445612450374">2009</xref>) has shown that in the corpus of casual conversation, keying <italic>nu</italic> can be described along a continuum representing the degree to which a speaker is aligned/disaligned vis-a-vis the interlocutor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1461445612450374">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1461445612450374" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Continuum of keys constructed by <italic>nu</italic> in casual interaction.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1461445612450374-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>On one extreme of this continuum we find alignment in the form of joking with the addressee; on the other, disalignment in the form of belittling him or her, with the additional possibilities of mocking/mocking at addressee’s expense/ridiculing/provoking/provoking disrespectfully in between. The majority of keying <italic>nu</italic> tokens in the casual talk corpus, which consists of conversations among family and friends, fall close to the joking extreme. In the talk-radio data, on the other hand, the majority of tokens fall close to the opposite extreme. Moreover, we find additional hues of key constructed by <italic>nu</italic> which vary from scorn to sheer contempt, thus stretching the continuum further beyond the point at which the casual talk continuum ended (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1461445612450374">Figure 2</xref>). The study of <italic>nu</italic> in the political phone-in radio program thus reveals subtleties of key constructed by <italic>nu</italic> which are not found in the casual conversation database.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1461445612450374" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Continuum of keys constructed by <italic>nu</italic> in radio talk.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1461445612450374-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>In sub-section 5.2, we investigate a keying <italic>nu</italic> token constructing a humorous mocking tone. In sub-sections 5.1, 5.3, 5.4, and 5.5 we explore other keying <italic>nu</italic> tokens, gradually moving towards the contemptuous extreme along the continuum. We examine the mocking, ridiculing, belittling, and contemptuous keys constructed by <italic>nu</italic> in the political phone-in radio program, in order to decipher how a sequential element might gain affective functions.</p>
<sec id="section10-1461445612450374">
<title>5.1. Ridiculing</title>
<p>In the following interaction, the caller complains about the lack of attention paid to a month-long strike on public transportation at the relatively remote southern town of Be′er Sheva. Throughout the interaction, the host, broadcasting from a studio centrally located in Tel-Aviv-Jaffa, responds with cynicism concerning the general situation of the country. His cynicism peaks following the caller’s plea that one of the Labor Kneset members deal with the problem:</p>
<p>Excerpt 4: ‘Be′er Sheva Public Transportation Strike’ 15.12.04</p>
<graphic id="img4-1461445612450374" position="anchor" xlink:href="10.1177_1461445612450374-img4.tif"/>
<p>This <italic>nu</italic> functions in an entirely different realm compared to the <italic>nu</italic> tokens investigated so far. It is also found in a different structural environment. This is not stand-alone <italic>nu</italic>, as in all the cases above, but rather <italic>nu</italic> accompanying same-speaker talk. It differs structurally also in that it is accompanied by more prominent prosody – a marked vowel elongation signaling heightened emotional involvement on the part of the host. We are not concerned here with the sequential realm, as can be gathered from the fact that the person who uttered <italic>nu</italic> – the host in our case – continues speaking in the immediately following intonation unit (line 349). Furthermore, when the caller does respond (line 350), it is not to any hastening functions of this <italic>nu</italic>: we see no further elaboration of his ongoing talk. In fact, there has been no ongoing talk by the caller in the immediately preceding 11 intonation units (lines 337–347), and in the lines preceding those, the caller had <italic>completed</italic> his conversational action – a plea that someone from the Labor party tend to the long-lasting strike (lines 331–336).</p>
<p>The host cynically asks the caller why try getting Be′er Sheva’s public transportation back to work if in any event, none of the public services one could ride to is worth the effort involved in getting there (lines 337–344). The host ties all three public services – transportation, medicine, and education – together in the utterance <italic>xevre, ze hakol beyaxad, nu–.</italic> (‘you guys, it’s all together, <italic>nu</italic>’, or ‘it’s all part of the same deal, <italic>nu</italic>’, lines 346–347). The utterance <italic>xevre</italic> is a low-register, slightly ridiculing term of address towards a group of people, composed of the base of <italic>xaverim</italic> (‘friends’), suffixed by the slightly belittling morpheme <italic>-eh</italic> (instead of the MASC PL <italic>-im</italic> suffix).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-1461445612450374">7</xref></sup> It addresses the caller as representative of the residents of Be′er Sheva – or perhaps as representative of the program’s audience in general – who, in the host’s opinion, do not understand the dire state which society is in. <italic>Nu</italic> here functions to strengthen the ridiculing tone of the utterance.</p>
<p>In response to the <italic>nu</italic> of excerpt 4, line 348, the caller accepts the general grim picture depicted by the host (<italic>ze hakol beyaxad, ze naxon</italic>, ‘it’s all part of the same deal, that’s true’, lines 350–351), accepts being appointed representative of the public (by his employment of first-person plural <italic>narim . . . nomar</italic> (‘we will give up’, ‘we will say’, lines 354–355)), but rejects the host’s implication that there is no use in fighting for change (lines 354–356). In so doing, the caller accepts the host’s argument while rejecting his ridiculing key. We therefore see the caller indirectly relate to the keying function of this <italic>nu</italic>.</p>
<p>In order to explain how a token functioning in the sequential realm of discourse comes to function also in its interpersonal realm, as a keying token, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1461445612450374">Maschler (2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1461445612450374">2009</xref>) posited another continuum along which <italic>nu</italic> could be described – that of metalanguage:
<disp-quote>
<p>On one of its ends would be <italic>nu</italic> urging non-metalingual actions [such as the dictionary example (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1461445612450374">Avenyon, 1998</xref>) <italic>nu kvar, bo! hasha′a me′uxeret!</italic> (‘<italic>nu</italic> already, come! It’s late!), found only in the casual conversation corpus<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-1461445612450374">8</xref></sup>]; on the other would be <italic>nu</italic> urging metalingual actions <italic>via explicit metalingual utterances</italic>. The majority of cases fall in between these two ends – urging metalingual actions (mostly, further development of a topic) <bold>un</bold>accompanied by a longer metalingual utterance. In other words, sometimes the metalingual utterance is spelled out, as in [. . .] <italic>nu, tasbir!</italic> (‘<italic>nu</italic>, explain!’). But more frequently, the metalingual utterance is only implied and is to be gathered from context [as in the <italic>Survivor</italic> excerpt (excerpt 1, line 19), for example]. This is the case particularly with [. . .] keying <italic>nu</italic>. The metalingual utterance is seldom spelled out in these instances. (2009: 75–77)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>For example, in <italic>xevre, ze hakol beyaxad, nu–</italic> (‘you guys, it’s all together, <italic>nu</italic>’, lines 346–348), <italic>nu</italic> can be interpreted as <italic>urging an implied metalingual utterance</italic>. This <italic>nu</italic> is what remains of a metalingual utterance not verbalized, but still in the background, such as <italic>nu, ′atem lo mevinim</italic>? (‘<italic>nu</italic>, don’t you (PL) get it?’). As is often the case with metalingual utterances in discourse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1461445612450374">Maschler, 2009</xref>), they are redundant because they can easily be gathered from context.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-1461445612450374">9</xref></sup>
<disp-quote>
<p>[W]hat is left of these longer metalingual utterances – the <italic>nu</italic> – embodies only the key, from derogatory to joking; it verbalizes only the tone encompassed by the longer utterance vaguely in the background. Like the smile of the Cheshire Cat, then, the keying <italic>nu</italic> token is all that remains of the longer metalingual utterance implied. In this way, a word functioning in the sequential realm of discourse comes also to have an interpersonal keying function. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1461445612450374">Maschler, 2009</xref>: 76–77)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>In the following section we will see that an examination of the structural properties of the various <italic>nu</italic> tokens throughout the corpus sheds more light on the path from sequential to affective token.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1461445612450374">
<title>5.2. Structural features of keying vs sequential nu</title>
<p>The preceding excerpt is not representative of keying <italic>nu</italic> tokens in that the great majority of them (26, 93%) occur before, rather than after, the utterance they modify, as will be demonstrated in all of the following examples. However, <italic>all</italic> keying <italic>nu</italic> tokens (28, 100%) – those preceding as well as those following the utterance they modify – share the structural property of <italic>not</italic> occurring as stand-alone utterances. This is in contrast to sequential <italic>nu</italic> tokens (both urging further development of ongoing topic and granting permission to proceed), which, in the great majority of cases, are <italic>un</italic>accompanied by additional same-speaker talk, as can be seen in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1461445612450374">Table 3</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-1461445612450374" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p><italic>Nu</italic> tokens accompanied and unaccompanied by same-speaker talk.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-1461445612450374" xlink:href="10.1177_1461445612450374-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th/>
<th align="left">Stand-alone <italic>nu</italic></th>
<th align="left">Non stand-alone <italic>nu</italic></th>
<th align="left">Total</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Urging further development of ongoing topic</td>
<td>12 (92%)</td>
<td>1 (7%)</td>
<td>13 (100%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Granting permission to perform action</td>
<td>8 (73%)</td>
<td>3 (27%)</td>
<td>11 (100%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Keying token</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>28 (100%)</td>
<td>28 (100%)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>We see that only a single <italic>nu</italic> token urging further development of an ongoing topic (7%) and three tokens of ‘go-ahead’ <italic>nu</italic> (27%) are accompanied by additional talk by the same speaker.</p>
<p>The exceptions to this strong tendency, such as the one <italic>nu</italic> urging further development of an ongoing topic,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-1461445612450374">10</xref></sup> are telling. When examined closely, we see that <italic>they indeed begin to acquire keying functions as well</italic>. At the start of the interaction from which excerpt 5 is taken, the caller is driving his car and communicating with the host via the speaker-phone on his cell phone. Because reception is unsatisfactory, he pulls off to the side of the road, picks up the receiver, and proceeds to elaborate his political views. Following several minutes, when his views become less coherent, the host invites him to clarify his thesis employing humorous mockery:</p>
<p>Excerpt 5: ‘The Privilege of Talking on the Radio’ 14.1.05</p>
<graphic id="img5-1461445612450374" position="anchor" xlink:href="10.1177_1461445612450374-img5.tif"/>
<p>The <italic>nu</italic> at line 361 both urges the caller to further develop his thesis in a clearer form (lines 355–358) while at the same time continuing to construct the humorous mocking key which the host had begun at line 352 with the vocative <italic>yakiri</italic> (‘my dear’) – a highly marked form of address on these programs. It functions to soften his slight reprimand that the caller may not be fully aware of the privilege of talking on the radio and its implication not to waste the audience’s time with vague theses (lines 353–354). His request <italic>bo tomar ′eyze mishna sdura, sheteza′azea, mosdot ′arets veshilton</italic>. (‘come tell us some well-formed earthshaking thesis’, lines 355–357), softened by self-mockery resulting from employing the extremely high-register idioms <italic>mishna sdura</italic> (lit., ‘organized Mishnah<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-1461445612450374">11</xref></sup>’, ‘well-formed thesis’) and <italic>mosdot ′arets veshilton</italic> (lit., ‘bases of the land and its regime’<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-1461445612450374">12</xref></sup>), is reiterated by lower-register <italic>tagid mashehu</italic> (‘say something’) of line 359. When the caller laughs in response (line 360), the host’s immediately following <italic>nu both</italic> urges him to continue his thesis more comprehensibly <italic>and</italic> continues to humorously mock him in a way that softens the reprimand by pointing out the positive dramatic circumstances of the discourse – a unique opportunity of <italic>standing on the side of the road, holding a receiver</italic>, with <italic>the entire nation on their toes</italic>, waiting to hear what he has to say (lines 362–366). The token of <italic>nu</italic> intensifies this humorous mockery. An English ‘equivalent’ of this particular <italic>nu</italic> might be <italic>come on</italic>.</p>
<p>Not surprisingly, this sequential token is accompanied by the structural features of a keying token – the accompaniment of additional same-speaker talk. It is thus an exception proving the general pattern found in this database, that keying <italic>nu</italic> tokens are never stand-alone tokens, whereas the great majority of sequential <italic>nu</italic> tokens are.</p>
<p>Such borderline cases illuminate another aspect of the process by which an element functioning in the sequential realm might come to have also keying functions. According to Traugott’s Invited Inferencing Theory of Semantic Change (1999), conversational implicatures become conventionalized as a result of processes of metaphor and metonymy in communication. As Dahl explains:
<disp-quote>
<p>if some condition happens to be fulfilled frequently when a certain category is used, a stronger association may develop between the condition and the category in such a way that the condition comes to be understood as an integral part of the meaning of the category. (1985: 11)</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p>Since attempting to control an interlocutor’s actions (the ‘category’ in Dahl’s terminology) is inherently impolite, this action will often be accompanied by mitigating devices, such as the humorous mocking of excerpt 5 (Dahl’s ‘condition’). If the two (category and condition) co-occur frequently enough in the culture, sequential <italic>nu</italic> may begin to acquire the particular keying hues (humorous mockery in this case) in addition to its sequential role. As often happens in such processes of semantic change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1461445612450374">Traugott, 1999</xref>), the two may become dissociated from each other. Thus, eventually, the keying function might become dissociated from the sequential one, and in certain contexts, <italic>nu</italic> will come to function only in its affective role, as we have seen, for example, with the ridiculing <italic>nu</italic> of excerpt 4 and as will be demonstrated in the following excerpts.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1461445612450374">
<title>5.3. Belittling</title>
<p>The great majority of keying <italic>nu</italic> tokens in the talk-radio data, however, do not provide a humorous mocking key. Closer to the contemptuous extreme on the continuum of keys (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1461445612450374">Figure 2</xref>), we find <italic>nu</italic> which belittles the caller for contradicting him- or herself. In excerpt 6, for instance, an interaction which took place several months preceding the evacuation of the Gaza Strip, the caller demands a referendum on whether or not to evacuate. She claims that such a referendum will awaken public debate on the topic. At line 200, following the host’s question, she stresses that such public debate currently does not take place:</p>
<p>Excerpt 6: ‘Referendum’ 9.2.05  </p>
<graphic id="img6-1461445612450374" position="anchor" xlink:href="10.1177_1461445612450374-img6.tif"/>
<p>In lines 313–321, the host disconnects conducting a referendum from the occurrence of public debate on the topic of evacuation: just as a referendum will not guarantee public debate, so public debate can take place regardless of a referendum. His argument ends with the question <italic>lama lo ′osim ′otam?</italic> (‘why aren’t they (i.e. discussions of public debate) taking place?’). Following a relatively long pause, the caller admits very quietly: <italic>′osim ′otam. ′osim ′otam</italic>. (‘they <italic>are</italic> taking place’. ‘they <italic>are</italic> taking place’, lines 323–324). The host overlaps her repetition of this clause with <italic>nu! me′a ′axuz!</italic> (<italic><underline>nu</underline>!</italic> lit., ‘one hundred percent!’, lines 325–326). The idiom <italic>me′a ′axuz!</italic> (‘one hundred percent!’) is employed in Hebrew roughly in equivalence to English <italic>great!</italic> In other words, in light of the caller’s utterance at line 323, the situation is ‘great’ in the host’s eyes, because it is precisely the way he had claimed it to be earlier; namely, that public debate is already taking place regardless of a referendum.</p>
<p>Again, this non-stand-alone <italic>nu</italic> clearly does not function in the sequential realm. Structurally, it is followed by same-speaker talk by the host, and its marked exclamatory prosody manifests the speaker’s heightened emotional involvement while verbalizing it. In response to it, the caller does not continue with her ongoing action, but rather begins a new action of opposing the host’s argument, as indicated by the discourse marker <italic>′aval</italic> (‘but’)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13-1461445612450374">13</xref></sup> and the content of lines 327–329. With this <italic>nu</italic>, the host celebrates both the caller’s implied agreement with him on the topic as well as the inner-contradiction in her talk, arising from the fact that earlier on in the conversation (lines 200–201) she had explicitly claimed that currently public debate does not take place. Celebrating an inner-contradiction in an opponent’s talk is a belittling move because it brings the opponent’s weakness into relief. The host accomplishes this belittling move with a token of <italic>nu</italic>. Without it, the <italic>me′a ′axuz!</italic> (‘great!’) of line 326 could be interpreted here lacking the belittling quality. Upon hearing this <italic>nu</italic>, and even before the host completes his <italic>great!</italic>, the caller immediately addresses her self-contradiction by giving an explanation which attempts to minimize it and even make it disappear altogether (lines 327–329).</p>
<p>This <italic>nu</italic> could be interpreted as hastening a metalingual action such as <italic>nu, ′at lo ro′a sheze bidyuk soter ′et ma she′amart kodem vetomex bema sh′ani ′omer?</italic> (‘<italic>nu</italic>, don’t you see that you’re contradicting what you’ve just said and supporting my argument?’). The metalingual action of grasping the implications of her utterance which the caller is urged to perform here is clear from context; there is no need to verbalize it. All that is left is the belittling tone accompanying urging a metalingual action of this sort. Furthermore, since the situation of an opponent being urged to become aware of arguments that contradict what s/he had previously said is a fairly recurrent phenomenon in heated argument, applying the above theory of semantic change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1461445612450374">Dahl, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1461445612450374">Traugott, 1999</xref>) we see how over time, <italic>nu</italic> might gain belittling qualities.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1461445612450374">
<title>5.4. Contempt</title>
<p>Furthest beyond the extreme of belittling the addressee on the continuum of keys constructed for casual talk, we find cases of deep contempt constructed by <italic>nu</italic> in our radio corpus. Examine, for instance, the following interaction about long-lasting accusations of corruption directed against the prime minister at the time, Ariel Sharon, following his son’s pleading guilty in a criminal trial concerning his violating the political parties’ funding law:</p>
<p>Excerpt 7: ‘Fathers and Sons’ 4.1.06</p>
<graphic id="img7-1461445612450374" position="anchor" xlink:href="10.1177_1461445612450374-img7.tif"/>
<p>This interaction involves a caller who is a ‘regular’ to the program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1461445612450374">Dori-Hacohen, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1461445612450374">Katovich and Reese, 1987</xref>). Interactions with ‘regulars’ tend to be more extreme than with other callers, as hosts act more freely knowing the ‘regular’ will return to the program regardless of how he or she is treated. This caller began the interaction by urging the police to investigate the prime minister for corruption and to indict him, since his son had pleaded guilty in the affair. The host claims that the prime minister’s son, Omri Sharon, had indeed pleaded guilty in the affair (lines 151–155). He is interrupted at mid-utterance (line 155), but based on the host’s earlier (and subsequent) talk and on the caller’s acquaintance with him, it is clear (to us and to the caller) that the continuation of this utterance would have been something along the lines that this does not constitute sufficient grounds for incriminating the prime minister himself. However, before the host manages to complete his argument, the caller co-constructs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1461445612450374">Lerner, 1991</xref>): <italic>vehu– ′eh, hu ha′aba shelo</italic> (‘and he– uh, he’s his father’, lines 156–157), implying that the son’s pleading guilty incriminates the father since clearly, the father (and head of the party) knows about his son’s misconduct.</p>
<p>This argument is met with strong disagreement and much irony on the part of the host, first with <italic>′a–h, hevanti</italic> (‘oh, I get it’, lines 159–160) and then via his absurd analogy <italic>′az ′ani ′asiti ′averat tnu′a, veyishlexu ′et ′aba sheli, ya′asu lo shlilat rishayon</italic> (‘so I performed a traffic transgression, [. . .] and they’ll send my father, they’ll take away his driver license.’, lines 165–168). In other words, the host points out the ridiculousness of the son committing a crime and his father being punished for it.</p>
<p>The caller picks up on the irony already following his <italic>′a–h, hevanti</italic> (‘oh, I get it’, lines 159–160), and responds with irony of her own: <italic>hu lo yodea klum</italic> (‘he (the father) doesn’t know anything’, line 163); according to her, the father (as head of the party), Ariel Sharon, was perfectly aware of his son’s political funding corruption. In order to point out the absurdity of his analogy, the host, with dripping irony, adds: <italic>′at tsodeket. nu, ze– logika nexona shel xashiva</italic>. (‘you’re right. <italic>nu</italic>, that’s sound (correct) logical thinking’, lines 169–171). This non-stand-alone <italic>nu</italic> intensifies his irony and contempt. Without it (in a different context), such an utterance could have been interpreted literally. Again, the caller does not respond to this <italic>nu</italic> token as to a hastener of her ongoing action. Instead, she counters with <italic>betax sheze naxon</italic> (‘of course it’s correct’, line 172), only to be met with the host’s further contempt: <italic>beseder, ′etslex hakol naxon</italic>. (‘fine, with you everything is correct’, lines 173, 175), an utterance also alluding to the host’s long-term acquaintance with this caller’s opinions. As the old saying goes, ‘familiarity breeds contempt’.</p>
<p>At this point, the caller asks <italic>ma, hu lo yodea ma shehaben shelo ′ose?</italic> (‘what, he doesn’t know what his son is up to?’, lines 176–177), leading to the final escalation of contempt in the host’s <italic>nu be′emet</italic> (‘<italic>nu</italic>, really’, roughly equivalent (but far more contemptuous) to English <italic>oh come on</italic>, line 178), a cluster of two discourse markers expressing unmitigated reprimand (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1461445612450374">Maschler and Estlein, 2008</xref>), derision and contempt, preceding his request that she begin talking more seriously than she has up until now (line 179).</p>
<p>At this point, the caller indeed abandons this topic and, following the host’s demand, attempts to move on to another topic: <italic>tov. lama levazbez ′et hazman? ′ani yesh li dvarim xashuvim lehagid</italic>. (‘fine.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14-1461445612450374">14</xref></sup> why waste time? I I’ve got important things to say’, lines 180–182). However, the host counters this apparent cooperation with his demand with <italic>nu. ken, me′od xashuvim</italic>. (‘<italic>nu</italic>. right, very important’, lines 183–185). This is indeed <italic>nu</italic> granting her permission to move on to the next topic, but everything that had happened up until now in the interaction, along with his accompanying irony (<italic>ken, me′od xashuvim</italic>. (‘right, very important’)), all contribute to a highly contemptuous key accompanying this sequential <italic>nu</italic>.</p>
<p>Indeed, the sequential token at line 183 is another exception manifesting a non-stand-alone sequential <italic>nu</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-1461445612450374">Table 3</xref>). Again, we see how an utterance functioning in the sequential realm might come to have also keying functions in the discourse: if the situation of allowing an interlocutor to perform an action (continue her talk) is repetitively accompanied by irony and contempt (as may often be the case in heated argumentative discourse), over time the sequential token may become associated with contemptuous hues to the point of acquiring them regardless of the sequential function.</p>
<p>The contempt here is strong enough to cause the caller to pause for almost two seconds and take a deep breath (line 186) before moving on. However, the caller, being a ‘regular’, continues the interaction in spite of the disdain.</p>
<p>Contemptuous <italic>nu</italic> is not restricted to the host’s talk. In excerpt 8, the caller, another ‘regular’, is in the midst of complaining about the minister of defense for betraying the Israeli causes by leaning too much to the left. Such people, she asserts, are not fit to represent the nation. The host counters her argument as follows:</p>
<p>Excerpt 8: ‘The Minister of Defense’ 9.3.05</p>
<graphic id="img8-1461445612450374" position="anchor" xlink:href="10.1177_1461445612450374-img8.tif"/>
<p>The host employs an elaborate <italic>pre-</italic> (lines 147–150) to secure his turn at talk. In his pre-question (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1461445612450374">Schegloff, 1980</xref>) he inserts both the mitigating <italic>rak</italic> (‘just’) in <italic>′ani yaxol rak lish′ol she′ela?</italic> (‘may I just ask you a question?’, line 147) as well as an explanation for his following question. Hosts generally do not give accounts for asking questions as this is their institutional role. Both features of this <italic>pre</italic>- therefore suggest that the host knows this caller is a non-cooperating one (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1461445612450374">Dori-Hacohen, 2011</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16-1461445612450374">16</xref></sup> In his question, the host asks the caller if she has considered the myriad special army operations in which the minister of defense has participated (lines 151–155), thus suggesting that her criticism of the minister is unwarranted and that her claim that he should not represent the nation cannot be accepted. In response, the caller vehemently rejects the host’s question as irrelevant. She responds with <italic>′az ze marshe lo, ′et hateruf haze ′axshav?</italic> (‘so does this (i.e. the countless special operations the minister has participated in) allow him this insanity now?’), but not before preceding it with both English <italic>so what?</italic> as well as Hebrew <italic>nu ′az ma?</italic> (‘<italic>nu</italic> so what?’). This Israeli caller not only rejects the worthiness of the host’s argument; she also takes the opportunity to manifest her contempt towards him for having a different opinion. It is the Hebrew cluster in particular – the second one in the sequence – which delivers the more contemptuous tone.</p>
<p>This excerpt also suggests that it is not only hosts who employ contemptuous <italic>nu</italic> towards callers, but callers, too – and especially regular callers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1461445612450374">Dori-Hacohen, 2012</xref>) – may employ a similar practice to act contemptuously toward their host, albeit much less frequently (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1461445612450374">Table 2</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1461445612450374" sec-type="discussion">
<title>6. Discussion</title>
<p>We began this inquiry with the goal of further investigating the functions and grammaticization path of Hebrew <italic>nu</italic>. In the process, some particularities of Israeli political talk radio as illuminated by employment of <italic>nu</italic> were revealed. We have demonstrated that the study of the discourse marker <italic>nu</italic> in the political phone-in radio program reveals subtleties of key constructed by <italic>nu</italic> which are not found in the casual conversation database. Thus we have expanded our understanding of the ways this discourse marker can be employed in interaction. We have delved more deeply into the structural features of <italic>nu</italic> as they relate to its sequential and keying functions. These explorations have shed some new light on the question of how a sequential element might come to function also in the affective realm of discourse.</p>
<p>This is not the only case of a sequential token acquiring affective functions in discourse. Recently, Kasterpalu and Keevallik have analyzed the information receipt token <italic>ahah</italic> in third position in Estonian conversation, which is employed to mark ‘the gap between what the asker of the question knew before and what he/she just learned as a result of the answer’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1461445612450374">2010</xref>). They show that when the epistemic gap is large, there is an accompanying affective dimension to the receipt token, and its prosodic qualities change from neutral <italic>ahah</italic> to the heavily marked <italic>surprise</italic> token <italic>ah(h)aa</italic>. Thus, news receipt is not just about knowledge, but about the emotions accompanying it as well. Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-1461445612450374">Tanaka (2010)</xref> has recently shown that the Japanese response token <italic>hee</italic>, in addition to its usage as a newsmark, continuer, and assessment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1461445612450374">Mori, 2006</xref>), ‘has further uses in displaying <italic>appreciation</italic> for the cumulative epistemic coherence [. . .] of an informing in the light of other information or knowledge available to the <italic>hee</italic> producer’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-1461445612450374">Tanaka, 2010</xref>, emphasis ours). Estonian <italic>ahah</italic> and Japanese <italic>hee</italic>, then, are two more instances of sequential tokens having acquired affective functions as well.</p>
<p>However, the two studies above have not sought to explore the processes by which a sequential token might come to have also affective functions. In our study we have turned to grammaticization theory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1461445612450374">Hopper, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1461445612450374">Hopper and Traugott, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-1461445612450374">Traugott, 1989</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1461445612450374">1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1461445612450374">1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-1461445612450374">2003</xref>) in order to account for this phenomenon of language change.</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1461445612450374">Maschler (2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1461445612450374">2009</xref>) explores the phenomenon of sequential <italic>nu</italic> acquiring keying functions. In those studies, urging some metalingual utterance no longer verbalized but still in the background was posited in order to explain the change (see section 5.1). The implied metalingual actions urged in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-1461445612450374">Table 4</xref> explain the various keying tokens seen throughout this study.</p>
<table-wrap id="table4-1461445612450374" position="float">
<label>Table 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Metalingual actions urged by keying <italic>nu</italic> tokens.</p></caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table4-1461445612450374" xlink:href="10.1177_1461445612450374-table4.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="left"/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Excerpt</th>
<th align="left">Key</th>
<th align="left">Metalingual action urged</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>ridiculing</td>
<td>Realization of ridiculousness of opponent’s argument</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6</td>
<td>belittling</td>
<td>Realization of opponent’s self-contradiction + speaker’s celebration of it</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7, line 170</td>
<td>contempt</td>
<td>Realization of irony in speaker’s talk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7, line 178</td>
<td>contempt</td>
<td>Stopping opponent’s non-serious argument (in speaker’s judgment)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8</td>
<td>contempt</td>
<td>Very strong rejection of opponent’s argument</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>Since the metalingual action urged is clear from context, there is no need to verbalize it, a situation resulting in the fact that the speaker most often verbalizes only the <italic>nu</italic> token urging that metalingual action, and attaches it to the following utterance. This in turn results in non-stand-alone keying <italic>nu</italic>.</p>
<p>In the present study, a closer look at the structural properties of stand-alone versus non-stand-alone <italic>nu</italic> tokens (section 5.2) revealed an explanation not necessitating (but also not contradicting) such a hypothesized metalingual utterance. The tones on the disaligned extreme of the key continuum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1461445612450374">Figure 2</xref>) (belittling and contempt) stem from the inherent impoliteness in attempting to control an interlocutor’s actions (i.e. hastening and urging). This move is relatively unmitigated in these programs (unlike the majority of casual conversation cases), therefore resulting in affects on the disaligned extreme. Such tones originate also in the contempt often accompanying the action of reluctantly allowing an opponent to continue his/her talk in a heated argument (e.g. excerpt 7, line 183). The tones on the aligned extreme (joking, humorously mocking) originate from the fact that in certain contexts (e.g. excerpt 5), impolite actions are mitigated by compensatory humor and mockery, but such contexts are scarce in these political call-in programs. Over time, if the sequential action and its accompanying tone (from joking to contempt) are repeated over and over again, we have argued that by way of <italic>pragmatic strengthening</italic> of a connotation, a form acquires a new linguistic function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1461445612450374">Dahl, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1461445612450374">Traugott, 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1461445612450374">1999</xref>), and sequential <italic>nu</italic> begins to acquire the affective meanings, which eventually become dissociated from the sequential ones. In this way, a token starting out as a sequential one may become an affective token.</p>
<p>One possible objection to this argument might be that <italic>nu</italic> is simply acquiring the key of the surrounding discourse, regardless of the impoliteness inherent to its sequential functions. This claim is disproven by the fact that <italic>nu</italic> does not acquire just any key from the surrounding discourse (such as the tone of despair in excerpt 2, line 309, for instance), but specifically the keys represented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1461445612450374">Figure 2</xref> which can all be traced back to the basic impoliteness inherent to attempting to control another’s actions – by far the most frequent function of <italic>nu</italic> in casual talk, and most likely the primary one (as attested also by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1461445612450374">Avneyon’s (1998)</xref> classification of <italic>nu</italic> as an ‘urging word’).</p>
<p>There is no way to prove our suggested grammaticization path, since recordings of <italic>nu</italic> from an earlier period at which this form was first borrowed into the language (when <italic>nu</italic> might have functioned exclusively sequentially but not affectively) do not exist. Furthermore, it seems that already in the languages of origin (at least in Yiddish, Russian, and Polish, as discussed in section 1.1 above), <italic>nu</italic>/<italic>no</italic> had both sequential and emotive functions before being borrowed into Hebrew. However, the emotive functions existing in the languages of origin are probably not that relevant, because there is some evidence that the particular emotive functions developed in the Israeli Hebrew context are different from those developed in the languages of origin. More research is necessary for unraveling the precise emotive functions of the ‘equivalents’ of <italic>nu</italic> in those languages.</p>
<p>The grammaticization path hypothesized here, then, cannot be proven, but it can be supported by two more properties characterizing grammaticization – <italic>subjectification</italic> and <italic>intersubjectivization</italic>. In the process of grammaticization, discourse markers become ‘increasingly based in the speaker’s subjective belief/state/attitude toward the proposition’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-1461445612450374">Traugott, 1989</xref>: 35), and then more intersubjective, that is, more concerned with the ‘self’ of the addressee (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-1461445612450374">Traugott, 2003</xref>). By introducing the speaker’s stance towards the addressee’s arguments, keying <italic>nu</italic> is far more subjective and intersubjective than sequential <italic>nu</italic>.</p>
<p>Our study illuminates a special type of grammaticization, one involving emotion in discourse. One of the most common processes accompanying grammaticization is <italic>semantic loss</italic> or <italic>bleaching</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1461445612450374">Lehmann, 1995 [1982]</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-1461445612450374">von der Gabelentz, 1891</xref>), as for example when an element such as <italic>bekitsur</italic> (‘anyway’, lit. ‘in short’) loses its referential meaning related to the concept of ‘shortness’ and becomes a discourse marker employed to foreground subsequent discourse (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1461445612450374">Maschler, 2009</xref>). As <italic>nu</italic> is a non-referential item to begin with, no semantic loss is involved in our case. Here we find something altogether different – a case of grammaticization in which a non-referential item has <italic>acquired</italic> affective meaning. Affective meaning is, of course, very different from referential meaning. On the one hand, no reference to the extralingual world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1461445612450374">Becker, 1979</xref>) is involved; on the other hand, prosody plays a much more crucial role. Affect is also tied more tightly to the general key of the particular context in which the form occurs. Over recurrent use in similar contexts, however, and in keeping with current theories of semantic change (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1461445612450374">Traugott, 1995</xref>), we have suggested that tokens become dissociated from the particular context, so that Hebrew speakers come to associate specific affects with this token.</p>
<p>In the course of exploring the functions and employment of <italic>nu</italic>, some particularities of Israeli political talk radio were illuminated. We have shown, first of all, that this discourse marker is employed differently in this context as compared with its employment in casual everyday conversation. We have seen how <italic>nu</italic> is employed in a way that constructs the difference between the roles of host and caller, and how hosts employ it to manage the interactions in ways that achieve this particular institutional setting (sections 3 and 4).</p>
<p>Several factors contribute to the differences between the functions and distribution of <italic>nu</italic> in the two genres. Israeli political phone-in radio talk exhibits:</p>
<list id="list1-1461445612450374" list-type="bullet">
<list-item><p>no tokens of <italic>nu</italic> hastening non-verbal actions (with the exception of one token hastening a cognitive action, borderline between a verbal and a non-verbal one), for the simple reason that talk-radio participants are not generally mutually engaged in other actions besides their talk;</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>a much higher rate of ‘go-ahead’ <italic>nu</italic> (21% of all tokens, as opposed to 3% in casual conversation) because such tokens tend to follow metalingual announcements by the interlocutor of performing some action in the discourse realm</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>announcements which are much more common in the non-narrative discourse constituting these programs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1461445612450374">Hacohen, 2007</xref>) than in narrative discourse, common in the casual conversation database. Furthermore, at least in Israel, callers do not refrain from taking the role of allowing the host to ‘go ahead’.</p></list-item></list>
<p>Katriel, in her study of therapeutic discourse on Israeli talk radio (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1461445612450374">2004</xref>), found that the sense of equality between host and caller is increased due to the spontaneity of the radio phone-in interaction. She demonstrated that the cultural context in Israel is more communal and less rigidly constructed than was described for the United States or the United Kingdom. As in television interviews (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-1461445612450374">Weizman, 2008</xref>), in Israel the interactional norms for hosts (or interviewers) and callers (or interviewees) are not kept quite as strictly as they are in the US or the UK (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1461445612450374">Clayman and Heritage, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1461445612450374">Greatbatch, 1986</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1461445612450374">1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1461445612450374">Heritage and Clayman, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1461445612450374">Hutchby, 1991</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1461445612450374">1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1461445612450374">1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1461445612450374">O’Keeffe, 2006</xref>), thereby creating a less rigid division of labor between host and caller.</p>
<p>However, the most striking difference between <italic>nu</italic> in casual talk as opposed to <italic>nu</italic> in the radiophonic data has to do with its keying function. We have seen that while this function is manifested by less than a quarter of all casual talk cases, in the radio programs, over half the tokens carry this function. Interestingly, the study of Icelandic <italic>nú</italic> (see note 6) has revealed a related pattern. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1461445612450374">Hilmisdóttir (2007)</xref> has studied over 14 hours of Icelandic discourse, both everyday conversations as well as a call-in radio program. She shows that this token functions in three categories throughout her data: as a temporal marker, tone particle, and utterance particle. The finding relevant for our purposes concerns tone particles, ‘particles that do not have a semantico-referential function but instead modify the whole utterance by giving it a certain tone’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1461445612450374">2007</xref>: 48). She finds that Icelandic <italic>nú</italic> ‘give[s] the utterance in which it occurs a decisive tone’ (p. 228). While the everyday conversations in her database manifest a frequency of between 0.16 and 0.17 tokens of tone <italic>nú</italic> particles per minute, the call-in program manifests a frequency of 1.48 tokens per minute. Hilmisdóttir attributes this difference to ‘the activities in which the interlocutors are engaged. [. . .] argumentative discourse is one of the main environments in which the tone particle <italic>nú</italic> is employed’ (p. 151). Similarly, we have seen that the political phone-in programs investigated in our study are highly argumentative (see further, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1461445612450374">Dori-Hacohen, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>We would like to suggest that the specific clustering of Hebrew <italic>nu</italic> along the key continuum, close to the extreme of belittling the addressee and beyond, constitutes one of the means employed particularly by the host (almost five times more frequently than by the caller; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1461445612450374">Table 2</xref>) to construct the argumentative tone of the Israeli political phone-in interaction. Employment of <italic>nu</italic> as a keying device suggests, then, that an institutional setting can be established not only via particular sequential practices (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1461445612450374">Greatbatch, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1461445612450374">Hutchby, 1991</xref>) or withholding of certain elements (such as minimal responses; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1461445612450374">Heritage, 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1461445612450374">Schegloff, 1982</xref>), but also through specific keying uses of discourse markers: hosts make abundant use of particular keying functions of <italic>nu</italic> – functions not very common in casual conversation – in order to set the tone of the institutional interaction to the ‘appropriate’ argumentative and sometimes abusive key.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<app-group>
<app id="app1-1461445612450374">
<title>Abbreviations</title>
<p>FEM feminine</p>
<p>SG singular</p>
<p>PL plural</p>
<sec id="section15-1461445612450374">
<title>Appendix: Transcription conventions</title>
<p>Each line denotes an intonation unit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1461445612450374">Chafe, 1994</xref>) and is followed by an English gloss. Where this gloss is not close enough to an English utterance, it is followed by a third line supplying a usually literal (but sometimes functional) translation. Utterances under consideration (mostly <italic>nu</italic> tokens) are given in <bold>boldface</bold>.</p>
<p>Transcription basically follows <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1461445612450374">Chafe (1994)</xref>, with a few additions:</p>
<list id="list2-1461445612450374" list-type="simple">
<list-item><p>. . . – half second pause (each extra dot = another 1/2 second)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>. . – perceptible pause of less than half a second</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>(3.56) – measured pause of 3.56 seconds</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>, – comma at end of line – continuing intonation (‘more to come’)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>. – period at end of line – sentence final falling intonation</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>? – question mark at end of line – sentence final rising intonation, ‘appeal intonation’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1461445612450374">Du Bois et al., 1992</xref>)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>! – exclamation mark at end of line – sentence final exclamatory intonation</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>ø – lack of punctuation at end of line – a fragmentary intonation unit, one which never reached completion.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>– two hyphens – elongation of preceding vowel sound</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>square bracket to the left of two consecutive lines indicates beginning of overlapping speech, two speakers talking at once</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>alignment such that the right of the top line is placed over the left of the bottom line indicates latching, no interturn pause</p></list-item>
<list-item><p><italic>pp</italic> – <italic>pianissimo</italic> (spoken very softly) (other musical notation as needed)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>/??????/ – transcription impossible</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>/words within slashes/ indicate uncertain transcription</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>{in curly brackets} – transcriber’s comments</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>[xxxxx] – material within square brackets <italic>in the gloss</italic> indicates exuberances of translation (what is not there in the original)</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>′ – uninverted quotation mark in the middle of a transliterated word indicates the glottal stop phoneme.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>’ – inverted quotation mark in the middle of a transliterated word indicates an elided form (e.g. <italic>ts’xa</italic> instead of <italic>tsrixa</italic> (‘needs’, FEM, SG)).
</p>
</sec>
</app>
</app-group>
<ack>
<p>Previous versions of this work were presented at the Seventh Oranim Conference ‘Hebrew – A Living Language’, 2 February 2010, Oranim, Israel and at the panel on minimal responses at the International Conference on Conversation Analysis (ICCA), 4–8 July 2010, Mannheim, Germany. We thank the participants for their comments and suggestions, as well as the anonymous reviewers.</p>
</ack>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1461445612450374">
<label>1.</label>
<p>For transcription conventions, see <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-1461445612450374">Appendix</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1461445612450374">
<label>2.</label>
<p>Adapting Chafe’s studies of English intonation (1994: 60) to Hebrew, by ‘continuing intonation’ we refer to a range of non-terminal Hebrew pitch contours (all transcribed by a comma) and distinguished from: 1) the terminal falling pitch contour associated with the end of a declarative sentence or a question-word question; and 2) the terminal high rising pitch contour associated with a yes/no question.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1461445612450374">
<label>3.</label>
<p>The overhearing audience here consists of the other ‘survivors’ co-present in the tribal council, as well as the imagined home audience.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1461445612450374">
<label>4.</label>
<p>For a study of Hebrew ′<italic>ata yodea</italic> (‘you know’), see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1461445612450374">Maschler (in press)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-1461445612450374">
<label>5.</label>
<p>See <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1461445612450374">Maschler (2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1461445612450374">2009</xref>) for a sequential explanation of how this single form might come to be employed in both of these functions.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-1461445612450374">
<label>6.</label>
<p>According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1461445612450374">Kryk-Kastovsky (1997)</xref>, Old English <italic>nu</italic> (from which English <italic>now</italic> has evolved) in its primary usage as an adverb of time is first attested in 825 ad. At almost the same time, another, non-propositional, discoursal use of <italic>nu</italic> is attested. This Old English form is related to:
<disp-quote>
<p>the Old Germanic form <italic>nú</italic> dating from the 8th century, which later became Middle High German <italic>nú, nuo, nuon</italic>, late Middle High German <italic>nun</italic>, Old Saxon <italic>nu</italic>, Middle Low German, Middle Dutch <italic>nū</italic>, Dutch <italic>nu</italic>, Old Norse <italic>nū</italic>, Swedish, Danish <italic>nu</italic>. All these Germanic forms can be traced back to the PIE [Proto Indo-European] <italic>nú.</italic> It is therefore not surprising that parallel forms occur in many non-Germanic languages, cf. the particle use of Sanskrit <italic>nú</italic> glossed in German as ‘nun, jetzt, also, gewiss’, i.e. both a time adverb and DP [‘discourse particle’], Greek <italic>ny</italic> (adverb and an enclitic particle), Latin <italic>nunc</italic> (adverb and DP), Lithuanian <italic>nū</italic> (adverb and DP), OCS [Old Church Slavonic] <italic>nyně</italic>, Russian <italic>nyně</italic> ‘now’ vs. <italic>no</italic> ‘but’, vs. <italic>nu</italic> (particle), Old Irish verbal particle <italic>no-, nu-.</italic> (1997: 323)</p>
<p>Related forms exist in a variety of languages (three of which were discussed in section 1.1), not all of which are Indo-European: English <italic>now</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1461445612450374">Aijmer, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1461445612450374">Kryk-Kastovsky, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-1461445612450374">Schiffrin, 1987</xref>), Swedish <italic>nu, nå</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1461445612450374">Lehti-Eklund, 1992</xref>), Swedish (spoken in Finland) <italic>nu</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1461445612450374">Hakulinen and Saari, 1995</xref>), Norwegian <italic>nå</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1461445612450374">Andvik, 1992</xref>), Russian <italic>nu</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1461445612450374">Grenoble, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr56-1461445612450374">Multisilta, 1995</xref>), Polish <italic>no</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1461445612450374">Kryk, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1461445612450374">Kryk-Kastovsky, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-1461445612450374">Wierzbicka, 1976</xref>), Danish <italic>nu, nå</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-1461445612450374">Steensig, 2001</xref>), and Icelandic <italic>nú</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1461445612450374">Hilmisdóttir, 2007</xref>), as well as Yiddish <italic>nu</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1461445612450374">Rosten, 2003 [1968]</xref>), Czech and Slovak (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1461445612450374">Kryk-Kastovsky, 1997</xref>), Estonian (Keevallik, personal communication), Romani (Matras, personal communication) and Kazakh (Auer, personal communication). However, much more research is necessary in order to understand the contact history of these parallels in this array of languages.</p>
</disp-quote>
</p>
<p><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1461445612450374">Auer and Maschler (in preparation)</xref> are currently editing a collection of studies based on the FRIAS workshop ‘Language Contact in Pragmatics’ which brought together linguists working on this discourse marker in 17 different languages during November 2011. For details, see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.frias.uni-freiburg.de/lang_and_lit/veranstaltungen/internationales-kolloquium-zum-sprachkontakt">http://www.frias.uni-freiburg.de/lang_and_lit/veranstaltungen/internationales-kolloquium-zum-sprachkontakt</ext-link></p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-1461445612450374">
<label>7.</label>
<p>English ‘you guys’, far from being perfect, is the closest we could come up with.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-1461445612450374">
<label>8.</label>
<p>With the possible exception of the one <italic>nu</italic> found in the radio corpus (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1461445612450374">Table 1</xref>), which is employed as a self-hastener of the cognitive action of remembering a name. See section 2.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-1461445612450374">
<label>9.</label>
<p>For support for this argument based on speaker interpretations, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1461445612450374">Maschler (2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1461445612450374">2009</xref>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-1461445612450374">
<label>10.</label>
<p>A non-stand-alone ‘go-ahead’ token of <italic>nu</italic> is examined in excerpt 7 later.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-1461445612450374">
<label>11.</label>
<p>This fixed idiom goes back to that part of the Talmud (the Jewish Canon) called Mishnah, the collection of oral texts which <italic>husderu</italic> (‘were assembled’) to form the canonic written text.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-1461445612450374">
<label>12.</label>
<p>The prior-text (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1461445612450374">Becker, 1979</xref>) here is the last line of a famous poem by the national poet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1461445612450374">Bialik (1933)</xref> called <italic>′al hashxita</italic> (‘Concerning the Slaughter’), written following the Kishinev pogrom in 1903.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn13-1461445612450374">
<label>13.</label>
<p><italic>′aval</italic> (‘but’) is one of the only Hebrew discourse markers which occasionally appear at the non-intonation-unit initial position, as it is found here (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1461445612450374">Mulder and Thompson, 2008</xref>, for English <italic>but</italic>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn14-1461445612450374">
<label>14.</label>
<p>For a study of Hebrew <italic>tov</italic> (‘okay, fine’, lit. ‘good’), see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1461445612450374">Maschler (2009)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn15-1461445612450374">
<label>15.</label>
<p>For this discourse marker, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1461445612450374">Maschler (in press)</xref>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn16-1461445612450374">
<label>16.</label>
<p>The host indeed ends this interaction by disconnecting the caller, a rare occurrence in the corpus (see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1461445612450374">Dori-Hacohen, 2012</xref>).</p></fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<bio>
<title>Author biographies</title>
<p><bold>Yael Maschler</bold> teaches Linguistics at the Department of Hebrew Language, University of Haifa. She is interested in the crystallization of grammatical structure from interaction. Her articles explore bilingual discourse, discourse markers, discourse and morpho-syntax (comparative studies of self-repair), syntax of spoken language, and stance-taking. Her book <italic>Metalanguage in Interaction: Hebrew Discourse Markers</italic> was published by John Benjamins in 2009. She has recently organized an international workshop with Peter Auer from the Freiburg Institute for Advanced Studies (FRIAS), bringing together linguists working on the particle <italic>nu</italic> in 17 different languages and is co-editing a collection based on this workshop (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1461445612450374">Auer and Maschler, in preparation</xref>).</p>
<p><bold>Gonen Dori-Hacohen</bold> received his PhD from the Department of Communication at the University of Haifa, Israel. He uses discourse analysis, in its various branches, to study the intersection of talk, politics, and culture. His dissertation described the ways linguistic and interactional features construct Israeli radio phone-in programs as a public sphere. He is an Assistant Professor at the Department of Communication, University of Massachusetts, Amherst, USA.</p>
</bio>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Aijmer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Now may we have a word on this: The use of ‘now’ as a discourse particle</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Kytö</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. (eds) <source>Corpus Linguistics Hard and Soft</source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rodopi</publisher-name>, <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Andvik</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <source>A Pragmatic Analysis of Norwegian Modal Particles</source>. <publisher-loc>Arlington</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Summer Institute in Linguistics and The University of Texas at Arlington Publications in Linguistics</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Auer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maschler</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds.) (<comment>in preparation</comment>) <source>Language Contact in Pragmatics: The Discourse Marker nu and Its Variants Across the Languages of Europe and Beyond</source>. <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Walter de Gruyter</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Avneyon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Milon Sapir Entsiklopedi</source> [<trans-source xml:lang="en">The Encyclopedic Sapphire Dictionary</trans-source>]. <publisher-loc>Or Yehuda</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hed ′Artsi Publishing Ltd/Eitav Publishing House Ltd</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1975</year>) <article-title>Listener responses to filled pauses in relation to floor apportionment</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Social and Clinical Psychology</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>423</fpage>–<lpage>424</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Beattie</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>) <article-title>The dynamics of interruption and the filled pause</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Social and Clinical Psychology</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>283</fpage>–<lpage>284</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>Text-building, epistemology, and esthetics in Javanese shadow theater</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yengoyan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Imagination of Reality</source>. <publisher-loc>Norwood, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ablex</publisher-name>, <fpage>211</fpage>–<lpage>243</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bialik</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1933</year>) <source>Kitvey Ch. N. Bialik</source> [<trans-source xml:lang="en">Writings of Ch. N. Bialik</trans-source>]. <publisher-loc>Tel Aviv</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Axdut</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Brody</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Particles borrowed from Spanish as discourse markers in Mayan languages</article-title>. <source>Anthropological Linguistics</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>507</fpage>–<lpage>521</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chafe</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <source>Discourse, Consciousness, and Time: The Flow and Displacement of Conscious Experience in Speaking and Writing</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Clayman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heritage</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>The News Interview: Journalists and Public Figures on the Air</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Couper-Kuhlen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A sequential approach to affect: The case of ‘disappointment’</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Haakana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laakso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Selting</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Talk in Interaction: Comparative Dimensions</source>. <publisher-loc>Helsinki</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Finnish Literature Society</publisher-name>, <fpage>94</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>Ö</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <source>Tense and Aspect Systems</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dori-Hacohen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Citizens talk about public affairs: The description of the political phone-in program on Israeli public radio</article-title>. <comment>PhD dissertation</comment>, <publisher-name>University of Haifa</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dori-Hacohen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>‘I have a question for you’: Two practices for achieving institutional interaction in Israeli radio phone-in programs</article-title>. <source>Pragmatics</source> <volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>527</fpage>–<lpage>548</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dori-Hacohen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>‘With whom do I have the pleasure?’: Caller categories in Israeli political radio phone-in programs</article-title>. <source>Journal of Pragmatics</source> <volume>44</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>280</fpage>–<lpage>297</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Du Bois</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cumming</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schuetze-Coburn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Paolino</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <source>Discourse Transcription: Santa Barbara Papers in Linguistics</source>, <volume>vol. 4</volume>. <publisher-loc>Santa Barbara</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department of Linguistics, University of California, Santa Barbara</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Even-Shoshan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Milon even shoshan</source> [<trans-source xml:lang="en">The Even Shoshan Dictionary</trans-source>]. <publisher-loc>Jerusalem</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hamilon Hexadash Inc</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Frankel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Yalda</source> [<trans-source xml:lang="en">A Girl</trans-source>]. <publisher-loc>Tel Aviv</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Mapa</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goffman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>) <source>Forms of Talk</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Pennsylvania Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Greatbatch</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Some standard uses of supplementary questions in news interviews</article-title>. <source>Language and Linguistics</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>86</fpage>–<lpage>123</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Greatbatch</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>A turn-taking system for British news interviews</article-title>. <source>Language in Society</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>401</fpage>–<lpage>430</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Grenoble</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <source>Deixis and Information Packaging in Russian Discourse</source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Benjamins</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gumperz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>) <source>Discourse Strategies</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hacohen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Narrative and argumentation in Israel radio phone-ins</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Van Eemeren</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Willard</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garssen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <conf-name>Proceedings of the 6th ISSA Conference</conf-name>. <conf-loc>Amsterdam: SicSat</conf-loc>, <fpage>549</fpage>–<lpage>556</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hakulinen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Temporaalisesta adverbista diskurssipartikkeliksi</article-title>. <source>Virittäjä</source>. <comment>Kotikielen seuran aikakausilehti 99</comment>, <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>481</fpage>–<lpage>663</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heritage</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1985</year>) <article-title>Analyzing news interviews: Aspects of the production of talk for an overhearing audience</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>van Dijk</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Handbook of Discourse Analysis, Vol. 3: Discourse and Dialogue</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>119</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heritage</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Clayman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Talk in Action: Interactions, Identities, and Institutions</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hilmisdóttir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A sequential analysis of <italic>nú</italic> and <italic>núna</italic> in Icelandic conversation</article-title>. <comment>PhD dissertation</comment>, <publisher-name>Department of Scandinavian Languages and Literature</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>University of Helsinki</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hopper</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Emergent grammar</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Aske</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beery</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Michaelis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Filip</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Proceedings of the Thirteenth Annual Meeting of the Berkeley Linguistics Society</source>. <publisher-loc>Berkeley, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Berkeley Linguistics Society</publisher-name>, <fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>157</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hopper</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Traugott</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Grammaticalization</source>, <edition>2nd edn.</edition> <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hutchby</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>The organization of talk on talk radio</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Scannell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Broadcast Talk</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAGE</publisher-name>, <fpage>119</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hutchby</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Confrontation Talk: Arguments, Asymmetries, and Power on Talk Radio</source>. <publisher-loc>Mahwah, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hutchby</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Beyond agnosticism? Conversation analysis and the sociological agenda</article-title>. <source>Research on Language and Social Interaction</source> <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hymes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1986</year>) <article-title>Models of the interaction of language and social life</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Gumperz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hymes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Directions in Sociolinguistics</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Basil Blackwell</publisher-name>, <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kasterpalu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keevallik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Marking the epistemic gap in news receipts</article-title>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the International Conference on Conversation Analysis (ICCA 2010)</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Mannheim, Germany</conf-loc>, <conf-date>8 July</conf-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Katovich</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reese</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>The regular: Full-time identities and membership in an urban bar</article-title>. <source>Journal of Contemporary Ethnography</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>308</fpage>–<lpage>343</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Katriel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Dialogic Moments: From Soul Talks to Talk Radio in Israeli Culture</source>. <publisher-loc>Detroit</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wayne State University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kryk</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>The pragmatics of interjections: The case of Polish</article-title> <source>no. Journal of Pragmatics</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>–<lpage>137</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kryk-Kastovsky</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>From temporal adverbs to discourse particles: An instance of cross-linguistic grammaticalization?</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Nevalainen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kahlas-Tarkka</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>To Explain the Present: Studies in the Changing English Language in Honour of Matti Rissanen</source>. <publisher-loc>Helsinki</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Société Néophilologique</publisher-name>, <fpage>319</fpage>–<lpage>328</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995 [1982]</year>) <source>Thoughts on Grammaticalization</source>. <publisher-loc>Munich</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lincom Europa</publisher-name>. (<comment>First published 1982 as <italic>Thoughts on Grammaticalization: A Programmatic Sketch</italic>, no. 48 in the series Arbeiten des Kölner Universalien-Projektes. Cologne: University of Cologne, Institut für Sprachwissenschaft</comment>.)</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lehti-Eklund</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Användingen av partikeln <italic>nå</italic> i helsingforssvenska samtal</article-title>. <conf-name>Svenskans Beskrivining 19, Förhandlingar vid Nittonde sammankomsten för svenskans beskrivining</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Stockholm den</conf-loc> <conf-date>2–3 April</conf-date>, <fpage>174</fpage>–<lpage>184</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lerner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>On the syntax of sentences-in-progress</article-title>. <source>Language in Society</source> <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>441</fpage>–<lpage>458</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maschler</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>The games bilinguals play: A discourse analysis of Hebrew–English bilingual conversation</article-title>. <comment>PhD dissertation</comment>, <publisher-name>University of Michigan</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Ann Arbor</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maschler</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Metalanguaging and discourse markers in bilingual conversation</article-title>. <source>Language in Society</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>325</fpage>–<lpage>366</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maschler</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title><italic>Rotse lishmoa keta?</italic> ‘Wanna hear something weird/funny [lit. “a segment”]?’: The discourse markers segmenting Israeli Hebrew talk-in-interaction</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Jucker</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ziv</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Discourse Markers: Descriptions and Theory</source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Benjamins</publisher-name>, <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Maschler</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Discourse markers in bilingual conversation. Special issue of</article-title> <source>International Journal of Bilingualism</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>561</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maschler</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The discourse marker <italic>nu</italic>: Israeli Hebrew impatience in interaction</article-title>. <source>Text</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>89</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maschler</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Metalanguage in Interaction: Hebrew Discourse Markers</source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam and Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Benjamins</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maschler</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>in press</year>) <article-title>Emergent projecting constructions: The case of Hebrew <italic>yada</italic> (‘know’)</article-title>. <source>Studies in Language</source>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Maschler</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Estlein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Stance-taking in Israeli Hebrew casual conversation via be ′emet (‘really, actually, indeed’, lit. ‘in truth’)</article-title>. <source>Discourse Studies</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>283</fpage>–<lpage>316</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Matras</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Utterance modifiers and universals of grammatical borrowing</article-title>. <source>Linguistics</source> <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>281</fpage>–<lpage>331</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mazo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Voloshin</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Forms and functions of the discourse marker <italic>nu</italic> in Russian and Hebrew conversations</article-title>. <comment>A Seminar Paper</comment>. <publisher-name>Department of English, University of Haifa at Oranim</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The workings of the Japanese <italic>hee</italic> in informing sequences</article-title>. <source>Journal of Pragmatics</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>1175</fpage>–<lpage>1205</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mulder</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The grammaticization of English <italic>but</italic> as a final particle in English conversation</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Laury</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Crosslinguistic Studies of Clause Combining: The Multifunctionality of Conjunctions</source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam and Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Benjamins</publisher-name>, <fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>204</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Multisilta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Pragmatic particles <italic>nu</italic> and <italic>vot</italic> in spoken Russian</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Wårvik</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tanskanen</surname><given-names>S-K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hiltungen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <conf-name>Organization in Discourse: Proceedings from the Turku Conference</conf-name> (<comment>Anglicana Tukuensia 14</comment>). <conf-loc>Turku: University of Turku</conf-loc>, <fpage>381</fpage>–<lpage>392</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>O’Keeffe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Investigating Media Discourse</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rosten</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003 [1968]</year>) <source>The New Joys of Yiddish</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Arrow Books</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Salmons</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Bilingual discourse marking: Code switching, borrowing, and convergence in some German–American dialects</article-title>. <source>Linguistics</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>453</fpage>–<lpage>480</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schegloff</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1980</year>) <article-title>Preliminaries to preliminaries: ‘Can I ask you a question?’</article-title>. <source>Sociological Inquiry</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>104</fpage>–<lpage>152</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schegloff</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Discourse as an interactional achievement: Some uses of ‘uh huh’ and other things that come between sentences</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Tannen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Georgetown University Roundtable on Languages and Linguistics (GURT) 1981: Analyzing Discourse: Text and Talk</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Georgetown University Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>71</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schegloff</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>On the organization of sequences as a source of ‘coherence’ in talk-in-interaction</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Dorval</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Conversational Organization and its Development (Advances in Discourse Processes XXIX)</source>. <publisher-loc>Norwood, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ablex</publisher-name>, <fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schegloff</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Sequence Organization in Interaction: A Primer in Conversation Analysis</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schegloff</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sacks</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>) <article-title>Opening up closings</article-title>. <source>Semiotica</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>289</fpage>–<lpage>327</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schiffrin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <source>Discourse Markers</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schiffrin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <source>Approaches to Discourse</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sorjonen</surname><given-names>M-L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Responding in Conversation: A Study of Response Particles in Finnish</source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam and Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Benjamins</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sorjonen</surname><given-names>M-L</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Recipient activities: The particle <italic>no</italic> as a go-ahead response in Finnish conversations</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Language of Turn and Sequence</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>165</fpage>–<lpage>195</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Steensig</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Sprog i virkeligheden - bidrag til en interaktionel lingvistik</source>. <publisher-loc>Aarhus</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Aarhus Universitetsforlag</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stivers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>‘No no no’ and other types of multiple sayings in social interaction</article-title>. <source>Human Communication Research</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>260</fpage>–<lpage>293</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The Japanese response token <italic>Hee</italic> for appreciating an informing as epistemically coherent</article-title>. <conf-name>Paper presented at the International Conference on Conversation Analysis (ICCA 2010)</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Mannheim, Germany</conf-loc>, <conf-date>8 July</conf-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tannen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2007 [1989]</year>) <source>Talking Voices: Repetition, Dialogue, and Imagery in Conversational Discourse</source>, <edition>2nd edn.</edition> <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Traugott</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>On the rise of epistemic meanings in English: An example of subjectification in semantic change</article-title>. <source>Language</source> <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Traugott</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Subjectification in grammaticalisation</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Subjectivity and Subjectivisation: Linguistic Perspectives</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Traugott</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The role of pragmatics in semantic change</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Verschueren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <conf-name>Pragmatics in 1998: Selected Papers from the 6th International Pragmatics Conference</conf-name>, <volume>vol. II</volume>. <publisher-loc>Antwerp</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Pragmatics Association</publisher-name>, <fpage>93</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Traugott</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>From subjectification to intersubjectification</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Motives for Language Change</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>124</fpage>–<lpage>139</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr77-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>von der Gabelentz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1891</year>) <source>Die Sprachwissenschaft. Ihre Aufgaben, Methoden, und bisherigen Ergebnisse</source>. <publisher-loc>Leipzig</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Weigel</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr78-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Weizman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Positioning in Media Dialogue: Negotiating Roles in the News Interview</source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Benjamins</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr79-1461445612450374">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wierzbicka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>Particles and linguistic relativity</article-title>. <source>International Review of Slavic Linguistics</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>327</fpage>–<lpage>367</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>