<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CUS</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcus</journal-id>
<journal-title>Cultural Sociology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1749-9755</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1749-9763</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1749975512458626a</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1749975512458626a</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Closure: The Rush to End Grief and What It Costs Us</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>Tony</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1749975512458626">University of Bath, UK</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>489</fpage>
<lpage>491</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Berns</surname><given-names>Nancy</given-names></name>
</person-group> <source>Closure: The Rush to End Grief and What It Costs Us</source> <publisher-name>Temple University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>, <year>2011</year>, <price>£16.99</price> (ISBN-13: <isbn>978-1439905777</isbn>), <page-count count="xiii"/> + <page-count count="214"/> pp.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications and the British Sociological Association</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>‘Closure’ has been a fashionable word in the USA since the early 1990s, and since the middle of the 2000s I have begun to hear it over here in the UK too. Whether the word has spread yet, either in English or in translation, to other European countries, I do not know. Anyway, I have long been puzzled quite what the word means, why people use it and how it came to enter popular discourse, not least as the word is not found in academic literature on loss and grief. So I looked forward to reading Nancy Berns’ sociological tour of this little piece of contemporary American culture. Hers is a book that was just waiting to be written.</p>
<p>Berns employs two analytical tools familiar to readers of <italic>Cultural Sociology</italic> – feeling rules, and social constructionism. More specifically, she shows that closure provides a new language for talking about feelings associated with loss and grief. And she uses Goffman’s concept of framing: closure is ‘a frame used to explain how we should respond to loss’ (p. 4).</p>
<p>What I found particularly illuminating is Berns’ documentation of closure’s ‘tangled web’ of different, even opposing meanings. She identifies six types of closure talk: closing a chapter, remembering, forgetting, getting even, knowing, and confessing or forgiving. These are all promoted as ways of ending the pain of loss. This means that virtually any policy, practice, commodity or service – from techniques for letting go to memorials for remembering, from taking revenge through witnessing capital punishment, to forgiving via restorative justice – can be sold by business or claimed by politicians as providing closure.</p>
<p>At this point, Berns makes a telling comparison with a TV advertisement for beef burgers that depicts a sizzling barbeque. The ad relies on the sound of the sizzle to sell the beef – no sizzle, no sale – even though the sizzle is unrelated to the beef’s quality. Closure is the sizzle that sells caskets, funeral services, political programs, public memorials, etc., etc. The implication is that if you do not buy a particular product or support a political project, you will not find closure. Berns’ advice to American consumers and voters is to forget the vacuous promise of closure and judge the product for itself. Berns is no ivory tower sociologist, for she concludes that Americans are being manipulated by promises of closure – hence the subtitle’s concern with what closure costs us. By relativizing both closure talk and other ways of talking about grief, she offers an alternative hope: choose from a range of discourses a way to talk about your grief that works for you yourself.</p>
<p>Following <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1749975512458626a">Stroebe et al. (1992)</xref>, my own work on the culture of grief (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1749975512458626a">Walter, 1999</xref>) argues that grieving Britons have to traverse a culture advocating two conflicting norms: the modernist norm that the dead are to be left behind a.s.a.p. (reflected in research into ‘grief work’), versus the romantic norm that love is eternal (reflected in research into ‘continuing bonds’). I had presumed that closure’s promise follows only after modernist ‘letting go’. But Berns’ documentation of ‘closure’ shows that – though more often referring to modernist letting go – it can also refer to romantic continuing bonds. You can find closure by letting go of the dead, or by finding an enduring place for them in your heart – by forgetting or by remembering. Closure’s offer is simply to end the pain of grief; it derives not from modernism, but from a culture with a low pain threshold.</p>
<p>Berns could have linked her analysis with a currently respected model in bereavement research, namely Stroebe and Schut’s dual process model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1749975512458626a">1999</xref>). This shows that grief is not a linear process but an ongoing oscillation between the pain of loss and having to carve out a new life. This fits Berns’ argument that healing can begin before the pain is over.</p>
<p>The book lacks any sustained consideration of quite how ‘new’ closure is and exactly how it arrived into popular culture. Though popular use of the <italic>word</italic> is, I think, new, the cultural norm that mourning should be time-limited was clearly documented in Geoffrey Gorer’s classic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1749975512458626a">1965</xref>) study of grief and mourning in mid-20th-century Britain. And though it is only in the past two decades that the American funeral industry has used the word ‘closure’ to sell its goods and services, claims that its wares are indispensable for psychological health were documented in Jessica Mitford’s mid-20th century exposé (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1749975512458626a">1963</xref>). Berns certainly discusses both Mitford and the American funeral industry, but does not make clear which is chicken and which egg: was the industry key to promoting the idea of closure, or was closure generated elsewhere in American culture and then used by the funeral industry? This book, whose evidence comprises a myriad of closure citations from American popular culture of the 2000s, leaves me with questions. How new <italic>is</italic> the concept of closure and its place in culture, business and politics? Or is it just the word that is new?</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1749975512458626a">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gorer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1965</year>) <source>Death, Grief and Mourning in Contemporary Britain</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cresset</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1749975512458626a">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mitford</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1963</year>) <source>The American Way of Death</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Hutchinson</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1749975512458626a">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stroebe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schut</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The dual process model of coping with bereavement: Rationale and description</article-title>. <source>Death Studies</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>224</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1749975512458626a">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stroebe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gergen</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gergen</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stroebe</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Broken hearts or broken bonds: Love and death in historical perspective</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source> <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>1205</fpage>–<lpage>1212</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1749975512458626a">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>On Bereavement: The Culture of Grief</source>. <publisher-loc>Buckingham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Open University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>