<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RSW</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">sprsw</journal-id>
<journal-title>Research on Social Work Practice</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1049-7315</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-7581</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1049731512474103</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1049731512474103</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Systematic Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Interventions to Reduce Distress in Adult Victims of Rape and Sexual Violence</article-title>
<subtitle>A Systematic Review</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Regehr</surname>
<given-names>Cheryl</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049731512474103">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1049731512474103"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Alaggia</surname>
<given-names>Ramona</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049731512474103">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dennis</surname>
<given-names>Jane</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1049731512474103">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pitts</surname>
<given-names>Annabel</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049731512474103">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Saini</surname>
<given-names>Michael</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1049731512474103">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1049731512474103"><label>1</label>University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1049731512474103"><label>2</label>Campbell Collaboration, Bristol, United Kingdom</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1049731512474103">Cheryl Regehr, Factor-Inwentash Faculty of Social Work, Academic Programs, University of Toronto, 27 King’s College Circle, Toronto, Ontario, Canada M5 S 1A1. Email: <email>cheryl.regehr@utoronto.ca</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>23</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>257</fpage>
<lpage>265</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>
<italic>Objectives:</italic> This article presents a systematic evaluation of the effectiveness of interventions aimed at reducing distress in adult victims of rape and sexual violence. <italic>Method:</italic> Studies were eligible for the review if the assignment of study participants to experimental or control groups was by random allocation or parallel cohort design. <italic>Results:</italic> Six studies including 405 participants met eligibility criteria. Meta-analyses revealed that specific cognitive and behavioral interventions (cognitive-processing therapy, prolonged exposure therapy, and eye movement desensitization reprocessing) had a statistically significant effect on posttraumatic stress disorder and depression symptoms in comparison to the control groups. Other outcomes that had demonstrated improvement included anxiety, guilt, and dissociation. <italic>Conclusion:</italic> Many studies assessing the effectiveness of interventions for decreasing trauma symptoms combine victims of sexual violence in adulthood with other trauma-based samples despite the profound differences in these experiences. This review again points to the need for increased research that focuses specifically on the effectiveness of treatment models for adult victims of sexual violence.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>sexual assault</kwd>
<kwd>rape</kwd>
<kwd>systematic review</kwd>
<kwd>cognitive processing therapy</kwd>
<kwd>prolonged exposure therapy</kwd>
<kwd>eye movement desensitization reprocessing</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Estimates of the incidence and prevalence of rape and other forms of sexual assault vary depending on how terms are defined, what types of sexual assaults are included, the time frame during which the data are collected, sampling methods used, age and gender of the population studied, and the location of the sample (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1049731512474103">Acierno, Resnick, &amp; Kilpatrick, 1997</xref>; Burgess, Regehr, &amp; Roberts, 2012). Further, as few countries have undertaken studies that comprehensively document the prevalence of rape and sexual assault, worldwide incidence is difficult to determine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1049731512474103">British Council, 2006</xref>). Nevertheless, available data confirm that sexual violence and rape are experienced by a large minority of women throughout the world. For instance, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1049731512474103">Painter (1991</xref>) reported that one in four women in the United Kingdom had experienced rape or attempted rape, a rate that has remained relatively stable over time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1049731512474103">Welch &amp; Mason, 2007</xref>). A national random sample of 6,926 women in Sweden found that 1 in 6, or 16% of the respondents, had experienced sexual violence by a former husband or cohabitant and that 1 in 4, or 25% of the respondents, had been subject to sexual violence by a man outside of a relationship (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1049731512474103">Lundgren, Heimer, Westerstrand, &amp; Kalliokoski, 2002</xref>) . In the United States, findings from the National Violence Against Women Survey (NVAWS) reported that 17.6% of surveyed women and 3% of surveyed men were raped at some time in their lives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1049731512474103">Tjaden &amp; Thoennes, 2006</xref>). The World Health Organization World Report on Violence and Health reports percentages of women who experienced sexual assault in the previous 5 years ranging from 8% in Brazil and 6% in Albania, to 0.8% in Botswana (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1049731512474103">Krug, Dahlberg, Mercy, Zwi, &amp; Lozano, 2002</xref>).</p>
<p>A disturbing trend of increased rates of rape has been more recently documented in war-torn countries where sexual assault is used as a weapon of war. For example, in provinces across the Democratic Republic of Congo, “the shockingly high number is equivalent to 1,152 women raped every day, 48 raped every hour, or four women raped every five minutes” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1049731512474103">Africa Research Bulletin, 2011</xref>, p. 18839C). In South Africa, infant rape has emerged as another form of rape where, “there is growing support for the theory that infant rape is related to a myth that intercourse with a very young virgin infant will enable the perpetrator to rid himself of HIV/AIDS ….” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1049731512474103">Pitcher &amp; Bowley, 2002</xref>, p. 274). These forms of systematic rape are of enormous concern clearly warranting focused investigation in terms of complex effects and specific treatments, but are outside of the scope of the current review with its particular Western focus.</p>
<p>Beginning with the articulation of Rape Trauma Syndrome in the <italic>American Journal of Psychiatry</italic> by Burgess and Holmstrom (1974), the traumatic aftermath of sexual assault on adult victims has become a focus of social and legal policy, scholarly inquiry, and mental health interventions. As the negative effects of sexual assault have become better recognized, there is increasing attention to the possibility that psychosocial interventions may reduce suffering and limit distress. There are now several treatments modalities available for victims of rape and sexual assault including pharmacology; behavioral techniques such as flooding, systematic desensitization, eye movement desensitization and reprocessing; cognitive behavioral therapy; cognitive therapy; relaxation; rational–emotive therapy; group therapy; hypnosis; family/couple therapy; existential therapy; humanistic approaches; and psychodynamic therapy. A critical review of this literature, however, reveals many articles based on clinical impressions, but few studies measuring outcomes of treatment.</p>
<p>One of the issues in evaluating posttraumatic stress interventions is the degree to which symptoms spontaneously remit. For instance, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1049731512474103">Rothbaum, Foa, Riggs, Murdock, and Walsh (1992</xref>) reported that, while 94% of the 95 rape victims in their study met the criteria for posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) at 1 week post rape, this reduced to 47% at 94 days post rape. Once the 3-month marker occurs, it has been suggested that symptoms of PTSD become relatively persistent. Thus, the natural diminishing of symptoms of PTSD requires that controlled studies be considered when discussing efficacy. While there are hundreds of original reports describing the effectiveness of treatments for individuals who have been exposed to traumatic events, the vast majority are not empirically based studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1049731512474103">Solomon &amp; Johnson, 2002</xref>). Several nonsystematic reviews of treatment for rape and sexual assault are reported in the literature that provide a useful beginning information on this topic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1049731512474103">Falsetti, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1049731512474103">Foa &amp; Rothbaum, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1049731512474103">Foa, Rothbaum, &amp; Steketee, 1993</xref>). More recent reviews and meta-analyses provide up-to-date data but have not been limited to studies with control groups, and thus the analyses have not accounted for the issue of spontaneous remission (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1049731512474103">Taylor &amp; Harvey, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1049731512474103">Vickerman &amp; Margolin, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Other reviews have examined the reduction of distress in populations experiencing symptomology of PTSD, but these reviews are not specific to adult victims of rape and sexual assault. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1049731512474103">Bisson and Andrew (2007</xref>) completed a Cochrane Review of psychological treatments to reduce symptoms of PTSD. Although they found evidence that individual trauma-focused cognitive behavioral therapy/exposure therapy (TFCBT), eye movement desensitization and reprocessing (EMDR), stress management and group TFCBT were effective in the treatment of PTSD, their study population included war veterans, female assault (mainly sexual assault) survivors, refugees and police officers, and mixed groups of individuals who had experienced a variety of traumatic events including road traffic accidents, assaults, bereavement, and industrial accidents. Similarly, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1049731512474103">Sherman (1998</xref>) completed a meta-analysis of controlled and clinical trials of psychotherapeutic treatments for PTSD. These included samples of combat veterans from the Vietnam and Lebanon wars, crime-related victims, severe bereavement sufferers, and victims of rape. Sherman examined cognitive, and psychodynamic treatments, in group and individual settings and found the overall impact of psychotherapy on PTSD and psychiatric symptomatology was significant (<italic>d </italic>= .52, <italic>r</italic> = .25) with a nonzero, 95% confidence interval suggesting that the true effect lies between .39 and .68. However, no data were available specifically for those who were victims of rape. Such lack of differentiation may be problematic, as research on trauma interventions has demonstrated that while some interventions may be useful with certain populations, they may in fact increase symptoms in some groups of victims (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1049731512474103">Bisson, Jenkins, Alexander, &amp; Bannister, 1997</xref>; Mayou, Ehlers &amp; Hobbs, 2000; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1049731512474103">Regehr, 2001</xref>). This finding requires careful examination with victims of sexual violence in order to ensure that treatments do not have iatrogenic effects.</p>
<p>While there may appear to be some similarity of response between individuals exposed to different traumatic events such as rape, life-threatening accidents, and disasters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1049731512474103">Rothbaum, Ninan, &amp; Thomas, 1996</xref>), there is evidence that trauma associated with rape may be different than other forms of trauma in part due to the strong element of self-blame, the higher incidence of concurrent depression, and the increased risk of suicide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1049731512474103">Connor &amp; Davidson, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1049731512474103">Kimerling, Ouimette, &amp; Wolfe, 2002</xref>). For instance, PTSD has been reported to affect between 9% and 15% of the general population and almost 50% of individuals who have been raped (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1049731512474103">Feeny, Foa, Treadwell, &amp; March, 2004</xref>). Using a representative sample to assess the differential risks of PTSD across types of trauma exposure, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1049731512474103">Breslau, Davis, Andreski, and Peterson (1991</xref>) reported that the incidence of PTSD was highest after rape (49%, <italic>SE</italic> = 12.2) followed by other forms of sexual assault (23%, <italic>SE</italic> = 10.8). The incidence of PTSD after being shot or stabbed was 15% (<italic>SE</italic> = 13.7), a serious car accident was 2.3% (<italic>SE</italic> = 1.3), other kinds of serious accidents was 16.8% (<italic>SE </italic>= 6.2) and following natural disaster was 3.8 (<italic>SE</italic> = 3.0).</p>
<p>Due to the well-documented negative consequences of sexual assault, such as PTSD, and secondary depression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1049731512474103">Resnick, Acierno, Holmes, Kilpatrick, &amp; Jager, 1999</xref>), it is imperative that effective and efficient treatment options for these victims are identified (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1049731512474103">Rothbaum, Astin, &amp; Marsteller, 2005</xref>). This systematic review examines the effectiveness of interventions to reduce distress that specifically target adult victims of rape and sexual violence.</p>
<sec id="section1-1049731512474103" sec-type="methods">
<title>Method</title>
<p>The methodology for this review was guided by the <italic>Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions 5.1 </italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1049731512474103">Higgins &amp; Green, 2011</xref>). This review included experimental and parallel cohort quasi-experimental evaluations of psychological intervention programs to reduce distress in adult victims of sexual assault. Studies were eligible for the review if they used (1) random assignment to create treatment and comparison or control groups; or (2) parallel cohort designs in which groups were assessed at the same points in time. Single-group designs and single-subject designs were excluded. Study participants included adults who had experienced sexual assault or rape as adults; studies with participants that identified primarily as victims of childhood sexual abuse were not included. Sexual assault is defined to encompass rape; attempted rape; forced oral sex, anal sex, penetration with objects, touching of intimate parts; and other types of threats or coercion in which unwanted sexual contact is attempted or occurs between the victim and offender. Rape refers to forced or attempted sexual intercourse of a male or female, by any offender.</p>
<p>Any type of psychological and/or psychosocial in nature intervention was eligible for inclusion in the review. These interventions may have included behavioral techniques such as exposure, systematic desensitization, eye movement desensitization and reprocessing (EMDR); cognitive behavioral therapy; cognitive therapy; relaxation; and psychodynamic therapy. We also identified “other” categories of interventions to ensure we remained flexible in the retrieval process of this review. Since the main objective of this review was to compare psychosocial interventions to reduce distress, interventions that were exclusively based on pharmacology were excluded. Studies that compared psychosocial treatments to pharmacological treatment and studies that combined psychosocial treatments with pharmacological treatments were considered.</p>
<p>The assessment of the primary outcome of trauma symptoms included the independent rating of severity of traumatic stress symptoms using a standardized measure such as the Clinician Administered PTSD Symptom scale (CAPS, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1049731512474103">Blake et al., 1995</xref>) and severity of self-reported traumatic stress symptoms using a standardized measure such as the Impact of Event scale (IES; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1049731512474103">Horowitz, Wilner, &amp; Alvarez, 1979</xref>). Secondary outcomes included decreased levels of depression, anxiety, and guilt; and increases in positive functioning (e.g., social support, peer relations, locus of control, and self-efficacy). Secondary outcome measures included (1) severity of depressive symptoms using scales such as the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1049731512474103">Beck, Ward, Mendelson, Mock, &amp; Erbaugh, 1961</xref>); (2) severity of anxiety symptoms using scales such as the Spielberger State Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1049731512474103">Spielberger, 1983</xref>).</p>
<sec id="section2-1049731512474103">
<title>Search Strategy</title>
<p>Searches were conducted on 19 electronic data bases including the Cochrane database on systematic reviews, Medline, Embase, PsychINFO, Eric, Socia Sciences Abstracts, Criminal justice abstracts, Gender studies database, and Dissertation abstracts international. Journals relevant to the sexual assault/rape/sexual violence were hand-searched by researchers to uncover studies not found by electronic database searches. Reviewers checked the reference lists of all relevant articles that were obtained, including those from previously published reviews. Potentially relevant articles were identified, retrieved, and assessed for possible inclusion in the review. Face-to-face discussions at meetings, e-mails, requests on listserves, and formal letters of request for information from authors, presenters, and experts were solicited via e-mail to assist the review team to locate relevant studies. Special attention was made to search and collect relevant studies captured in the gray literature.</p>
<p>Titles and abstracts of studies yielded by the searches were screened by two independent reviewers to determine their eligibility for inclusion in the review. To facilitate this screening, we used Mobius Analytics SRS, which is an online tool designed to facilitate and accelerate the execution of systematic reviews. This tool enables rapid generation of forms, virtual collaborative communities, automated management of the progression of studies, and real-time data monitoring and reporting [http://srsnexus.com/cms/products2.aspx]. Mobius Analytics has the advantage of being web-based, where each member of the review team has a secure login and password to enter the program.</p>
<p>The screening of the studies was carried out by a three-stage procedure. The assessment of the methodological quality of each study was based on criteria established in the Cochrane Collaboration Handbook (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1049731512474103">Higgins &amp; Green, 2011</xref>) and focused on the generation of allocation sequence, degree of allocation concealment, intention to treat, blinding of assessors, attrition, and reporting of the data. The first stage of screening determined whether a study might be appropriate for the review based on the study’s title and abstract. The second stage consisted of a strict screening process where two reviewers independently reviewed full copies of articles to determine whether studies should remain in the review based on the inclusion and exclusion criteria. The third stage consisted of a data extraction form to record data from the articles that have made it past the two previous screenings.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1049731512474103">
<title>Analysis</title>
<p>In all six studies included in the analysis, outcome data relevant to the inclusion criteria (PTSD, anxiety, and depression) were measured based on continuous scales. Continuous data were analyzed by measuring the standard mean difference between the treatment and comparison groups based on the reported means and standard deviations for each group. Standard mean differences (SMD) allowed for comparisons to be made across studies when scales measured the same outcomes (e.g., traumatic stress symptoms) in different ways. Given the small sample sizes in both the treatment and the comparison groups, we used RevMan 5.1’s formula for SMD by calculating the Hedges’ <italic>g</italic>. The Hedges’ <italic>g</italic> is similar to the Cohen’s <italic>d</italic>, except that it includes an adjustment for small sample bias. To pool SMDs, inverse variance methods were used to weight each effect size by the inverse of its variance to obtain an overall estimate of effect size. For each individual study data, confidence intervals of 95% were used and then used to pool estimates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1049731512474103">Hasselblad &amp; Hedges, 1995</xref>). The unit of allocation in each included study was the individual; no studies allocated by group or cluster.</p>
<p>Our primary analysis involved an assessment of the effectiveness of eligible psychological treatments as defined by our protocol (whether cognitive behavioral or psychodynamic in nature and regardless of the degree to which exposure elements were incorporated). Thus, we first pooled data for all eligible active treatment groups within each study against no-treatment control, using a formula to combine means and standard deviations for this purpose (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1049731512474103">Higgins &amp; Green, 2011</xref>, section 7.7.3.8).</p>
<p>Subgroup analyses of the effects of the different types of intervention (cognitive-processing therapy, prolonged exposure (PE), stress inoculation therapy, eye movement desensitization and reprocessing) were conducted only if there was a sufficient number of studies (two or more) per category. To assess the extent of differences between trials, we assessed the degree of heterogeneity in three ways: by visual inspection of the forest plots; by performing the χ<sup>2</sup> test of heterogeneity (where a significance level less than 0.10 would be interpreted as evidence of heterogeneity); and by examining the τ and <italic>I</italic>
<sup>2</sup> statistics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1049731512474103">Higgins &amp; Green, 2011</xref>; section 9.5.2).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1049731512474103">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The search strategy yielded 7,587 titles and abstracts that were entered into Refworks. After removing duplicates from Refworks there were 5,779 articles included in Level 1 screening. Titles and abstracts were screened by two independent raters (κ = .82) and disagreements were resolved by a third reviewer. At the second screening level, 54 studies were included and full-text articles were retrieved for all 64 titles. Based on this third screen with full-text articles, 44 titles were excluded, with 10 studies being included in the final analysis. Of the 10 included studies, 6 were withdrawn with reason of only reporting multivariate outcome data or because on closer inspection the sample included participants sexually abused as children. On further analysis, of the excluded studies, two were subsequently determined to be eligible. Therefore, six studies with usable outcome data for meta-analysis were included (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1049731512474103">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1049731512474103" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Screening process for included studies.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1049731512474103-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Four studies within this review are randomized controlled trials (RCTs; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1049731512474103">Foa, Rothbaum, Riggs, &amp; Murdock, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1049731512474103">Resick, Nishith, Weaver, Astin, &amp; Feuer, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1049731512474103">Rothbaum, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1049731512474103">Rothbaum et al., 2005</xref>). Two studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1049731512474103">Resick, Jordan, Girelli, Hutter, &amp; Marhoefer-Dvorak, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1049731512474103">Resick &amp; Schnicke, 1992</xref>) are “quasi experimental,” featuring data from nonrandomized, “naturally occurring” waitlist control groups. All studies within this review are of parallel design; in all cases, allocation was by individual participant and in no case was any form of “matching” or stratifying by any participant characteristic undertaken by investigators. In each case, active treatments were compared with waitlist control groups (WLCs), an understandable ethical requirement, but inevitably a limitation on collection of controlled follow-up data. Two studies compared just one active treatment with WLC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1049731512474103">Resick et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1049731512474103">Rothbaum, 1997</xref>); two studies compared two active treatments with WLC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1049731512474103">Resick et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1049731512474103">Rothbaum et al., 2005</xref>); and two studies compared three active treatments versus WLC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1049731512474103">Foa et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1049731512474103">Resick et al., 1988</xref>).</p>
<p>Investigators were rigorous in documenting dropouts from all studies and in several cases detailed assessments were made to compare the baseline characteristics of those leaving the study with those remaining. Only one study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1049731512474103">Foa et al., 1991</xref>) found a notable difference (those with lower incomes and working in “blue-collar” jobs were more likely to leave treatment). Dropout varied from 14% to 30%, but we assessed risk of bias to the results of this review on factors including evenness of distribution of dropout and method of analysis (e.g., intention to treat analysis). A dropout of 30% was highest in the study involving the interventions delivered with the greatest intensity and the longest duration of any included within the review (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1049731512474103">Resick et al., 2002</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1049731512474103">Rizvi, Vogt, and Resick (2009</xref>) examined predictors of dropout from cognitive processing therapy (CPT) and PE by examining 145 women with PTSD who participated in at least one treatment session as part of an RCT. In comparison with treatment completers, those who dropped out were younger, had lower levels of education and lower IQ, and had higher levels of anger.</p>
<p>In an analysis pooling the results of the various treatments (both for RCTs and for quasi-randomized trials), all six studies demonstrated improvements in PTSD. Five studies administered self-report measures of PTSD, three in RCT trials (combined <italic>n</italic> = 249; SMD = −1.9; 95% CI [−2.73, −1.07]; <italic>I</italic>
<sup>2</sup> = 75%; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1049731512474103">Figure 2</xref>), and two in quasi RCT trials (combined <italic>n</italic> = 88; SMD = −0.55; 95% CI [−1.00, 0.09]; <italic>I</italic>
<sup>2</sup> = 0%; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1049731512474103">Figure 3</xref>). All four studies using clinician assessed PTSD demonstrated improvements in the treatment groups over the WLC (combined <italic>n</italic> = 293; SMD = −1.81; 95% CI [−2.90, −0.72]; <italic>I</italic>
<sup>2</sup> = 89%; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1049731512474103">Figure 4</xref>). All six studies demonstrated improvements in depression, four RCT trials (combined <italic>n</italic> = 292; SMD = −1.09; 95% CI [−1.65, −0.53]; <italic>I</italic>
<sup>2</sup> is 67%; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1049731512474103">Figure 5</xref>), and two quasi-randomized trials (combined <italic>n</italic> = 88; SMD = −0.48; 95% CI [−0.94, −0.02]; <italic>I</italic>
<sup>2</sup> = 0%; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1049731512474103">Figure 6</xref>). In addition, three studies demonstrated improvements in anxiety (combined <italic>n</italic> = 123; SMD = −1.12; 95% CI [−1.60, −0.64]; <italic>I</italic>
<sup>2</sup> = 20%); one in guilt (<italic>n</italic> = 164; SMD = −0.69; 95% CI [−1.06, −0.32]); and two in dissociation (combined <italic>n</italic> = 78; SMD = −0.94; 95% CI [−1.43, −0.45]; <italic>I</italic>
<sup>2</sup> = 0%) when compared with waitlist controls. Pooled analysis of RCTs for PE demonstrated improvements in PTSD, depression, anxiety, guilt, and dissociation; EMDR demonstrated improvements in PTSD, depression, anxiety, and dissociation; CPT demonstrated improvements in PTSD, depression, and guilt.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1049731512474103" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Self-report posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) in randomized controlled trials (RCT).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1049731512474103-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig3-1049731512474103" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Self-report posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) in quasi-randomized trials.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1049731512474103-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig4-1049731512474103" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Clinician assessed posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) in randomized controlled trials (RCT).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1049731512474103-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig5-1049731512474103" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Depression in randomized controlled trials (RCT).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1049731512474103-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig6-1049731512474103" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Depression in quasi-randomized trials.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1049731512474103-fig6.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1049731512474103">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Sexual violence and rape are horrifying events experienced by a sizable minority of women across the world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1049731512474103">Krug et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1049731512474103">Lundgren et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1049731512474103">Painter, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1049731512474103">Tjaden &amp; Thoennes, 2006</xref>). The consequences of sexual violence on individual women are pervasive and often long lasting including depression, posttraumatic stress and anxiety; social and work adjustment problems; and sexual dysfunction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1049731512474103">Burgess &amp; Holmstrom, 1974</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1049731512474103">Feeny et al., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1049731512474103">Resick, 1983</xref>). The professional and scholarly literature is replete with interventions aimed at reducing the traumatic aftermath of rape. However, most of this literature focuses on case reflections, descriptive analyses, and uncontrolled studies. Based on this review, it is clear that very few reported studies use rigorous randomized control methods to evaluate efficacy of treatments. Yet, given the fact that a proportion of trauma symptoms spontaneously remit in the early stages post assault (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1049731512474103">Rothbaum, Foa, Riggs, Murdock, &amp; Walsh, 1992</xref>), controlled studies are required to determine the effectiveness of interventions. The aim of this review was to examine all available evidence regarding treatment interventions that effectively reduce symptoms of distress in victims of rape.</p>
<p>Six studies with usable outcome data for meta-analysis were included in the final analysis of this review. EMDR was examined in two small RCTs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1049731512474103">Rothbaum 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1049731512474103">Rothbaum et al., 2005</xref>); CPT was assessed in two studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1049731512474103">Resick &amp; Schnicke, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1049731512474103">Resick et al., 2002</xref>); PE in three studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1049731512474103">Foa et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1049731512474103">Resick et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1049731512474103">Rothbaum et al., 2005</xref>); SIT in two studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1049731512474103">Foa et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1049731512474103">Resick et al., 1988</xref>); and Supportive Counselling, Supportive Psychotherapy, and Assertiveness Training were delivered in one study each (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1049731512474103">Foa et al., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1049731512474103">Resick et al., 1988</xref>).While this review also sought to investigate and compare the effectiveness of other forms of psychotherapy, in particular psychodynamic therapy, no published or unpublished such studies met the inclusion criteria. In an analysis pooling the results of the various treatments (both for RCTs and for quasirandomized trials), all six studies demonstrated improvements in PTSD and depression; three studies demonstrated improvements in anxiety; one in guilt and two in dissociation when compared with waitlist controls. Pooled analysis of RCTs for PE demonstrated improvements in PTSD, depression, anxiety, guilt, and dissociation; EMDR demonstrated improvements in PTSD, depression, anxiety, and dissociation; CPT demonstrated improvements in PTSD, depression, and guilt. While we have argued that rape victims have unique posttraumatic reactions, it is useful to note that these findings are consistent with a previous systematic review (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1049731512474103">Bisson &amp; Andrew, 2007</xref>) and two recent RCTs with traumatized populations exposed to a range of horrifying and life-threatening events (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1049731512474103">Nijdam, Gersons, Reitsma, de Jongh, &amp; Olff, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1049731512474103">Shalev et al., 2012</xref>).</p>
<p>Drop-out rates are an issue to be considered in the interpretation of results. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1049731512474103">Resick, Jordan, Girelli, Hutter, and Marhoefer-Dvorak (1988</xref>) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1049731512474103">Rothbaum et al. (2005</xref>) reported drop-out rates of 14% and 18%, respectively, during the course of the trial but dropouts were evenly distributed between groups. While <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1049731512474103">Resick and Schnicke (1992</xref>) also reported a drop-out rate of 14%, this occurred solely in the intervention arm. Most concerning was the 30% drop-out rate reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1049731512474103">Resick et al. (2002</xref>) for CPT, the intervention delivered with the greatest intensity and the longest duration of any included within the review.</p>
<sec id="section6-1049731512474103">
<title>Limitations</title>
<p>The number of studies included in the analysis was low. As with other RCTs, sample size of the studies is low; however, results of the analyses with this limited data are strong and compelling.</p>
<p>It is important to note that the presented research has been conducted primarily with middle-class White Anglo-Saxon women in the United States; it is unknown how these therapeutic approaches work for individuals from other cultures, abilities, and social classes. There may also be possible variations on the effectiveness of these interventions by type of sexual assault (e.g., single vs. repeated assaults, known vs. unknown perpetrators, assaults under “normal” living conditions vs. those that happen during other traumatic events such as war). Thus, the therapeutic approaches reviewed to date may not be as effective for all types of adult sexual assault survivors.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1049731512474103">
<title>Implications for Social Work Practice</title>
<p>Given the community incidence of sexual violence and rape and the sequelae of this traumatic exposure in terms of symptoms of PTSD, depression and anxiety, victims are commonly seen among any mental health treatment population. Not surprisingly, therefore, a vast array of treatment interventions has arisen with the intention of reducing the extreme distress experienced by victims. Research on trauma interventions with other populations has demonstrated that while some interventions may be useful with certain populations, they may in fact increase symptoms in some groups of victims (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1049731512474103">Bisson et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1049731512474103">Mayou, Ehlers, &amp; Hobbs, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1049731512474103">Regehr, 2001</xref>). It is therefore incumbent upon researchers and practitioners in mental health to ensure that treatment interventions provided are helpful and not iatrogenic.</p>
<p>This review demonstrates that certain types of cognitive and behavioral interventions (CPT, PE, and EMDR) are indeed effective in reducing symptoms of depression, PTSD, and anxiety in victims of rape and sexual violence. This is heartening and reinforces the findings of the efficacy of these approaches with other traumatized populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1049731512474103">Bisson &amp; Andrew, 2007</xref>). Nevertheless, an analysis of those individuals who drop out of CPT and PE treatment suggests that some individuals may be more likely to benefit than others. Such individuals include those who are older, have higher levels of education and intelligence, and lower initial levels of anger (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1049731512474103">Rizvi, Vogt, &amp; Resick, 2009</xref>). Others have suggested that individuals recommended for these types of treatment should be assessed to have the capacity to tolerate high anxiety arousal, have no active suicidal ideation, and no current life crises (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1049731512474103">Foy et al., 2000</xref>). On the contrary, however, individuals with higher levels of fear and depression have been shown to benefit from CPT and PE in the form of greater reduction in PTSD symptoms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1049731512474103">Rizvi et al., 2009</xref>). It is suggested that models of treatment that involve exposure should be used only when a sound therapeutic alliance has been formed and a thorough assessment has been completed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1049731512474103">Calhoun &amp; Atkeson, 1991</xref>). In addition, individuals embarking on this treatment should do so with full and informed consent, and therapists are advised to carefully monitor levels of distress during the treatment.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1049731512474103">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>Rape trauma syndrome was first identified as a distinct entity by Burgess and Holmstrom in 1974. This groundbreaking article set the stage for subsequent changes in sexual assault law (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1049731512474103">Koss, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1049731512474103">Regehr, Alaggia, Lambert, &amp; Saini, 2008</xref>), in societal views regarding sexual violence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1049731512474103">Brownmiller, 1975</xref>), mental health diagnosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1049731512474103">American Psychiatric Association [APA], 1980</xref>), and treatment of victims. Treatment approaches reported in the scholarly and professional literature have flourished. Yet, despite the widespread recognition of sexual violence and its aftermath for almost four decades, there continues to be a surprising and discouraging paucity of rigorous evaluations of interventions aimed at reducing distress experienced by victims. This review again points to the need for controlled studies that evaluate interventions that will best assist in relieving distress in victims in the form of PTSD, depression, and anxiety.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>The article represents a summary of a review published by the Campbell Systematic Reviews.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn1-1049731512474103">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The authors declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2-1049731512474103">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The authors disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This research was generously supported by funds from the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council of Canada.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Acierno</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Resnick</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kilpatrick</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Health impact of interpersonal violence section I: Prevalence rates, case identification, and risk factors for sexual assault, physical assault, and domestic violence in men and women</article-title>. <source>Behavioral Medicine</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">Africa Research Bulletin</collab>. (<year>2011, May</year>). <source>Democratic Republic of Congo: Horrendous Rape Statistics</source> <comment>(Vol. 48, Issue 5, 18839C-40C)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">American Psychiatric Association</collab>. (<year>1980</year>). <source>Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders</source> (<edition>3rd ed</edition>.). <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Author</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Beck</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ward</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mendelson</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mock</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Erbaugh</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1961</year>) <article-title>An inventory for measuring depression</article-title>. <source>Archives of General Psychiatry</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>561</fpage>–<lpage>571</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bisson</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Andrew</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Psychological treatment of post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD)</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews</source>, <volume>3</volume>.
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bisson</surname>
<given-names>J. I.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jenkins</surname>
<given-names>P. L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Alexander</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bannister</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Randomized controlled trial of psychological debriefing for victims of acute burn trauma</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Psychiatry</source>, <volume>171</volume>, <fpage>78</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Blake</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Weathers</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nagy</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kaloupek</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gusman</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Charney</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Keane</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>The development of a clinician-administered PTSD scale</article-title>. <source>Journal of Traumatic Stress</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>90</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Breslau</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Davis</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Andreski</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Peterson</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Traumatic events and posttraumatic stress disorder in an urban population of young adults</article-title>. <source>Archives of General Psychiatry</source>, <volume>48</volume>, <fpage>216</fpage>–<lpage>222</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">British Council</collab>. (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Violence against women a briefing document on international issues and responses</article-title>. <comment>Retrieved from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.britishcouncil.org/waw.pdf">http://www.britishcouncil.org/waw.pdf</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brownmiller</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1975</year>). <source>Against our will: Men, women and rape</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Simon and Schuster</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Burgess</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holmstrom</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1974</year>). <article-title>Rape trauma syndrome</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Psychiatry</source>, <volume>131</volume>, <fpage>981</fpage>–<lpage>986</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Burgess</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Regehr</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Roberts</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <source>Victimology: Theories and applications</source> (<edition>2nd ed</edition>.). <publisher-loc>Burlington, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Jones and Bartlett</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Calhoun</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Atkenson</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>Treatment of rape victims: Facilitating psychosocial adjustment</source>. <publisher-loc>Toronto, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pergamon Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Connor</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Davidson</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Familial risk factors in posttraumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>Annals of the New York Academy of Science</source>, <volume>821</volume>, <fpage>35</fpage>–<lpage>51</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Falsetti</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>The decision-making process of choosing a treatment for patients with civilian trauma-related PTSD</article-title>. <source>Cognitive and Behavioral Practice</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>121</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Feeny</surname>
<given-names>N. C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Foa</surname>
<given-names>E. B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Treadwell</surname>
<given-names>R. H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>March</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Posttraumatic stress disorder in youth: A critical review of the cognitive and behavioral treatment outcome literature</article-title>. <source>Professional Psychology: Research and Practice</source>, <volume>35</volume>, <fpage>466</fpage>–<lpage>476</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Foa</surname>
<given-names>E. B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rothbaum</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <source>Treating the trauma of rape: Cognitive therapy for PTSD</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Foa</surname>
<given-names>E. B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rothbaum</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Riggs</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Murdock</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Treatment of posttraumatic stress disorder in rape victims: A comparison between cognitive-behavioral procedures and counselling</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology</source>, <volume>59</volume>, <fpage>715</fpage>–<lpage>723</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Foa</surname>
<given-names>E. B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rothbaum</surname>
<given-names>B. O.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Steketee</surname>
<given-names>G. S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Treatment of rape victims</article-title>. <source>Journal of Interpersonal Violence</source>, <volume>8</volume>, <fpage>256</fpage>–<lpage>276</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Foy</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Glynn</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schnurr</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jankowski</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wattenberg</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Weiss</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Group therapy</article-title>. In <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Foa</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Keane</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Friedman</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (Eds.), <source>Effective treatments for PTSD: Practice guidelines for the international society for traumatic stress studies</source> (pp. <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>175</lpage>). <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hasselblad</surname>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hedges</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Meta-analysis of screening and diagnostic tests</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>117</volume>, <fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>178</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Higgins</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Green</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <source>Cochrane handbook for systematic reviews of interventions</source> <comment>Version 5.1. Retrieved from</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cochrane-handbook.org">http://www.cochrane-handbook.org</ext-link>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Horowitz</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wilner</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Alvarez</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>Impact of events scale: A measure of subjective stress</article-title>. <source>Psychosomatic Medicine</source>, <volume>41</volume>, <fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>218</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kimerling</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ouimette</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wolf</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Gender and PTSD</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Guilford</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Koss</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Blame, shame and the community: Justice responses to violence against women</article-title>. <source>American Psychologist</source>, <volume>55</volume>, <fpage>1332</fpage>–<lpage>1343</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Krug</surname>
<given-names>E. G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dahlberg</surname>
<given-names>L. L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mercy</surname>
<given-names>J. A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zwi</surname>
<given-names>A. B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lozano</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>World report on violence and health</source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lundgren</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Heimer</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Westerstrand</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kalliokoski</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <source>Captured Queen – Men’s violence against women in equal Sweden: A prevalence study</source>. <publisher-loc>Stockholm, Sweden</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>British Council</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mayou</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ehlers</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hobbs</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Psychological debriefing for road traffic accident victims</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Psychiatry</source>, <volume>176</volume>, <fpage>589</fpage>–<lpage>593</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nijdam</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gersons</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Reitsma</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>de Jongh</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Olff</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Brief eclectic psychotherapy v. eye movement desensitization and reprocessing therapy for post-traumatic stress disorder: randomized control trial</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Psychiatry</source>, <volume>200</volume>, <fpage>224</fpage>–<lpage>231</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Painter</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <source>Wife rape, marriage and law: Survey report, key findings and recommendation</source>. <publisher-loc>England: Manchester University</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department of Social Policy and Social Work in British Council</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pitcher</surname>
<given-names>G. J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bowley</surname>
<given-names>D. M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Infant rape in South Africa</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>, <volume>359</volume>, <fpage>274</fpage>–<lpage>275</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Regehr</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Crisis debriefings for emergency responders: Reviewing the evidence</article-title>. <source>Journal of Brief Treatments and Crisis Intervention</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Regehr</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Alaggia</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lambert</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Saini</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Victims of sexual violence in the Canada criminal courts</article-title>. <source>Victims and Offenders</source>, <volume>3</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>15</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Resick</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>The rape reaction: Research findings and implications for intervention</article-title>. <source>The Behavior Therapist</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>132</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Resick</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jordan</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Girelli</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hutter</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Marhoefer-Dvorak</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>A comparative outcome study of behavioural group therapy for sexual assault victims</article-title>. <source>Behavior Therapy</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>385</fpage>–<lpage>401</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Resick</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nishith</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Weaver</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Astin</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Feuer</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>A comparison of cognitive-processing therapy with prolonged exposure and a waiting condition for the treatment of chronic posttraumatic stress disorder in female rape victims</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology</source>, <volume>70</volume>, <fpage>867</fpage>–<lpage>879</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Resick</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schnicke</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Cognitive processing therapy for sexual assault victims</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology</source>, <volume>60</volume>, <fpage>748</fpage>–<lpage>756</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Resnick</surname>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Acierno</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holmes</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kilpatrick</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jager</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Prevention of post-rape psychopathology: preliminary findings of a controlled acute rape treatment study</article-title>. <source>Journal of Anxiety Disorders</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>359</fpage>–<lpage>370</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rothbaum</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>A controlled study of eye movement desensitization and reprocessing in the treatment of posttraumatic stress disordered sexual assault victims</article-title>. <source>Bulletin of the Menninger Clinic</source>, <volume>61</volume>, <fpage>317</fpage>–<lpage>334</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rothbaum</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Astin</surname>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Marsteller</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Prolonged exposure versus eye movement desensitization and reprocessing (EMDR) for PTSD rape victims</article-title>. <source>Journal of Traumatic Stress</source>, <volume>18</volume>, <fpage>607</fpage>–<lpage>616</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rothbaum</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Foa</surname>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Riggs</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Murdock</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Walsh</surname>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>A prospective examination of posttraumatic stress disorder in rape victims</article-title>. <source>Journal of Traumatic Stress</source>, <volume>60</volume>, <fpage>748</fpage>–<lpage>756</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rothbaum</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ninan</surname>
<given-names>P. T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Sertraline in the treatment of rape victims with posttraumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>Journal of Traumatic Stress</source>, <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>865</fpage>–<lpage>871</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rizvi</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vogt</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Resick</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Cognitive and affective predictors of treatment outcome in cognitive processing therapy and prolonged exposure for posttraumatic stress disorder</article-title>. <source>Behavior Research and Therapy</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>737</fpage>–<lpage>743</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shalev</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ankri</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Israeli-Shalev</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Peleg</surname>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Adessky</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Freedman</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Prevention of posttraumatic stress disorder by early treatment</article-title>. <source>Archives of General Psychiatry</source>, <volume>69</volume>, <fpage>166</fpage>–<lpage>176</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sherman</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Effects of psychotherapeutic treatments for PTSD: A meta-analysis of controlled clinical trials</article-title>. <source>Journal of Traumatic Stress</source>, <volume>11</volume>, <fpage>413</fpage>–<lpage>435</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Solomon</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Johnson</surname>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Psychological treatment of posttraumatic stress disorder: A practice friendly review of outcome research</article-title>. <source>Psychotherapy in Practice</source>, <volume>58</volume>, <fpage>947</fpage>–<lpage>959</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Spielberger</surname>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <source>Manual for the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory</source>. <publisher-loc>Palo Alto, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Consulting Psychologists Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Harvey</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Effects of psychotherapy with people who have been sexually assaulted: A meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Aggression and Violent Behavior</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>273</fpage>–<lpage>285</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tjaden</surname>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Thoennes</surname>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <source>Extent, nature, and consequences of rape victimization: Findings from the National Violence Against Women Survey</source>. <comment>Special Report</comment>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Institute of Justice and the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vickerman</surname>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Margolin</surname>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Rape treatment outcome research: Empirical findings and state of the literature</article-title>. <source>Clinical Psychology Review</source>, <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>431</fpage>–<lpage>448</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1049731512474103">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Welch</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mason</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Rape and sexual assault</article-title>. <source>British Medical Journal</source>, <volume>334</volume>, <fpage>1158</fpage>–<lpage>1159</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>