<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PPQ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spppq</journal-id>
<journal-title>Party Politics</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1354-0688</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1460-3683</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1354068812462932</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1354068812462932</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Special issue articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Economic liberalization and political moderation</article-title>
<subtitle>The case of anti-system parties</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Sokhey</surname>
<given-names>Sarah Wilson</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff1-1354068812462932">Department of Political Science, University of Colorado, Boulder, USA</aff>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1354068812462932"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yildirim</surname>
<given-names>A. Kadir</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff2-1354068812462932">Department of Political Science, Furman University, Greenville, USA</aff>
</contrib>
<bio>
<title>Author biographies</title>
<p>
<bold>Sarah Wilson Sokhey</bold> is an Assistant Professor of Political Science at the University of Colorado, Boulder. Her research addresses the politics of economic reform, the welfare state and business-state relations with a focus on post-communist countries.</p>
<p>
<bold>A. Kadir Yildirim</bold> is an Assistant Professor of Political Science at Furman University. His main research interests center around economic liberalization, democratization, political Islam and politics of the Middle East.</p>
</bio>
</contrib-group>
<contrib-group content-type="issue">
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name>
<surname>Brocker</surname>
<given-names>Manfred</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="guest-editor">
<name>
<surname>Künkler</surname>
<given-names>Mirjam</given-names>
</name>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1354068812462932">Sarah Wilson Sokhey, Department of Political Science, University of Colorado, UCB 333, Boulder, CO 80309, USA. Email: <email>sarah.sokhey@colorado.edu</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>3</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<issue-title>Special Issue on — Religious parties and the inclusion-moderation thesis</issue-title>
<fpage>230</fpage>
<lpage>255</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>16</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>26</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Although economic liberalization has been argued to promote political liberalization, this relationship is poorly understood and we do not consistently observe greater economic openness leading to more open and moderate political systems. We examine the connection between liberalization and moderation in the context of Islamist and Communist parties, both of which are characterized by ideologies opposed to democracy and the market. When will these ideological parties moderate by adopting more pragmatic agendas? We argue that competitive liberalization spurs the emergence of more moderate parties, but crony liberalization does not. In support of this, we use two sets of most different case comparisons in which we compare two instances of competitive liberalization (Turkey and Hungary) and two instances of crony liberalization (Egypt and Bulgaria). Our research offers an important clarification to existing explanations and a more generalizable theory of how and why liberalization is linked to political moderation.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Anti-system parties</kwd>
<kwd>liberalization</kwd>
<kwd>moderation</kwd>
<kwd>Muslim Democratic Parties</kwd>
<kwd>post-Communist</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1354068812462932">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Economic liberalization has long been thought to contribute to political moderation. Yet, there are numerous instances around the world in which economic liberalization has not had this effect. This empirical outcome might exist because we lack a precise explanation of the causal mechanism by which this economic liberalization contributes to political change. To better explain this theoretical question and empirical puzzle, we analyze the relationship between economic liberalization and political moderation in the case of Islamist and Communist parties. In the Middle East, we observe the moderation of Islamist parties into Muslim Democratic Parties (MDPs), aiming to represent the same constituents as Islamist parties but adopting much more pragmatic stances that are not opposed to democracy and the market. Likewise, in the post-communist countries of Eastern Europe, we see some Communist successor parties winning elections after reinventing themselves with more pragmatic, rather than ideological, policy stances. This is a powerful comparison because in an important but often overlooked way Islamist and Communist parties share a commonality: both kinds of parties have ideological foundations that oppose democracy and the free market.</p>
<p>We argue that economic liberalization is critical to party moderation, but that the effect depends on the type of liberalization. Liberalization may be competitive (meaning it establishes open and competitive business practices) or crony (thereby maintaining a group of elites who monopolize the economy). Competitive liberalization will increase the likelihood that moderate parties win elections, but crony liberalization will not. This is an important clarification to previous theories which have not distinguished among types of economic liberalization.</p>
<p>A major contribution of this article is its comparative research design, which advances a generalizable theory about political moderation. We use two sets of most different case comparisons: competitive liberalization (Turkey and Hungary) and crony liberalization (Egypt and Bulgaria). Our research design provides us with a basis on which to identify the critical determinant for why radical parties moderate in some cases, but not others. Furthermore, by using cases from very different cultural contexts, we are able to evaluate our hypotheses more broadly than other studies.</p>
<p>The article is organized as follows. First, we explain why the moderation of Islamist and traditional Communist parties is similar, and how we can leverage it to reach a generalizable theory. Next, we consider how well existing theories of political moderation explain when MDPs or pragmatic Communist successor parties would emerge. We then present our theory that competitive liberalization promotes moderation, but crony liberalization does not. Finally, we use two sets of most different case comparisons to present four empirical cases which suggest that the type of liberalization is a critical determinant of whether ideological or pragmatic parties moderate.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1354068812462932">
<title>Why Islamist and Communist parties?</title>
<p>Islamist and Communist parties share extremist ideological origins, i.e. opposition to democracy and free market. This makes both parties cases of what have conventionally been called ‘anti-system’ parties – parties that seek to change the very nature of government itself, thereby placing them on the ideological extremes of the political spectrum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr84-1354068812462932">Sartori, 1976</xref>). Their ideological make-up is perceived ‘as a threat to the regime, and often as a threat to democracy tout court’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1354068812462932">Capoccia, 2002</xref>: 10). Traditional Islamist parties’ goal of a state founded on a set of Islamic principles and laws resonates with traditional communist parties’ agenda for a future based on an economic and political system with common ownership and a classless society. Specifically, political Islam envisions an extensive and dominant economic role for the state, including state ownership. Although private enterprise is not frowned upon, important limitations on ownership and economic activity aim to ensure the realization of key Islamic principles such as equity and social justice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr70-1354068812462932">Kuran, 1995</xref>). Additionally, Islamist and Communist parties share an anti-imperialist discourse by adhering to an anti-capitalist and anti-globalization stance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1354068812462932">Bayat, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr102-1354068812462932">Wallerstein, 1992</xref>).<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1354068812462932">1</xref>
</sup> Both types of party thus traditionally share an imagined form of state, a critical view of a liberal economy and an instrumental view of democracy.</p>
<p>In explaining party moderation, we distinguish between ideological versus pragmatic parties. For both Islamist and Communist parties, there is a continuum of being highly ideological on the one end to being highly pragmatic at the other extreme. As an ideal-type, an ideological party refers to parties that maintain their extremist ideological core standing in opposition to democracy and the free market as described above. In contrast, the ideal-type of a pragmatic party is one which upholds a policy agenda embracing democracy and the free market while maintaining a value structure that gives the party its identity (i.e. Muslim values or socialist ideals). Based on this classification, Islamist parties and Communist parties are ideological parties, while MDPs and Communist successor parties are pragmatic parties. We should note that the Communist successor parties in Eastern Europe have adopted increasingly pragmatic stances but to widely varying degrees. We think of the ideological/pragmatic distinction in a continuum for both Islamic and Communist parties. We use ideological to mean what Sartori would call ‘anti-system’ but we consider our terminology to be more universal and more accurate for contemporary circumstances.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1354068812462932">2</xref>
</sup> Historically, this transformation from ideological to pragmatic parties is akin to the case of ‘anti-system’ parties like the Christian Democrats which transformed from a confessional party to one that was much more moderate and open to competitive democracy, but still intended to represent a religious constituency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr61-1354068812462932">Kalyvas, 1996</xref>).</p>
<p>Today, Islamist and traditional Communist parties are the two major types of party in the world that may retain an extremist ideology opposed to democracy and the market (i.e. ‘anti-system’). There are, of course, authoritarian or fascist parties which oppose competitive democracy and capitalism; however, these are often ad hoc parties created to prop up authoritarian regimes, rather than an entire class of party. Fringe parties including anarchist groups might also be what could be classified as ‘anti-system’ parties, but they fail to attract a discernible social base. Islamist and traditional Communist parties are the two major groups of ideological parties that enjoy a strong following on a global scale.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1354068812462932">
<title>Explanations for the moderation of Islamist and Communist parties</title>
<p>Existing research offers various explanations on the general conditions conducive to moderation, but does not specify the link between shifts among elites and support from the constituency that might explain why pragmatic parties emerge. In other words, the literature has focused much less on demand side theories explaining party moderation.</p>
<p>Research on the moderation of Communist successor parties in Eastern Europe has focused heavily on various differences in the regimes prior to 1989 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1354068812462932">Bunce, 1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1354068812462932">2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1354068812462932">Ekiert, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1354068812462932">Fish, 1998</xref>). The literature has identified two main explanations including: (1) how the domestic environment pushed the Communist successor party to adapt, and (2) how the regime legacy affected the party’s leadership style (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1354068812462932">Ishiyama, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr64-1354068812462932">Kitschelt, 2002</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-1354068812462932">Kitschelt et al. (1999</xref>) point to the nature of the Communist-era regime to explain whether Communist successor parties were popular after 1989. Specifically, they focus on the style of leadership during the Communist era, including whether the system was national accommodative (as in Hungary) or patrimonial (as in Bulgaria). Likewise, Grzymala-Busse (2002) points to varying Communist regime legacies to explain why these parties successfully reinvented themselves or not (with the measure of success being winning elections). This research does acknowledge differences in Communist-era constituencies, although the focus remains on how regime legacies influenced party officials.</p>
<p>Existing explanations – for good reasons – focus on the parties and their leaders as the key agents of moderation. This means, however, that these explanations have given less attention to how differences in Communist-era regimes affected constituencies which would in turn influence whether the parties had an incentive to moderate. In fact, prior to 1989, constituencies in countries across Eastern Europe diverged greatly in part because of economic differences during the Communist period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1354068812462932">Fehér and Arato, 1991</xref>). For instance, Grzymala-Busse (2002) traces differences in communist-era responses to regime crises and how these did or did not translate into a ‘usable past’ in the post-communist period. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr112-1354068812462932">Ziblatt and Biziouras (2002</xref>) make a similar argument, focusing on macro-level factors and the organizational capacity inherited from the communist-era. Although some countries followed a traditional Soviet model, others responded to crises with economic liberalization. Economic models, in turn, changed the nature of Communist-era constituents who would determine the outcomes of early post-Communist elections. Our theory builds on the fundamental insight that differences in Communist-era regimes matter by highlighting the development of a nascent sector of small and medium-size enterprises (SMEs) in some countries but not others prior to 1989.</p>
<p>While post-communist studies have focused on the legacy of former Communist regimes, the literature on Islamist moderation revolves around three distinct arguments. One argument is that the inclusion of Islamist parties in formal political structures by way of elections, for example, offers an opportunity for conservative Islamist parties to adapt to the rules and constraints of an existing system, and eventually to moderate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1354068812462932">Brooks, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1354068812462932">El-Ghobashy, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr85-1354068812462932">Schwedler, 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr86-1354068812462932">2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr106-1354068812462932">Willis, 2004</xref>). Among parties included in the system, however, the extent of moderation varies as well as how far this moderation resonates with the electorate. Others argue that when Islamist parties face state repression they act to moderate their ideological stance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1354068812462932">Cizre, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr90-1354068812462932">Somer, 2007</xref>). Among repressed Islamist groups, however, some choose to moderate their stance, whereas others remained conservative as before, if not more so.</p>
<p>The third explanation for Islamist moderation is economic liberalization. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr111-1354068812462932">Zakaria (2004</xref>) argues that economic opening leads the business class to grow independent of the state and political elite, which in turn leads to the creation of a vested interest in a liberal order. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-1354068812462932">Nasr (2005</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-1354068812462932">2009</xref>), from a broader perspective, claims that economic liberalization benefits middle classes the most; these middle classes eventually become the drivers of moderation since most of the middle classes are religiously observant. The argument is most forcefully applied to the case of Turkey (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1354068812462932">Gumuscu, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr110-1354068812462932">Yavuz, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Thus, in both literatures, i.e. political moderation in the Middle East and Eastern Europe, economic liberalization is identified as an important factor. Liberalization, however, does not always produce viable pragmatic political parties. In addition to our inability to explain the empirical variation in the effect of liberalization, we also lack a strong theoretical explanation of the means by which liberalization leads to the emergence of more moderate parties.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1354068812462932">
<title>Competitive vs. crony liberalization</title>
<p>Although there is a compelling theoretical argument and some empirical evidence that liberalization affects political moderation, not all economic liberalization is the same. Critically, we argue that the type of liberalization should determine whether or not pragmatic parties will be more likely to emerge. We identify two ideal types of liberalization – competitive and crony. <italic>Competitive liberalization</italic> minimizes obstacles to integration with the global economy and opens the domestic economy to allow for the greater participation of a wide array of business owners. In contrast, <italic>crony liberalization</italic> represents the politicization of the economic reform process; integration to the global economy via trade and the financial sector remains limited and highly selective to ensure the protection of elite’s privileges. In both cases, the domestic economy opens up (or liberalizes), but a competitive process allows for a wider array of businesses to participate while the crony variant does not.</p>
<p>The difference between competitive and crony capitalism can be seen in several measures of liberalization provided by the World Economic Forum presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1354068812462932">Table 1</xref>. These measures include overall competition, local competition, market dominance, anti-monopoly policy, trade barriers, access to loans and tariff rates. Where competitive liberalization occurs, we should observe more competition, less market dominance, effective anti-monopoly policy, limited trade barriers, easy access to loans and lower tariff rates. The overall assessment should reveal an open and competitive economy. Our distinction between competitive versus crony liberalization does not pertain solely to the degree of liberalization, but rather to a qualitative difference between two ideal types. The indicators in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1354068812462932">Table 1</xref> imply the type of liberalization rather than just a measure of the degree of liberalization.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1354068812462932" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Economic liberalization indicators (global rank in parentheses, out of 139 countries).</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1354068812462932" xlink:href="10.1177_1354068812462932-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>
</th>
<th>Bulgaria</th>
<th>Egypt</th>
<th>Hungary</th>
<th>Turkey</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Competition (overall)</td>
<td>4.1 (71<sup>st</sup>)</td>
<td>4.0 (81<sup>st</sup>)</td>
<td>4.3 (52<sup>nd</sup>)</td>
<td>4.2 (61<sup>st</sup>)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Intensity of local competition</td>
<td>4.5 (95<sup>th</sup>)</td>
<td>4.6 (91<sup>st</sup>)</td>
<td>5.3 (39<sup>th</sup>)</td>
<td>5.7 (15<sup>th</sup>)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Extent of market dominance</td>
<td>3.4 (87<sup>th</sup>)</td>
<td>3.3 (95<sup>th</sup>)</td>
<td>3.7 (62<sup>nd</sup>)</td>
<td>4.2 (45<sup>th</sup>)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Effective anti-monopoly policy</td>
<td>3.3 (114<sup>th</sup>)</td>
<td>3.5 (106<sup>th</sup>)</td>
<td>4.0 (66<sup>th</sup>)</td>
<td>4.6 (34<sup>th</sup>)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Prevalence of trade barriers</td>
<td>4.1 (107<sup>th</sup>)</td>
<td>4.0 (114<sup>th</sup>)</td>
<td>5.6 (15<sup>th</sup>)</td>
<td>4.6 (65<sup>th</sup>)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ease of access to loans</td>
<td>2.8 (62<sup>nd</sup>)</td>
<td>3.0 (49<sup>th</sup>)</td>
<td>2.5 (86<sup>th</sup>)</td>
<td>2.6 (77<sup>th</sup>)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Trade-weighted tariff rates</td>
<td>0.9 (4<sup>th</sup>)</td>
<td>13.8 (123<sup>rd</sup>)</td>
<td>0.9 (4<sup>th</sup>)</td>
<td>4.4 (60<sup>th</sup>)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1354068812462932">
<p>
<italic>Source:</italic> World Economic Forum (2010–2011).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The key observable implication of the distinction between these two types of liberalization is whether they allow the development of small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs). We argue that competitive liberalization should drive party moderation because it allows for the growth of SMEs, resulting in constituents who will support pragmatic political platforms. Conversely, crony liberalization impedes the growth of SMEs thereby preventing the emergence of a strong constituent base for pragmatic parties; the weak and marginalized SME owners continue supporting ideological political discourse.</p>
<p>SMEs constitute the key mechanism through which economic liberalization drives party moderation. This is for two reasons. First, SME owners make up a key constituency for Islamist and Communist parties. In the case of Islamist parties, SME owners have long been identified as a key constituency of such parties (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr76-1354068812462932">Nasr, 2005</xref>). As the beneficiaries of change in the post-liberalization period, SMEs’ rise and transformation correspond with former Communist parties’ soul searching, i.e. whether and how to reposition to tap into social changes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1354068812462932">Curry and Urban, 2003</xref>). Furthermore, business associations have been an important mechanism through which SME owners organized to advance their interests both in the Middle East as in the cases of MUSIAD (Independent Businessmen’s and Industrialists’ Association) and TUSKON (Confederation of Businessmen and Industrialists in Turkey) in Turkey and in Eastern Europe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1354068812462932">Bateman, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1354068812462932">Duvanova, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr82-1354068812462932">Recantini and Ryterman, 2000</xref>). Hence, change in SMEs should have a corresponding change in their political representation. In brief, what we recognize as moderation in ideological parties is, in fact, a set of new policy positions developed to respond to the material interests of SME owners.</p>
<p>Second, SME owners stand to gain the most from liberalization. Under competitive liberalization, SMEs are able to find greater opportunities for growing and thriving (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1354068812462932">Gulalp, 2001</xref>). In a changing socio-economic environment and with a vested interest in an open system, SME owners develop more liberal political and economic preferences that would enable them to continue benefiting from the liberal system. Indeed, such a transformation brings SME owners closer to other business owners who operate in a liberal system. Business owners prefer low uncertainty, low polarization, transparency, and the rule of law along with a liberal economy, which in turn perpetuate the conditions under which they were able to rise in the first place (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1354068812462932">Drabek and Payne, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1354068812462932">Frye, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr63-1354068812462932">Keefer and Knack, 2002</xref>). Hence, the polarizing discourse of radical Islamist and traditional Communist parties does not appeal to them. Conversely, crony liberalization does not allow for the growth of SMEs nor does it provide SMEs with the same incentive to support more moderate discourse. In Islamist cases, SMEs will remain a marginalized group and will support more radical discourse as a result. In post-communist cases, SMEs in crony systems will remain a marginal group with little sway on the larger political system; SMEs will also have little incentive to actively push for more moderate political agendas as their chances of success are so low. Thus, where crony liberalization occurs, we should observe that the SME sector is small in size and tends to support ideological parties (in the Islamist crony cases) or is less likely to be politically influential (in the post-communist crony cases). Overall, our theory emphasizes how economic liberalization changes the electorate and gets the parties to think more closely about capturing shifting constituencies. In particular, a thriving SME sector makes for a larger moderate constituency that plays a crucial role in encouraging parties to moderate.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1354068812462932">
<title>Empirical evidence from four cases</title>
<p>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1354068812462932">2</xref> explicates our two sets of most different case comparisons and summarizes our main empirical findings. We selected four cases that match on the type of liberalization. While Hungary and Turkey conform to the competitive liberalization model, Bulgaria and Egypt are cases of crony liberalization.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-1354068812462932" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Summary of Case Comparisons.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-1354068812462932" xlink:href="10.1177_1354068812462932-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th colspan="2">
</th>
<th>
<italic>Key similarity</italic> Type of Economic Liberalization</th>
<th>
<italic>Causal Mechanism</italic> Shifts in the Constituency</th>
<th>
<italic>Same Outcome</italic> Ideological/Pragmatic Party</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">
<bold>Competitive Cases</bold>
</td>
<td>Hungary</td>
<td>Liberalization during Communist era as part of Kadar regime’s strategy tostay in power beginning in the late 1950s</td>
<td>Development of SMEs from the 1960s through the 1980s</td>
<td>Pragmatic Communist successor party (Hungarian Socialist Party)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Turkey</td>
<td>Liberalization begun in 1980 to address an ISI-induced balance of paymentscrisis</td>
<td>Dramatic increase in SMEs in the 1980s and 1990s</td>
<td>Pragmatic Muslim Democratic party (Justice &amp; Development Party) </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td rowspan="2">
<bold>Crony Cases</bold>
</td>
<td>Bulgaria</td>
<td>Relatively high growth rates in the 1960s and strong Soviet ties precludecompetitive liberalization; crony liberalization continues in the 1990s</td>
<td>Small enterprises marginalized; large enterprises continue to control theeconomy throughout the 1990s </td>
<td>Ideological Communist successor party (Bulgarian Socialist Party) </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Egypt</td>
<td>
<italic>Infitah </italic>policy introduced in 1971 results in economy withwealth concentrated in the hands of a small number of big firms; reforms in the1990s perpetuated the crony system</td>
<td>SMEs extremely disadvantaged relative to larger firms; the “infitahclass” dominates the economy</td>
<td>Ideological Islamist Party (Muslim Brotherhood)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>In presenting the cases, we follow the structure laid out in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-1354068812462932">Table 2</xref>:</p>
<list list-type="order">
<list-item>
<p>Type of Liberalization (one key similarity)</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>The Development of the Constituency (causal mechanism)</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Moderation of Ideological Party, or Not (same outcome)</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Alternate Explanations</p>
</list-item>
</list>
<p>We present evidence that: (1) the constituency was changing (or, not in cases where there is crony liberalization) and, (2) that pragmatic parties actively courted the changing constituency (or, not in crony liberalization cases), and (3) that SMEs were supporters of formerly ideological parties that chose to moderate. Finally, we also consider differences across the cases that could serve as alternate explanations for the moderation of ideological parties. Here, the paired cases are useful in demonstrating that certain factors which might have predicted divergent outcomes regarding party moderation actually resulted in similar outcomes.</p>
<p>All of our cases are competitive democracies except for Egypt. Despite the fact that Egypt is not yet a democracy, we find it a useful case to include. First, even if Egypt fails to fulfil all of the requirements of a procedural definition of democracy, the fact that there have been recurring legislative elections in Egypt since the 1980s suggests that opposition parties including the Islamist Muslim Brotherhood play a ‘dual game’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr73-1354068812462932">Mainwaring and Scully, 2003</xref>). The regime game dictates that the MB (along with other opposition groups) challenge the legitimacy of the regime in order to instigate a regime change. The electoral game by contrast requires the opposition to pay greater attention to the electorate's demands to increase its support base. Hence, rather than an exclusive focus on delegitimizing the current regime, opposition groups are simultaneously pushed into electoral politics à la democratic regimes <italic>and</italic> oppose the existing regime. This is also consistent with how elections can serve the long-term goals of the Muslim Brotherhood, including ‘promoting its message, participating in parliamentary institutions, and encouraging democratic practices that the group expects to be the primary beneficiary of in some future political game’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1354068812462932">Blaydes, 2010</xref>: 170). In providing evidence of political business cycles in authoritarian elections, Blaydes identifies an important commonality with some democratic systems. Second, Egypt held its first free elections with the first round of parliamentary elections on 28 November 2011. Although it remains to be seen how far Egypt will proceed in its democratic venture, the fact that free elections were held and the possibility of alternation of power is in the horizon implies a change in the underlying structure of electoral politics, thereby satisfying a crucial element of procedural definition of democracy. We should emphasize, however, that our argument here is not contingent on Egypt becoming or remaining a competitive democracy.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1354068812462932">
<title>Competitive liberalization in Hungary and Turkey</title>
<sec id="section7-1354068812462932">
<title>Type of liberalization</title>
<p>Turkey and Hungary both experienced competitive liberalization prior to the emergence of a pragmatic party. <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1354068812462932">Table 1</xref> reveals that Hungary and Turkey share important similarities in the effects of their competitive liberalization. Both have high rates of overall competition and local competition, ranking in the top 50 percent of all countries in both areas.</p>
<p>Hungary became one of the most economically liberal regimes in the Eastern bloc during Communist times, significantly modifying the model of a traditionally Soviet centrally-planned economy. Comprehensive economic liberalization was officially introduced in 1968 with the New Economic Mechanism (NEM), including a host of economic reform measures that continued through the 1980s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1354068812462932">Brown, 1966</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr97-1354068812462932">Tesche and Tohamy, 1994</xref>). There was increased freedom of enterprises and allowances for a small private sector in the 1970s. Small private enterprises were fully legalized in 1981, and in 1983 public enterprises, i.e. state companies, were allowed to form subsidiaries and contract work out to private actors. Major changes continued in the 1980s. An income tax was introduced in 1982, private enterprises were allowed to hire more employees (up to 500), and complete foreign ownership of private businesses was permitted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr97-1354068812462932">Tesche and Tohamy, 1994</xref>). In short, a nascent SME sector began to develop before the collapse of communism in 1989 and this was a major difference with Communist regimes like Bulgaria.</p>
<p>In Turkey, reforms began in January of 1980 and were abrupt, minimizing the politicization of the reform process. The World Bank oversaw a structural adjustment programme to ensure the transformation from an ISI economy to an open and ‘export-led’ economy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr83-1354068812462932">Rodrik, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr88-1354068812462932">Senses, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr103-1354068812462932">Waterbury, 1992</xref>). In less than a decade, major liberalization reforms were undertaken in domestic pricing mechanisms, trade (governmental support for exports and gradual reduction of quantitative import restrictions and tariffs), the financial sector (capital movement and interest rates) and exchange rates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1354068812462932">Bugra, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1354068812462932">Cecen et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr89-1354068812462932">Snowden, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr96-1354068812462932">Taşkin and Yeldan, 1996</xref>). Turgut Ozal – a leading economic advisor and the Prime Minister after 1983 – overcame domestic resistance to reforms, especially from big businesses, by recourse to international constraints imposed by the World Bank and the IMF.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1354068812462932">
<title>Liberalization and constituency</title>
<p>Liberalization in both cases led to changes in constituencies, resulting in the emergence of pragmatic parties. Economic liberalization in Hungary prior to 1989 directly led to a socio-economic transformation with political implications. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-1354068812462932">Kornai (1991</xref>) indicates that the private sector’s rate of growth from 1953 to 1989 was tremendous. Those employed full time in the formal private sector more than doubled from 58,000 in 1953 to 164,000 in 1964 even before the most extensive reforms. By 1985, the private sector provided 87 percent of the market for repairs and maintenance and more than half of the secondary construction market. By the time there were competitive elections in 1989, SMEs were already a notable segment of the Hungarian economy, albeit one subject to significant bureaucratic constraints on their activities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-1354068812462932">Kornai, 1991</xref>).<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1354068812462932">3</xref>
</sup> It is important to emphasize that the development of SMEs predated the fall of communism in 1989, although the SME sector grew substantially in the 1990s as Hungary pursued even more competitive liberalization. By 1995, Eurostat reported that Hungary had 11,000 small and medium-sized firms (compared to only 3,600 in Bulgaria) (cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1354068812462932">Bateman, 2000</xref>: 278).<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1354068812462932">4</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Economic liberalization in Hungary prior to 1989 also directly contributed to a socio-economic transformation with political implications. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1354068812462932">Bozóki (1993</xref>) writes that: ‘The process of “petty-embourgeoisement” during the Kadar period produced a collective mindset amongst most Hungarians that is utterly different from traditional Communist culture and transformed the matrix of interests and the economic structure of society’ (ibid., p. 276). The changes in Hungary allowed for the development of small and medium-sized enterprises that fostered the development of a society more inclined to favour liberalization and, in turn, political openness. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr99-1354068812462932">Tokes (1996)</xref> echoes this point writing that the major success of the NEM initiative was, ‘… the unintended restoration of individual initiative through the vehicle of private enterprise and the consequent corrosive effects of the second economy on the social cohesion of the regime’s core political constituencies’ (ibid., p. 115).</p>
<p>In Turkey, we likewise saw the development of SMEs as an unintended consequence of liberalization. In the 1980s and 1990s, SMEs grew dramatically in Turkey and were aided by the new trade policy – export promotion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1354068812462932">Bugra, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1354068812462932">Hansen, 1991</xref>). Smaller firms’ edge in flexible production and subcontracting put them in an advantageous position vis-à-vis big firms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1354068812462932">Gulalp, 2001</xref>). Collectively, liberalization had an important impact on the dynamics of the Turkish economy. There was a shift in the centrality of economic production from Istanbul-based big business to the politically and geographically peripheral parts of Turkey.</p>
<p>According to a survey of Turkish SME owners, 75 percent of SME owners were politically conservative. About 60 percent were first-time business owners and 75 percent in business for less than two decades, implying that their fortunes were directly tied to the economic liberalization process in Turkey. Only 6 percent received subsidies from the state and 83 percent support democracy as a regime type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1354068812462932">Esen and Conkar, 1999</xref>). As in Hungary, Turkey’s pragmatic party, the JDP, would actively seek out the support of these small businesses.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1354068812462932">
<title>Same outcome: Pragmatic party emerges</title>
<p>In Hungary, the Communist successor party – the Magyar Socialist Party (MSzP) – modified its agenda to be a very pragmatic Communist Party and did so before the first competitive elections in 1990. In October of 1989, the MSzP adopted a party manifesto in which it rejected all forms of Stalinism, but embraced socialist ideals and explicitly promoted the adoption of a market-based economy. The MSzP described itself as a ‘modern socialist party’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54-1354068812462932">Hungarian Socialist Party Manifesto 1989</xref>) which had abandoned ‘a dogmatic commitment to Marxism’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr81-1354068812462932">Racz, 1993</xref>: 651). Party leaders in the mid-1990s portrayed the MSzP as ‘a genuine catch-all party embracing left-wing ideals and capable of laying the foundation of a new social consensus Hungary badly needs’.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1354068812462932">5</xref>
</sup> Another more conservative, orthodox Communist Party called the Workers’ Party also emerged, but never won representation in any post-communist election. MSzP leader Imre Pozsgay referred to the Workers’ Party as a blessing because it allowed the MSzP to delineate itself from the ‘real’ communists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1354068812462932">Grzymała-Busse, 2002</xref>: 114). The MSzP was no longer an ideological Communist party but rather a new pragmatic party of the left which was willing to adapt its policy stances to changing conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1354068812462932">Evans and Whitefield, 1995</xref>).</p>
<p>The MSzP actively courted business people and entrepreneurs by supporting market reforms, arguing that they should be considered closer to right-wing liberals (like Fidesz on the right) than far-left parties (like the Workers’ Party). Furthermore, there is evidence that SMEs were an important source of support for the MSzP in these early elections. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1354068812462932">Arato (1995</xref>: 75) estimates that the MSzP did well in the 1990 elections because at least 5 to 10 percent of its vote came from ‘centrist and liberal voters who had no personal economic grievances’ and ‘were not parts of the old [Communist] apparatus’.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1354068812462932">6</xref>
</sup> We argue that an important source of these centrist and liberal voters was precisely the SMEs that began developing during Communist times. In 1994, the MSzP enjoyed a major electoral win and one of the largest employment categories supporting the MSzP was skilled workers and entrepreneurs who represented 19 percent of professional groups supporting the Communist successor party, second only to pensioners (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-1354068812462932">Kovács, 1996</xref>).<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-1354068812462932">7</xref>
</sup> In 1997, the <italic>Budapest Business Journal</italic> wrote that: ‘The coalition of ex-communists and left-liberals is the free market’s best friend in Hungary’ (quoted in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1354068812462932">Murer, 1999</xref>: 204). By all accounts, the MSzP’s moderation was driven by a desire to capture SME support, which it was successful in doing.</p>
<p>Recent survey evidence reveals that SME owners have continued to be important supporters of the MSzP.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-1354068812462932">8</xref>
</sup> In 2002, 43 percent of SME owners said that they felt the most closely related to the MSzP over other political parties. Likewise, in 2002, 52 percent of SME employees identified with the MSzP. SME owners who felt closest to the MSzP remained high in 2006 and 2008 (at 35 and 18 percent, respectively), but dropped in 2010 to only 9 percent, which is very likely related to the financial crisis and the rise of the far right.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-1354068812462932">9</xref>
</sup> Nonetheless, prior to 2010, survey evidence shows that the MSzP was very popular among SME owners, and support for the MSzP among employees of SMEs remained high with 36, 28 and 19 percent responding that they felt closest to the Communist success party in 2006, 2008 and 2010, respectively.</p>
<p>Hungary has experienced regular alternation in power between the MSzP on the left and the new Fidesz party on the right with the MSzP winning 11, 33 and 32 percent of the vote in the 1990, 1994 and 1998 elections, respectively. Between 1999 and 2001, the party’s approval ratings were at 40 percent or higher (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1354068812462932">Grzymała-Busse, 2002</xref>). More recently, the MSzP has continued to be a major political contender. The MSzP won 43 percent of the votes in the 2006 parliamentary elections and 20 percent of the vote in the 2010 elections.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-1354068812462932">10</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Critically, economic liberalization preceded the most significant measures of political liberalization in Hungary, including the fall of communism. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50-1354068812462932">Hare et al. (1981</xref>) note that: ‘The economic reform was exclusively confined to the economic sphere and was not at all concerned with seeking modifications in the social and power relations in Hungarian society’ (p. 29). In other words, it was not the Hungarian Communist Party that was politically more moderate under Communism, but rather Hungarian economic strategy in the Communist era was more liberal and led to changes in the constituency. This helps to rule out the argument that Hungary has a pragmatic Communist successor party due to any political or social liberalization during the Communist era; rather, economic liberalization in the Communist era created a constituency with different economic interests than in other countries which led to the emergence of a more pragmatic Communist Party.</p>
<p>Likewise, in Turkey the change in the economic centre of gravity in the 1980s foreshadowed an important political shift. Necmettin Erbakan’s National Outlook Movement (NOM) had been established in the 1960s to represent the marginalized Islamic groups among which SME owners were an important constituency. Erbakan’s Islamist movement in the 1970 s garnered support mainly from the poor and new immigrants to urban areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr87-1354068812462932">Sen, 2004</xref>: 45; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr98-1354068812462932">Tekeli and Gokceli, 1977</xref>: 67). Not until the late 1990s – when the dominance of the conservative Islamist discourse was challenged within the NOM – would there be the emergence of a pragmatic Muslim democratic party, the Justice and Development Party.</p>
<p>The moderation of Turkey’s Islamic constituency led the JDP to adopt a new, moderate platform in 2001 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1354068812462932">Atacan, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1354068812462932">Dagi, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr108-1354068812462932">Yakis, 2002</xref>). JDP officials revealed that policy preferences of society at large and of SME owners played a key role in the party’s transformation. The JDP actively sought to address the policy preferences of smaller firms through MUSIAD – the Independent Industrialists and Businessmen’s Association (MUSIAD), a business association founded in 1990 to represent SMEs, and currently one of the most influential business associations. In addition, prospective JDP officials conducted surveys with a large sample of the population to gauge societal preferences on various policy areas. Among the issues that were highlighted by survey respondents were democracy, employment, the economy, civil liberties and EU membership (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr109-1354068812462932">Yakis interview, 2008</xref>). As a result, the JDP was established on a Muslim democratic platform emphasizing democracy, a liberal economy and Muslim values (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1354068812462932">Gumuscu, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr77-1354068812462932">Nasr, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr90-1354068812462932">Somer, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr110-1354068812462932">Yavuz, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>The level of electoral support for the JDP indicates that there is a significant overlap between the JDP’s moderate discourse and the preferences of the Islamic constituency, including SMEs. The JDP won the parliamentary elections in 2002, 2007 and 2011. In 2002, the party claimed a landslide victory with 34 percent of the votes and close to two-thirds of parliamentary seats due to the 10 percent national threshold for parties to receive any parliamentary seats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr79-1354068812462932">Özel, 2003</xref>). The 2007 legislative elections were conducted under the shadow of extra-democratic interventions by the military and other secular elite actors such as the judiciary and the RPP producing an electoral victory with 47 percent of the votes. In 2011, the party won 50 percent of the votes, winning an unprecedented third straight term in office, whereas the Islamist NOM garnered less than 3 percent of votes in all three elections. The JDP is a direct response to the increasingly visible and changing demands and policy preferences of SME owners. The NOM’s ideological conservatism in several policy areas was far from reflecting the demands of the electorate. SME owners and their political representative, the JDP, successfully challenged the secular, urban upper classes and the elite at their own game, i.e. democracy and liberalism.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1354068812462932">
<title>Alternate explanations</title>
<p>Turkey and Hungary differ on several factors that might have potentially led the two countries on different trajectories regarding party moderation. Religion is one such factor. A large body of literature highlights religion’s role in spurring democratization (and, by extension of more pragmatic and less ideological politics) as it relates to some forms of Christianity.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-1354068812462932">11</xref>
</sup> By contrast, Islam has been viewed by some as an impediment to democratization and moderate politics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr72-1354068812462932">Lewis, 2002</xref>). Although the argument that Islam might be detrimental to democracy and moderation is contested by others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1354068812462932">Esposito and Voll, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51-1354068812462932">Hashemi, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr93-1354068812462932">Stepan and Robertson, 2003</xref>), if this argument were correct then Turkey’s Islamic heritage should push parties to be more ideological, while Hungary’s Christian heritage should not. Yet, the divergence of religious heritage in both countries shows incongruence with the similarity in outcome, i.e. the emergence of moderate-pragmatic parties. Others suggested repression of ideological parties as a factor leading to moderation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1354068812462932">Cizre, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr90-1354068812462932">Somer, 2007</xref>). If repression contributes to the moderation of extremist parties, then the existence of repression against the Islamist movement in Turkey should have led to moderation in Turkey, while the absence of oppression of Communism in Hungary after 1989 should not have led to moderation; however, this is not what happened. Finally, others suggested that the prospect of European Union (EU) membership might contribute to democratization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr68-1354068812462932">Kubicek, 2003</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr69-1354068812462932">2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr78-1354068812462932">Onis, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr101-1354068812462932">Vachudova, 2001</xref>).<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-1354068812462932">12</xref>
</sup> While we agree with the fundamental insight of this literature, namely that EU conditionality pushes countries in a more democratic direction, we argue that the implications are less clear for individual parties. In other words, that the EU demands stable democratic regimes in place and that prospective members abide by EU pressures to this end signals the strength of EU attraction on the part of governments, yet there is no clear-cut mechanism that would translate the same attraction on the part of individual parties, especially ideological parties. If anything, the prospect of EU membership adds another ideological rallying point against the government. Moreover, according to this alternative explanation, we should have observed different trajectories of moderation in these two cases because of different membership prospects for both countries. Yet, the Hungarian Communist successor party emerged as a pragmatic party just as the Turkish Islamist party did despite the low prospects for the Turkish bid for EU membership (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr94-1354068812462932">Steunenberg et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr100-1354068812462932">Ugur, 2010</xref>). In summary, although Hungary and Turkey differ on several major explanatory factors, they end up with the same outcome – the emergence of a pragmatic party.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1354068812462932">
<title>Crony liberalization in Bulgaria and Egypt</title>
<sec id="section12-1354068812462932">
<title>Type of liberalization</title>
<p>Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1354068812462932">1</xref> presents indicators suggesting that Bulgaria and Egypt have followed similar forms of crony liberalization; both rank among countries with the highest trade barriers and the least overall competition in the world and they lack effective anti-monopoly legislation. Bulgaria was a thoroughly Stalinized regime that experienced virtually no reform movements under Communism. In the 1960s, Bulgaria was still undergoing economic modernization and experiencing relatively high growth rates – unlike other East European Communist regimes like Hungary – and the leadership saw less of a need to seriously consider drastic reform measures (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1354068812462932">Brown, 1966</xref>). A New Economic Mechanism (NEM) was passed in agriculture in the late 1970s and in other sectors in 1982, but the reforms were restricted to limited decentralization and encouraging some foreign investment. Bulgaria’s NEM had very little in common with the Hungarian initiative of the same name (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1354068812462932">Brown, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1354068812462932">Goldman, 1997</xref>). In the mid-1980s, Decree No. 56 legalized some private businesses and initiated some market elements into how state-owned enterprises were run (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1354068812462932">Ganev, 2007</xref>: 44–45), but only towards the end of 1987 did the Bulgarian government begin to emphasize consumer goods issues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1354068812462932">Goldman, 1997</xref>).</p>
<p>In Egypt, the early 1970s marked the transition from an Arab socialist economy set up by Nasser to a market economy. Anwar Sadat initiated the well-known <italic>infitah</italic> (open door) policy in 1971 in the wake of Nasser’s death to reinstitute an economy that rested on an indigenous ‘capitalist elite’ for economic development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1354068812462932">Farah, 2009</xref>: 24). In order to attract foreign and Egyptian private capital for investment, Sadat introduced a new constitution and new regulations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr74-1354068812462932">Moustafa, 2007</xref>). Sadat’s <italic>infitah</italic> policy was unsuccessful, however, in creating the range of economic activities that it promised. Most foreign and local private investment came in economic sectors such as luxury construction and tourism with minimal effect on industrialization. Growth was largely due to increased public and private consumption (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1354068812462932">Cooper, 1982</xref>: 106).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1354068812462932">
<title>Liberalization and constituency</title>
<p>During the Communist era the Bulgarian economy was very different from that of Hungary and there was no nascent SME sector in 1989. Crony liberalization throughout most of the 1990s continued to stifle the growth of SMEs and heavily favoured the development of large firms with close connections to the state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1354068812462932">Ganev, 2007</xref>). As cited above, in 1995 there were three times fewer SMEs in Bulgaria compared to Hungary (Eurostat figures in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1354068812462932">Bateman (2000</xref>)). This situation began to change in the late 1990s and 2000s when the Bulgarian government initiated more serious economic reforms in reaction to the stagnating economy and, in part, to gain EU membership. Liberalization in the 1990s, however, followed the crony model and ensured that wealth became concentrated in the hands of a few state insiders and private businesses. This was most evident with Multigroup, Bulgaria’s most powerful conglomerate in the 1990s. Multigroup’s board of directors included many former high-ranking government officials and was able to exploit its close relations with the Communist successor party – the Bulgarian Socialist Party (BSP) – to dominate the state structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1354068812462932">Ganev, 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1354068812462932">2007</xref>). In the 1990s, the Bulgarian case was the epitome of the ‘winners take all’ scenario laid out by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52-1354068812462932">Hellman (1998</xref>) with disproportionately powerful big businesses as the greatest threat to the development of a true market system.</p>
<p>The type of liberalization in Egypt also precluded the growth of SMEs. A key outcome of <italic>infitah</italic> was the formation of a small coalition that dominated politics and the economy. Remnants of pre-Nasser landed elite and big business owners along with former technocrats and managers of state economic enterprises became major actors in the post-<italic>infitah</italic> period (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr57-1354068812462932">Ibrahim, 1994</xref>: 34). Collectively, these groups made up what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1354068812462932">Beinin (2005</xref>) called the ‘<italic>infitah</italic> class’. SME owners, by contrast, did not benefit from the liberalizing economy; relative to big businesses in Egypt, SMEs remained as disadvantaged as ever. And the masses saw little improvement in their income, unemployment progressively increased over time, and subsidies slowly withered away due to pressure from international financial institutions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr58-1354068812462932">Ibrahim, 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Egypt undertook two more reform efforts which also failed to create a liberal economic infrastructure. The Economic Reform and Structural Adjustment Programme (ERSAP) of the early 1990s had dismal effects on society while maintaining crucial elements of an illiberal economic regime for smaller firms. Major problems included the limited transparency of privatization efforts, the distorted nature of credit access, non-competitive market practices and public procurement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1354068812462932">Adly, 2009</xref>). In the mid-2000s, the Mubarak government engaged in yet another phase of economic reform that reinforced monopolies and quasi-monopolies to protect the interests and monopolies of well-connected big businessmen such as Osman Ahmed Osman, Ahmed Eizz and Mohamed Nosseir (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1354068812462932">Abdellatif and Ghoneim, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1354068812462932">Adly, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53-1354068812462932">Henry and Springborg, 2001</xref>). Moreover, privatization merely led to the creation of private monopolies instead of state monopolies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr95-1354068812462932">Stevens, 1993</xref>: 123 f.) failing to create the foundation for a competitive economy or the growth of SMEs.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1354068812462932">
<title>Same outcome: No Pragmatic Party Emerges</title>
<p>In Bulgaria, a pragmatic Communist successor party did not emerge. Rather, the Communist successor party – the BSP – remained a very ideological party declaring that it would not retreat from its Marxist origins and maintaining a largely unreformed economic agenda and foreign policy stance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1354068812462932">Frye, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr59-1354068812462932">Ishiyama, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr91-1354068812462932">Spirova, 2008</xref>). The BSP pursued economic policies relying on centralized economic planning and price controls; in fact, between 1992 and 1996 the percentage of prices under government regulation increased from 18 to 45 (Dobrinsky (1997) in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1354068812462932">Frye (2010</xref>)). BSP economic policies included support for high public protection along with almost complete opposition to privatization and international integration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr65-1354068812462932">Kitschelt et al., 1999</xref>). The BSP also proudly asserted that they had ‘… defied the imperialistic encroachments of the International Monetary Fund, rebuffed the “neoliberal Washington consensus”, and consistently championed a set of socially oriented market reforms’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1354068812462932">Ganev, 2001</xref>: 78). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr60-1354068812462932">Ishiyama and Bozóki (2002</xref>) quantify the extent to which Communist successor parties were for or against market-oriented reforms on a 0 to 1 scale with 1 being the most in favor of reforms; the BSP scored a 0.5 compared to a 0.86 score for the MSzP and 0.82 for the Polish Communist successor party. On foreign policy, the BSP in the 1990s also opposed the country’s inclusion in NATO and the EU, unlike its more moderate party equivalents in Hungary and Poland (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr91-1354068812462932">Spirova, 2008</xref>). Thus, on the continuum from ideological to pragmatic, we can see that the BSP was closer to ideological, while the MSzP was much closer to the pragmatic end of the spectrum.</p>
<p>In Bulgaria, no class of SME owners existed which would support a more pragmatic agenda in opposition to the BSP. A coalition of weakly organized non-communist parties formed the Union of Democratic Forces (UDF), emerging as the main opposition group in the early transition. The UDF advocated such unpopular policies that some even speculated certain UDF members were actually BSP supporters planted in the coalition to make sure it was not successful by being too anti-communist; when members of the UDF tried to moderate some of the extreme anti-communist stances they were kicked out of the party (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr62-1354068812462932">Karasimeonov, 1996</xref>). Ultimately, there was simply not strong popular support for an anti-communist agenda in Bulgaria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr80-1354068812462932">Petrova, 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>As of 1989, there were virtually no SMEs in the country and by 1995 there were only 3,600 small businesses in the entire country (Eurostat figures in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1354068812462932">Bateman (2000</xref>)). The divergent size of the SME sector in Hungary versus Bulgaria helps to explain why the Communist successor parties in each country had different bases of support. Although the MSzP in Hungary had its base among urban and more educated workers who had done relatively well during Communist times, the BSP sought support from rural voters, emphasizing the importance of agricultural policy and social welfare (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1354068812462932">Murer, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr91-1354068812462932">Spirova, 2008</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1354068812462932">Creed (1995</xref>) cites extensive evidence from election results in 1991 that the BSP won because it rallied support in rural areas and argues that the vote for the BSP resulted from a fear of those in rural areas that the agricultural sector would not fare well in the transition to the market. Thus, we see virtually an opposite type of constituency in Bulgaria than in Hungary. While in Hungary the MSzP sought to capture a nascent SME sector that would support competitive liberalization, in Bulgaria the BSP sought to capture rural voters in the agricultural sector who feared transition.</p>
<p>The BSP’s strategy worked and it won 47 percent of parliamentary seats with the UDF receiving 36 percent. In late 1991, the UDF edged out the BSP with 34.6 to 33.1 percent of the vote. A short-lived coalition of the UDF and the Turkish minority party, the Movement for Democratic Rights and Freedoms (which had won 7.6 percent of the seats), was undermined by a lack of cooperation from the sizable BSP minority. Attempts to confiscate former Communist Party property, to ban former Communists from office, and to investigate former party officials were mostly blocked when the BSP turned to the Constitutional Court (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1354068812462932">Ganev, 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1354068812462932">2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1354068812462932">Murer, 1999</xref>). After a no-confidence vote passed in 1994, the Movement for Democratic Rights and Freedoms left the coalition and the BSP won a landslide victory with 42.5 percent of the seats. The UDF won a mere 24 percent of the vote and no other party got more than 6.5 percent of seats. A newly formed Bulgarian Business Bloc (BBB) got a mere 4.7 percent of the vote (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr75-1354068812462932">Murer, 1999</xref>) indicating the minimal role played by SMEs in elections.</p>
<p>The BSP suffered a major electoral loss in 1997 and a more moderate faction of the Communist Party – led by Georgi Parvanov – subsequently successfully altered the party’s policy agenda to be more pro-EU and pro-NATO in practice, although a new party manifesto was not officially adopted (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr91-1354068812462932">Spirova, 2008</xref>). In this case, it was not the development of an SME sector, but a major economic crisis, which prompted partial party moderation and the formation of a larger left-leaning coalition spearheaded by the BSP. In 2000, the BSP formed a larger super-coalition of 19 socialist-leaning parties called the ‘Coalition for Bulgaria’; in the 2001 elections the coalition got 17 percent of the vote (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr91-1354068812462932">Spirova, 2008</xref>). The Coalition for Bulgaria continued to have success, winning 31 percent of the vote in 2005 and 17 percent in 2009.</p>
<p>In recent years, we can see some support for the BSP among SME owners and employees.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13-1354068812462932">13</xref>
</sup> As of 2006, survey data revealed that about one-third of SME owners identified with the BSP over other political parties. A large portion of SME employees reported feeling closest to the BSP at levels of 56, 34 and 25 percent in 2006, 2008 and 2010, respectively. In short, in the 2000s it appears that the BSP’s more recent strategy of moderation has garnered support from the SME sector.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14-1354068812462932">14</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>As in Bulgaria in most of the 1990s, in Egypt an ideological party has maintained popular support. Political Islam has represented the marginalized Islamic constituency and the Muslim Brotherhood (MB) has dominated Islamic activism in Egypt since its inception in 1928 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr104-1354068812462932">Wickham, 2002</xref>). Established by Hassan Al-Banna, the MB focused on both political issues and <italic>dawa</italic> (Islamic missionary activity and religious education). Throughout the 1970s and 1980s, political Islam gained greater traction as the <italic>infitah</italic> policy did not benefit a major segment of the Egyptian society; this is the period when the MB became the focal point of frustration with the government and started acting as a ‘de facto’ party (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1354068812462932">Brownlee, 2007</xref>), or a ‘quasi-party organization’ functioning both as a political party and as an Islamic <italic>dawa</italic> organization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr104-1354068812462932">Wickham, 2002</xref>).<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15-1354068812462932">15</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The MB campaigned on a unique platform, declaring Islam to be its panacea for Egypt’s ill-run economy and society (<italic>al-Islam Huwa al-Hall</italic>). The MB saw itself as the unmistakable representative of religion in the political arena and encouraged the voters to cast their votes for Islam. The MB highlighted problems in the economy and the deteriorating conditions of the middle and lower classes to develop a sharp critique of governmental policies, highlighting the failure of liberalization and calling for an Islamic system instead (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1354068812462932">Bayat, 1998</xref>: 157; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1354068812462932">Clark, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr104-1354068812462932">Wickham, 2002</xref>). For example, the former head of the political bureau of the MB stated that: ‘Only a few select people who are taking the ticket of being an NDP member [are benefiting from the economic policies]. They are also taking the membership of the Majlis Al-Sha’ab [People’s Assembly] only to benefit themselves.… These are people who are not responsible, not really feeling the problem of the ordinary Egyptian’ (AbdelHamed Al-Ghazali interview, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1354068812462932">2008</xref>). Indeed, interviews with SME owners revealed that they held critical views on politics and the economy putting them in sync with the MB. Of the SME owners interviewed, about 88 percent expressed unfavourable views on the Egyptian economic liberalization. Virtually all interviewees held positive views on the role that Islam might play in politics, and a significant majority preferred a highly political role for Islam, which confirms our assertion that SME owners’ political preferences underpin the MB’s highly critical and Islamist platform.</p>
<p>The MB participated in the 1984 and 1987 elections as a junior partner of the Wafd and Labor parties. In both elections, the alliance including the MB received the highest share of votes among opposition parties. The regime’s party, the National Democratic Party, has won every election in Egypt since Mubarak decided to hold elections, partly as a response to demands for political liberalization. In turn, Mubarak anticipated increased legitimacy to his rule. In 1987, the MB had 38 out of the 60 seats that the Islamic Alliance – consisting of the MB, Labor Party and the Liberal Party – won in parliamentary elections. After boycotting the 1995 elections, the MB won 17 seats in the 2000 parliamentary elections; as many seats as all other opposition parties combined. Building on its legitimacy as an effective provider of social services (Osama Farid interview, 2008) and its continued criticism of the regime and its policies, the MB won one-fifth of seats in the Egyptian lower house in 2005 elections, making it by far the largest opposition group. In contrast, a pragmatic Muslim democratic party – the Wasat Party – failed to establish itself as a viable party in Egyptian politics thus far (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr71-1354068812462932">Langohr, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr92-1354068812462932">Stacher, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr105-1354068812462932">Wickham, 2004</xref>).</p>
<p>Most recently, the MB established a political party of its own to compete in the first free elections in decades: the Freedom and Justice Party (<italic>Hizb al-Hurriya wa al-Adala</italic>). Early election results show that the Freedom and Justice Party leads polls with 36 percent of the votes cast.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16-1354068812462932">16</xref>
</sup> The new phase of political liberalization in the post-Mubarak era offers a unique opportunity to test two of the most important theories of moderation. According to the inclusion–moderation hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr85-1354068812462932">Schwedler, 2006</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr86-1354068812462932">2011</xref>), the official inclusion of the MB in the political system should induce the group in a moderate (i.e. less ideological and more pragmatic) direction. According to the liberalization hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1354068812462932">Brooks, 2002</xref>), the opening up of the Egyptian political system should allow a change in the MB platform toward a more moderate direction. Yet, early indications about the new party do not show signs of moderation. The party platform is still formed around the nexus of Islamic law and principled opposition to liberal economic policy in favor of a state-led policy, thereby failing to lend support to the theories mentioned above.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17-1354068812462932">17</xref>
</sup> Moreover, the MB endorsed the idea that those members acting independently of the movement’s political decision-making mechanism should be ostracized.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18-1354068812462932">18</xref>
</sup> The policy has been implemented more than once since the summer of 2011. A former leading figure in the group, Abdel Moneim Abul Fotouh, was expelled after he announced presidential run.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19-1354068812462932">19</xref>
</sup> The vehement opposition to what it perceives as encroachments to its monopoly over Islamic representation underscores the exclusive nature of the group. What explains this continued ideological discourse of the party, we argue, is that the underlying state of economic affairs, i.e. crony liberalization, has not changed since the fall of the Mubarak regime despite the fact that political liberalization is forthcoming. Hence, we expect the MB to continue as an ideological party unless we observe a change in the economy that would benefit the core constituency of the MB.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section15-1354068812462932">
<title>Alternate explanations</title>
<p>Looking at the same alternative explanations on moderation (religion, EU membership and repression), Bulgaria and Egypt differ on key factors that could explain the moderation of ideological parties, yet have the same outcome. Diverse religious backgrounds in Bulgaria (Christianity) and Egypt (Islam) predict one successful and one unsuccessful case of moderation, yet both cases have strong ideological parties. On EU membership, Bulgaria faced greater pressure from the EU for democratization, eventually leading to its membership. International pressures on Egypt, however, were less direct (no prospect of EU membership), implying lack of moderation. Finally, along similar lines, the repression hypothesis would suggest that ideological facing repression should moderate and those not facing repression should remain ideological. The Muslim Brotherhood in Egypt faced severe repression for decades, but the group did not show signs of moderation. By contrast, the same repressive pressure is not present for Bulgaria and the ideological party did not moderate. Overall, key variables from the literature fail to explain similar outcomes in Bulgaria and Egypt with respect to the dependent variable, i.e. non-moderation of the ideological party.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-1354068812462932">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>We have used two sets of most different case comparisons in which we trace how the type of liberalization affected the emergence and success of pragmatic versus ideological parties. These are powerful comparisons because they draw on extremely different regional contexts – post-communist Eastern Europe and the Middle East – which have previously been subject to culture-specific and historically contingent explanations. In the two cases of competitive liberalization (Hungary and Turkey), we see the successful emergence of pragmatic parties. In the two cases of crony liberalization (Bulgaria and Egypt), ideological parties did not moderate significantly until recently when in Bulgaria, the BSP engaged in partial moderation of the BSP, as we discussed above.</p>
<p>By pointing out a common mechanism of economic liberalization and SME growth through which Islamist and Communist parties moderate to become pragmatic parties, we underline the similar dynamics that drive moderation. In contrast to the common conception of economic liberalization as a standard process of reform – or some kind of strait jacket that will have the same effect under a wide variety of different circumstances – we underscore politicians’ leverage and discretion in shaping the liberalization reforms. Critically, the way in which liberalization unfolds will determine whether ideologically extreme parties moderate their agendas or not. We think that this research moves the discipline closer to a more general explanation of the connection between economic liberalization and political moderation.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>We would like to thank Dinissa Duvanova, Jennifer Fitzgerald, Jamus Jerome Lim, Amy Liu, Helen Milner, Irfan Nooruddin, Alberto Simpser, and three anonymous reviewers for useful comments and suggestions. All errors remain our own.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn20-1354068812462932">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<title>Notes</title>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1354068812462932">
<label>1.</label>
<p>We thank an anonymous reviewer for emphasizing this point.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1354068812462932">
<label>2.</label>
<p>Communist ideology is ‘anti-system’ in the Sartorian sense because it is opposed to the systems of competitive democracy and the market. We are interested in the post-communist era, but because Communist parties were the ‘system’ prior to 1989, the use of the term ‘anti-system’ may seem counterintuitive to some readers. Thus, we use the terms ideological versus pragmatic to avoid confusion. Our use is consistent with others’ characterizations of Communist successor parties as ideological versus pragmatic. For instance, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr112-1354068812462932">Ziblatt and Biziouras (2002</xref>) distinguish between Communist successor parties that retain an ideological commitment to Marxism and those that became ‘pragmatic social democrats’. In short, we consider the extent to which Communist successor parties have remained close to their historical ideological roots, just as Islamist parties may remain more ideological or not.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1354068812462932">
<label>3.</label>
<p>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr66-1354068812462932">Kornai (1991</xref>) offers one of the most definitive sources on the structure of the Hungarian economy at the time. Unfortunately, we do not have more precise data on the exact number of small businesses during the 1980s. Although Kornai’s conclusion that small businesses were a significant segment of the economy is somewhat qualitative, it is nonetheless authoritative because it builds on his research on the Hungarian economy conducted during the 1950s through the 1980s, including his classic 1980 work, <italic>Economics of Shortage </italic>(Amsterdam and New York: North Holland Publishing Co.).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1354068812462932">
<label>4.</label>
<p>By 2008, the difference in the number of small firms between the two countries decreased significantly due to the more competitive liberalization that occurred in Bulgaria in the 2000s. Bulgaria had 29,970 small and medium firms compared to 31,130 in Hungary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1354068812462932">Eurostat, 2008</xref>). Additionally, the previous difference in the number of small and medium firms cannot be attributed solely to differences in the population size. In 1990, Bulgaria had a population of 8.3 million compared to 10.3 million in Hungary (their populations today are 7.5 and 10 million, respectively; see the World Development Indicators for population data).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-1354068812462932">
<label>5.</label>
<p>Gyula Horn quoted in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1354068812462932">Grzymała-Busse (2002</xref>: 112).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-1354068812462932">
<label>6.</label>
<p>Arato’s assessment is not based on survey data, but rather on a comparison of vote shares received by the different parties along with his evaluation of which social groups were supporting which parties. He argues that strategic decisions by parties on the right were an important part of what allowed the MSzP’s strategy to be successful.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-1354068812462932">
<label>7.</label>
<p>Some skilled workers or entrepreneurs might not fall in the category of small or medium-sized firms, but this category of workers reported in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr67-1354068812462932">Kovács (1996</xref>) would have closely overlapped with the SME sector based on the categories into which respondents could place themselves. Respondents were asked to place themselves in one of the following groups: (1) students and women taking care of children, (2) unskilled workers and peasants, (3) skilled workers and entrepreneurs, (4) white collar, (5) leading white collar (i.e. management), (6) unemployed, and (7) pensioners. If anything, just looking skilled workers and entrepreneurs might understate support for the MSzP among those in the SME sector as unskilled workers, white collar and management likely included some SMEs.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-1354068812462932">
<label>8.</label>
<p>Survey data are taken from the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1354068812462932">European Social Survey (2002</xref>, 2006, 2008 and 2010). As recommended by the ESS for instances in which percentages are being compared across countries (here, Hungary and Bulgaria), the percentages reported here utilize the design weights which account for the fact that in all of the countries surveyed individuals over the age of 15 do not always have an equal likelihood of being selected.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-1354068812462932">
<label>9.</label>
<p>In the 2010 elections, support for the MSzP dropped amidst scandals involving the party’s leadership, and a far right party called Jobbik won unprecedented support with over 16 percent of the vote (compared to only 2.2 percent of the vote in 2006), making it the third largest party in the parliament. The 2010 election thus signifies a major shift in Hungarian politics, breaking with past trends. See Dani Bilefsky, ‘Hungarian Rightists, Both Center and Far, Advance’ (<italic>New York Times</italic>, 12 April 2010) and Pablo Gorondi, ‘Center-right Fidesz Wins Big in Hungarian Elections’ (<italic>Associated Press Online</italic>, 11 April 2010).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-1354068812462932">
<label>10.</label>
<p>Election results are available from the Hungarian National Election office at: http://www.valasztas.hu/en/ovi/index.html (accessed 4 December 2011).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-1354068812462932">
<label>11.</label>
<p>Among others, see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55-1354068812462932">Huntington (1993</xref>), <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1354068812462932">Bruce (2004</xref>) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr107-1354068812462932">Woodberry and Shah (2004</xref>) for an extensive discussion.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-1354068812462932">
<label>12.</label>
<p>We thank two anonymous reviewers for highlighting this point.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn13-1354068812462932">
<label>13.</label>
<p>Survey data are from the European Social Survey. Unfortunately, we do not have survey evidence of Bulgarian SMEs in the 1990s, but their numbers were so small that their political influence was negligible.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn14-1354068812462932">
<label>14.</label>
<p>In the other three cases presented here, it is clear that competitive liberalization preceded party moderation. In the Bulgarian case before 1997, we see crony liberalization and no party moderation. After 1997, the BSP was moderating its agenda concurrent with a more competitive liberalization policy being pursued by the UDF government in power.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn15-1354068812462932">
<label>15.</label>
<p>In general, Islamist parties serve dual functions throughout the Muslim world. On the one hand, they function as Islamic associations that serve a specific Muslim community, engaging in religious education, Islamic missionary activities. On the other hand, they function as political parties speaking on behalf of the religion and the whole Muslim community in their respective country. This duality, in turn, underlies a certain level of confusion about Islamist parties.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn16-1354068812462932">
<label>16.</label>
<p>‘Islamists Sweep Early Results in Egypt Vote’, <italic>AlJazeera</italic>, 4 December 2011. (http://www.aljazeera.com/news/middleeast/2011/12/201112320622436522.html)</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn17-1354068812462932">
<label>17.</label>
<p>The party programme can be accessed at: http://www.hurryh.com (accessed 17 November 2011).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn18-1354068812462932">
<label>18.</label>
<p>‘Egypt’s Brotherhood to Fire Members Joining Other Parties’, <italic>Reuters</italic>, 24 June 2011 (available at: http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/06/24/us-egypt-muslim-brotherhood-idUSTRE75N4OK20110624)</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn19-1354068812462932">
<label>19.</label>
<p>‘Egypt’s Muslim Brotherhood Expels Five Members’, <italic>Reuters Africa</italic>, 5 July 2011 (http://af.reuters.com/article/topNews/idAFJOE76405Z20110705); ‘Egypt’s Muslim Brotherhood Expels Presidential Hopeful’, <italic>Al Arabiya</italic>, 22 June 2011.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Abdellatif</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ghoneim</surname>
<given-names>AF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Competition, competition policy and economic efficiency in Egypt</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Sekkat</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Competition and Efficiency in the Arab World</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adly</surname>
<given-names>AI</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Politically-embedded cronyism: The case of post-liberalization Egypt</article-title>. <source>Business and Politics</source> <volume>11</volume>(<issue>4</issue>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Al-Ghazali</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Personal Interview. Muslim Brotherhood, and professor, Cairo University; Cairo</article-title>, <comment>11 November 2008</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Arato</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Party strategies and the Hungarian socialists’ road to power</article-title>. <source>Constellations</source> <volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Atacan</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Explaining religious politics at the crossroad: AKP-SP</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Carkoglu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rubin</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Religion Politics in Turkey</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bateman</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Neo-liberalism, SME development, and the role of business support in the transition economies and Central and Eastern Europe</article-title>. <source>Small Business Economics</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>298</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bayat</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Revolution without movement, movement without revolution: Comparing Islamic activism in Iran and Egypt</article-title>. <source>Comparative Studies in Society and History</source> <volume>40</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>136</fpage>–<lpage>169</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bayat</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Islamism and empire: The incongruous nature of Islamist anti-imperialism</article-title>. <source>Socialist Register</source> <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>38</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Beinin</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Political Islam and the new global economy: The political economy of an Egyptian social movement</article-title>. <source>New Centennial Review</source> <volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>111</fpage>–<lpage>139</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Blaydes</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Elections and Distributive Politics in Mubarak’s Egypt</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bozóki</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Hungary’s road to systemic change: The opposition roundtable</article-title>. <source>East European Politics and Societies</source> <volume>7</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>276</fpage>–<lpage>308</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brooks</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Liberalization and militancy in the Arab World</article-title>. <source>Orbis</source> <volume>46</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>611</fpage>–<lpage>621</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1966</year>) <source>The New Eastern Europe: The Khrushchev Era and After</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Praeger</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1988</year>) <source>Eastern Europe and Communist Rule</source>. <publisher-loc>Durham, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brownlee</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Authoritarianism in an Age of Democracy</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bruce</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Did Protestantism create democracy?</article-title> <source>Democratization</source> <volume>4</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bugra</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Political Islam in Turkey in historical context: Strengths and weaknesses</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Balkan</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Savran</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Politics of Permanent Crisis: Class, Ideology and State in Turkey</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nova Science Publishersc</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bunce</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The political economy of postsocialism</article-title>. <source>Slavic, East European, and Eurasian Studies</source>, <volume>58</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>756</fpage>–<lpage>793</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bunce</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Rethinking recent democratization: Lessons from the post-communist experience</article-title>. <source>World Politics</source> <volume>55</volume> <issue>(Jan.)</issue>: <fpage>167</fpage>–<lpage>192</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Capoccia</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Anti-system parties: A conceptual reassessment</article-title>. <source>Journal of Theoretical Politics</source> <volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>35</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cecen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dogruel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dogruel</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Economic growth and structural change in Turkey 1960–88</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Middle East Studies</source> <volume>26</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cizre</surname>
<given-names>Ü</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed.) (<year>2009</year>) <source>Secular and Islamic Politics in Turkey: The Making of the Justice and Development Party</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Clark</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Social movement theory and patron-clientelism: Islamic social institutions and the middle class in Egypt, Jordan, and Yemen</article-title>. <source>Comparative Political Studies</source> <volume>37</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>941</fpage>–<lpage>968</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cooper</surname>
<given-names>MN</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>) <source>The Transformation of Egypt</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Croom Helm</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Creed</surname>
<given-names>GW</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>The politics of agriculture: Identity and socialist sentiment in Bulgaria</article-title>. <source>Slavic Review</source> <volume>54</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>843</fpage>–<lpage>868</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Curry</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barth Urban</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>The Left Transformed in Post-Communist Societies</source>. <publisher-loc>Lanham, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dagi</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Transformation of Islamic political identity in Turkey: Rethinking the West and Westernization</article-title>. <source>Turkish Studies</source> <volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Drabek</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Payne</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The impact of transparency on foreign direct investment</article-title>. <source>Journal of Economic Integration</source> <volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>777</fpage>–<lpage>810</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Duvanova</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Bureaucratic corruption and collective action: Business associations in the postcommunist transition</article-title>. <source>Comparative Politics</source> <volume>39</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>441</fpage>–<lpage>461</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ekiert</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>The State against Society: Political Crises and their Aftermath in East Central Europe</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>El-Ghobashy</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The metamorphosis of the Egyptian Muslim brothers</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Middle East Studies</source> <volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>373</fpage>–<lpage>395</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Esen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kemalettin Conkar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>Orta Anadolu (Konya, Kayseri, Sivas ve Tokat) Girişimcilerinin Sosyo-Ekonomik Özellikleri, İşletmecilik Anlayişlari ve Beklentileri Araştirmasi</source>. <publisher-loc>Konya</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Konya Ticaret Odası</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Esposito</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Voll</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Islam and Democracy</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">European Social Survey</collab> (<year>2002–2010</year>) <article-title>Centre for Comparative Studies, City University</article-title>, <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.europeansocialsurvey.org">www.europeansocialsurvey.org</ext-link> <comment>(accessed 3 December 2011)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">Eurostat</collab> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Special feature on SMEs</article-title>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://epp.eurostat.ec.europa.eu/portal/page/portal/european_business/special_sbs_topics/small_medium_sized_enterprises_SMEs">http://epp.eurostat.ec.europa.eu/portal/page/portal/european_business/special_sbs_topics/small_medium_sized_enterprises_SMEs</ext-link> <comment>(accessed 3 December 2011)</comment>, pp. <fpage>10</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Whitefield</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Economic ideology and political success: Communist-successor parties in the Czech Republic, Slovakia, and Hungary compared</article-title>. <source>Party Politics</source> <volume>1</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>565</fpage>–<lpage>578</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Farah</surname>
<given-names>NR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Egypt’s Political Economy: Power Relations in Development</source>. <publisher-loc>Cairo</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American University in Cairo Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fehér</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Arato</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>1991</year>) <source>Crisis and Reform in Eastern Europe</source>. <publisher-loc>New Brunswick, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transaction Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fish</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>The determinants of economic reform in the post-communist world</article-title>. <source>East European Politics and Societies</source> <volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>31</fpage>–<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Frye</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The perils of polarization: Economic performance in the postcommunist world</article-title>. <source>World Politics</source> <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>308</fpage>–<lpage>337</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Frye</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <source>Building States and Markets after Communism: The Perils of Polarized Democracy</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ganev</surname>
<given-names>VI</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The Dorian Gray effect: Winners as state breakers in post-communism</article-title>. <source>Communist and Post-Communist Studies</source> <volume>34</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>125</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ganev</surname>
<given-names>VI</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Ballots, bribes, and state building in Bulgaria</article-title>. <source>Journal of Democracy</source> <volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>75</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ganev</surname>
<given-names>VI</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Preying on the State: The Transformation of Bulgaria After1989</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Goldman</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Revolution and Change in Central and Eastern Europe: Political, Economic, and Social Challenges</source>. <publisher-loc>Armonk, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>M. E. Sharpe</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grzymała-Busse</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Redeeming the Communist Past: The Regeneration of Communist Parties in East Central Europe</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gülalp</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Globalization and political Islam: The social bases of Turkey’s Welfare Party</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Middle East Studies</source> <volume>33</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>433</fpage>–<lpage>448</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gümüşçü</surname>
<given-names>Ş</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Class, status, and party: The changing face of political Islam in Turkey and Egypt</article-title>. <source>Comparative Political Studies</source> <volume>43</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>835</fpage>–<lpage>861</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hansen</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <source>The Political Economy of Poverty, Equity, and Growth: Egypt and Turkey</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr50-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hare</surname>
<given-names>PG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Radice</surname>
<given-names>HK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Swain</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>1981</year>) <source>Hungary. A Decade of Economic Reform</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Allen and Unwin</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr51-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hashemi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Islam, Secularism, and Liberal Democracy: Toward a Democratic Theory for Muslim Societies</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr52-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hellman</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Winners take all: The politics of partial reform in post-communist transitions</article-title>. <source>World Politics</source> <volume>50</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>203</fpage>–<lpage>234</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr53-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Henry</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Springborg</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <source>Globalization and the Politics of Development in the Middle East</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr54-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab collab-type="author">Hungarian Socialist Party Manifesto</collab> (<year>1989</year>) <source>World Affairs</source> <volume>151</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>224</fpage>–<lpage>225</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr55-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Huntington</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <source>The Third Wave: Democratization in the Late Twentieth Century</source>. <publisher-loc>Norman, OK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Oklahoma Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr56-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Huntington</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>The Clash of Civilizations and the Remaking of the New World Order</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Simon &amp; Schuster</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr57-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ibrahim</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Egypt’s landed bourgeoisie</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Oncu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Keyder</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ibrahim</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Developmentalism and Beyond</source>. <publisher-loc>Cairo</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American University in Cairo Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr58-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ibrahim</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A tale of two Egypts: Contrasting state-reported macro-trends with micro-voices of the poor</article-title>. <source>Third World Quarterly</source> <volume>32</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>1347</fpage>–<lpage>1368</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr59-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ishiyama</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Communist parties in transition: Structures, leaders, and process of democratization in Eastern Europe</article-title>. <source>Comparative Politics</source> <volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>147</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr60-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ishiyama</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bozóki</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2002</year>) <source>The Communist Successor Parties of Central and Eastern Europe</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>M. E. Sharpe</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr61-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kalyvas</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>The Rise of Christian Democracy in Europe</source>. <publisher-loc>Ithaca, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr62-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Karasimeonov</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Bulgaria's new party system</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Pridham</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lewis</surname>
<given-names>PG</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Stabilising Fragile Democracies: Comparing New Party Systems in Southern and Eastern Europe</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr63-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Keefer</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Knack</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Polarization, politics and property rights: Links between inequality and growth</article-title>. <source>Public Choice</source> <volume>111</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>154</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr64-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kitschelt</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Constraints and opportunities in the strategic conduct of post-communist successor parties</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Ishiyama</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bozóki</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Communist Successor Parties of Central and Eastern Europe</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>M. E. Sharpe</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>14</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr65-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kitschelt</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mansfeldova</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Markowski</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Toka</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <source>Post-Communist Party Systems: Competition, Representation, and Inter-Party Cooperation</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr66-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kornai</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>The Hungarian reform process: Visions, hopes, and reality</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Fehér</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Arato</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Crisis and Reform in Eastern Europe</source>. <publisher-loc>New Brunswick</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Transaction Publishers</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>27</fpage>–<lpage>98</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr67-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kovács</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Did the losers really win? An analysis of the electoral behavior in Hungary in 1994</article-title>. <source>Social Research</source> <volume>63</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>511</fpage>–<lpage>530</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr68-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kubicek</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>International norms, the European Union, and democratization: Tentative Theory and Evidence</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Kubicek</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>The European Union and Democratization</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr69-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kubicek</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The European Union and grassroots democratization in Turkey</article-title>. <source>Turkish Studies</source> <volume>6</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>361</fpage>–<lpage>377</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr70-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kuran</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Islamic economics and the Islamic subeconomy</article-title>. <source>Journal of Economic Perspectives</source> <volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>173</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr71-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Langohr</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Of Islamists and ballot boxes: Rethinking the relationship between Islamisms and electoral politics</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Middle East Studies</source> <volume>33</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>591</fpage>–<lpage>610</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr72-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lewis</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>What went wrong?</article-title> <source>Atlantic Monthly</source> (<issue>January</issue>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr73-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mainwaring</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Scully</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <source>Christian Democracy in Latin America: Electoral Competition and Regime Conflicts</source>. <publisher-loc>Stanford, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr74-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Moustafa</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>The Struggle for Constitutional Power: Law, Politics, and Economic Development in Egypt</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr75-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Murer</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Challenging expectations: A comparative study of the communist successor parties of Hungary, Bulgaria, and Romania</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Ishiyama</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed.) <source>Communist Successor Parties in Post-Communist Politics</source>. <publisher-loc>Commack, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nova Science Publishers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr76-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nasr</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The rise of Muslim democracy</article-title>. <source>Journal of Democracy</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>13</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr77-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nasr</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>The Rise of Islamic Capitalism: Why the New Middle Class Is the Key to Defeating Extremism</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Free Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr78-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Onis</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Domestic politics, international norms and challenges to the state: Turkey–EU relations in the post-Helsinki era</article-title>. <source>Turkish Studies</source> <volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr79-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Özel</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>After Tsunami</article-title>. <source>Journal of Democracy</source> <volume>14</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>80</fpage>–<lpage>94</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr80-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Petrova</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Bulgaria</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Pollack</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wielgohs</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Dissent and Opposition in Communist Eastern Europe: Origins of Civil Society and Democratic Transition</source>. <publisher-loc>Aldershot</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr81-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Racz</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>The socialist left opposition in post-communist Hungary</article-title>. <source>Europe–Asia Studies</source> <volume>45</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>647</fpage>–<lpage>670</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr82-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Recantini</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ryterman</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <source>Disorganization or Self-Organization?</source> <publisher-loc>World Bank</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr83-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rodrik</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Premature liberalization, incomplete stabilization: The Ozal decade in Turkey</article-title>. <source>CEPR Discussion Papers</source> <volume>402</volume>.
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr84-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sartori</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1976</year>) <source>Parties and Party Systems</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr85-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schwedler</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <source>Faith in Moderation: Islamist Parties in Jordan and Yemen</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr86-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schwedler</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Can Islamists become moderates? Rethinking the inclusion-moderation hypothesis</article-title>. <source>World Politics</source> <volume>63</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>347</fpage>–<lpage>376</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr87-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>AKP Milli Görüşçü mü? Parti Programlarında Milli Görüş</source>. <publisher-loc>Istanbul</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Net</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr88-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Senses</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Turkey’s stabilization and structural adjustment program in retrospect and prospect</article-title>. <source>Developing Economies</source> <volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>210</fpage>–<lpage>234</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr89-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Snowden</surname>
<given-names>PN</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Financial reform in Turkey Since 1980: Liberalization without stabilization</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Togan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Balasubramanyam</surname>
<given-names>VN</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Economy of Turkey Since Liberalization</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>St. Martin’s Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr90-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Somer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Moderate Islam and secularist opposition in Turkey: Implications for the world, Muslims and Secular Democracy</article-title>. <source>Third World Quarterly</source> <volume>28</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>1271</fpage>–<lpage>1289</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr91-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Spirova</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The Bulgarian Socialist Party: The long road to Europe</article-title>. <source>Communist and Post-Communist Studies</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>481</fpage>–<lpage>495</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr92-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stacher</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Post-Islamist rumblings in Egypt: The emergence of the Wasat Party</article-title>. <source>Middle East Journal</source> <volume>56</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>415</fpage>–<lpage>432</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr93-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stepan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Robertson</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>An ‘Arab’ more than ‘Muslim’ electoral gap</article-title>. <source>Journal of Democracy</source> <volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>30</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr94-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Steunenberg</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Petek</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rüth</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Between reason and emotion: Popular discourses on Turkey's membership of the EU</article-title>. <source>South European Society and Politics</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>449</fpage>–<lpage>468</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr95-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Stevens</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>The practical record and prospects of privatization programmes in the Arab world</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Niblock</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Murphy</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Economic and Political Liberalization in the Middle East</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr96-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Taşkin</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Erinç Yeldan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Export expansion, capital accumulation and distribution in Turkish manufacturing, 1980–9</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Togan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Balasubramanyam</surname>
<given-names>VN</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Economy of Turkey Since Liberalization</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>St. Martin’s Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr97-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tesche</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tohamy</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>A note on economic liberalization and privatization in Hungary and Egypt</article-title>. <source>Comparative Economic Studies</source> <volume>36</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>51</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr98-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tekeli</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gokceli</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>) <source>1973 ve 1975 Secimlerinde Secim Cografyasi Uzerine Bir Deneme</source>. <publisher-loc>Istanbul</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Milliyet Publishing</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr99-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tőkés</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Hungary’s Negotiated Revolution: Economic Reform, Social Change, and Political Succession</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr100-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ugur</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Open-ended membership prospect and commitment credibility: Explaining the deadlock in EU–Turkey accession negotiations</article-title>. <source>Journal of Common Market Studies</source> <volume>48</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>967</fpage>–<lpage>991</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr101-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vachudova</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The leverage of international institutions on democratizing states: Eastern Europe and the European Union</article-title>. <publisher-loc>San Domenico, Italy</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>EUI Working Papers</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr102-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wallerstein</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>The collapse of liberalism</article-title>. <source>Socialist Register</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>96</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr103-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Waterbury</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Export-led growth and the center–right coalition in Turkey</article-title>. <source>Comparative Politics</source> <volume>24</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>145</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr104-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wickham</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>Mobilizing Islam: Religion, Activism, and Political Change in Egypt</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr105-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wickham</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The path to moderation: Strategy and learning in the formation of Egypt’s Wasat Party</article-title>. <source>Comparative Politics</source> <volume>36</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>205</fpage>–<lpage>228</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr106-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Willis</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Morocco’s Islamists and the legislative elections of 2002: The strange case of the party that did not want to win</article-title>. <source>Mediterranean Politics</source> <volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>53</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr107-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Woodberry</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shah</surname>
<given-names>TS</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The pioneering protestants</article-title>. <source>Journal of Democracy</source> <volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr108-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yakis</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Ak Parti’nin Kimligi [The Identity of the JDP.]</article-title> <comment>Unpublished Document</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr109-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yakis</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Personal Interview. Former JDP parliamentarian</article-title>. <comment>Ankara, 29 August</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr110-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yavuz</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <source>Secularism and Muslim Democracy in Turkey</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr111-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zakaria</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Islam, democracy, and constitutional liberalism</article-title>. <source>Political Science Quarterly</source> <volume>119</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr112-1354068812462932">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ziblatt</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Biziouras</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Doomed to be radicals? Organization, ideology, and the communist successor parties in East Central Europe</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Bozóki</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ishiyama</surname>
<given-names>JT</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>The Communist Successor Parties of Central and Eastern Europe</source>. <publisher-loc>Armonk, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>M. E. Sharpe</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>