<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SIR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsir</journal-id>
<journal-title>Studies in Religion/Sciences Religieuses</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0008-4298</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2042-0587</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0008429812452084o</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0008429812452084o</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Reviews Of Books / Comptes Rendus</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reviews Of Books / Comptes Rendus: Emil L. Fackenheim: Philosopher, Theologian, Jew Sharon Portnoff, J.A. Diamond and M.D. Yaffe, eds Leiden: Brill NV, 2008. xv + 339 pp.</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ziegler</surname>
<given-names>Philip G.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0008429812452084o"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0008429812452084o">University of Aberdeen</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>41</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>510</fpage>
<lpage>512</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Portnoff</surname>
<given-names>Sharon</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Diamond</surname>
<given-names>J.A.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yaffe</surname>
<given-names>M.D.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, eds <publisher-loc>Leiden</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brill NV</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>. xv + <page-count count="339"/> pp.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) / Le(s) auteur(s), 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">The Canadian Corporation for Studies in Religion</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This volume collects more than a dozen substantial essays on the work of the prominent Jewish thinker and long time Professor of Philosophy at the University of Toronto, Emil Fackenheim, who passed away in 2003. A brief but moving foreword by Elie Wiesel sets the stage for what follows. The editors have organised the papers into three groupings. The first, ‘Fackenheim Then and Now,’ explores aspects of the development of Fackenheim’s thought from his first scholarly work on mediaeval philosophy in the 1950s, through his decades of wrestling with the significance of German idealism and on to the sustained confrontation with the intellectual, human and Jewish significance of the Holocaust which preoccupied the final three decades of his life. The essays in the second part of the volume concentrate on the more specifically philosophical aspects of Fackenheim’s work and explore his relationship to key figures in the tradition, including Spinoza, Hegel, Heidegger and Leo Strauss. The volume concludes with a set of studies into the Jewish-religious dimension of Fackenheim’s corpus, considering his creative recourse to middrashic, kabbalahistic and other elements of the Jewish theological tradition. The distinction between the philosophical and the theological which orders the second and third sections is rightly a fluid one, reflecting thereby a hallmark of Fackenheim’s own work, which sought to discern the possibilities arising precisely at the point of encounter with the truth which takes place at the intersection of modern philosophy, Jewish life and thought, and the actualities of contemporary history. The overall aim of the book, ‘to provide a forum through which to introduce Fackenheim’s thought to a broader audience’ (5), is well served by the scope and depth of the essays gathered here, a good many of which were written by former students of Fackenheim for whom their teacher’s legacy clearly provides a continuing provocation.</p>
<p>Several important themes can be traced across the whole of the volume. Pre-eminent perhaps among these is the question of Fackenheim’s wrestling with historicism in philosophy. A number of concerns are at stake here—Fackenheim’s reading of Maimonides and his refusal to repristinate the tradition of perennial philosophy; his analysis and critique of Heidegger’s thought, his relationship to Hegel’s legacy and its modification in view of the actualities of 20th-century history, whose rationality is unclear to say the least; his understanding of both revelation and radical evil and the distinctive ‘existential’ shape of the thought ingredient therein; as well as the nature of philosophy’s exposure to historical occurrence, a question whose point is sharpened almost unbearably in relation to the Holocaust. A number of contributors explore facets of this theme, and the complexities and tensions of Fackenheim’s work in this vein are set forth helpfully and with insight. Sharon Portnoff’s essay on Fackenheim’s ‘Hegelian Return to Contingency’ offers an extended account of this theme.</p>
<p>A second overarching theme is the ordered relation of life and thought. Fackenheim is well known for his view that thought ‘follows’ life—as Minerva’s owl takes flight at the close of the day—and that, in particular, any possibility of thought resisting utter disruption in confrontation with the unique nihil of the Holocaust lies with the actuality of lived resistance in the midst of the event itself. This claim is central to the argument of his influential work, <italic>To Mend the World</italic> (1982). Some of the most interesting essays in this volume demonstrate that Fackenheim’s thinking about this central issue remained unsettled to the end—Benjamin Pollock’s essay, ‘Thought Going to School with Life,’ stands out as a provocative and detailed re-examination of this theme, taking its cue from an enigmatic note found in Fackenheim’s papers which announced that, on this crucial matter: ‘I have changed my mind’ (57).</p>
<p>A third overarching motif—and one very closely related to the two just discussed—is Fackenheim’s struggle to see that the form of thought, both theological and philosophical, should comport properly with its subject matter. There is in Fackenheim a deep appreciation of Hegel’s insistence upon the mutual intertwining of rationality and actuality. But when actuality is taken to include within it the particularities of Jewish existence, the radical evil of the Holocaust, human freedom, the reality of genuine transcendence as well as the commanding voice of the God of Abraham, Isaac and Jacob, then the shape of rationality itself becomes a matter of genuine contest and revision. Fackenheim’s sustained wrestling with the challenges of philosophical historicism and existentialism is an essential part of this contest; so too is his unflinching reflection upon the significance of the Shoah for both philosophy (‘Can we still think?’) and Jewish existence (‘Can we still be Jews?’). Further, as writers in the final section make clear, Fackenheim’s eventual rediscovery of the discursive form of Midrash as the medium for authentically Jewish thought is itself an attempt to inhabit a mode of thinking that keeps faith with reality. As one essayist observes, for Fackenheim ‘the tradition from which the Jew begins and to which he/she returns, following his/her encounter with immediacy after reflection, is the tradition of Midrash which takes the form of a stubborn persistence of Jewishness’ and which ‘confirms God’s presence in history, but it does so by both confirming and suffering the contradictions inherent in that presence’ (27).</p>
<p>We are reminded at the outset of something which the essays, taken as a whole, aptly demonstrate: the mobility and expansiveness of Fackenheim’s thought, its exposure to existence and its patience upon paradox make for a ‘profoundly unfinished intellectual oeuvre’ (6). This is no criticism. It is rather a testimony to the seriousness, stature and humility of a thinker who has much still to teach us about what is demanded of thoughtful religion and pious thought in our times.</p>
</body>
</article>