<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PHG</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spphg</journal-id>
<journal-title>Progress in Human Geography</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0309-1325</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1477-0288</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0309132513475754c</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0309132513475754c</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book review symposium</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Editors’ response 2</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Daniels</surname>
<given-names>Stephen</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff1-0309132513475754c"><italic>University of Nottingham, UK</italic></aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Delyser</surname>
<given-names>Dydia</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff2-0309132513475754c"><italic>Louisiana State University, USA</italic></aff>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Entrikin</surname>
<given-names>J. Nicholas</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff3-0309132513475754c"><italic>University of California, Los Angeles, USA</italic></aff>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>37</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>315</fpage>
<lpage>317</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>We welcome these commentaries, for they extend the conversation between geography and the humanities to environmental science and environmental history, respectively. While both authors present an affirmative view of the humanities, it is a view somewhat holistic, even utopian; one not shared by most of the contributors to our volume <italic>Envisioning Landscapes, Making Worlds</italic>. At the same time, the commentaries express a difference between UK and US perspectives that the book, as a gathered community of scholars, was trying to close.</p>
<p>The main question of Mike Hulme’s commentary – ‘What does it mean to be human in a changing world?’ – is central to our volume, as are his themes of imagination, values and narrative. It is heartening to hear how humanities scholarship in geography can impact powerfully on wider currents of learning about the physical environment and offer, as geography of all subjects is positioned to do, a richer, integrative, more ecumenical vision of the world. Nevertheless, few of the contributors would endorse Hulme’s view of meaning as a matter of historical decline and cultural recovery – that ‘we know how the world works but we no longer know what it means’. This is deliberate overstatement, to be sure, but it seems to endorse a narrow and disenchanting narrative of human knowledge, one of the progressive success of science, and the displacement of the symbolic by the functional, positioning a renewed humanist subjectivity as redemptive force for scientific objectivity. The book expressly questions such a distinction, not only by including a good number of empirical case studies – some of scientific and technological practice itself – but also by addressing examples of meaning, imagination and narrative as matters subject to debate and dispute, of culture as a contested terrain as well as common ground. Some contributors are sympathetic to Hulme’s view of the healing, holistic, restorative task of the humanities, but a reading of David Lowenthal’s chapter on ‘Restoration: Synoptic Reflections’ would reveal the historical complexities of restoration as a cultural movement, its ironies and ambiguities – even, as in river restoration, its complicity with modern, progressive technologies.</p>
<p>Even with divergence of view among the authors represented in our volume, we wonder whether Anglophone human geographers are, as Hulme suggests, ‘internally torn and confused’, seeking out cross-disciplinary work as ‘restorative therapy’. Most contributors are sceptical of integrative, unitary views of culture or humanity, seeking more, not less, difference and distinction, and recognizing fragmentation and paradox as central characteristics of the places they study. Indeed, some of the very qualities that Hulme valorizes elsewhere in his commentary – ambiguity, locality, positionality – are difficult to reconcile with a holistic view of the humanities. Arguably, subjectivity itself can be fragmenting. So, like many scholars now, Hulme considers his own life-story as an example of subjective positionality and movement: ‘establishing what I know about the world and … [seeking] to assimilate this knowledge in my own life-story’. This autobiographical impulse is appealing but scarcely evident in our collection where the traditional humanities slogan ‘know thyself’, with which Denis Cosgrove finishes his commentary, is understood not as a personal matter, but as one of critical reflection and scholarly scepticism about one’s place in the world. If there is a strain of cultural recovery in the book, it is rediscovering the power of the humanities tradition within a self-effacing geographical tradition, in practices as varied as mapping and regional inquiry.</p>
<p>In contrast to the confidence of Mike Hulme in the potential effect of humanities scholarship on scientific knowledge more widely, Robert Wilson writes from a more beleaguered vantage point marked by the veritable ‘crisis of the humanities’, and one which seems particularly serious for geography. New developments in UK human geography, for better or worse, have recently been dominated by kinds of cultural geography, and other fields which have undergone a cultural turn. While not all of this work may be said to be humanities connected (indeed it is often social-scientific rather than humanities based; ‘social-cultural’ not ‘cultural-historical’), the situation certainly seems to be different to one Wilson finds: ‘In the United States it is common for departments to have no geographer doing this kind of [humanities] work whatsoever’. We might add that human geography in the UK has been remarkably successful in initiating projects with a new Arts and Humanities Research Council, with which Hulme has been supportively engaged. This perhaps explains the defensive tone of Wilson’s commentary in contrast to the confidence of Hulme’s.</p>
<p>Wilson finds our collection ‘fragmented’, as if this is a sign of wider ‘splintering’, break-up, even a fall from grace from a mythical sounding past era of ‘common, good, collective institutions and solidarity’. If this is a familiar, plaintive trope of cultural criticism, the situation Wilson describes does seem serious, particularly the decline of the historical in human geography. There are significant differences between chapters in <italic>Envisioning Worlds </italic>– of period and place, position and perspective – inevitably so with such a span of generations and (sub)disciplinary affiliation, but what is the evidence of fragmentation? We would like to think that differences are a matter of unity in diversity, with four clear themes organizing the collection, not shards of some broken whole. The chapters are short because we asked contributors to focus on a single instance, such as a particular location, event, artwork, or a disarmingly simple question (‘do places have edges’?) to open up much wider issues and questions. What does link all chapters is that traditional hallmark of the humanities – history – whether of context in the past or perspective on the present. So history here is a matter of sensibility, rather than subfield – a historicized human geography rather than historical geography – and it mixes with many other newer variants of humanities scholarship from performance to memory study. This perhaps answers Wilson’s concern that we do not dwell much on the field of humanistic geography, notably the influence of Ley and Samuels’ (1978) collection. Humanistic geography, at that time, as Cosgrove points out in his Prologue, had few effective connections with the humanities, it was largely social-science driven, and largely ahistorical, a product of behavioural and phenomenological traditions; only later did subsequent collections like <italic>Textures of Place </italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0309132513475754c">Adams et al., 2001</xref>) offer more historical sensibility.</p>
<p>In a university world under the pressures of public engagement and social and economic impact, most chapters in our volume are, as Wilson observes, ‘written by academics mostly for other academics’. This is indeed the main forum of the conversation between geography and the humanities the book was trying to create. There is indeed a place for the more public conversation Wilson cites by environmental historians, as in a recent volume <italic>The Public Value of the Humanities</italic>, edited by literary historian Jonathan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0309132513475754c">Bate (2011</xref>), in which geographers and geographical themes are strongly represented. Writing accessibly and appealingly is clearly a virtue and our volume includes some of the finest writers in geography. All chapters are written in an essay form, which of all genres is arguably the most accommodating to a wide readership, with the capacity, within a small compass, to communicate learning and scholarship. Even so, with no apologies, some chapters take on recondite topics using technical language. This is significant, for the humanities’ liberal arts heritage is more than a matter of public dissemination; it is at the heart of specialist research questions and ways of answering them, including, as Hulme recognizes, environmental issues that are inherently interdisciplinary, but which themselves may demand richly engaged specialized research to answer. It was as part of precisely such an effort to draw scholars of different backgrounds into conversation explicitly through their grounding in humanities approaches that we sought to create this volume. Perhaps the two commentaries on the volume, offered by scholars in different subdisciplines from ourselves, will indeed help to invigorate these discussions.</p>
<sig-block>
<sig>Stephen Daniels</sig>
<sig>
<italic>University of Nottingham, UK</italic>
</sig>
<sig>Dydia Delyser</sig>
<sig>
<italic>Louisiana State University, USA</italic>
</sig>
<sig>J. Nicholas Entrikin</sig>
<sig>
<italic>University of California, Los Angeles, USA</italic>
</sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0309132513475754c">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adams</surname>
<given-names>PC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hoelscher</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Till</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2001</year>) <source>Textures of Place: Exploring Humanist Geographies</source>. <publisher-loc>Minneapolis, MN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0309132513475754c">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bate</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (ed.) (<year>2011</year>) <source>The Public Value of the Humanities</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bloomsbury Academic</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0309132513475754c">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ley</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Samuels</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>1978</year>) <source>Humanistic Geography: Prospects and Problems</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Taylor and Francis</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>