<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IDV</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spidv</journal-id>
<journal-title>Information Development</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0266-6669</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1741-6469</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0266666912446497</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0266666912446497</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A new perspective on the ICT Development Index</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dobrota</surname>
<given-names>Marina</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0266666912446497"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Jeremic</surname>
<given-names>Veljko</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0266666912446497"/>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0266666912446497"/>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Markovic</surname>
<given-names>Aleksandar</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff1-0266666912446497">University of Belgrade</aff>
</contrib>
<bio>
<title>About the authors</title>
<p>
<bold>Marina Dobrota</bold> works as a Teaching Assistant at the Faculty of Organizational Sciences, University of Belgrade, Serbia, where she got her BSc and MSc degrees. Currently, she is a PhD student. Her major interests are in applied statistics, ICT development strategy, data mining in medicine and biostatistics. Contact: University of Belgrade, Faculty of Organizational Sciences, Department of Statistics, Jove Ilica 154, 11000 Belgrade, Serbia. Phone: +381 11 3950822. Fax: +381 11 2461221. Email: <email>dobrotam@fon.rs</email>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Veljko Jeremic</bold> works as a Teaching Assistant at the Faculty of Organizational Sciences, University of Belgrade, Serbia, where he got his BSc and MSc degrees. He is in the process of submitting PhD dissertation. His major interests are applied statistics, computational statistics, business decision making and simulation methods. Contact: University of Belgrade, Faculty of Organizational Sciences, Department of Statistics, Jove Ilica 154, 11000 Belgrade, Serbia. Phone: +381 11 3950822. Fax: +381 11 2461221. Email: <email>jeremicv@fon.rs</email>
</p>
<p>
<bold>Aleksandar Markovic</bold> is a Full Professor at the Faculty of Organizational Sciences, University of Belgrade, Serbia, where he got his MSc and PhD degrees in Business Decision Making. Areas of his research include: business decision making, e-business and simulation methods. Contact: University of Belgrade, Faculty of Organizational Sciences, Department of Management, Jove Ilica 154, 11000 Belgrade, Serbia. Phone: +381 11 3950864. Fax: +381 11 2461221. Email: <email>aca@fon.rs</email>
</p>
</bio>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0266666912446497">Veljko Jeremic, University of Belgrade, Faculty of Organizational Sciences, Laboratory for Statistics, Jove Ilica 154, 11000 Belgrade, Serbia. Phone: +381 11 3950822. Fax: +381 11 2461221 E-mail: <email>jeremicv@fon.rs</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>28</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>271</fpage>
<lpage>280</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Information and Communication Technology (ICT) represents an important structural part of modern society; this is why countries strive for constant progress in ICT and why it draws such significant attention. Bearing this in mind, the main goal of this paper is to present an I-distance methodology that holds a new perspective on the measurement of information development, to compare it to the ICT development index (IDI), and to point out improvements that such methodology provides. IDI combines 11 indicators related to three ICT categories: Access, Use and Skills (by weighting the first two by 40 percent and the third by 20 percent). The approach presented in this study uses the same indicators, synthesizing them into one value. Subsequently, which variables are the most relevant for measuring ICT development level of countries are able to be determined. Consequently, the I-distance method provides useful insight into developing countries and ways that enhance their ranking. The results show that the correlation between the I-distance values and IDI values is very strong, <italic>r</italic> = 0.961, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01, which makes I-distance an acceptable measurement method for evaluating countries’ ICT development levels.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>information and communication technology</kwd>
<kwd>ICT Development Index</kwd>
<kwd>I-distance method</kwd>
<kwd>ranking of countries</kwd>
<kwd>ICT development structure</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<disp-quote>
<p>The I-distance method creates a measure of information development based on one synthesized indicator.</p>
</disp-quote>
<sec id="section1-0266666912446497">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Information and Communication Technology (ICT) has not only become important to modern society, but it has also become a basic structural part of it. ICT has a wide range of economic effects and thus plays an important role in strengthening economic growth and raising socio-economic development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0266666912446497">Apostol 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0266666912446497">Dimelis and Papaioannou 2011</xref>). ICT influences the industrial structure of regions and contributes to prosperity on many levels: effecting productivity gains resulting from the development of ICTs, creating new business models and opportunities, creating better educational performance (something positively associated with greater household Internet access), and so on (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0266666912446497">International Telecommunication Union 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Countries constantly strive to progress in informational development, aiming to build an inclusive information society (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0266666912446497">Parker 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-0266666912446497">Vicente and Lopez 2011</xref>). An increasing number of countries are moving towards more intensive ICT usage. This is due to the real social and economic benefits that only occur through the successful use of ICTs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0266666912446497">Gholami et al 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0266666912446497">Heeks 2010</xref>). If an economy is not able to recognize and exploit the advantages of employing and investing in new technologies, economic growth and development will not rise to its full capacity.</p>
<p>The ICT Development Index (IDI) is a benchmarking tool used to monitor information society development worldwide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0266666912446497">International Telecommunication Union 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0266666912446497">2011</xref>). It combines 11 indicators related to ICT Access, Use and Skills into a single composite index. The main purpose of IDI is to measure the level of ICT development, progress in ICT development, differences between countries with different levels of ICT development, and the development potential of ICTs (International Telecommunication Union 2011).</p>
<p>ICT is composed of three parts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0266666912446497">International Telecommunication Union 2011</xref>), which include the aforementioned 11 indicators related to ICT Access, Use and Skills:</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>
<bold>ICT Access </bold>reflects the level of network infrastructure and access to ICTs, capturing its readiness. It includes five infrastructure and access indicators: fixed telephony, mobile telephony, international Internet bandwidth, households with computers, and households with Internet access.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>
<bold>ICT Use </bold>reflects the level of use of ICTs in society, capturing its intensity. It includes three ICT intensity and usage indicators: Internet users, fixed broadband, and mobile broadband.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>
<bold>ICT Skills</bold> reflects the result/outcome of efficient and effective ICT use, capturing its capability or skills as indispensable input indicators. It includes three proxy indicators: adult literacy, gross secondary and tertiary enrolment (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0266666912446497">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
</list-item>
</list>
<fig id="fig1-0266666912446497" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>ICT Development Index: Indicators and Weights.</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="fig1-0266666912446497" xlink:href="10.1177_0266666912446497-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The selection of indicators takes the evolution of the information society into account as it goes through its different stages of development, referring to technology convergence and the emergence of new technologies. Therefore, the indicators in each part may change over time to reflect technological developments, since these indicators also strive to recognise the relevance of any particular indicator in its contribution to the main objectives and conceptual framework of the IDI.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0266666912446497">
<title>Problem definition</title>
<p>The goal of this study has been to rank countries according to their ICT development structure and to compare the results achieved with their ranking based on the ICT development index (IDI). Thereby, a fresh statistical approach to ranking countries is here proposed through the use of the statistical I-distance method (see below), so as to provide a new perspective on the IDI, as it is significantly believed to contribute to its improvement.</p>
<p>The issue at hand is to improve the methodology used to measure a country’s development level according to their ICT structure; more specifically, the IDI index methodology has predefined the pattern for measuring a country’s ICT structure, which includes ICT Access and ICT Use at 40 percent and ICT Skills at 20 percent. Therefore, IDI is based on a set of input criteria, which are weighted using a defined subjective approach.</p>
<p>Conversely, within the I-distance method, calculations can be made in order to define a set of variables relevant to the analysis (see below). Based on the correlation between the criteria and the I-distance measure, the I-distance method lends a better view on the importance of input criteria, and, consequently, the order of importance of input criteria is able to be determined. In such manner, this method provides an answer to the question: “What variables are more important in measuring the ICT development level of countries?” This fact supersedes the issue of subjectively assigned weights, showing exactly what criteria are most important, and may even dismiss some variables as being redundant.</p>
<p>As indicated above, the methodology of IDI includes 11 indicators, divided into three groups. The main data source used in this study is a set of the aforementioned IDI indicators, the first five of which refer to ICT Access, the next three show ICT Use, and the last three represent ICT Skills. These indicators are (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0266666912446497">International Telecommunication Union 2011</xref>):</p>
<list list-type="bullet">
<list-item>
<p>
<bold>Fixed Telephone Lines per 100 Inhabitants </bold>– Telephone lines connecting a subscriber’s terminal equipment to the public switched telephone network (PSTN) and which have a dedicated port on a telephone exchange, though this may not be the same as an access line or a subscriber. The number of ISDN channels and fixed wireless subscribers are included in this indicator.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>
<bold>Mobile Cellular Telephone Subscriptions per 100 Inhabitants </bold>– The number of subscriptions to a public mobile telephone service using cellular technology, which provides access to the Public Switched Telephone Network (PSTN). While post-paid and prepaid subscriptions are included in this indicator, it does not differentiate between subscriptions and subscriber (person). Therein, as one subscriber may have multiple subscriptions, it would be useful to further distinguish between the number of mobile subscriptions and the number of individuals using a mobile phone.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>
<bold>International Internet Bandwidth (bit/s) per Internet User </bold>– The capacity that backbone operators provide to carry Internet traffic. This is measured in bits per second per Internet user.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>
<bold>The Proportion of Households with a Computer </bold>– A computer refers to a desktop or laptop computer. This does not include equipment that may have some embedded computing abilities, such as mobile cellular phones, personal digital assistants or TV sets.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>
<bold>The Proportion of Households with Internet Access at Home </bold>– not assumed to be only via a computer. This may also be by mobile phone, game console, digital TV, etc. Access can be via a fixed or mobile network.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>
<bold>Internet Users per 100 Inhabitants </bold>– The increasing use of the Internet through mobile devices is not necessarily reflected in these estimates.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>
<bold>Fixed Broadband Internet Subscribers per 100 Inhabitants </bold>– Subscribers to paid, high-speed access to the public Internet (over a TCP/IP connection). Subscribers with access to data communications (including the Internet) via mobile cellular networks are excluded in this indicator.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>
<bold>Mobile Broadband Subscriptions per 100 Inhabitants </bold>– Subscriptions to mobile cellular networks with access to data communications at broadband speeds, irrespective of the device used to access the Internet (handheld computer, laptop, or mobile cellular telephone). These services are typically referred to as “3G” or “3.5G”.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>
<bold>Adult Literacy Rate</bold> – The percentage of the population aged 15 years and over who can both read and write, as well as understand a short simple statement regarding his/her everyday life.</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>
<bold>Gross Enrolment Ratio (Secondary and Tertiary Level)</bold> – the total enrolment in a specific level of education, regardless of age, expressed as a percentage of the eligible official school-age population that corresponds to the same level of education in a given school-year.</p>
</list-item>
</list>
<p>In the study presented here, the I-distance method on these referred indicators has been performed. In addition, the I-distance method is thoroughly elaborated upon below, followed by the results of the proposed method.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0266666912446497">
<title>The I-distance method</title>
<p>Quite often, the ranking of specific marks is done in such a way that can seriously affect the process of taking exams, sports competitions, UN participation, university ranking, medicine selection and many other areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0266666912446497">Al-Lagilli et al. 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0266666912446497">Ivanovic 1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0266666912446497">Ivanovic and Fanchette 1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0266666912446497">Jeremic and Radojicic 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0266666912446497">Jeremic et al. 2011a</xref>).</p>
<p>I-distance is a metric distance in an n-dimensional space, which has recently made a significant breakthrough in a number of scientific achievements. It was originally proposed and defined by B. Ivanovic and has appeared in various publications since 1963 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0266666912446497">Ivanovic 1973</xref>). A notable, striking affirmation of the method has been its use in University ranking (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0266666912446497">Jeremic et al. 2011a</xref>), and evaluating the socio-economic development of countries (Jeremic et al. 2012). Ivanovic devised this method to rank countries according to their level of development based on several indicators. Many socio-economic development indicators were considered, but the problem was how to use all of them in order to calculate a single synthetic indicator, which will thereafter represent the rank.</p>
<p>For a selected set of variables (in this case ICT indicators) chosen to characterize the entities (in this case countries), the square I-distance between the two entities <italic>e<sub>r</sub>
</italic> and <italic>e<sub>s</sub>
</italic> is defined as:
<disp-formula id="disp-formula1-0266666912446497">
<mml:math id="mml-disp1-0266666912446497">
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi mathvariant="normal">D</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn mathvariant="normal">2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msup>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">=</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:munderover>
<mml:mo movablelimits="false" stretchy="false">∑</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
</mml:munderover>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msubsup>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mi mathvariant="italic">σ</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msubsup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:munderover>
<mml:mo movablelimits="false" stretchy="false">∏</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">−</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:munderover>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">−</mml:mo>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msubsup>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
</mml:math>
<graphic alternate-form-of="disp-formula1-0266666912446497" xlink:href="10.1177_0266666912446497-eq1.tif"/>
</disp-formula>
</p>
<p>
<italic>d(r,s)</italic> - distance between the values of variable for entities <italic>e<sub>r</sub>
</italic> and <italic>e<sub>s</sub>
</italic>
</p>
<p>
<italic>σ<sub>i</sub>
</italic> - standard deviation of variable <italic>X<sub>i</sub>
</italic>
</p>
<p>
<italic>r<sub>ji.p</sub>
</italic> - partial coefficient of the correlation between variables <italic>X<sub>i</sub></italic> and<italic> X<sub>j</sub>
</italic>, excluding <italic>X<sub>p</sub>
</italic> <italic>(j&lt;i, p=1,2,…j-1)</italic>
</p>
<p>XT=(X1, X2,… Xk) - selected set of variables</p>
<p>The I-distance measurement is based on calculating the mutual distances between the entities being processed, whereupon they are compared to one another, so as to create a rank. In order to rank the entities (in this case, countries), it is necessary to have one entity fixed as a referent in the observing set. The entity with the minimum value for each variable, or a fictive entity, can be set up as the referent one. The ranking of entities in the set is based on the calculated distance from the referent entity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0266666912446497">Jeremic et al. 2011c</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0266666912446497">Knezevic et al. 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0266666912446497">Radojicic et al. 2012</xref>).</p>
<p>The construction of the I-distance is iterative; it is calculated through the following steps (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0266666912446497">Ivanovic 1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0266666912446497">Jeremic et al. 2011d</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0266666912446497">Jovanovic et al. 2012</xref>):</p>
<list list-type="order">
<list-item>
<p>Calculate the value of the discriminate effect of the variable <inline-formula id="inline-formula1-0266666912446497">
<mml:math id="mml-inline1-0266666912446497">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> (the most significant variable which provides the largest amount of information on the phenomena that are to be ranked (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0266666912446497">Ivanovic 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0266666912446497">Jeremic et al. 2012b</xref>))</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Add the value of the discriminate effect of <inline-formula id="inline-formula2-0266666912446497">
<mml:math id="mml-inline2-0266666912446497">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> which is not covered by <inline-formula id="inline-formula3-0266666912446497">
<mml:math id="mml-inline3-0266666912446497">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Add the value of the discriminate effect of <inline-formula id="inline-formula4-0266666912446497">
<mml:math id="mml-inline4-0266666912446497">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> which is not covered by <inline-formula id="inline-formula5-0266666912446497">
<mml:math id="mml-inline5-0266666912446497">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="inline-formula6-0266666912446497">
<mml:math id="mml-inline6-0266666912446497">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>X</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</p>
</list-item>
<list-item>
<p>Repeat the procedure for all variables (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0266666912446497">Jeremic et al. 2011b</xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0266666912446497">2011e</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0266666912446497">2012a</xref>).</p>
</list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0266666912446497">
<title>Results and discussion</title>
<p>The results of the I-distance method, as well as a comparison of the I-distance and the IDI ranking, are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0266666912446497">Table 1</xref>. A total of 111 countries have been included in the analysis. In order to assess the I-distance measurement, a Pearson correlation coefficient between the I-distance values and IDI values has also been calculated. Such correlation is significant at a 0.01 level (p &lt; 0.01), and very strong, r = 0.961. The fact that the method correlates so closely with the IDI ranking, proves that it is equally suitable and greatly connected to the subject of interest. This validates the I-distance method as an acceptable measurement for evaluating countries in their ICT development level. In addition, this method provides a different perspective on the importance of each input variable, and a correction in the weighting factor for each ICT indicator should therein occur. As for the compared ranking of countries gained by the two methods, a Spearman’s rho statistic has additionally been calculated. The correlation is also significant with r<sub>s</sub> = 0.962, p &lt; 0.01.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0266666912446497" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>I-distance rank, IDI rank and rank change</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0266666912446497" xlink:href="10.1177_0266666912446497-table1.tif"/>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0266666912446497" xlink:href="10.1177_0266666912446497-table1a.tif"/>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0266666912446497" xlink:href="10.1177_0266666912446497-table1b.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Country</th>
<th>I-distance</th>
<th>Rank I-distance</th>
<th>IDI</th>
<th>Rank IDI</th>
<th>Change</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Iceland</td>
<td>44.799</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>8.06</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Korea (Rep.)</td>
<td>41.556</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>8.4</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>−1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Finland</td>
<td>41.194</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>7.87</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sweden</td>
<td>40.971</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>8.23</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>−2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Denmark</td>
<td>40.377</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>7.97</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>−1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Switzerland</td>
<td>37.793</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>7.67</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Netherlands</td>
<td>37.163</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>7.61</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Australia</td>
<td>36.64</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>7.36</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Norway</td>
<td>35.84</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>7.6</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Luxembourg</td>
<td>35.439</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>7.78</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>−4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>United Kingdom</td>
<td>34.774</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>7.6</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>−1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>New Zealand</td>
<td>33.623</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>7.43</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>−1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Germany</td>
<td>32.027</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>7.27</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Austria</td>
<td>31.937</td>
<td>14</td>
<td>7.17</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Portugal</td>
<td>31.194</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>6.64</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Belgium</td>
<td>30.889</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>6.83</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>France</td>
<td>30.697</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>7.09</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>−1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Singapore</td>
<td>30.514</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>7.08</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Spain</td>
<td>30.162</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>6.73</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Slovenia</td>
<td>29.89</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>6.75</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Lithuania</td>
<td>29.69</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>6.04</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Italy</td>
<td>29.655</td>
<td>22</td>
<td>6.57</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Japan</td>
<td>29.485</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>7.42</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>−11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Israel</td>
<td>29.195</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>6.87</td>
<td>19</td>
<td>−5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>United States</td>
<td>28.5</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>7.09</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>−8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Russia</td>
<td>28.299</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>5.38</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Greece</td>
<td>27.754</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>6.28</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Estonia</td>
<td>27.074</td>
<td>28</td>
<td>6.16</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Canada</td>
<td>26.958</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>6.69</td>
<td>24</td>
<td>−5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Montenegro</td>
<td>26.933</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>5.03</td>
<td>47</td>
<td>17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Croatia</td>
<td>26.804</td>
<td>31</td>
<td>6.21</td>
<td>29</td>
<td>−2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ireland</td>
<td>26.456</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>6.78</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>−11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Saudi Arabia</td>
<td>26.375</td>
<td>33</td>
<td>5.42</td>
<td>42</td>
<td>9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Czech Republic</td>
<td>25.593</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>5.97</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hungary</td>
<td>25.553</td>
<td>35</td>
<td>6.04</td>
<td>32</td>
<td>−3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Malta</td>
<td>24.662</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>6.43</td>
<td>27</td>
<td>−9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bulgaria</td>
<td>24.252</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>5.19</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Poland</td>
<td>24.21</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>5.95</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>−2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Panama</td>
<td>23.981</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>4.09</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>22</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Latvia</td>
<td>23.356</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>5.9</td>
<td>38</td>
<td>−2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ukraine</td>
<td>22.663</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>4.34</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Belarus</td>
<td>22.554</td>
<td>42</td>
<td>5.01</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Uruguay</td>
<td>22.186</td>
<td>43</td>
<td>4.93</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>United Arab Emirates</td>
<td>22.131</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>6.19</td>
<td>30</td>
<td>−14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Slovak Republic</td>
<td>22.045</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>5.94</td>
<td>37</td>
<td>−8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Argentina</td>
<td>22.003</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>4.64</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cyprus</td>
<td>21.419</td>
<td>47</td>
<td>5.98</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>−13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Romania</td>
<td>21.166</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>5.2</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>−4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Serbia</td>
<td>20.684</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>5.11</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>−3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Vietnam</td>
<td>20.134</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>3.53</td>
<td>73</td>
<td>23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Oman</td>
<td>19.821</td>
<td>51</td>
<td>4.38</td>
<td>56</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bahrain</td>
<td>19.568</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>5.57</td>
<td>41</td>
<td>−11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Kazakhstan</td>
<td>19.494</td>
<td>53</td>
<td>4.02</td>
<td>62</td>
<td>9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Chile</td>
<td>19.279</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>4.65</td>
<td>51</td>
<td>−3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Qatar</td>
<td>18.902</td>
<td>55</td>
<td>5.6</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>−15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Armenia</td>
<td>18.801</td>
<td>56</td>
<td>3.87</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Brunei Darussalam</td>
<td>18.474</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>5.61</td>
<td>39</td>
<td>−18</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Seychelles</td>
<td>18.202</td>
<td>58</td>
<td>3.94</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TFYR Macedonia</td>
<td>16.998</td>
<td>59</td>
<td>4.98</td>
<td>49</td>
<td>−10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Venezuela</td>
<td>16.819</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>4.11</td>
<td>60</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Azerbaijan</td>
<td>15.882</td>
<td>61</td>
<td>3.78</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mongolia</td>
<td>15.484</td>
<td>62</td>
<td>3.41</td>
<td>77</td>
<td>15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Moldova</td>
<td>15.413</td>
<td>63</td>
<td>4.47</td>
<td>53</td>
<td>−10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Georgia</td>
<td>15.397</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>3.65</td>
<td>71</td>
<td>7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bosnia &amp; Herzegovina</td>
<td>14.921</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>4.31</td>
<td>58</td>
<td>−7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Brazil</td>
<td>14.872</td>
<td>66</td>
<td>4.22</td>
<td>59</td>
<td>−7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Malaysia</td>
<td>14.574</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>4.45</td>
<td>54</td>
<td>−13</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Kyrgyzstan</td>
<td>14.495</td>
<td>68</td>
<td>2.84</td>
<td>89</td>
<td>21</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Jordan</td>
<td>14.111</td>
<td>69</td>
<td>3.83</td>
<td>67</td>
<td>−2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Uzbekistan</td>
<td>13.889</td>
<td>70</td>
<td>2.55</td>
<td>96</td>
<td>26</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Colombia</td>
<td>13.706</td>
<td>71</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>69</td>
<td>−2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fiji</td>
<td>13.627</td>
<td>72</td>
<td>3.16</td>
<td>84</td>
<td>12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Costa Rica</td>
<td>13.259</td>
<td>73</td>
<td>3.99</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>−9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mexico</td>
<td>12.813</td>
<td>74</td>
<td>3.75</td>
<td>70</td>
<td>−4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Turkey</td>
<td>12.794</td>
<td>75</td>
<td>4.42</td>
<td>55</td>
<td>−20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Thailand</td>
<td>12.753</td>
<td>76</td>
<td>3.3</td>
<td>79</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Peru</td>
<td>12.608</td>
<td>77</td>
<td>3.52</td>
<td>74</td>
<td>−3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Jamaica</td>
<td>12.594</td>
<td>78</td>
<td>3.41</td>
<td>76</td>
<td>−2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mauritius</td>
<td>11.895</td>
<td>79</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>63</td>
<td>−16</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>South Africa</td>
<td>11.852</td>
<td>80</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>86</td>
<td>6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Philippines</td>
<td>11.8</td>
<td>81</td>
<td>3.22</td>
<td>82</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tunisia</td>
<td>11.059</td>
<td>82</td>
<td>3.43</td>
<td>75</td>
<td>−7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Botswana</td>
<td>11.023</td>
<td>83</td>
<td>2.59</td>
<td>95</td>
<td>12</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Indonesia</td>
<td>10.899</td>
<td>84</td>
<td>2.83</td>
<td>91</td>
<td>7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ecuador</td>
<td>10.869</td>
<td>85</td>
<td>3.37</td>
<td>78</td>
<td>−7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>China</td>
<td>10.833</td>
<td>86</td>
<td>3.55</td>
<td>72</td>
<td>−14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>El Salvador</td>
<td>10.823</td>
<td>87</td>
<td>2.89</td>
<td>87</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Paraguay</td>
<td>10.711</td>
<td>88</td>
<td>2.87</td>
<td>88</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Honduras</td>
<td>10.576</td>
<td>89</td>
<td>2.72</td>
<td>93</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sri Lanka</td>
<td>10.394</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>2.79</td>
<td>92</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>The Dominican Rep.</td>
<td>10.138</td>
<td>91</td>
<td>3.21</td>
<td>83</td>
<td>−8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bolivia</td>
<td>9.817</td>
<td>92</td>
<td>2.83</td>
<td>90</td>
<td>−2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Guatemala</td>
<td>8.792</td>
<td>93</td>
<td>2.65</td>
<td>94</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Namibia</td>
<td>7.169</td>
<td>94</td>
<td>2.36</td>
<td>97</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Syria</td>
<td>7.063</td>
<td>95</td>
<td>3.05</td>
<td>85</td>
<td>−10</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Egypt</td>
<td>6.455</td>
<td>96</td>
<td>3.28</td>
<td>81</td>
<td>−15</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Zimbabwe</td>
<td>6.366</td>
<td>97</td>
<td>1.81</td>
<td>106</td>
<td>9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Nicaragua</td>
<td>5.275</td>
<td>98</td>
<td>2.31</td>
<td>98</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Morocco</td>
<td>4.9</td>
<td>99</td>
<td>3.29</td>
<td>80</td>
<td>−19</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cambodia</td>
<td>3.492</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>1.99</td>
<td>100</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Lao PER</td>
<td>3.062</td>
<td>101</td>
<td>1.9</td>
<td>103</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ghana</td>
<td>3.037</td>
<td>102</td>
<td>1.9</td>
<td>102</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>India</td>
<td>2.664</td>
<td>103</td>
<td>2.01</td>
<td>99</td>
<td>−4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Bhutan</td>
<td>1.85</td>
<td>104</td>
<td>1.93</td>
<td>101</td>
<td>−3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mauritania</td>
<td>1.623</td>
<td>105</td>
<td>1.58</td>
<td>109</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Uganda</td>
<td>1.595</td>
<td>106</td>
<td>1.49</td>
<td>110</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Angola</td>
<td>1.471</td>
<td>107</td>
<td>1.58</td>
<td>108</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Nigeria</td>
<td>1.069</td>
<td>108</td>
<td>1.85</td>
<td>104</td>
<td>−4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Senegal</td>
<td>1.055</td>
<td>109</td>
<td>1.78</td>
<td>107</td>
<td>−2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pakistan</td>
<td>0.861</td>
<td>110</td>
<td>1.83</td>
<td>105</td>
<td>−5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mozambique</td>
<td>0.17</td>
<td>111</td>
<td>1.3</td>
<td>111</td>
<td>0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<p>As can be seen from <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0266666912446497">Table 1</xref>, Iceland, Korea, Finland, Sweden and Denmark are the countries that top the I-distance method list. Iceland, which comes in first for the I-distance ranks, takes third place in the IDI rank, and, while Korea tops the IDI rank, it takes second place in the I-distance rank. A very interesting finding is that the first five countries show the same strength in both measurement methods, far above other countries. This is easily explained, since eight of the top ten are highly developed European countries, and Europe is the world's leading region in ICT infrastructure and services. This comes as no surprise, as the, Old Continent’ has a population that is much more homogenous and its constant commitment to ICT values is easily understood. All of these European countries have a large percentage of Internet users; computers and telephone lines there are practically universally accessible as well. These are the exact factors that result in European countries attaining higher positions. Similarly, both Korea and Australia are developed countries that are members of the Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD ) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0266666912446497">Dobrota et al. 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-0266666912446497">World Bank 2011</xref>).</p>
<p>Angola, Nigeria, Senegal, Pakistan and Mozambique come in at the bottom of the I-distance rank. The situation in these countries is very unlike those that top the rank. The percentage of households with a computer, let alone Internet access, is extremely low. The same is true for the percentage of telephone lines. For instance, in Mozambique there are only 4.2 Internet users per 100 people (95 percent for Iceland); thus, only a small part of this country is embracing the development of ICT. Overall, most countries at the bottom of the rank are low-income countries and are from the group of Least Developed Countries (LDCs).</p>
<p>The differences between the IDI and I-distance ranks are also shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0266666912446497">Table 1</xref>. It is interesting to note that the difference between these ranks is less than 10 in all of the 82 cases (73.87 percent of total). For 21.62 percent of them, the difference is among 10 and 20. Only in 4.51 percent is there a difference greater than 20. Great differences appear for the countries of Panama, Vietnam, Kyrgyzstan and Uzbekistan. The largest difference in rank is in the case of Uzbekistan, which is ranked as being in the 70th place by I-distance, but in the 96th by IDI (a 26 rank difference).</p>
<p>If the issue were to be observed in regard to Serbia, it would be found that this country is ranked in the middle, by both the I-distance and IDI rankings (with a difference in rank of only 3). In Serbia, 50.9 per cent of households own a computer and 40.2 per cent have an Internet connection. This is rather below those countries which top the ranking list, where the percentage of households owning a computer and having an Internet connection increases to 93 percent and 92 percent respectively. Serbia may score high enough to be ranked in the middle, but it is quite obvious that it is still far off from meeting European Union development goals. ICT variables clearly reflect Serbia’s current situation, as 43.7 percent of population has never used computer, while the European average is 26 percent. Likewise, 54.1 percent have never used the Internet, while the European average is 30 percent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0266666912446497">Nita 2011</xref>; RZS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0266666912446497">2011</xref>). There are certain differences in Serbia throughout its regions in terms of ICT usage and development. For instance, Belgrade and northern Serbia (the province of Vojvodina) are significantly better than southern Serbia. These regions are more aware of the importance of ICT, and they consequently more readily invest in this area, as prosperity and economic benefit which are to be brought by ICT development. This is also evident concerning the development of Vojvodina’s ICT Cluster, which is the strongest in its field in Serbia, as well as the development of an IT Park in the town of Indjija (also in Vojvodina).</p>
<p>As has been previously implied, one of the main objectives this paper is to present the relevance of ICT indicators. Namely, the I-distance method uses the same indicators, but puts them into a specific order of importance. This allows for a better understanding of the ranking results of the I-distance method, as well as for a better comprehension of the differences between the I-distance and IDI results. In that, it is essential to establish an order of importance for the indicators since it provides an answer to the question: “What are the variables that are the most relevant for measuring the ICT development level of countries?” Accordingly, a Pearson correlation coefficient of each variable with the I-distance value has been calculated as to determine the significance of input variables. These correlations are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0266666912446497">Table 2</xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0266666912446497" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Variable importance as measured by correlation with the I-distance</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0266666912446497" xlink:href="10.1177_0266666912446497-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Variables</th>
<th>Correlation with the I-distance</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Fixed (wired)-broadband Internet subscriptions per 100 inhabitants</td>
<td>0.837**</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fixed-telephone lines per 100 inhabitants</td>
<td>0.823**</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Percentage of households with Internet access</td>
<td>0.798**</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Percentage of individuals using the Internet</td>
<td>0.792**</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Percentage of households with a computer</td>
<td>0.788**</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>International Internet bandwidth (bit/s) per Internet user</td>
<td>0.782**</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Active mobile-broadband subscriptions per 100 inhabitants</td>
<td>0.766**</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tertiary gross enrolment ratio</td>
<td>0.682**</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mobile-cellular telephone subscriptions per 100 inhabitants</td>
<td>0.656**</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Adult literacy rate</td>
<td>0.650**</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Secondary gross enrolment ratio</td>
<td>0.621**</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn6-0266666912446497">
<p>
<italic>Note</italic>: **<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<p>The results show that all the variables are significantly correlated to the I-distance measurement values. The most statistically significant variable for determining ICT development structure appears to be <italic>Fixed (wired)-broadband Internet subscriptions per 100 inhabitants</italic>, where r = 0.837, p&lt;0.01. This is not surprising, since previous research has shown a relatively high awareness of cable modem and DSL availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0266666912446497">Savage and Waldman 2005</xref>). In addition, much previous research has emphasized Internet connections as being quite significant in determining a country’s development level. Very high relevant positions are taken by the three important variables: <italic>Percentage of households with Internet access</italic>, <italic>Percentage of individuals using the Internet</italic> and <italic>Percentage of households with a computer</italic>. It is evident that these variables most certainly signify not only a country’s ICT development structure, but also are important indicators of social and economic benefit.</p>
<p>It is essential for lower-ranked countries to improve these most significant ICT development indicators in order to improve their overall position in the ranking process. This is also very important for Serbia in order to increase its own prosperity and improve its own general progress. For example, <italic>Fixed (wired)-broadband Internet subscriptions per 100 inhabitants</italic> in Serbia is only 8.5, which is far less than the same variable for Iceland or in Korea, which amounts to approximately 35 per 100 inhabitants. Similarly, about 40.2 per cent of Serbian households have Internet access, and 40.9 per cent of individuals use the Internet; whereas in Iceland and in Korea, these percentages are greater than 90 percent.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0266666912446497">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>There is a constant tendency of economies towards the expansion of their ICT and towards an overall transition into the global information society (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0266666912446497">Parasyuk 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0266666912446497">Pyrig 2010</xref>). The main goal of this paper has been to present a new perspective on the measurement of countries’ informational development, as implemented by using the I-distance method, and to compare it with the ICT development index.</p>
<p>Firstly, through the use of the I-distance method, this paper has proposed a fresh approach to the evaluation of countries’ ICT development. Moreover, it is one that uses the same 11 indicators related to the three ICT categories: Access, Use and Skills, and yet unlike the IDI that weighs the first two categories by 40 percent and the third by 20 percent, I-distance can arrange them according to a specific order of importance. This reveals which variables are most relevant in measuring the ICT development level of countries, provides useful insight into developing countries, and suggests a way to enhance their ranking by supplying a comprehensive international performance evaluation based on quantitative indicators, benchmarks, and by identifying areas of high and low growth in ICT-related development. The main advantages of the method are reflected in the fact that the recent expansion of this method is noticeable in a number of studies where the key to ranking entities is the use of a large number of criteria. The advantage is therein presented that the I-distance method creates one synthesized unbiased indicator that incorporates many criteria into one criterion. Certainly, this is one of the main contributions of this paper. In addition, I-distance proposes a different approach in determining the weighting factor. Compared to IDI methodology, the I-distance approach does not rely on subjectively chosen weights; rather, it arranges criteria in a specific order. In particular, it defines the most significant variable which provides the largest amount of information on the phenomena that are to be ranked and consequently all of the other variables that are to follow.</p>
<p>Secondly, I-distance has proven to be an exceptional measurement tool, which is further confirmed by the results of the Pearson correlation coefficient between the I-distance values and the IDI values. The correlation is very strong, r = 0.961, p &lt; 0.01. Accordingly, the differences between the ranks are found to be less than 10 in 73.87 percent, 10 to 20 in 21.62 percent of cases, and only in 4.51 percent is the difference greater than 20.</p>
<p>Thirdly, the results presented in this study clearly show that Serbia has a long road ahead of it in order to achieve European Union development goals and become a full member of the EU. The ICT development indicators are significantly lower than EU standards and Serbia must definitely focus on improving them. Although ICT was among the most vibrant and fastest growing sectors in Serbia, experiencing double-digit annual growth in the years prior to the global recession, the economic crisis hit Serbia severely, producing significant negative consequences to the ICT industry as well. This resulted in a steep decline: in 2009 alone, the IT market in Serbia fell by 22.20 percent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0266666912446497">Mijacic et al. 2011</xref>). However, it is also worth mentioning that Serbia started building an IT Park in the town of Indjija, which is planned to be finished by 2013 and shall be spread over 250,000 m<sup>2</sup>, making it Europe’s largest. The Park will provide housing to IT services and technology providers, employing up to 25,000 individuals.</p>
<p>Finally, a new approach to evaluating the ICT development index has been presented in this paper. This novel approach is not based on arbitrarily chosen weighting factors, and it may be able to significantly contribute to emerging research in the field of ICT development structure. In brief, the paper presented here has indicated that the I-distance method creates one synthesized unbiased indicator that incorporates many ICT indicators into one indicator.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Al-Lagilli</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jeremic</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Seke</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jeremic</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Radojicic</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Evaluating the health of nations: a Libyan perspective</article-title>. <source>Libyan Journal of Medicine</source> <volume>6</volume>: <issue>6021</issue>. <comment>doi: 10.3402/ljm.v6i0.6021</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Apostol</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Knowledge, education and technological progress in the new economy</article-title>. <source>Metalurgia International</source> <volume>14</volume> (<issue>SI5</issue>): <fpage>78</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dimelis</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Papaioannou</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>ICT growth effects at the industry level: A comparison between the US and the EU</article-title>. <source>Information Economics and Policy</source> <volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>37</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dobrota</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Milenkovic</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jeremic</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Djokovic</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Neural networks in determining the level of countries’ economic development</article-title>. In<italic>: </italic>
<source>Proceedings of the VIII Congress of Entrepreneurs and Scientists</source>, <publisher-loc>Belgrade, Serbia</publisher-loc>, <comment>01–02 November 2011</comment>, pp. <fpage>547</fpage>–<lpage>553</lpage>. <comment>Belgrade: FON</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gholami</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Higon</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hanafizadeh</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Emrouznejad</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Is ICT the key to development?</article-title> <source>Journal of Global Information Management</source> <volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>66</fpage>–<lpage>83</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Heeks</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Do information and communication technologies (ICTs) contribute to development?</article-title> <source>Journal of International Development</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>625</fpage>–<lpage>640</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">International Telecommunication Union</collab> (<year>2009</year>). <source>Measuring the Information Society – The ICT Development Index 2009</source>, <publisher-name>ITU</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">International Telecommunication Union</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <source>Measuring the Information Society 2011</source>. <comment>Available at:</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.itu.int/ITU-D/ict/publications/idi/2011/">http://www.itu.int/ITU-D/ict/publications/idi/2011/</ext-link> <comment>(accessed 7 November 2011)</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ivanovic</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>). <source>A method of establishing a list of development indicators</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>UNESCO</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ivanovic</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>). <source>Classification theory</source>. <publisher-loc>Belgrade</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Institute for Industrial Economic</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ivanovic</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fanchette</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1973</year>). <source>Grouping and ranking of 30 countries of Sub-Saharan Africa, Two distance-based methods compared</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>UNESCO</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jeremic</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Radojicic</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>A new approach in the evaluation of team chess championships rankings</article-title>. <source>Journal of Quantitative Analysis in Sports</source> <volume>6</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): Article 7. doi: 10.2202/<fpage>1559</fpage>–<lpage>0410</lpage>.1257</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jeremic</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bulajic</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Martic</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Radojicic</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011a</year>) <article-title>A fresh approach to evaluating the academic ranking of world universities</article-title>. <source>Scientometrics</source> <volume>87</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>587</fpage>–<lpage>596</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jeremic</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Isljamovic</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Petrovic</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Radojicic</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Markovic</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bulajic</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011b</year>) <article-title>Human development index and sustainability: What’s the correlation?</article-title> <source>Metalurgia International</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>67</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jeremic</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vukmirovic</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Radojicic</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Djokovic</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011c</year>) <article-title>Towards a framework for evaluating ICT infrastructure of countries: a Serbian perspective</article-title>. <source>Metalurgia International</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>18</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jeremic</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Markovic</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Radojicic</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011d</year>) <article-title>ICT as crucial component of socio-economic development</article-title>. <source>Management</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>60</issue>): <fpage>5</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jeremic</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Seke</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Radojicic</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jeremic</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Markovic</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Slovic</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aleksic</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011e</year>) <article-title>Measuring health of countries: a novel approach</article-title>. <source>HealthMED</source> <volume>5</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1762</fpage>–<lpage>1766</lpage>. </citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jeremic</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Slovic</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Radojicic</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2012a</year>) <article-title>Measuring human capital: a statistical approach</article-title>. <source>Actual Problems of Economics</source> <volume>5</volume>: (<issue>In press</issue>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jeremic</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bulajic</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Martic</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Markovic</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Savic</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jeremic</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Radojicic</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2012b</year>). <article-title>An evaluation of European countries health systems through distance based analysis</article-title>. <source>Hippokratia</source> <volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>175</fpage>–<lpage>179</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jovanovic</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jeremic</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Savic</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bulajic</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Martic</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>How does the normalization of data affects the ARWU ranking?</article-title> <source>Scientometrics</source> <comment>Online First, doi: 10.1007/s11192-012-0674-0.</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Knezevic</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jeremic</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zarkic-Joksimovic</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bulajic</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Evaluating the Serbian banking sector: a statistical approach</article-title>. <source>Metalurgia International</source> <volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>171</fpage>–<lpage>174</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mijacic</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kappenmann</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sredojevic</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <source>ICT in Serbia: at a glance</source>. <comment>GIZ, ACCESS and Vojvodina ICT Cluster. Available at:</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vojvodinaictcluster.org/Images/ICT_in_Serbia_At_a_Glance_2011.pdf">http://www.vojvodinaictcluster.org/Images/ICT_in_Serbia_At_a_Glance_2011.pdf</ext-link> <comment>(accessed 1 November 2011)</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nita</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>An extended approach to e-inclusion and its implications for Romania</article-title>. <source>Romanian Journal of European Affairs</source> <volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>63</fpage>–<lpage>80</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Parasyuk</surname>
<given-names>IV</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Information models in evaluation of economic development of a region</article-title>. <source>Actual Problems of Economics</source> <volume>112</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>239</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Parker</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The digital divide is still with us</article-title>. <source>Information Development</source> <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>. </citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pyrig</surname>
<given-names>DZ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Application of information technologies in management of innovative potential development</article-title>. <source>Actual Problems of Economics</source> <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Radojicic</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Isljamovic</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Petrovic</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jeremic</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>A novel approach to evaluating sustainable development</article-title>. <source>Problemy Ekorozwoju – Problems of Sustainable Development</source> <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>81</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="web">
<collab collab-type="author">RZS</collab> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Serbian Republic Bureau of Statistics</article-title>. <comment>Available at:</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://webrzs.stat.gov.rs/WebSite/Public/PageView.aspx?pKey=205">http://webrzs.stat.gov.rs/WebSite/Public/PageView.aspx?pKey=205</ext-link> <comment>(accessed 15 September 2011)</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Savage</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Waldman</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Broadband Internet access, awareness, and use: Analysis of United States household data</article-title>. <source>Telecommunications Policy</source> <volume>29</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>615</fpage>–<lpage>633</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vicente</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lopez</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Assessing the regional digital divide across the European Union-27</article-title>. <source>Telecommunications Policy</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>220</fpage>–<lpage>237</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-0266666912446497">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<collab collab-type="author">World Bank</collab> (<year>2011</year>). <source>List of economies</source>. <comment>Available at:</comment> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://siteresources.worldbank.org/DATASTATISTICS/Resources/CLASS.XLS">http://siteresources.worldbank.org/DATASTATISTICS/Resources/CLASS.XLS</ext-link> <comment>(accessed 18 November 2011)</comment>
</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>