<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JPH</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjph</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Planning History</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1538-5132</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-6585</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1538513212456970</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1538513212456970</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>San Francisco’s Diamond Heights</article-title>
<subtitle>Urban Renewal and the Modernist City</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Brandi</surname>
<given-names>Richard</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1538513212456970">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1538513212456970"/>
</contrib>
<bio>
<title>Author Biography</title>
<p>
<bold>Richard Brandi</bold> is an architectural historian and historic preservation specialist based in San Francisco. He gave a presentation about Diamond Heights at the 2009 Society for American City and Regional Planning History Conference.</p></bio>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1538513212456970">
<label>1</label>San Francisco, CA, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1538513212456970">Richard Brandi, 125 Dorchester Way, San Francisco, CA 94127, USA. Email: <email>rbrandi@earthlink.net</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>5</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>133</fpage>
<lpage>153</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>In 1951, architect Vernon DeMars produced an ambitious urban renewal plan for a nearly vacant and hilly site in the middle of San Francisco. The plan called for a mix of houses, apartments, and high rises, all suited to take advance of the views, and a shopping center, churches, playgrounds, and schools. Built from 1961 to 1981 with designs by Joseph Esherick, Claude Oakland, working for builder Joseph Eichler, and others, Diamond Heights was critically acclaimed at the time but now is unknown, a unique example of urban renewal and modernist city planning.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>urban renewal</kwd>
<kwd>modern architecture</kwd>
<kwd>city planning</kwd>
<kwd>Vernon DeMars</kwd>
<kwd>Joseph Eichler</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1538513212456970">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Scholars are reevaluating the legacy of postwar federal urban renewal (1949 to 1973) and the means to preserve it.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1538513212456970">1</xref>
</sup> Much of the existing literature emphasizes the negative consequences of urban renewal—that it blithely destroyed hundreds of vibrant neighborhoods in a heavy handed imitation of Le Corbuiser’s Radiant city, forced thousands of the urban poor and black from their homes, and bulldozed hundreds of acres of irreplaceable urban fabric.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1538513212456970">2</xref>
</sup> The physical legacy of urban renewal—with its mid-century architectural style, sleek surfaces shorn of ornament, and expansive plazas sited close to freeways—is often portrayed as bleak, cold, uninviting, too autocentered, and full of wasted spaces.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1538513212456970">3</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Urban renewal is undergoing a reevaluation by scholars who see it as a much more complicated phenomenon than previously credited. <sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1538513212456970">4</xref>
</sup> Some scholars see urban renewal as a justified or inevitable response to the real problems cities faced in the middle of the twentieth century.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1538513212456970">5</xref>
</sup> Those who appreciate modern architecture or the recent past see much that deserves to be preserved for its historical and architectural significance. Many agree urban renewal was so large and multifarious that simple generalizations are impossible. While the debate has been renewed, a revised consensus has not yet been reached.</p>
<p>San Francisco embarked upon federal urban renewal in the 1950s and 1960s with many of the same goals and intentions as other cities and with the full panoply of projects, including slum and skid row clearance, downtown luxury high-rise living, office buildings, hotels, convention and cultural centers, middle-income housing developments, low-income housing projects, and light industrial parks.</p>
<p>This article looks at San Francisco’s experience with urban renewal through the experience of a large project that has received scant attention: Diamond Heights. The legacy of urban renewal in San Francisco is usually portrayed as a battle between class and race through the examples of the Yebra Buena and Western Addition projects.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1538513212456970">6</xref>
</sup> While the latter projects were significant, there are only two of nine urban renewal projects implemented in the city during 1949 to 1973 (Western Addition A-1 and A-2, Diamond Heights, South of Market, Golden Gateway, Chinese Cultural Center, Hunters Point, Indian Basin, and Stockton/Sacramento). During this time, four proposed projects were dropped (Mission Street Corridor, Community Renewal Program, Italian Cultural Center, Regal Pale Brewery).<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-1538513212456970">7</xref>
</sup> Additionally, various conservation, rehabilitation, and code enforcement activities were undertaken by the redevelopment agency and other city departments during the 1960s and 1970s. The variety of San Francisco’s urban renewal projects makes sweeping generalizations impossible on the basis of the Western Addition and Yerba Buena projects.</p>
<p>Of the nine projects, Diamond Heights rivals the Western Addition and Yerba Buena projects in terms of size and impact. The Diamond Heights project did not involve massive residential displacement nor did they disproportionately affect black people. Because Diamond Heights appears to be atypical and quite successful, an understanding of its significance may broaden the legacy of urban renewal in San Francisco.</p>
<p>Although it is San Francisco’s largest urban renewal project by acreage, it has received scant attention.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-1538513212456970">8</xref>
</sup> Designated a redevelopment area in 1950, Diamond Heights is home to 7,900 people who live in a variety of single-family houses, duplexes, rental apartments, and condominiums built between 1961 and 1981. Approximately 20 percent of the units are federally assisted housing.</p>
<p>There is also a 50,000-square-foot shopping center, three churches, firehouse, two playgrounds, a primary school (now used by the San Francisco Police Academy), and a high school.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-1538513212456970">9</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Diamond Heights covers three hills in the center of San Francisco and it is physically isolated from adjourning neighborhoods due to the steep topography (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1538513212456970">Figure 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-1538513212456970" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Diamond Heights Redevelopment Project (shaded black), north is top of map. <italic>Source</italic>: San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, “Redevelopment in Diamond Heights,” Plate 1, March 1950.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538513212456970-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The hills provide commanding vistas of downtown San Francisco and the East Bay when not obscured by fog. Platted using the standard street grid, the resultant slopes were too steep even for San Francisco: 1/3 of the streets had a slope greater than 20 percent and 1/3 had a slope greater than 30 percent.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-1538513212456970">10</xref>
</sup> Many parcels were inaccessible and most streets existed only on paper. By 1950, less than 10 percent of the land contained structures.</p>
<p>The San Francisco Redevelopment Agency hoped Diamond Heights would reduce the housing shortage and also make it easier for those about to be displaced by the Western Addition project to find housing. “The new housing provided by redevelopment Area B [i.e. Diamond Heights] would ease the San Francisco housing shortage, making possible more rapid redevelopment of built up areas of blight.”<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-1538513212456970">11</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The agency knew that many residents of the Western Addition could not afford Diamond Heights but hoped that easing the overall demand for housing would make more affordable housing available elsewhere.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-1538513212456970">12</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<sec id="section2-1538513212456970">
<title>Redeveloping Vacant Land</title>
<p>The proposal to designate 325 acres of nearly vacant land as “blighted” was not typical.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13-1538513212456970">13</xref>
</sup> Neither a slum nor a deteriorated district, Diamond Heights was largely in a natural state (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-1538513212456970">Figure 2</xref>). But faulty street plans that made development difficult or impossible was one of the characteristics of blight in the California Community Redevelopment Act.</p>
<fig id="fig2-1538513212456970" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Diamond Heights looking north before redevelopment, circa 1950s. The Miraloma Park middle-class neighborhood is in the foreground and downtown San Francisco is in the background. <italic>Source</italic>: Anna Bland Smith, <italic>San Francisco’s Glen Park and Diamond Heights</italic>, 119.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538513212456970-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Diamond Heights appeared to have several advantages. More than one-half of the land was owned by the city or state and did not need to be purchased or condemned.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14-1538513212456970">14</xref>
</sup> This included Glen Canyon that had been acquired as a site for a reservoir during the 1910s but was no longer needed. At the base of the canyon was a city-owned park and playground. The San Francisco Public Housing Authority owned three blocks but had not built anything.</p>
<p>Another advantage was the scarcity of paved or graded streets. Although grading and contouring the hilly site would be necessary, the project would not be constrained by an existing street system, so it could be designed with modern principles of subdivision planning. Finally, the relatively few existing structures meant that the displacement of residents, which had slowed the Western Addition project, should not pose a problem. The project area had a population of only 374 people and 158 houses, along with a few stables, two abandoned quarries, and a truck storage yard.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15-1538513212456970">15</xref>
</sup> The agency hoped to be able to move these buildings but ultimately seventy structures were retained and rehabilitated.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16-1538513212456970">16</xref>
</sup> Most of these are located in the southern boundary of the project area where the project boundaries meshed with the existing streets.</p>
<p>However, contrary to the Redevelopment Agency’s hopes, the Diamond Heights project drew adverse public reaction, mainly from residents who lived or owned property in the area.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17-1538513212456970">17</xref>
</sup> There were several concerns: the area was not blighted, the loss of the rural atmosphere, the project’s boundary lines were arbitrarily drawn, too many existing houses were included in the project area, and there was distrust whether property owners would receive a fair price. Some felt the agency was inconsistent by allowing so-called cracker box houses to remain within the project area.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18-1538513212456970">18</xref>
</sup> One property owner in Diamond Heights compared the uncertainty posed by redevelopment to the fear of nuclear war:<disp-quote>
<p>Now, we have lived with the strain around here for the last three or four years about the atom bomb but I hope to God we got no bomb on us from the Planning Commission. I think I have got more trust in my fellow man than that but I don’t know.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19-1538513212456970">19</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>The Agency Chairman said he thought that 113 of the 158 houses in the project area could remain.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20-1538513212456970">20</xref>
</sup> In general, the agency attempted to give owners a number of options: they could move their house and sell the lot, sell the lot and house, or exchange their property for other lots in the project area.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21-1538513212456970">21</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Despite objections, the tentative plan for Diamond Heights was finalized in March 1952, but it was almost ten years before housing was built in Diamond Heights. There were a number of reasons for the delay. The Redevelopment Agency admitted that the scope of the project was greater than they had anticipated. There were protracted negotiations with other city departments.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22-1538513212456970">22</xref>
</sup> The project was stalled until the constitutionality of California’s Community Redevelopment Law was resolved. <sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23-1538513212456970">23</xref>
</sup> A court confirmed that the “faulty planning” of streets met the definition of blight under California law.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24-1538513212456970">24</xref>
</sup> After its finding, the United States Supreme Court issued its far-reaching decision in <italic>Berman v. Parker</italic> (1954),<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn101-1538513212456970">101</xref></sup> upholding the constitutionality of the District of Columbia Redevelopment Act.</p>
<p>In January 1956, the project finally began when the Housing and Home Finance Agency prepared a loan and capital grant for Diamond Heights.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25-1538513212456970">25</xref>
</sup> The San Francisco Redevelopment Agency spent the next three years buying or condemning land before securing the total of 636 parcels.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26-1538513212456970">26</xref>
</sup> Eventually, about one-half of the privately held land was purchased, and the other half was condemned under eminent domain.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27-1538513212456970">27</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>It appears that the Redevelopment Agency would allow houses to remain as long as the land was not needed for streets or community facilities.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28-1538513212456970">28</xref>
</sup> Several pre-1950 homes exist in the redevelopment area, mostly along the project area’s southern and eastern edges. From 1960 to1962, the agency graded the area and orchestrated the laying of streets, underground utilities, sewers, and streetlights.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29-1538513212456970">29</xref>
</sup> Two million cubic yards of earth was moved and the soil was used to construct a flat area for the community center and parking lot between Red Rock Hill and Gold Mine Hill.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30-1538513212456970">30</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1538513212456970">
<title>Community Planning by Vernon DeMars</title>
<p>In 1951, Architect Vernon DeMars produced the plan for Diamond Heights. He envisioned a middle-class community of singles, couples, and larger families. Residents would have a choice of living in high-rise towers, one-, two-, or three-story row houses, or two-or-three story apartment blocks and condominiums. The neighborhood would have its own shopping center, schools, churches, firehouse, and playgrounds<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31-1538513212456970">31</xref>
</sup> (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-1538513212456970">Figure 3</xref>). Diamond Heights was built largely to his plan although the high rises were not constructed.</p>
<fig id="fig3-1538513212456970" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Model of the Diamond Heights Project in 1960 looking south. Five towers are shown on Red Rock Hill. <italic>Source</italic>: Crown Zellerbach Corporation, The City of Gold, The Story of City Planning in San Francisco, 1960, 35.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538513212456970-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>DeMars received a BA in architecture from University of California, Berkeley, in 1931. He was the district architect of the Farm Security Administration (1936–42) in San Francisco where he worked on low-cost housing. DeMars was the chief of housing standards at the National Housing Agency from 1943 to 1944 and he entered private practice n 1945. He joined the faculty of U.C. Berkeley’s architecture department in 1953, the same year that he began a fifteen-year partnership with architect Donald Reay. The farmworker housing DeMars designed during the 1930s owed much to International Style prototypes, namely the parallel rows of housing oriented to the sun. Le Corbusier’s hypothetical design for a farmstead was the model for a Yuba City, California project.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32-1538513212456970">32</xref>
</sup> But DeMars was also concerned with community planning along the lines of the neighborhood unit concept of the Regional Plan of New York (1929). His design for a farmworker settlement in Woodville, California (1940), employed many elements of the neighborhood unit concept, which he also used in the plan for Diamond Heights.</p>
<p>DeMars’ curvilinear street design transverse the hilly site and enabled each house or townhouse to have street access and an opportunity for views. Preserving and maximizing views for the future residents was integral to the concept. DeMars envisioned high-rise apartments on the summit of Red Rock Hill surrounded by two- to three-story structures. Apartments would step down the slopes so as to preserve the views from the apartments on the upper slopes while Gold Mine Hill and Fairmount Hill would consist solely of low-rise structures (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-1538513212456970">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig4-1538513212456970" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>DeMars’ Design for Red Rock Hill in Diamond Heights. <italic>Source</italic>: San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, Tentative Plan, 1951, plate 15.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538513212456970-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Access was provided by one major street, Diamond Heights Boulevard. This four-lane boulevard gently winds its way south from Clipper Street, then steeply descends and narrows into the Glen Park neighborhood. Side streets branch off along contours around the hills. The limited access provided by Diamond Heights Boulevard discourages traffic from other parts of the city from driving through Diamond Heights, as DeMars had intended. In 1956, Carl Feiss called the plan “an extraordinarily sympathetic scheme on the steepest possible terrain (even for San Francisco) as delightful and informal a community as is to be found in the annals of contemporary town design.”<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33-1538513212456970">33</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The Redevelopment Agency started sales in 1961 before grading was completed.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34-1538513212456970">34</xref>
</sup> The agency claimed that the land was sold “under architectural standards believed to be as high as any in any public development in the country,” by which they meant the use of design competitions for major projects and design review of individual houses, both subject to conformity with DeMars general site plan.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35-1538513212456970">35</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The Red Rock Hill site was a high-profile undertaking that received extensive news media and critical attention. In June 1961, the agency held what it called an experimental design competition in an attempt to secure high-quality design.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36-1538513212456970">36</xref>
</sup> The agency claimed this was the only one of its kind in the nation and acknowledged the willingness of the federal Urban Renewal Agency of Housing and Home Finance Agency to allow for the novel approach.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37-1538513212456970">37</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The program for Red Rock Hill was to accommodate 990 apartments on the twenty-two-acre site. The agency hired an advisory committee made up of six local architects and developers (architects John Carl Warnecke, Ernest J. Kump, Don Burkholder, and developers Sanford B. Weiss and Gerson Bakar) to determine the strengths and weaknesses of the submissions. Of ninety entries, ten were judged worthy of receiving a $1,000 award. The agency rejected six designs for various reasons, leaving developers a choice of four. The twenty-two-acre Red Rock parcel was offered for sale to the highest bidder with the proviso that the winning bidder use one of the four approved designs and the associated architects.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38-1538513212456970">38</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>All four designs combined several multistory high-rise towers with one-to-three-story buildings. The common tower/low-rise motif was probably due to the presence of DeMars’ concept, the need to fit nearly 1,000 units on a twenty-two-acre site, and a San Francisco City Planning Department desire to place tall structures on hilltops. The designs exhibited “an informality but with a strong San Francisco character that stepped up to monumentality” according to the redevelopment agency.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39-1538513212456970">39</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The winner of the land auction was San Francisco Redevelopers and they selected the design by Cohen and Levorsen of San Francisco. San Francisco Redevelopers, Inc., was a partnership of Irvin Kahn of San Diego and Norman Smith.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40-1538513212456970">40</xref>
</sup> Architect B. Clyde Cohen, AIA, attended MIT and the University of California, Berkeley, and received a BA and an MA in architecture. James K. Levorsen attended Stanford University and the University of Okalahoma and received a BA in architecture. Both claimed to have a wide range of experience in designing apartment buildings and tract and custom homes.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41-1538513212456970">41</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The Cohen and Levorsen design called for 340 apartments in low-rise structures and 650 apartments in high-rise towers. The towers varied from seven to twelve stories and were connected to form chains that undulated in plan and elevation (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-1538513212456970">Figure 5</xref>). The low-rise structures were also connected to form chains with two-story apartments over a parking level. The architectural advisory panel considered the Cohen and Levorsen design to be well conceived and tightly disciplined while allowing the structures to follow the topography naturally. The panel particularly liked the way the entire project resembled the “sophisticated” San Francisco’s row house.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42-1538513212456970">42</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<fig id="fig5-1538513212456970" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Cohen and Levorsen’s Wining Design for Red Rock Hill. <italic>Source</italic>: San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, “Architectural Advisory Panel Evaluation Report Diamond Heights Red Rock Hill Competition,” June 30, 1961, 27.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538513212456970-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Simultaneous with the first phase of Red Rock, the Redevelopment Agency hired architect Lawrence Lackey and landscape architects Royston, Hanamoto, and Mayes, to prepare a schematic plan for an eighteen-acre community center to be located in the saddle between Red Rock Hill and Gold Mine Hill.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43-1538513212456970">43</xref>
</sup> Their plan took the shape of a diamond with a shopping center on the right, a grammar school on the left, and a church at the top of the diamond. Connecting these facilities was a five-acre playground and landscaping enabling pedestrians to circulate. The designers recommended a modest and informal design of residential character. They stressed the need for the roofs, buildings masses, and open spaces to be aesthetically pleasing when seen from above, as the center would be overlooked by houses on Red Rock Hill and Gold Mine Hill. The shopping center, designed by Morris and Lohrbach, opened in 1965 with 43,000 square feet of ground level space, 7,000 feet of second-story space, and 150,000 square feet of ground-level parking for 340 cars<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44-1538513212456970">44</xref>
</sup> (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-1538513212456970">Figure 6</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig6-1538513212456970" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Shopping center circa 1965. <italic>Source</italic>: Anna Bland Smith, <italic>San Francisco’s Glen Park and Diamond Heights</italic>, 122.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538513212456970-fig6.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The developer of both Red Rock Hill and the shopping center was San Francisco Redevelopers which ran into financial difficulties and stopped work in 1964. According to newspaper accounts, the shopping center was then about 85 percent complete, the townhouses along Diamond Heights Boulevard were about 60 percent finished, and the high-rise towers had not been started.</p>
<p>The townhouses, built under General Electric’s Medallion all-electric home program with electric radiant ceiling heating and all-electric kitchens, were selling more slowly than expected. The developer’s plans for building five, fifteen-story apartment towers were cut back to three or four.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45-1538513212456970">45</xref>
</sup> San Francisco Redevelopers resumed construction in December 1964.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn46-1538513212456970">46</xref>
</sup> San Francisco Redevelopers eventually completed the shopping center but sold their interests in the townhouses and apartment towers to General Electric in 1965 after a loss of $1.5 million.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47-1538513212456970">47</xref>
</sup> The only part of the Cohen and Levorsen scheme that was realized are the townhouses along Diamond Heights Boulevard that appear to incorporate the undulating linkages of the original design (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-1538513212456970">Figure 7</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig7-1538513212456970" position="float">
<label>Figure 7.</label>
<caption>
<p>Townhouses by Cohen and Levorsen (Author 2008).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538513212456970-fig7.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>General Electric (GE) entered urban redevelopment to showcase its all-electric living concept (GE Medallion Home, Live Better Electrically). Beginning in 1963, with an unsuccessful bid with First Hartford Realty Company to construct high rises in Hartford Connecticut’s Bushnell Plaza renewal area, GE later joined with Reynolds Metals in a redevelopment project for Louisville’s waterfront. In 1965, GE took over the Red Rock project.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn48-1538513212456970">48</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>GE further reduced the planned number of towers to two but did not resume construction on the townhouses until December 1967.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn49-1538513212456970">49</xref>
</sup> By then, the plan for Red Rock Hill had been scaled back further. There would be only one tower, and half of the twenty-two acres were rezoned for lower densities, while the densities on the other half were sharply increased. According to press accounts, the cost of land was excessive for the densities in the original plan and the resultant rent levels would be too high for the market.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn50-1538513212456970">50</xref>
</sup> General Electric pulled out in 1968 after completing only the townhouses. The high-rise towers were never built because they would have been too expensive to construct for the rents that could be charged.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn51-1538513212456970">51</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The Ring Brothers, a southern California developer of multi-unit housing, took over after General Electric. Instead of apartment towers, the Ring Brothers constructed a complex of three- and four-story apartments, called Diamond Heights Village, to a 1972 design by Arthur Gensler and Joseph Esherick.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn52-1538513212456970">52</xref>
</sup> The Ring Brothers also constructed condominiums on the site.</p>
<p>In 1961, the Redevelopment Agency sold three parcels for church sites along Diamond Heights Boulevard. St. Adian’s Episcopal Church was completed in 1963, St. Nicholas Orthodox Church in 1964, and Missouri Synod Lutheran Church in 1965 (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-1538513212456970">Figure 8</xref>). A firehouse designed by Rockrise and Watson was completed in 1963 in a brutalist vein and a high school was designed by Reid &amp; Tarics Associates and built in 1972. By 1964, 60 percent of the land had been sold. The final land sales were held in 1971 for scattered sites on Gold Mine Hill and Fairmont Hill. <sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn53-1538513212456970">53</xref>
</sup> Overall, Diamond Heights contains fifteen residential housing projects ranging in size from 21 to 396 units and 647 single-family homes or duplexes. Some of the major developers include the Ring Brothers, Eichler Homes, and Galli Construction.</p>
<fig id="fig8-1538513212456970" position="float">
<label>Figure 8.</label>
<caption>
<p>Missouri Synod Lutheran Church (Author 2008).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538513212456970-fig8.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>The Ring Brothers built more units than any other developer in Diamond Heights: 719 units in four projects, comprising 32 percent of the total number of units. The firm hired Fisher, Friedman and Associates to design condominiums on Carnelian Way and Topaz Way.</p>
<p>Eichler Homes built 100 houses in Diamond Heights, their first homes in San Francisco. The three- and four-bedroom designs were offered in a choice of six floor plans priced at $34,950 to $46,500.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn54-1538513212456970">54</xref>
</sup> Architect Claude Oakland designed the street facades with garage doors and blank walls on the ground story and narrow vertical windows on the second story. Inside, each house had an open court, front entrance patio, or deck off the rear with nearly floor-to-ceiling glass siding doors. The second story contained three or four bedrooms. These homes were built on the north side of Amethyst, both sides of Amber Drive, and the north side of Cameo Way at Duncan.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn55-1538513212456970">55</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The Galli Construction Company, a family-owned San Francisco builder, constructed sixty-three houses in Diamond Heights to designs by architects Hayes &amp; Smith. The three- and four-bedroom, two-and-a-half bath houses features pitched roofs, a thirteen-foot ceiling in the family room, and extensive wood siding and cedar shingles.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn56-1538513212456970">56</xref>
</sup> This was the first time the company had used architects in thirty-eight years of business, “but we’re sold. We pay more for design but we get more.”<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn57-1538513212456970">57</xref>
</sup> The houses sold for $40,000–$45,000. Hayes &amp; Smith also produced a one-story plan for downward sloping hillside lots with 1,580 square feet of interior space, an atrium, and a 700-square-foot deck. The three-bedroom, two-bath homes cost $42,500.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn58-1538513212456970">58</xref>
</sup> A number of other builders were involved in Diamond Heights.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn59-1538513212456970">59</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The agency also sold lots by auction directly to individuals who wished to build custom homes.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn60-1538513212456970">60</xref>
</sup> The first individual owners to build a house in Diamond Heights were Mr. and Mrs. Allan Unger. A groundbreaking ceremony was held on November 1, 1961, and was attended by local officials, the chairman of the Redevelopment Agency, and the news media. The Ungers purchased a lot at 120 Turquoise Way that overlooked Glen Canyon for $8,950 on May 9, 1961. At the auction, architect Max R. Garcia approached the couple and offered them his services. The Ungers did not know Garcia but they hired him anyway, confident that “Anyone can build a house.”<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn61-1538513212456970">61</xref>
</sup> The seven-room, three- and one-half bath house cost $35,000.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn62-1538513212456970">62</xref>
</sup> These custom houses cost about twice as much as tract houses did at the time such as the one the Unger’s bought in Daly City a couple of years before. The Unger’s property was on the lower slopes of Red Rock Hill and not subject to formal plan review. But the Redevelopment Agency did pressure builders and owners to conform to the agency’s goals of a harmonious composition of masses, colors, textures, and roofs when viewed from public rights of way. Architects on the Redevelopment Agency staff informally reviewed plans and made suggestions for improved designs. Most accepted their recommendations.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn63-1538513212456970">63</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Diamond Heights also has nearly 500 units of low-income housing.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn64-1538513212456970">64</xref>
</sup> This was not public housing in the sense that was commonly understood at the time. The housing was not owned or operated by the San Francisco Public Housing Agency.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn65-1538513212456970">65</xref>
</sup> Instead, using special low-cost Federal Housing Administration (FHA) loans, limiting developers’ profits, and setting artificially low prices for lots, the Redevelopment Agency encouraged private builders to undertake the construction.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn66-1538513212456970">66</xref>
</sup> With low-cost land and financing, the developers could afford to build housing that could be profitability rented or sold at below-market rates. Justin Herman, the Redevelopment Agency director, called this housing “privately built, privately owned, and moderate income” to distinguish it from public housing or housing for welfare recipients. He also insisted that the developers use much higher-quality design so the projects did not look like public housing projects.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn67-1538513212456970">67</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The controversy then taking place about displacing black families from the Western Addition redevelopment project was a key factor in the agency’s concern with rehousing the “below-moderate-income families.” The Redevelopment Agency anticipated a sharp rise in the volume of displacements and wanted to build large volumes of moderate-priced private housing in redevelopment areas to meet the need.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn68-1538513212456970">68</xref>
</sup> While acknowledging that the Redevelopment Agency had no responsibility for public housing, the agency recognized that racial discrimination was a deterrent to relocation. During 1961, the Redevelopment Agency and the Board of Supervisors unanimously adopted a policy of allocating sites for subsidized housing, and on January 18, 1962, the agency allocated four sites in Diamond Heights for moderate-priced private housing.</p>
<p>After a design competition, the Redevelopment Agency selected three developers who offered designs that did not resemble the typical public housing: Robert Chuckrow Construction, San Francisco Redevelopers, and the Mission Neighborhood Centers.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn69-1538513212456970">69</xref>
</sup> The four sites would hold a total of 471 units. The first complex of 275 units, called <italic>Glenridge,</italic> was a cooperative built with low-interest, long-term loans. Buyers would enjoy low monthly payments but would not be able to sell at a profit during the first twenty years. The other projects would be low-cost apartment rentals.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn70-1538513212456970">70</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>However, the proposal to build moderate-income housing in Diamond Heights was opposed by some property owners in Diamond Heights and Glen Park. One problem was that, in an effort to reduce unit costs, the agency wanted to rezone certain sites for higher densities. The protesters feared that higher densities and the provision to limit purchasers to those making less than $6,400 for a family of two would reduce property values. As one resident explained, “our homes go up in value on the open market but who wants to buy a $40,000 house surrounded by low cost semi-public houses valued at one-fourth the price?”<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn71-1538513212456970">71</xref>
</sup> Others voiced concerns that the below-market purchase price would attract a lower strata of the population. The protesters said the issue was not race: “I can hardly believe my ears that this has become a racial issue. Glen Park is already integrated and has been for years,” said Mrs. Dorothy Pariani, president of the Glen Park Property Owners Association.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn72-1538513212456970">72</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Justin Herman tried to reassure the protesters that the moderate-income projects would not create a slum. He explained “undesirable families” would not be able to qualify because FHA required purchasers to have enough money to maintain their houses. He said, “welfare recipients” would not qualify and the people buying these homes “will in their own self interest throw out objectionable families to uphold the neighborhood.”<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn73-1538513212456970">73</xref>
</sup> Herman prevailed and the Board of Supervisors approved the zoning change.</p>
<p>Herman explained the importance of providing affordable housing for people displaced by relocation, of which 90 percent were black. The problem was not limited to racial discrimination: according to Herman, “If it were theoretically possible to eliminate discrimination, Negroes still don’t make enough money to get into housing in San Francisco.”<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn74-1538513212456970">74</xref>
</sup> The answer, he thought, was to provide job training so that blacks could get higher paying jobs. In the meantime, public housing or its equivalent was needed. Herman thought he had found a way in Diamond Heights by what he called the Robin Hood plan.</p>
<p>His plan involved selling land at very low prices for moderate-income housing and setting higher prices in the rest of the project. “The moderate income residents [on lots sold for $1,547] will have as much play area and view as people in $65,000 houses.”<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn75-1538513212456970">75</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Diamond Heights won critical acclaim. <italic>Progressive Magazine</italic> awarded Cohen and Levorsen a citation for residential design in 1964 for Red Rock Hill.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn76-1538513212456970">76</xref>
</sup> Galli Construction Company and its architects, Hayes &amp; Smith, received an award from <italic>Practical Builder Magazine</italic> for the design of a two-story over-garage townhouse.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn77-1538513212456970">77</xref>
</sup> <italic>House and Home</italic> said the process used in Diamond Heights “resulted in high standards of center-city housing without the cookie-cutter sameness that can come from a single developer.”<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn78-1538513212456970">78</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Writing at the time of construction, Roger Montgomery favorably cited Diamond Heights for its design process. He said that the Redevelopment Agency worked with reliable market information, allowed changes to be made without long bureaucratic delays, and permitted powerful public leadership to influence design without sacrificing flexibility.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn79-1538513212456970">79</xref>
</sup> The Redevelopment Agency exerted leadership in design by the use of a conceptual plan discussing prototypical form, height, and scale; design competitions with the option of several approved designs for developers to choose from; and the subtle but effective pressure the agency exerted over the designs of hundreds of custom homes.</p>
<p>However, recent critics do not hold Diamond Heights in such high esteem. Architecture critic Sally Woodbridge says of Diamond Heights, “The general architectural level is undistinguished and does not compare favorably with older parts of the city.”<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn80-1538513212456970">80</xref>
</sup> Peter Booth Wiley calls it, “A solid middle class community. However, the project did little to enhance the reputation of its architects or to recommend this prime location as a desirable place to live. Many of the buildings are looking a little bit shabby, owing to the use of cheap materials.”<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn81-1538513212456970">81</xref>
</sup> Wiley’s reference to cheap materials may refer to the architectural style of Diamond Heights. Most of the structures fall loosely under the rubric of the post–World War II Bay Area Tradition. That is to say, many of the homes use flat or shed roofs; exterior wood siding; a sense of informality; easy access to the outdoors though patios; decks or atriums; and are sited with to take advantage of the view<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn82-1538513212456970">82</xref>
</sup> (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-1538513212456970">Figure 9</xref>). However, Diamond Heights was the product of many architects. Little is known about many of these architects, since only a few have local or regional reputations.</p>
<fig id="fig9-1538513212456970" position="float">
<label>Figure 9.</label> <caption>
<p>Turquoise Way (Author 2008).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538513212456970-fig9.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1538513212456970">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Diamond Heights cannot be easily compared to other urban redevelopment projects in San Francisco or in other cities. Diamond Heights has features found in some urban residential redevelopment projects, 1950s suburban subdivisions, and traditional San Francisco neighborhoods. Many projects in other cities were concerned with blighted areas or slums that were located in or adjacent to the downtown or were located in highly urban places. Many urban renewal residential projects were not large enough to include the full range of services needed in a modern neighborhood and could support little more than a convenience store.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn83-1538513212456970">83</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Diamond Heights was not a slum or blighted in the conventional sense, was surrounded by middle-class residential neighborhoods far from downtown, and was not all that urban. Diamond Heights ignored the street grid but used a conventional, curvilinear street system, not superblocks. It was also designed with a full range of neighborhood amenities. Comparing the design of Diamond Heights with other developments is also not straightforward. Although questions of design are fraught with the dangers of subjectivity and changing notions of taste, redevelopment project designs were often controversial.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn84-1538513212456970">84</xref>
</sup> Public housing projects are often faulted for an excessive reliance on modernist high rises in the large cities of the East and Midwest.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn85-1538513212456970">85</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>However, many residential redevelopment projects including market-rate and low-income housing exhibit design excellence. Successful designs include Portland Center in Portland, Oregon, by Skidmore, Owings &amp; Merrill, and Lawrence Halprin &amp; Associates (1968–71); St. Louis Plaza Square by Harris Armstrong and Hellmuth, Obata &amp; Kassabaum (1960–61); St. Francis Square by Marquis &amp; Stoller and Halprin (1963–65) in San Francisco’s Western Addition; Minneapolis’s Cedar Square West by Ralph Rapson (1968–73); and Chicago’s Hyde Park by I. M. Pei and Harry Weese (1957–61).<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn86-1538513212456970">86</xref>
</sup> Also, notable is Lafayette Park in Detroit by Mies van der Rohe and others (begun 1956).</p>
<p>In common with other urban redevelopment projects, Diamond Heights’s purpose was to attract the middle class to live in San Francisco by offering many of the amenities found in suburbia. Diamond Heights quickly became a middle- or upper-income neighborhood of 7,900 residents. Of that total, 458 units (20 percent) were federally assisted housing (the goal was up to 500 units).<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn87-1538513212456970">87</xref>
</sup> These statistics, the financial success of the land auctions, and the story of the Ungers, who moved from the suburbs to Diamond Heights, suggest that the urban renewal program goals were achieved.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn88-1538513212456970">88</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The original designer, Vernon DeMars, felt the project turned out “very much as we thought:”<disp-quote>
<p>Then we had these different kinds of housing types more or less zoned for different streets and different areas and locations. This was pretty much carried out . . . And since what we proposed was so general, whatever they did, if they followed the rule roughly, would be acceptable. I mean, it was exactly our idea, except that we had in mind some higher apartment houses in the middle of it. They didn’t quite do that. It doesn’t have the image of projecting up and making a tower that you can see from around and say, “That’s Diamond Heights.” That’s the only part that didn’t go. But <italic>that</italic> project I don’t feel disappointed in.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn89-1538513212456970">89</xref>
</sup>
</p>
</disp-quote></p>
<p>Comparison can also be made with suburban subdivisions because Diamond Heights looks and feels like a suburb and it contains many of the ideal suburban amenities: convenient automobile access to downtown, generous and free automobile parking at the shopping center, unlimited street or off-street parking for homes and apartments, a quiet and safe street layout, nearby playgrounds, and proximity to nature. The Redevelopment Agency contrasted Diamond Heights with the nearby Miraloma Park built in the 1930s. In Diamond Heights, “we may look towards an even more complete job of neighborhood reconstruction based on up to date principles of community design.” Such principles include homes with “sweeping views . . . scientifically oriented to get plenty of sunshine and little wind . . . quiet streets  . . . enough off street parking” at the neighborhood shopping center yet that are located “so most housewives could walk” to shopping for their daily needs.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn90-1538513212456970">90</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>The emphasis on walking is not usually associated with contemporary suburban living (although the neighborhood unit concept did foster pedestrian access to community services). In that sense, it may be useful to think of Diamond Heights as marrying the conveniences of the suburbs with the desirable characteristics of San Francisco’s traditional neighborhoods. Desirable San Francisco characteristics include views from the houses, the two- to three-story row house form, considerable architectural variety within the same street, short walking distances to local shopping, and convenient public transit to downtown.</p>
<p>Diamond Heights succeeded in maximizing the views for the residents’ enjoyment. The Redevelopment Agency reiterated the importance of views in its design competition, for its low-income housing, and for the entire project area. The importance of views probably reflects the site’s natural advantages and the increased market value of views.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn91-1538513212456970">91</xref>
</sup> Diamond Heights also offered considerable architectural variation and has public transit feeder service to connect with downtown lines as do most San Francisco neighborhoods.</p>
<p>Unlike most of San Francisco, Diamond Heights had a master plan. Most residential districts in San Francisco were platted using the standard street grid and homes were built by large numbers of small-scale builders. A notable exception at the beginning of the twentieth century was the construction of eleven residential developments (called residential parks). These developments were self-consciously influenced by the ideals of the Garden City and City Beautiful movements and are characterized by curvilinear streets with large, detached homes and often with common green spaces and grand boulevards. They are exclusively residential and did not include, indeed they universally prohibited, commercial uses in the districts.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn92-1538513212456970">92</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>But these were the exception and the pattern reverted to merchant builders or other entrepreneurs who built rows of houses or small apartments on the standard street grid.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn93-1538513212456970">93</xref>
</sup> The merchant builders do not resemble the community builders who comprehensively planned developments such as Duncan McDuffie in St. Francis Wood or Harry B. Allen in Sea Cliff. <sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn94-1538513212456970">94</xref>
</sup> Instead, they were often family-run businesses concerned with building affordable houses quickly on the standard city grid in a range of facades to suit current tastes. After World War II, a few larger-scale residential projects were undertaken by private industry in San Francisco, but these are not comparable to Diamond Heights because they lacked integral planning, comprehensive design, and neighborhood facilities.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn95-1538513212456970">95</xref>
</sup> Diamond Heights may be a unique example of urban renewal, although all projects faced specific situations and impacted the larger community in different ways.</p>
<p>Finally, another way to look at Diamond Heights is to ask what would have happened if it had not been a redevelopment project. Critics of urban redevelopment since the time of Jane Jacobs and Martin Anderson have argued urban redevelopment was not necessary because market forces and private industry would have eventually undertaken whatever rebuilding was needed. There may be enough evidence to speculate about what would have happened to the Diamond Heights area if it had not been redeveloped.</p>
<p>After World War II, merchant builders were active in many parts of San Francisco. Houses and apartment buildings were going up on Twin Peaks adjacent to Diamond Heights throughout the 1950s and 1960s. Indeed, small-scale home building was occurring in Diamond Heights, on the southern slopes of Fairmont Hill, in the early 1950s. The original southern boundary of the project area was shortened and moved up Fairmont Hill (from Laidley Street to Bemis and Miguel streets), probably because construction was taking place on these streets as the project was being debated.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn96-1538513212456970">96</xref>
</sup> The litigants who sued the Redevelopment Agency claimed that private development was possible in at least some areas and that the large sections owned by the city could have been subdivided and replatted fairly easily.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn97-1538513212456970">97</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>If private developers had been allowed or encouraged to work in Diamond Heights, they probably would have used the patterns that were then in effect. Although it is impossible to predict what would have happened, it is reasonable to suppose that existing streets would have been extended where feasible and new ones cut through with minimal grading. One can imagine that this would have led to ad hoc developments without the comprehensive grading scheme and community facilities found in Diamond Heights. The lower and more easily accessible sites would have been built first. These homes probably would have been smaller and cost less than the $40,000–50,000 custom homes built later in Diamond Heights<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn98-1538513212456970">98</xref>
</sup> (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-1538513212456970">Figure 10</xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig10-1538513212456970" position="float">
<label>Figure 10.</label>
<caption>
<p>Construction of houses by private developers on the edge of Diamond Heights (left) circa 1951. <italic>Source</italic>: San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, Tentative Plan, plate 17.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1538513212456970-fig10.tif"/>
</fig>
<p>Speculating a bit further, by the time the lower sites were occupied in the late 1950s or early 1960s, inflation and the higher market values accruing to view sites would have made it profitable to develop the steeper slopes and summits. At the same time, growing environmental awareness might have pressured the city to preserve the summits as open space or parks. This pattern was seen during the 1950s and 1960s in a number of other sites including Twin Peaks, Golden Gate Heights, Mount Sutro, Edgehill, Mount Davidson, Tank Hill, and Bernal Heights.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn99-1538513212456970">99</xref>
</sup>
</p>
<p>Instead, Diamond Heights was developed with a strong design bias toward providing views for the buildings’ occupants. As a result, the public generally does not have access to the views, except along patches of some streets on Fairmont Hill and Gold Mine Hill. None of the summits are available to the public.<sup>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn100-1538513212456970">100</xref>
</sup> This lack of public access and the absence of an overlook may contribute to Diamond Heights’ anonymity because it has not become a destination for viewing such as occurs on Twin Peaks and other summits. If redevelopment had not occurred, it is possible that the summits of Red Rock Hill, Gold Mine Hill, and Fairmont Hill would be open to the public.</p>
<p>Diamond Heights is a good example of the ambiguities of history. Diamond Heights achieved its urban renewal goals; created middle-class and low-income housing; used sophisticated planning seldom seen in San Francisco; and produced a racially integrated, stable neighborhood. But the designation of the area as a redevelopment area in 1950 arrested private developers who probably would have built fewer numbers of less expensive houses away from the summits and allowed the public to enjoy remarkable views.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="fn102-1538513212456970">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no conflicts of interest with respect to the authorship and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn103-1538513212456970">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research and/or authorship of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<title>Notes</title>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1538513212456970">
<label>1.</label>
<p>This thesis is focused on “urban renewal” as it became known through the 1949 Housing Act and subsequent acts through 1973. The San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, along with all 400 redevelopment agencies in California, was dissolved on February 1, 2012, as a result of California’s chronic budget deficits (<italic>California Redevelopment Association et al. v. Ana Matosantos</italic>).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1538513212456970">
<label>2.</label>
<p>A search of the term urban renewal on Proquest revealed a total of 345 dissertations and theses. Of these, 101 deal with some aspect of US postwar urban renewal and most of these (77 percent) were written before 1980. Abstracts are available for works published after about 1983; only four appear to conclude that urban renewal even partially met its goals.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1538513212456970">
<label>3.</label>
<p>A classic view is expressed by architectural historian Spiro Kostof: “With the blessing of municipal authorities and the real-estate industry, they set out to install the Modernist city in American downtowns . . . Entire neighborhoods were gutted and replaced with commercial towers lapped by vast open spaces, slabs, and cruciform skyscrapers of early Corbusian derivation, grimly executed and with barren parking lots for greenery.” Spiro Kostof, <italic>A History of Architecture </italic>(New York, NY: Oxford University Press, 1995), 726.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1538513212456970">
<label>4.</label>
<p>For example, the 2007 Conference Society of Architectural Historians and the 12th National Conference on Planning History held in 2007 featured many papers on the subject.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-1538513212456970">
<label>5.</label>
<p>See Hilary Ballon and Kenneth T. Jackson, <italic>Robert Moses and the Modern City: The Transformation of New York </italic>(New York, NY: W. W. Norton, 2007); Jon C. Teaford, “Urban Renewal and Its Aftermath,” <italic>Housing Policy Debate</italic> 11, no. 2 (Fannie Mae Foundation, 2000); Alexander Garvin, <italic>The American City: What Works, What Doesn’t</italic> (New York, NY: McGraw Hill, 1996).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-1538513212456970">
<label>6.</label>
<p>Chester Hartman, <italic>City for Sale, The Transformation of San Francisco</italic> (Berkeley and Los Angeles: University of California Press, 2002).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-1538513212456970">
<label>7.</label>
<p>Work paper from David Hasset, San Francisco Redeployment Agency.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-1538513212456970">
<label>8.</label>
<p>The Diamond Heights redevelopment project has never been the subject of a detailed study.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-1538513212456970">
<label>9.</label>
<p>San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, <italic>1986 Fact Book</italic>, 1986, 88.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-1538513212456970">
<label>10.</label>
<p>“Site Planning and Design,” Steven B. McBride, West Virginia University Website, wvu.edu/AQ11 WebBook/McBride/ section3.html.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-1538513212456970">
<label>11.</label>
<p>“Redevelopment in Diamond Heights,” San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, March 1950, v.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-1538513212456970">
<label>12.</label>
<p>The Agency wrote “Although only a small portion of those residing in the Jefferson Square area [Western Addition project] can afford new private hosing, any increase in supply will effect [<italic>sic</italic>] the general housing market and thus aid in solving the re-housing problem of the Jefferson Square neighborhood.” San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, “Redevelopment in Diamonds Heights,” March 1950, 23; Mel Scott, <italic>The San Francisco Bay Area, A Metropolis in Perspective</italic> (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1959), 289.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn13-1538513212456970">
<label>13.</label>
<p>In 1953, the San Francisco Redevelopment Agency claimed six other cities were planning to redevelop “open blighted lands,” but it did not identify the cities, “Report to Mayor Elmer E. Robinson, for the Fiscal Year 1952-1953,” San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, p. 3. However, a report by the federal government in 1957 listed three “open lands projects”: An urban renewal project in South Pasadena (project R-9) and two slum clearance projects in Puerto Rico (project U-5-27(A) and (project U 5-9), “Urban Renewal Project Directory,” Housing and Home Finance Agency, Urban Renewal Administration, March 31, 1957, 23–25.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn14-1538513212456970">
<label>14.</label>
<p>The city owned eighty-nine acres and another ninety-four acres were allocated to streets (although most existed only on paper). The San Francisco Housing Authority owned twenty-nine acres, and the state of California owned twelve acres, for a total of 60.4 percent of the total land. Ibid., 6.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn15-1538513212456970">
<label>15.</label>
<p>“New Contours, New Houses for Blighted Hills,” <italic>Journal of Housing,</italic> October 1952, Vol. 9, No. 10, 372.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn16-1538513212456970">
<label>16.</label>
<p>
<italic>1986 Fact Book</italic>, San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, 1986, 88.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn17-1538513212456970">
<label>17.</label>
<p>“And I object strenuously to the term “blighted area . . . the people in the area feel they are sort of covered up by tin cans, garage out there,” said Mr. Messer in “Public Hearing on the Redevelopment of the Diamond Heights [<italic>sic</italic>], Transcript of the Public Hearing held by the Redevelopment Agency of San Francisco on January 15, 1952, regarding the Tentative Redevelopment Plan,” 21.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn18-1538513212456970">
<label>18.</label>
<p>The derogatory term “cracker box house” refers to small, nearly square shaped, wood framed houses with flat roofs with plain, stucco facades built by small builders in the 1950s. For example, Everett Griffin, chairman of the San Francisco Redevelopment Agency told architects, “In case you had any doubts, there will be no punched out, drab, cracker-boxes, row on row, in Diamonds Heights,” in a speech before the northern California Chapter of AIA on December 8, 1960, San Francisco Redevelopment Agency archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn19-1538513212456970">
<label>19.</label>
<p>“Public Hearing on the Redevelopment of the Diamond Heights [<italic>sic</italic>], Transcript of the Public Hearing held by the Redevelopment Agency of San Francisco on January 15, 1952, Regarding the Tentative Redevelopment Plan,” 36.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn20-1538513212456970">
<label>20.</label>
<p>Ibid., 6.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn21-1538513212456970">
<label>21.</label>
<p>“New Contours, New Houses for Blighted Hills,” <italic>Journal of Housing,</italic> October 1952, Vol. 9, No. 10, 372.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn22-1538513212456970">
<label>22.</label>
<p>“Report to Mayor Elmer E. Robinson, For the Fiscal Year 1952-1953,” San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, 5.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn23-1538513212456970">
<label>23.</label>
<p>
<italic>Redevelopment Agency v. Hayes</italic> (1954) 122 Cal. App.2d 777.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn24-1538513212456970">
<label>24.</label>
<p>“Redevelopment and Blight, The Summary Report from the Joint Interim Hearing of the Senate Committee on Housing and Land Use and the Senate Select Committee on Redevelopment,” California Legislature, Sacramento, California, November 16, 1995, 3. According to this report, from 1945 until 1993, state law did not explicitly define blight but listed its characteristics. A law passed in 1993 defined blight in such a way so as to put limitations on the types of projects that would qualify under redevelopment law.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn25-1538513212456970">
<label>25.</label>
<p>Scott, <italic>The San Francisco Bay Area, A Metropolis in Perspective</italic>, 290.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn26-1538513212456970">
<label>26.</label>
<p>Michael Harris, “First Land Bought in Diamond Heights,” <italic>San Francisco Chronicle, </italic>October 3, 1956.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn27-1538513212456970">
<label>27.</label>
<p>“Progress report to Mayor Christopher for the Period October 1955 to September 1963,” Redevelopment Agency of the City and County of San Francisco, 1–2.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn28-1538513212456970">
<label>28.</label>
<p>This conclusion is based on a check of the streets of Diamond Heights against a plan map in the report, “Summary of Diamonds Heights Redevelopment Plan, Map A,” February 1, 1969, San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, and the transcript of the public hearing.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn29-1538513212456970">
<label>29.</label>
<p>“Progress report to Mayor Christopher for the Period October 1955 to September 1963,” Redevelopment Agency of the City and County of San Francisco, 2.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn30-1538513212456970">
<label>30.</label>
<p>Garrett Eckbo, <italic>Public Landscape: Six Essays on Government and Environmental Design in the San Francisco Bay Area</italic> (Berkeley: Institute of Governmental Studies, UC Berkeley, 1978), 95.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn31-1538513212456970">
<label>31.</label>
<p>The first report on Diamond Heights stated that the majority of housing would be for moderate-income families although “some luxury” and “some low rent public housing” may ultimately be included. San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, “Redevelopment in Diamonds Heights,” 20.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn32-1538513212456970">
<label>32.</label>
<p>Roger Montgomery, “Mass Producing Bay Area Architecture,” Sally Woodbridge, <italic>Bay Area Houses</italic> (Layton, UT: Gibbs M. Smith,1988), 232.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn33-1538513212456970">
<label>33.</label>
<p>Carl Feiss, “Critique: The Architecture of Redevelopment in U.S.A.,” <italic>Progressive Architecture</italic>, Vol. XXXVII, No. 8 (August 1956), 123.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn34-1538513212456970">
<label>34.</label>
<p>One contemporary observer suggested that the project was too large to award to a single developer or to sell at once to several developers as was done in other redevelopment projects. See George Thomas Kingsley, “The Design Process in Urban Renewal: An Analysis of the San Francisco Experience” (Master’s Thesis, University of California, Berkeley, 1963), 87.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn35-1538513212456970">
<label>35.</label>
<p>“1961 Annual Report,” San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, 5.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn36-1538513212456970">
<label>36.</label>
<p>“. . . to elevate the urban design consequences of the redevelopment process to a higher level than is likely to result without special attention to the esthetics of the ultimate construction,” statement by the members of the San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, “Architectural Advisory Panel Evaluation Report Diamond Heights Red Rock Hill Competition,” June 30, 1961, 2.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn37-1538513212456970">
<label>37.</label>
<p>“1961 Annual Report,” San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, 16.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn38-1538513212456970">
<label>38.</label>
<p>“Four Diamond Heights Red Rock Hill Designs Selected by the San Francisco Redevelopment Agency From the Ten Winners in the Redevelopment Agency—AIA National Architectural Competition,” San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, June 30, 1961, 2.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn39-1538513212456970">
<label>39.</label>
<p>Ibid., 3.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn40-1538513212456970">
<label>40.</label>
<p>“Agency OKs Plan for Diamond Heights Center,” <italic>San Francisco Chronicle</italic>, December 13, 1961 and <italic>San Francisco Call Bulletin</italic>, December 4, 1964.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn41-1538513212456970">
<label>41.</label>
<p>“Developer Guide Statement, Diamond Heights Red Rock Hill Competition,” San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, [n.d.], 20.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn42-1538513212456970">
<label>42.</label>
<p>“Architectural Advisory Panel Evaluation Report Diamond Heights Red Rock Hill Competitor,” San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, June 30, 1961, 29.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn43-1538513212456970">
<label>43.</label>
<p>“Diamond Heights Neighborhood Center, an Urban Design and Report,” Lawrence Lackey, AIA Urban Design Consultant, Royston, Hanamoto &amp; Mayes, Landscape Architects, 1961.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn44-1538513212456970">
<label>44.</label>
<p>Diamond Heights accommodates the automobile to a much greater extent than is common in San Francisco, For example, the nearby Miraloma Park neighborhood center built in the 1930s has twenty-three stores and businesses and only 116 parking spots, of which fifteen are free. From a visual inspection made January 31, 2008.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn45-1538513212456970">
<label>45.</label>
<p>The number and height of the towers vary in different sources.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn46-1538513212456970">
<label>46.</label>
<p>“Diamond Heights Work Resumed,” <italic>San Francisco Chronicle</italic>, December 16, 1964.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn47-1538513212456970">
<label>47.</label>
<p>GE had already held a 10 percent share in the project. During this time period, San Francisco Redevelopers also purchased a Chevrolet plant in Oakland for $2.5 million, hired architects to design a forty-story building for the Chinatown Cultural Center redevelopment project, were in arrears $400,000 to the Redevelopment Agency, and the IRS and state of California filed liens against them for unpaid taxes. Donald Canter, “Projects Stalled Here—No Cash,” <italic>San Francisco Call Bulletin</italic>, December 4, 1964.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn48-1538513212456970">
<label>48.</label>
<p>“General Electric Enters Renewal Field in Big Way,” <italic>The Journal of Housing</italic>, No 6, 1965, 312.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn49-1538513212456970">
<label>49.</label>
<p>Donald Canter, “Diamond Heights Work to Resume,” <italic>San Francisco Examiner</italic>, November 6, 1967.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn50-1538513212456970">
<label>50.</label>
<p>Donald Canter, “New Plan to Solve GE’s Red Rock Hill Troubles,” <italic>San Francisco Examiner</italic>, June 6, 1967. “Realistic Red Rock Hill Development,” <italic>San Francisco Chronicle</italic> June 7, 1967.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn51-1538513212456970">
<label>51.</label>
<p>Scott Baillie, “Another Outfit May Try to Develop Red Rock,” <italic>San Francisco Chronicle</italic>, April 23, 1969.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn52-1538513212456970">
<label>52.</label>
<p>Sally Woodbridge, John Woodbridge, and Chuck Byrne, <italic>San Francisco Architecture, The Illustrated Guide to Over 1,000 of the Best Buildings, Parks, and Public Artworks in the Bay Area</italic> (San Francisco: Chronicle Books, 1992), 175.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn53-1538513212456970">
<label>53.</label>
<p>“Last of the Diamond in the Heights,” <italic>San Francisco Sunday Examiner and Chronicle</italic>, January 17, 1971.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn54-1538513212456970">
<label>54.</label>
<p>Robert J. Keely, “Eichler Comes to the City,” <italic>San Francisco Chronicle</italic>, March 25, 1962.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn55-1538513212456970">
<label>55.</label>
<p>“New Standard of Quality in Urban Renewal Design,” <italic>House &amp; Home</italic> 9, no 10 (February 1964): 96.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn56-1538513212456970">
<label>56.</label>
<p>“A Brilliant Use of Textures,” <italic>San Francisco Chronicle</italic>, March 8, 1964.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn57-1538513212456970">
<label>57.</label>
<p>“Today’s Best Built-for-Sale Houses—And What Makes Them Sell,” <italic>House and Home</italic> XXIV, no.4 (October, 1963): 100.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn58-1538513212456970">
<label>58.</label>
<p>“Diamond Heights Townhouses,” <italic>San Francisco Examiner</italic>, August 2, 1964.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn59-1538513212456970">
<label>59.</label>
<p>For example, the Heyman Brothers built sixteen houses on Cameo Drive priced at $38,000–$40,000, De Narde Co. built six houses at Amber and Turquoise Way for $42,000, and Elm Construction Co. planned to build twenty houses at Duncan and Amber Drives. See Donald Canter, “Houses Bloom on Diamond Heights,” <italic>San Francisco News-Call Bulletin</italic>, April 5, 1962.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn60-1538513212456970">
<label>60.</label>
<p>Joseph Bodovitz,” “Red Rock Hill Lots on Block,” <italic>San Francisco Examiner</italic>, January 22, 1961.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn61-1538513212456970">
<label>61.</label>
<p>Interview with Allan Unger and Jane Unger (Mr. and Mrs. Unger) on January 5, 2008.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn62-1538513212456970">
<label>62.</label>
<p>“The First Home on Red Rock Hill,” <italic>San Francisco Chronicle</italic>, November 2, 1961.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn63-1538513212456970">
<label>63.</label>
<p>From a speech given by Everett Griffin, chairman of the San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, before the Golden Gateway Luncheon meeting of the Northern California Chapter of AIA, San Francisco, December 1960, as quoted in Kingsley, “The Design Process in Urban Renewal: An Analysis of the San Francisco Experience,” 97–98.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn64-1538513212456970">
<label>64.</label>
<p>For a concise overview of urban renewal and the public housing provisions of Title III of the 1949 Housing Act and its evolution, see Alexander von Hoffman, “A Study in Contradictions: The Origins and Legacy of the Housing act of 1949,” <italic>Housing Policy Debate</italic> 11, no. 2, Fannie Mae Foundation, 2000.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn65-1538513212456970">
<label>65.</label>
<p>The San Francisco Public Housing Authority proposed to use 16 acres in Diamond Heights for low rent housing but on March 9, 1950, the Planning Commission refused to approve a zoning change that would have allowed it, “Redevelopment in Diamond Heights,” San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, 7.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn66-1538513212456970">
<label>66.</label>
<p>Herman credited the Housing Act of 1961 with providing new financial tools and techniques that made the scheme feasible. He may have been referring to Section 221(d)(3) amendments to the 1934 National Housing Act that allowed the FHA to insure rental housing mortgages at below market rates. See von Hoffman, “A Study in Contradictions: The Origins and Legacy of the Housing act of 1949,” 319. The Glenridge project is a section 221(d)(3) project.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn67-1538513212456970">
<label>67.</label>
<p>“1961 Annual Report,” San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, 5, 10, 16.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn68-1538513212456970">
<label>68.</label>
<p>“1962 Annual Report,” San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, 3.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn69-1538513212456970">
<label>69.</label>
<p>“Progress Report to Mayor Christopher for the Period October 1955 to September 1963,” Redevelopment Agency of the City and County of San Francisco, p. 3. See also a fact sheet titled, “Moderate-Priced Private Housing for Families in San Francisco,” San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, May 21, 1963.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn70-1538513212456970">
<label>70.</label>
<p>Apparently, changes occurred with the developers and architects involved with “moderate income” projects on Diamond Heights. As built, there are a total of 488 units of subsidized housing under various programs.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn71-1538513212456970">
<label>71.</label>
<p>
<italic>San Francisco News Call Bulletin</italic>, 1963, n.d.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn72-1538513212456970">
<label>72.</label>
<p>Jim Leonard, “Protests Delay Diamond Heights Plan,” <italic>San Francisco News Call Bulletin</italic>, May 28, 1963, 24.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn73-1538513212456970">
<label>73.</label>
<p>“Gold Plated Slum—Glen Park Furor,” <italic>San Francisco Chronicle</italic>, May 23, 1963, n.p.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn74-1538513212456970">
<label>74.</label>
<p>“New Standard of Quality in Urban Renewal Design,” <italic>House and Home</italic>, February 1964, 99.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn75-1538513212456970">
<label>75.</label>
<p>Ibid.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn76-1538513212456970">
<label>76.</label>
<p>“Eleventh Annual Design Awards,”<italic> Progressive Architecture</italic> XLV, no. 1 (January 1964): 106.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn77-1538513212456970">
<label>77.</label>
<p>“New Standard of Quality in Urban Renewal Design,” <italic>House &amp; Home</italic>, February 1964, 96.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn78-1538513212456970">
<label>78.</label>
<p>Ibid., 93.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn79-1538513212456970">
<label>79.</label>
<p>Roger Montgomery, “Improving the Design Process in Urban Renewal,” in <italic>Urban Renewal: The Record and the Controversy,</italic> ed. James Q. Wilson (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1966), 481.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn80-1538513212456970">
<label>80.</label>
<p>Sally Woodbridge, et. al., <italic>San Francisco Architecture,</italic> 175.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn81-1538513212456970">
<label>81.</label>
<p>Peter Booth Wiley, <italic>National Trust Guide—San Francisco, America’s Guide for Architecture and History Travelers</italic> (New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2000), 382.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn82-1538513212456970">
<label>82.</label>
<p>Sally Woodbridge, ed., <italic>Bay Area Houses</italic> (Layton, Utah: Gibbs M. Smith Inc, New Edition, 1988), 10, 248–53.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn83-1538513212456970">
<label>83.</label>
<p>Alexander Garvin, <italic>The American City: What Works, What Doesn’t,</italic> 2nd ed. (New York: McGraw-Hill, 2002), 166. The examples he cites are high-rise residential redevelopment projects such as New York’s Stuyvesant Town (seventy-five acres, 8,800 units) and Chicago’s Lake Meadow (seventy acres, ten buildings with 2,033 apartments), and Prairie Shores (fifty-five acres, five buildings with 1,677 apartments).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn84-1538513212456970">
<label>84.</label>
<p>Roger Montgomery writing in 1965 said, “In most places, urban renewal experience has produced mixed results, missed opportunities and often shockingly bad design.” Roger Montgomery, “Aesthesis in Urban Renewal,” <italic>The Journal of Housing</italic> no. 11 (1965): 602.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn85-1538513212456970">
<label>85.</label>
<p>von Hoffman, “A Study in Contradictions: The Origins and Legacy of the Housing Act of 1949,” 2000, 312. Hoffman notes that smaller cities and those in the South and West more often used low-rise designs.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn86-1538513212456970">
<label>86.</label>
<p>Richard Longstreth, “The Difficult Legacy of Urban Renewal,” <italic>CRM Journal</italic>, Winter 2006, 17.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn87-1538513212456970">
<label>87.</label>
<p>
<italic>Fact Book 1986</italic>, San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, 1986, 88.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn88-1538513212456970">
<label>88.</label>
<p>This is suggestive, as no study has been done about the origins of the residents of Diamond Heights.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn89-1538513212456970">
<label>89.</label>
<p>Vernon Armand DeMars, “A Life in Architecture: Indian Dancing, Migrant Housing, Telesis, Design for Urban Living, Theater, Teaching” (Regional Oral History Office, Bancroft Library, University California, 1992), 474.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn90-1538513212456970">
<label>90.</label>
<p>Redevelopment in Diamond Heights, “San Francisco Redevelopment Agency,” March 1950, p. 24. Diamond Heights accommodates the automobile to a much greater extent than is common in San Francisco. For example, the Miraloma Park neighborhood center has 23 stores and businesses along two city streets and 101 metered parking spots and 15 free spaces. From a visual inspection made January 31, 2008.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn91-1538513212456970">
<label>91.</label>
<p>There are no studies of the value of views in San Francisco.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn92-1538513212456970">
<label> 92.</label>
<p>Partick McGrew, “Neighborhoods and Innovators: An Architect’s View of San Francisco’s Subdivisions before 1915,” <italic>The Argonaut</italic>, San Francisco Museum and Historical Society, 46.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn93-1538513212456970">
<label> 93.</label>
<p>Carolyn Loeb, <italic>Entrepreneurial Vernacular: Developers Subdivisions in the 1920s</italic> (Baltimore: John Hopkins University Press, 2001).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn94-1538513212456970">
<label> 94.</label>
<p>Marc A. Weiss, <italic>The Rise of the Community Builders</italic> (New York: Columbia University Press, 1987), 2, 51, 58, 120.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn95-1538513212456970">
<label> 95.</label>
<p>The Metropolitan Life Insurance company began construction of Parkmerced as a planned community in 1941, one of a number housing projects during the 1940s and 1950s, most famously Stuyvesant Town. However, Parkmerced was not a slum clearance or a low-income project. This 200-acre project was built on a golf course in the southwest corner of San Francisco near the Pacific Ocean and a lake (Lake Merced). Delayed by WWII, the first units opened in 1944 consisting of two- and three-story wood framed apartments. After the war, several thirteen-story concrete towers were added. The complex has a small shopping center (more akin to the convenience store referred to by Gavin) but was not programmed with any other facilities such as schools, parks, or churches. Two other subdivisions were laid out over former cemeteries: Anza Vista, 110 acres bordered by Geary Street, St Joseph’s Ave, Turk and Masonic Streets; and Laurel Heights, 54 acres, bordered by California, Geary, Parker Streets, and Presidio Avenue. See Hansen, <italic>San Francisco Almanac</italic>, 123. Finally, a suburban style shopping center with a few apartments, Stonestown, opened in 1952 near Parkmerced.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn96-1538513212456970">
<label> 96.</label>
<p>Two active builders were identified in the project area by the Redevelopment Agency, “Thomas Valerga, a private builder, owns 5.2 acres and is in the process of making large-scale cuts for new housing sites on Fairmont Hill,” and Atlas Realty owned four acres on Gold Mine Hill. Additionally, the Crocker Estate Company owned twenty-two acres on Gold Mine Hill and “have shown interest in developing this property,” from “Redevelopment on Diamond Heights,” San Francisco Redevelopment Agency, 1950, 7–8.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn97-1538513212456970">
<label> 97.</label>
<p>
<italic>Redevelopment Agency v. Hayes</italic>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn98-1538513212456970">
<label> 98.</label>
<p>The author was raised in a five-room, one bath, stucco front, rectangle-shaped row house built in 1956, one of the five identical houses built by a father and son builder on vacant lots in Visitation Valley. These homes sold for $16,000 and look nearly identical to scores of others built by builders on the slopes of Twin Peaks in the 1950s.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn99-1538513212456970">
<label> 99.</label>
<p>There has been no published scholarly study of San Francisco’s postwar development in the outlying residential areas. These observations are based on anecdotal evidence and popular history. See Jacqueline Proctor, <italic>San Francisco’s West of Twin Peaks</italic> (Charleston: Arcadia Publishing, 2006); and Anna Bland Smith, <italic>San Francisco’s Glen Park and Diamond Heights</italic> (Charleston: Arcadia Publishing, 2007).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn100-1538513212456970">
<label>100.</label>
<p>One of the approved designs for Red Rock Hill did include a provision for a public viewing area but this design was not selected.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn101-1538513212456970">
<label>101.</label>
<p>Berman et al v. Parker et al 348 U.S. 26 (1954).</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
</back>
</article>