<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JFM</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjfm</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Feline Medicine and Surgery</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1098-612X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1532-2750</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1098612X12466552</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1098612X12466552</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Case Series</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Three clinical cases of <italic>Anaplasma phagocytophilum</italic> infection in cats in Poland</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Adaszek</surname><given-names>Łukasz</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1098612X12466552">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Górna</surname><given-names>Marta</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1098612X12466552">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Skrzypczak</surname><given-names>Maciej</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1098612X12466552">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Buczek</surname><given-names>Krzysztof</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1098612X12466552">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Balicki</surname><given-names>Ireneusz</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-1098612X12466552">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Winiarczyk</surname><given-names>Stanisław</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1098612X12466552">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1098612X12466552"><label>1</label>Department of Epizootiology and Infectious Diseases, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Life Sciences, Lublin, Poland</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1098612X12466552"><label>2</label>Second Department of Gynecology, Professor F. Skubiszewski University School of Medicine, Lublin, Poland</aff>
<aff id="aff3-1098612X12466552"><label>3</label>Department and Clinic of Animal Surgery, University of Life Sciences, Lublin, Poland</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1098612X12466552">Łukasz Adaszek PhD, Department of Epizootiology and Infectious Diseases, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Life Sciences, 30 Głęboka St 20-612, Lublin, Poland Email: <email>ukaszek0@wp.pl</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2013</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>333</fpage>
<lpage>337</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© ISFM and AAFP 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">International Society of Feline Medicine and American Association of Feline Practitioners</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>The purpose of this study was to describe <italic>Anaplasma phagocytophilum</italic> infection of three cats in Poland showing signs of fever, swollen and painful joints, pale mucous membranes and epistaxis. Morulae consistent with <italic>A phagocytophilum</italic> were present within the neutrophils of two of the cats. A polymerase chain reaction (PCR) was found targeting the 16S rRNA gene amplified DNA consistent with <italic>A phagocytophilum</italic> in the blood of all three cats. The sequence of the PCR product obtained showed 99.6–100% homology with the sequence <italic>of A phagocytophilum</italic>, gene number EU 090186 from Genbank. Applied therapy (including administration of tetracyclines for 3 weeks) resulted in a gradual clinical recovery.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1098612X12466552" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Granulocytic anaplasmosis (GA) is an infectious multi-organ disease of humans and animals accompanied by thrombocytopenia. The aetiological factors of the disease are the microorganisms previously classified within the family of <italic>Rickettsiaceae</italic>, genus <italic>Ehrlichia.</italic> Currently, they are classified within the order of <italic>Rickettsiales</italic>, family <italic>Anaplasmataceae</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1098612X12466552">1</xref></sup> The 16S rRNA gene sequence studies made it possible to classify three pathogens considered, until recently, as separate species, and being aetiological factors of anaplasmosis in cats and dogs (<italic>Anaplasma phagocytophilum</italic>), horses (<italic>A phagocytophilum, Ehrlicha equi</italic>) and humans (human granulocytic ehrlichiosis agent) to the taxon of <italic>A phagocytophilum</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1098612X12466552">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>Recently, some cases of animal granulocytic anaplasmosis have been reported in Poland. Serological monitoring carried out in dogs, cattle and pigs, for example, indicated contact with rickettsia, which proves indirectly the occurrence of <italic>Anaplasma</italic> species microorganisms in Poland.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1098612X12466552">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1098612X12466552">3</xref></sup> The absolute confirmation of their presence was the detection of rickettsia genetic material in ticks and wild ruminants and horses coming from various regions of the country.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1098612X12466552">4</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1098612X12466552"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1098612X12466552"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1098612X12466552">7</xref></sup> Before that, anaplasmosis had never been diagnosed in cats in Poland. In other regions of the world the disease is diagnosed rarely in this species.</p>
<p>The aim of this research was to present the first cases of <italic>A phagocytophilum</italic> infection in cats in Poland.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1098612X12466552" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and methods</title>
<p>The study was carried out on three cats, aged from 2 to 6 years, from the following regions: Lublin (case 1), Masovia (case 2) and Przemyśl (case 3). Two were male cats and one female. All the cats had contact with ticks, after which the clinical signs were observed: fever, swollen and painful joints, pale mucous membranes and epistaxis. In all three cases, the ticks from the body surface of the sick cats had been removed by their owners; hence, it was not possible to determine their species.</p>
<sec id="section3-1098612X12466552">
<title>Case 1</title>
<p>Case 1 was a European shorthair male, aged 2 years and 5 months and weighed 5.2 kg. It was admitted to the clinic with the following signs: loss of appetite and thirst, apathy and paleness of mucous membranes. The internal body temperature was 39.8°C; the accessible lymph nodes were not enlarged, but palpation of the abdomen revealed a two-sided tenderness of the area below the ribs. Moreover, swelling and painfulness of both ankle joints was also observed. As reported in the anamnesis by the owners, the cat had suffered from periodic (occurring every 2 days) bleeding from the nose that had receded spontaneously. A radiographic examination demonstrated no lesions in the skeletal system of the problem joints. The observed signs had persisted for 5 days and had occurred approximately 3–4 days after the removal of the tick from the body surface of the animal.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1098612X12466552">
<title>Case 2</title>
<p>Case 2 was a European shorthair, non-neutered 3-year-old male and weighed 4.1 kg. Its owners had observed its difficulty in walking accompanied by painful wrist joints and ankle joints for about 2 weeks. A radiographic examination showed no lesions in the skeletal system of the problem joints. Ticks had been removed from the body surface of the cat about 3 weeks previously. The animal was apathetic, had reduced appetite and the accessible mucous membranes were pale. Its internal body temperature was 39.1°C; the accessible lymph nodes were not enlarged.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1098612X12466552">
<title>Case 3</title>
<p>A female 6-year-old European shorthair cat was admitted to the clinic. According to the owners, the animal had been apathetic and showed no desire to play for about 2 days. A tick had been removed from the body surface of the animal about a week previously. The internal body temperature was 39.6°C, appetite and thirst were reduced. The accessible lymph nodes were not enlarged. Except for the signs reported by the owners, clinical examination revealed no other abnormalities.</p>
<p>Blood for haematological tests, molecular tests for anaplasmosis and babesiosis, and for speed tests for feline leukaemia virus (FeLV), feline immunodeficiency virus (FIV) and feline coronavirus infection was obtained from the sick animals.</p>
<sec id="section6-1098612X12466552">
<title>Haematological tests</title>
<p>Blood for the haematological tests was placed into 3-ml test tubes with ethylenediamine tetra-acetic acid (EDTA), shaken and tested (about 300 µl) in an Exigo (Boule) analyser.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1098612X12466552">
<title>Blood smear tests</title>
<p>Blood smears were made on a degreased microscopic glass, stained with the Diff Quick (POCH Lublin) method and viewed under an Olympus CH 20 (Olympus Optical) microscope when dry. Blood smears were screened for presence of <italic>Babesia, Anaplasma</italic> and <italic>Mycoplasma</italic> species.</p>
<p>Tests for FeLV, FIV and feline coronavirus infection were performed according to the manufacturer’s instructions (BioVeto Test).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1098612X12466552">
<title>DNA isolation</title>
<p>DNA for the analysis was extracted from 100 µl of fresh blood. DNA isolation was carried out with a DNA blood mini kit (DNA Gdan’sk).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-1098612X12466552">
<title>Polymerase chain reaction</title>
<p>Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) amplification was performed using a programmable thermal cycler (Biometra). The PCR reaction for <italic>Babesia/Theileria</italic> species was carried out using a pair of primers, ie, RLB R2 and RLB F2, which made it possible to amplify the DNA section with a 390–430 base-pair-long fragment of the 18S rRNA conservative gene.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1098612X12466552">8</xref></sup> The PCR reaction for <italic>Anaplasma</italic> species was carried out according to a method described by Adaszek et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1098612X12466552">9</xref></sup> using the following primers: EHR 521: 5’-TGT AGG CGG TTC GGT AAG TTA AAG-3’; EHR 747: 5’ GCA CTC ATC GTT TAC AGC GTG-3’. This limited the DNA section to a length of 247 bp of the conserved part of the 16S rRNA gene. The positive control was the DNA of <italic>A phagocytophilum</italic> from human blood (National Reference Center for Borreliae of Max von Pettenkofer Institute of Ludwig Maximilian University Munich) and the negative control was DNA from the blood of a healthy cat. Each reaction was composed of 35 cycles with the denaturation stage at 94°C for 30 s, primers were attached at a temperature of 56°C for 30 s and the threads were elongated at a temperature of 72°C for 45 s.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1098612X12466552">
<title>Electrophoresis</title>
<p>The PCR products were analysed with the electrophoresis method in a 1% agarose gel and Tris-borate-EDTA (TBE) buffer at a voltage of 10 V/cm for 50 mins.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1098612X12466552">
<title>Sequencing</title>
<p>The PCR reaction products purified with the QIAquick PCR Purification Kit (Qiagen) were sequenced by the DNA Sequencing and Synthesis Service of the Institute of Biochemistry and Biophysics at Polish Academy of Science in Warsaw. The sequencing results were received via email and developed using the computer software Lasergene DNA Star. The same software was used to analyse the sequence of <italic>A phagocytophilum</italic> isolates and compare them with sequences available in the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) Genebank.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1098612X12466552" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-1098612X12466552">Table 1</xref> demonstrates low content of haemoglobin in the erythrocytes, decreased haematocrit and thrombocytopenia. Each cat was negative for FeLV p27 antigen, and antibodies against FIV and feline coronavirus. <italic>Babesia</italic> protozoa and <italic>Mycoplasma</italic> species bacteria were not found in the erythrocytes in the blood smears, whereas in two cats (cases 1 and 3) morulae of <italic>Anaplasma</italic> species were observed in neutrophils (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1098612X12466552">Figure 1a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1098612X12466552">b</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-1098612X12466552" position="float">
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Results of haematological examination of the blood sampled from sick cats on the day after onset of clinical signs</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-1098612X12466552" xlink:href="10.1177_1098612X12466552-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Investigated parameters</th>
<th align="left">RBC (10<sup>12</sup>/l)</th>
<th align="left">WBC (10<sup>9</sup>/l)</th>
<th align="left">HGB (mmol/l)</th>
<th align="left">HCT (%)</th>
<th align="left">PLT (10<sup>9</sup>/l)</th>
<th align="left">Morulae in the blood smears</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Case 1 (Lublin)</td>
<td>5.12</td>
<td>4.6</td>
<td>7.7</td>
<td>23</td>
<td>34</td>
<td>+</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Case 2 (Masovia)</td>
<td>4.31</td>
<td>5.0</td>
<td>5.31</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>+</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Case 3 (Przemyśl)</td>
<td>3.95</td>
<td>4.2</td>
<td>4.80</td>
<td>21</td>
<td>47</td>
<td>−</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Range</td>
<td>6.5–10</td>
<td>5.5–19</td>
<td>4.96–9.31</td>
<td>24–45</td>
<td>100–400</td>
<td>−</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-1098612X12466552">
<p>HCT = haematocrit; HGB = haemoglobin; PLT = platelets; RBC = red blood cells; WBC = white blood cells</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig1-1098612X12466552" position="float">
<label>Figure 1</label>
<caption>
<p>(a, b) Presence of <italic>Anaplasma</italic> species morulae (arrows) in neutrophils</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_1098612X12466552-fig1.tif"/></fig>
<p>The PCR test for <italic>Babesia</italic> species did not show the presence of the genetic material of protozoa in the blood of the diseased animals. However, the presence of the genetic material of <italic>Anaplasma</italic> species was observed in all three samples.</p>
<p>The sequences of <italic>Anaplasma</italic> species products with a length of 247 bp obtained from the PCR reaction and developed in the Lasergene DNA Star showed a high level of similarity (99.6–100%) to the 16S rRNA gene section sequence of <italic>A phagocytophilum</italic> strain Lublin, isolated in an earlier study from a horse in Poland, listed in the Genbank under the number GU183908.</p>
<p>The treatment of the cats involved oxytetracycline (5 mg/kg IM: Oxyvet; Biowet Puławy) administered intramuscularly twice daily (q12h) for 2 days, then changed to doxycycline (Ronaxan; Merial) administered for 3 weeks at a dose of 10 mg/kg of body mass, and dexamethasone (0.2 mg/kg SC: Dexasone; ScanVet) for 3 days. The applied therapy led to a significant improvement in the state of health of all cats 48 h after application of the drugs. Complete recovery of the infected animals was observed within 3 weeks.</p>
<p>Haematological tests performed a month after the initiation of the treatment did not show any abnormalities.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1098612X12466552" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p><italic>Anaplasma phagocytophilum</italic> is a microorganism able to infect many animal species and humans. The main vector of the microorganisms in Europe is the tick <italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1098612X12466552">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1098612X12466552">11</xref></sup> The reservoirs of rickettsias are rodents and wild ruminantas.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1098612X12466552">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1098612X12466552">12</xref></sup> Feline anaplasmosis is a relatively rare disease, as evidenced by the many clinical reviews on this subject. There are only a few specific reports that include detailed case descriptions regarding the disease in domestic cats.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1098612X12466552">13</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1098612X12466552"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1098612X12466552"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1098612X12466552"/>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1098612X12466552">17</xref></sup> In Poland the disease was previously detected only in horses and dogs,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1098612X12466552">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1098612X12466552">6</xref></sup> never in cats.</p>
<p>It ought to be noted that <italic>A phagocytophilum</italic> infection is diagnosed more rarely in cats than in dogs, possibly as a result of the specific behaviour of cats and the mechanical removal of ticks from their body surface while they groom.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1098612X12466552">18</xref></sup></p>
<p>In Europe, the DNA of these pathogens was detected occasionally in the blood of naturally infected cats from Sweden, Finland, Italy, UK, Ireland and Denmark, which showed signs of lethargy, anorexia, fever and tachypnoea.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1098612X12466552">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1098612X12466552">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1098612X12466552">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1098612X12466552">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1098612X12466552">20</xref></sup></p>
<p>In the cases described the diagnosis was established on the basis of haematological tests (thrombocytopenia and presence of morulae in neutrophils in two of the infected cats), molecular tests and applied therapy efficiency.</p>
<p>One of the most characteristic signs of anaplasmosis is thrombocytopenia,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1098612X12466552">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1098612X12466552">14</xref></sup> which may lead to bleeding from the mucous membranes. Thrombocytopenia might have been the reason why one of the patients developed bleeding from the nose — a clinical sign that has not been described previously in cats, but which has been observed in the course of anaplasmosis in dogs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1098612X12466552">21</xref></sup> The mechanisms that cause the platelet count to drop are not explained fully and may involve immunological destruction of thrombocytes, their increased phagocytosis by macrophages and reduced production by the bone marrow as a result of its hypoplasia.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1098612X12466552">12</xref></sup> For the cases studied here, the elimination of rickettsia from the body by tetracyclines also contributed to the withdrawal of this haematological irregularity. Tetracyclines appear to be the most efficacious in the treatment of anaplasmosis in cats, although in case of poor tolerance of this group of antibiotics, ampicillin or amoxicillin with clavulanic acid may be also used to combat the infection.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1098612X12466552">12</xref></sup> We also used dexamethasone in the therapy. An immune-mediated mechanism is partially responsible for the thrombocytopenia and decreased platelet function. The rationale for corticosteroid therapy has some scientific basis. Some clinicians prefer to use glucocorticoids and tetracycline in combination initially because of the difficulty in distinguishing between anaplasmosis and immune-mediated thrombocytopenia. Even though the use of corticosteroids in granulocytic anaplasmosis (GA) is ambiguous, it can also be indicated as a therapeutic mean in primary and secondary immune mediated haemolytic anaemia (IMHA) owing to stabilisation of erythrocyte membrane.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1098612X12466552">22</xref></sup></p>
<p>In one cat, the analysis of the blood smears stained using the Giemsa method showed no inclusions characteristic of <italic>A phagocytophilum</italic> in the leukocytes; similar observations were made by Lappin et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1098612X12466552">12</xref></sup> Out of the six cats in the bodies of which DNA of <italic>A phagocytophilum</italic> was detected using molecular biology techniques, the presence of morula in blood was shown only in one animal. Later, a cytological test did not reveal any of these structures in its blood cells. As the genetic material of the rickettsia was shown using the PCR method at an early stage of infection, one may assume that this technique is more sensitive than others (including serological methods), especially while detecting the acute phase of the infection.</p>
<p><italic>Anaplasma phagocytophilum</italic> infection in the cats was confirmed by molecular tests. The analysed 16S rRNA gene fragment of rickettsia showed 99.6–100% similarity to the corresponding sequence GU183908 Uncultured <italic>Anaplasma</italic> species clone Lublin-1, which was obtained in earlier studies of a clinical case of equine anaplasmosis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1098612X12466552">9</xref></sup> This suggests an endemic occurrence of this microorganism strain in Poland.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1098612X12466552" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>The fact that <italic>Anaplasma</italic> species infection has been detected in cats demonstrates the danger of this disease in areas of eastern Poland. This infection must be considered when severe pathological clinical signs follow contact between animals and ticks, and are accompanied by thrombocytopenia in a haematological test.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors thank Marcin Garbal and Jacek Kutrzuba for clinical consultations.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>This research received no specific grant from any funding agency in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Conflict of interest</label>
<p>The authors do not have any potential conflicts of interest to declare.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other">
<p><bold>Accepted:</bold> 10 October 2012</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1098612X12466552">
<label>1</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dumler</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barbet</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bekker</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dasch</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Reorganization of genera in the families Rickettsiaceae and Anaplasmataceae in the order Rickettsiales: unification of some species of Ehrlichia with Anaplasma, Cowdria with Ehrlichia and Ehrlichia with Neorickettsia, descriptions of six new species combinations and designation of Ehrlichia equi and ‘HGE agent’ as subjective synonyms of <italic>Ehrlichia phagocytophila</italic></article-title>. <source>Int J Sys Evo Microbiol</source> <year>2001</year>; <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>2145</fpage>–<lpage>2165</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1098612X12466552">
<label>2</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Adaszek</surname><given-names>Ł</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Winiarczyk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Epizootical situation of dogs ehrlichiosis in area of Lubelskie voivodship</article-title>. <source>Ann UMCS, sec DD</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>–<lpage>71</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1098612X12466552">
<label>3</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Winiarczyk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adaszek</surname><given-names>Ł</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Štefancˇikovà</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pet’ko</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cislakova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Puchalski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Serological investigations for borreliosis and ehrlichiosis in pig and cattle populations in the Lublin voivodeship</article-title>. <source>Med Weter</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>561</fpage>–<lpage>565</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1098612X12466552">
<label>4</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cisak</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chmielewska-Badora</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zwolin’ski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wójcik-Fatla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Polak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dutkiewicz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Risk of tick-borne bacterial diseases among workers of Roztocze National Park (south-western Poland)</article-title>. <source>Ann Agric Environ Med</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>132</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1098612X12466552">
<label>5</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zygner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jaros</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>We˛drychowicz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of Babesia canis, Borrelia afzelii, and Anaplasma phagocytophilum infection in hard ticks removed from dogs in Warsaw (central Poland)</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>153</volume>:<fpage>139</fpage>–<lpage>142</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1098612X12466552">
<label>6</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Adaszek</surname><given-names>Ł</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Winiarczyk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Identification of Anaplasma spp rickettsia isolated from horses from clinical disease cases in Poland</article-title>. <source>Zoonozes Public Health</source> <year>2011</year>; <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>514</fpage>–<lpage>518</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1098612X12466552">
<label>7</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Adaszek</surname><given-names>Ł</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klimiuk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Skrzypczak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Górna</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zie˛tek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Winiarczyk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The identification of Anaplasma spp isolated from fallow deer (Dama dama) on a free-range farm in eastern Poland</article-title>. <source>Pol J Vet Sci</source> <year>2012</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>393</fpage>–<lpage>394</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1098612X12466552">
<label>8</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Altay</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aydin</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dumanli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aktas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Molecular detection of Theileria and Babesia infections in cattle</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>158</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>301</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1098612X12466552">
<label>9</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Adaszek</surname><given-names>Ł</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Winiarczyk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Łukaszewska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>A first case of ehrlichiosis in a horse in Poland</article-title>. <source>Dtsch Tierärztl Wochenschr</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>116</volume>: <fpage>330</fpage>–<lpage>334</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1098612X12466552">
<label>10</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Neer</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Breitschwerdt</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lappin</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Consensus statement on ehrlichial disease of small animals from the Infectious Disease Study Group of the ACVIM</article-title>. <source>J Vet Int Med</source> <year>2002</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>309</fpage>–<lpage>335</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1098612X12466552">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Stuen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title><italic>Anaplasma phagocytophilum</italic> – the most widespread tick-borne infection in animals in Europe</article-title>.<source>Vet Res Commun</source> <year>2007</year>; <volume>31</volume> (<supplement>Suppl 1</supplement>): <fpage>78</fpage>–<lpage>79</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1098612X12466552">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lappin</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bjöersdorff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Breitschwerdt</surname><given-names>EB.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Feline granulocytotropic anaplasmosis</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
</person-group> (ed). <article-title>Infectious diseases of the dog and cat</article-title>. <edition>3rd ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>WB Saunders</publisher-name>, <year>2006</year>, pp <fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>229</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1098612X12466552">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lappin</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Breitschwerdt</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dunnigan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rha</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular and serologic evidence of <italic>Anaplasma phagocytophilum</italic> infection in cats in North America</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source> <year>2004</year>; <volume>225</volume>: <fpage>893</fpage>–<lpage>896</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1098612X12466552">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bjöersdorff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Svendenius</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Massung</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Feline granulocytic ehrlichiosis – a report of a new clinical entity and characterisation of the infectious agent</article-title>. <source>J Small Anim Pract</source> <year>1999</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>20</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage></citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1098612X12466552">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tarello</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Microscopic and clinical evidence for <italic>Anaplasma (Ehrlichia) phagocytophilum infection in Italian cats</italic></article-title>.<source>Vet Rec</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>156</volume>: <fpage>772</fpage>–<lpage>774</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1098612X12466552">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schaarschmidt-Kiener</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Graf</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>von Loewenich</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title><italic>Anaplasma phagocytophilum</italic> infection in a cat in Switzerland.</article-title> <source>Schweiz Arch Tierheilkd</source> <year>2009</year>; <volume>151</volume>: <fpage>336</fpage>–<lpage>341</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1098612X12466552">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Heikkilä</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bondarenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mihalkov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pfister</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spillmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title><italic>Anaplasma phagocytophilum</italic> infection in a domestic cat in Finland: Case report</article-title>. <source>Acta Vet Scand</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>62</fpage>–<lpage>66</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1098612X12466552">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Breitschwerdt</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Canine and feline anaplasmosis – emerging infectious diseases</article-title>. In: <conf-name>2nd CVBD Symposium Mazara Del Vallo</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Sicily, Italy</conf-loc>, <conf-date>25–28 April 2007</conf-date>, pp <fpage>6</fpage>–<lpage>14</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Leverkusen</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bayer HealthCare AG, Animal Health Division</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1098612X12466552">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Binns</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Birtles</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smithson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kenny</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Molecular evidence of tick-transmitted infections in dogs and cats in the United Kingdom</article-title>. <source>Vet Rec</source> <year>2005</year>; <volume>157</volume>: <fpage>645</fpage>–<lpage>648</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1098612X12466552">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Torina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alongi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Naranjo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Scimeca</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nicosia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>di Marco</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of anaplasma infections in Sicily, Italy</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source> <year>2008</year>; <volume>1149</volume>: <fpage>90</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1098612X12466552">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mazepa</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trepanier</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Clinical presentation of 26 Anaplasma phagocytophilum-seropositive dogs residing in an endemic area</article-title>. <source>J Am Anim Hosp Assoc</source> <year>2010</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>405</fpage>–<lpage>412</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1098612X12466552">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peek</surname><given-names>SF.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <article-title>Icterus</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sprayberry</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
</person-group> (eds). <source>Current therapy in equine medicine</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Saunders Elsevier</publisher-name>, <year>2009</year>, p <fpage>459</fpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>