<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">OTO</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spoto</journal-id>
<journal-title>Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0194-5998</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1097-6817</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0194599812451840</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0194599812451840</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Systematic Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Effect of Continuous Positive Airway Pressure on C-reactive Protein Levels in Sleep Apnea</article-title>
<subtitle>A Meta-analysis</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0194599812451840">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0194599812451840">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Samuelson</surname><given-names>Christian G.</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0194599812451840">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>Craig</given-names></name>
<degrees>MBChB</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0194599812451840">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>Michelle</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0194599812451840">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>Kanwar</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, JD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0194599812451840">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>Ninos J.</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0194599812451840">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Pa-Chun</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD, MSc</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3-0194599812451840">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Hsin-Ching</given-names></name>
<degrees>MD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4-0194599812451840">4</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0194599812451840"><label>1</label>Rush University Medical Center, Chicago, Illinois, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-0194599812451840"><label>2</label>Advanced Center for Specialty Care, Advocate Illinois Masonic Medical Center, Chicago, Illinois, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff3-0194599812451840"><label>3</label>Department of Otolaryngology, Cathay General Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan</aff>
<aff id="aff4-0194599812451840"><label>4</label>Department of Otolaryngology, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, Kaohsiung Medical Center, Taiwan</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0194599812451840">Michael Friedman, MD, Advanced Center for Specialty Care, 30 North Michigan Ave, Suite 1107, Chicago, IL 60602, USA Email: <email>hednnek@aol.com</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>147</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>423</fpage>
<lpage>433</lpage>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>4</day>
<month>9</month>
<year>2011</year>
</date>
<date date-type="rev-recd">
<day>7</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>10</day>
<month>2</month>
<year>2012</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© American Academy of Otolaryngology—Head and Neck Surgery Foundation 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Official journal of the American Academy of Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery Foundation</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<sec id="section1-0194599812451840">
<title>Objective</title>
<p>Evaluate the effects of continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) on C-reactive protein (CRP) levels, reported either as a primary or secondary end point among patients with obstructive sleep apnea-hypopnea syndrome (OSAHS) based on a meta-analysis of published studies.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-0194599812451840">
<title>Data Sources</title>
<p>English-language searches of PubMed, Ovid, and the Cochrane databases were completed. Reference sections of identified studies were also examined for additional relevant articles to review.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-0194599812451840">
<title>Review Methods</title>
<p>Studies of adult patients with OSAHS who reported pre- and post-CPAP treatment CRP were reviewed and analyzed. Two independent reviewers extracted data from 10 peer-reviewed studies, which were combined using a random effects meta-analysis model.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-0194599812451840">
<title>Results</title>
<p>The CPAP treatment was found to lead to a significant reduction in CRP levels (17.8%, <italic>P</italic> = .002). This corresponds to an effect size of −0.485 (−0.731, −0.240). Sensitivity analysis was done to determine the impact of study design. Both case-control studies and case-series studies yielded a significant effect. Sensitivity analysis also yielded a significant effect for studies with average body mass index &lt;30, studies where CPAP was employed over automatic positive airway pressure, and studies treating patients ≤3 months. Analysis of publication bias, however, revealed a likelihood of “missing” studies.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-0194599812451840">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Although there is a significant lack of high-quality studies addressing this question, this analysis suggests that treatment with CPAP leads to a statistically significant reduction in CRP levels. However, the mean pre- and posttreatment CRP levels observed are considered “high risk” for cardiovascular morbidity. The clinical significance of this finding as it relates to cardiovascular risk reduction and the relationship between CRP and OSAHS requires further study.</p>
</sec>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>continuous positive airway pressure</kwd>
<kwd>CPAP</kwd>
<kwd>C-reactive protein</kwd>
<kwd>CRP</kwd>
<kwd>obstructive sleep apnea-hypopnea syndrome</kwd>
<kwd>sleep apnea</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Systemic inflammation is ever increasingly being linked to a number of chronic diseases such as atherosclerosis, coronary artery and cerebrovascular disease, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, and osteoporosis. In addition, numerous systematic studies have identified inflammatory mediators as both a cause and a risk factor for the morbidity and mortality associated with these conditions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0194599812451840">1</xref></sup> C-reactive protein (CRP) is an easily testable, sensitive biomarker for systemic inflammation. Multiple studies have shown that elevated CRP is associated with the risk of future cardiac events, and the American Heart Association (AHA) recommends using CRP in risk factor assessment in adults without known cardiac disease. In addition to cardiac disease, there is also evidence linking elevated CRP levels to obstructive sleep apnea-hypopnea syndrome (OSAHS).</p>
<p>Obstructive sleep apnea-hypopnea syndrome is characterized by nighttime episodes of apnea and/or hypopnea, which result in a temporary oxygen desaturation. This results in persistent hypertension and prolonged systemic inflammation, both of which are secondary to sympathetic activation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0194599812451840">2</xref></sup> It is also thought that more severe OSAHS can lead to daytime hypoxic episodes that cause heart and end-organ damage by this same mechanism.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0194599812451840">2</xref></sup> Many studies have shown that there is a strong association between OSAHS and cardiovascular disease.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0194599812451840">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0194599812451840">4</xref></sup> In addition, recent studies have found CRP to be elevated in patients with OSAHS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0194599812451840">5</xref></sup> Furthermore, several studies have shown levels of CRP to correlate with severity of OSAHS.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0194599812451840">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0194599812451840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0194599812451840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0194599812451840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0194599812451840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0194599812451840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-0194599812451840"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0194599812451840">13</xref></sup> It remains controversial, however, if these results are applicable to all patients suffering from OSAHS.</p>
<p>A useful tool for the noninvasive treatment of OSAHS is continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP). Depending on the ability of the patient to tolerate it, CPAP can offer significant benefits. Continuous positive airway pressure eliminates hypoxic episodes and results in improved sleep. In addition, compliance with therapy can result in significant reduction in systolic/diastolic hypertension, particularly in drug-resistant patients. Furthermore, CPAP has also been shown to improve overall cardiac function and reduce mortality.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0194599812451840">14</xref></sup> Given the prevalence of OSAHS and its adverse consequences on cardiovascular health, several studies have examined the effect of CPAP on CRP levels.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0194599812451840">15</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0194599812451840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0194599812451840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0194599812451840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0194599812451840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0194599812451840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0194599812451840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0194599812451840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0194599812451840"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0194599812451840">24</xref></sup> Unfortunately, these trials were small in sample size, and many lacked sufficient statistical power to detect a significant change in serum CRP following CPAP therapy.</p>
<p>The purpose of this investigation is to evaluate the effects of CPAP on CRP levels, reported either as a primary or secondary end point, among patients with OSAHS. We hypothesize that, in gaining significant numbers of patients, we will clarify the relationship between CPAP and CRP, as well as the relationship between CRP and OSAHS.</p>
<sec id="section6-0194599812451840" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="section7-0194599812451840">
<title>Literature Search</title>
<p>A computerized search was conducted to identify literature on the topic of CRP levels in patients with OSAHS after treatment with CPAP. The comprehensive literature search was performed using PubMed, Ovid, and the Cochrane database. Search terms included the following keywords: <italic>C-reactive protein and CPAP; OSAHS, CRP and CPAP; CPAP and inflammatory markers;</italic> and <italic>CPAP and cardiovascular risk factors</italic>. The reference sections of identified studies were examined for additional relevant articles to review.</p>
<p>The initial search was performed independently by the reviewers Michael Friedman (M.F) .and Michelle Fisher (M.D.F). Based on the search results and reference section reviews, 136 articles were identified. Initial screening of article titles and abstracts retrieved from the search was performed based on the inclusion/exclusion criteria. After discussion between the 2 reviewers, 64 articles were found to be relevant to this study.</p>
<p>The 64 articles then underwent second-stage review. The articles were read and discussed in detail by the 2 reviewers. Those articles that did not meet inclusion criteria pertaining to automatic positive airway pressure (APAP)/CPAP compliance were excluded. In some articles, key data were missing, including pre- and posttreatment CRP levels. The authors of the articles were contacted to try to receive additional data. The articles were excluded if the authors did not respond with enough data for inclusion. At the end of this process, 10 studies were identified that presented adequate data and met inclusion criteria (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0194599812451840"><bold>Figure 1</bold></xref>).</p>
<fig id="fig1-0194599812451840" position="float">
<label>Figure 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Graphic representation of literature review and how inclusion/exclusion criteria were used to arrive at studies to be included for statistical analysis. PRISMA outline was used. APAP, automatic positive airway pressure; CPAP, continuous positive airway pressure; CRP, C-reactive protein; PSG, polysomnography.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0194599812451840-fig1.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-0194599812451840">
<title>Inclusion/Exclusion Criteria</title>
<p>The study was designed to review those studies reporting CRP levels before and after CPAP treatment in patients with OSAHS. The research inquiry for the study was to determine the effect of APAP or CPAP in patients with OSAHS on CRP levels. The following inclusion criteria were used:</p>
<list id="list1-0194599812451840" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>All subjects reported must be older than 18 years.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>The study must have both pre- and post-APAP/CPAP CRP values reported.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Pretreatment polysomnography must be abnormal, resulting in the diagnosis of OSAHS.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>All levels of OSAHS (mild, moderate, and severe) were included.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Subjects must have reported using CPAP for &gt;4 h/night, &gt;5 times/wk.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>APAP/CPAP had to be used for ≥1 month before repeat CRP.</p></list-item>
</list>
<p>Only studies written in English were included for review. In addition, case reports, abstracts, and letters to the editor were not reviewed.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section9-0194599812451840">
<title>Statistical Analysis</title>
<p>Data were retrieved and were reviewed systematically. All calculations and plot synthesis were carried out using the Comprehensive Meta-Analysis Software Package (Englewood, New Jersey).</p>
<list id="list2-0194599812451840" list-type="order">
<list-item><p>Cochran’s <italic>Q</italic> test for determining heterogeneity was applied, where <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05 was considered a significant difference of sample population between studies. The <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> value was calculated from pre- and post-CPAP CRP levels.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Standard difference in means between pre- and posttreatment CRP levels was calculated using the random effects model. All studies were weighted for effect. A forest plot was synthesized.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Sensitivity analysis was done to determine the effect of study design (randomized controlled trial, case controlled, case series), treatment modality (CPAP/APAP), body mass index (BMI &lt;30), and duration of treatment (≤3 months). Forest plots were synthesized.</p></list-item>
<list-item><p>Analysis of publication bias was performed by calculating Egger’s regression intercept. Precision funnel plots with imputed values were created using Duval and Tweedie’s trim and fill method.</p></list-item>
</list>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-0194599812451840">
<title>Analysis of Bias</title>
<p>After extensive discussion between the reviewers, risk-of-bias tables were created for included articles.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-0194599812451840" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<p>Ten studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0194599812451840">15</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0194599812451840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0194599812451840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0194599812451840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0194599812451840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0194599812451840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0194599812451840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0194599812451840"/><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0194599812451840"/>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0194599812451840">24</xref></sup> comprising data from a total of 325 patients were included for review (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0194599812451840"><bold>Table 1</bold></xref>). Of those analyzed, 93.14% (80%-100%) were men, and the mean (weighted) age was 51.54 years (range, 44-55.3 years). The average duration of treatment was 4 months (range, 1-6 months), and the average nightly use of CPAP was 5.49 hours (range, 4.7-6.6 hours). The average BMI was 33.12 (range, 29.3-46.1). The average apnea-hypopnea index was 55.7 (46-91) events per hour, and the average Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) score was 14.7 (10.5-15.8). The level of evidence of each study is also included. Among the included studies, 2 are randomized controlled studies, 2 are case-controlled studies, and 6 are case series.</p>
<table-wrap id="table1-0194599812451840" position="float">
<label>Table 1.</label>
<caption>
<p>Characteristics of Included Studies</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table1-0194599812451840" xlink:href="10.1177_0194599812451840-table1.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Author</th>
<th align="center">Year</th>
<th align="center">Country</th>
<th align="center">No. Patients</th>
<th align="center">Treatment</th>
<th align="center">Duration, mo</th>
<th align="center">Design</th>
<th align="center">LOE</th>
<th align="center">Age, y</th>
<th align="center">BMI</th>
<th align="center">ESS</th>
<th align="center">AHI</th>
<th align="center">% Male</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Carneiro et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0194599812451840">16</xref></sup></td>
<td>2009</td>
<td>Brazil</td>
<td>7</td>
<td>CPAP</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>CCS</td>
<td>3b</td>
<td>40.1</td>
<td>46.1</td>
<td>10.5</td>
<td>91</td>
<td>100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dorkova et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0194599812451840">17</xref></sup></td>
<td>2008</td>
<td>Slovakia</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>APAP</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>RCT</td>
<td>1b</td>
<td>51.3</td>
<td>32.8</td>
<td>12.6</td>
<td>65</td>
<td>93.75</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Drager et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0194599812451840">18</xref></sup></td>
<td>2007</td>
<td>Brazil</td>
<td>12</td>
<td>CPAP</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>CS</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>44</td>
<td>29.9</td>
<td>14.1</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Drummond et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0194599812451840">19</xref></sup></td>
<td>2009</td>
<td>Portugal</td>
<td>98</td>
<td>APAP</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>CS</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>55.3</td>
<td>33.2</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>52</td>
<td>100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Iesato et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0194599812451840">20</xref></sup></td>
<td>2007</td>
<td>Japan</td>
<td>36</td>
<td>APAP</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>CS</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>49.8</td>
<td>28.9</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>58</td>
<td>100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ishida et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0194599812451840">22</xref></sup></td>
<td>2009</td>
<td>Japan</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>CPAP</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>CS</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>29.3</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>80</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Kohler et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0194599812451840">15</xref></sup></td>
<td>2009</td>
<td>UK</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>APAP</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>RCT</td>
<td>1b</td>
<td>48.1</td>
<td>35.8</td>
<td>15.8</td>
<td align="center">—</td>
<td>100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Partuno et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0194599812451840">23</xref></sup></td>
<td>2007</td>
<td>Italy</td>
<td>16</td>
<td>CPAP</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>CS</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>47</td>
<td>35.2</td>
<td>14.1</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>81.25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td/>
<td/>
<td/>
<td>15</td>
<td>APAP</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>CS</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>46.7</td>
<td>36.4</td>
<td>15.8</td>
<td>47</td>
<td>80</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Steiropoulos et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0194599812451840">24</xref></sup></td>
<td>2007</td>
<td>Greece</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>CPAP</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>CS</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>46.8</td>
<td>36.36</td>
<td>13</td>
<td>57</td>
<td>80</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Yokoe et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0194599812451840">21</xref></sup></td>
<td>2003</td>
<td>Japan</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>CPAP</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>CCS</td>
<td>3b</td>
<td>47.7</td>
<td>31.7</td>
<td>12.6</td>
<td>58</td>
<td>100</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn1-0194599812451840">
<p>Abbreviations: AHI, apnea-hypopnea index; APAP, automatic positive airway pressure; BMI, body mass index; CCS, case-controlled study; CPAP, continuous positive airway pressure; CS, case series; ESS, Epworth Sleepiness Scale; RCT, randomized controlled trial. LOE, level of evidence: 1b (randomized controlled trials), 3b (individual case-controlled study), and 4 (case series).</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<sec id="section12-0194599812451840">
<title>Quality of Data</title>
<p>Analysis of the types of bias associated with each type of study is outlined in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0194599812451840"><bold>Table 2a-c</bold></xref>.</p>
<table-wrap id="table2-0194599812451840" position="float">
<label>Table 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Randomized Controlled Trials, Case-Controlled Studies, and Case-Series Studies</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table2-0194599812451840" xlink:href="10.1177_0194599812451840-table2.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Study</th>
<th align="center">Design-Bias</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" colspan="2">(a) Randomized Controlled Trials</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Kohler et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0194599812451840">15</xref></sup></td>
<td>Randomized and blinded study on 100 men with moderate/severe OSA. Patients received either therapeutic or sham CPAP. Blood levels of markers were taken at 4 weeks and reported. Given the short duration, there may be a reporting bias that may not accurately represent the true long-term effects. In addition, there is no indication that there was control for collection bias.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Drager et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0194599812451840">18</xref></sup></td>
<td>Randomized study of 24 patients with severe OSA treated with either CPAP or no treatment for 4 months. At that time, CRP levels, catecholamine levels, and arterial measurements were taken/reviewed by people blinded to the treatment. Although collection bias was controlled for, there was no blinding in the treatment, which may act as a source of bias.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">(b) Case-Controlled Studies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Carneiro et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0194599812451840">16</xref></sup></td>
<td>Plasma levels of inflammatory cytokines were evaluated in 16 obese males with OSA with 13 BMI-matched controls. Plasma levels were redrawn 3 months after CPAP therapy.<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0194599812451840">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Yokoe et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0194599812451840">21</xref></sup></td>
<td>Thirty patients with OSA were matched with 14 obese control patients. Inflammatory markers were drawn prior to and after 1 month of CPAP treatment in the OSA group.<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0194599812451840">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="2">(c) Case-Series Studies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Dorkova et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0194599812451840">17</xref></sup></td>
<td>Thirty-two patients with severe OSA and metabolic syndrome were treated with 8 weeks of CPAP therapy. CRP and inflammatory mediators were analyzed pre- and posttreatment.<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0194599812451840">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Drummond et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0194599812451840">19</xref></sup></td>
<td>Ninety-eight male patients with moderate to severe OSA were treated with APAP. CRP levels were drawn prior to treatment and at 6 months.<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0194599812451840">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Iesato et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0194599812451840">20</xref></sup></td>
<td>Study of 36 male patients with OSA, selected from a larger group to undergo 3-month CPAP therapy. CRP levels and inflammatory markers were drawn before and after treatment.<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0194599812451840">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Ishida et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0194599812451840">22</xref></sup></td>
<td>Fifty-five patients with OSA were treated with CPAP for 6 months. Pre- and post-CRP levels were drawn, and overall compliance was noted. CRP levels were compared in compliant and noncompliant patients.<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0194599812451840">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Partuno et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0194599812451840">23</xref></sup></td>
<td>Thirty-one patients with severe OSA underwent standard CPAP titration and then were randomized to either CPAP or APAP for 3 months. CRP levels were drawn prior to and after treatment.<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0194599812451840">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Steiropoulos et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0194599812451840">24</xref></sup></td>
<td>Fifty-three patients newly diagnosed with OSA were treated with CPAP for 6 months. Pre- and post-CRP levels were drawn. CRP levels were compared in compliant and noncompliant patients.<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0194599812451840">a</xref></sup></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn2-0194599812451840">
<p>Abbreviations: APAP, automatic positive airway pressure; BMI, body mass index; CPAP, continuous positive airway pressure; CRP, C-reactive protein; OSA, obstructive sleep apnea.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn3-0194599812451840">
<label>a</label>
<p>Given the lack of randomization/blinding, there is a risk of sampling/selection, measurement, reader, and reporting bias.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-0194599812451840">
<title>Effect of Positive Pressue on CRP Levels</title>
<p>The mean (SD) CRP of these studies reduced from 4.3 ±0.39 mg/dL to 3.5 ±0.46 mg/dL following CPAP treatment (<italic>P</italic> = .002) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0194599812451840"><bold>Table 3</bold></xref>). This corresponds to a total standard mean difference of −0.485 (−0.731, −0.240; <italic>P</italic> &lt; .000) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0194599812451840"><bold>Figure 2</bold></xref>). <italic>I</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0194599812451840">2</xref></sup>, based on pre- and post-CRP levels, was 73.05. As such, if all studies are included, CPAP does lead to a significant reduction in CRP levels.</p>
<table-wrap id="table3-0194599812451840" position="float">
<label>Table 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Effect of Continuous Positive Airway Pressure on CRP Levels</p>
</caption>
<graphic alternate-form-of="table3-0194599812451840" xlink:href="10.1177_0194599812451840-table3.tif"/>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col align="left"/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
<col align="char" char="."/>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">Authors</th>
<th align="center">Sample Size</th>
<th align="center">Preoperative Mean (SD) CRP, mg/dL</th>
<th align="center">Postoperative Mean (SD) CRP, mg/dL</th>
<th align="center"><italic>P</italic> Value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Carneiro et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-0194599812451840">16</xref></sup></td>
<td>7</td>
<td>0.85 (0.29)</td>
<td>0.72 (0.34)</td>
<td>.109</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dorkova et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-0194599812451840">17</xref></sup></td>
<td>16</td>
<td>0.39 (0.37)</td>
<td>0.28 (0.21)</td>
<td>.196</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Drager et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-0194599812451840">18</xref></sup></td>
<td>12</td>
<td>0.37 (1.80)</td>
<td>0.20 (1.20)</td>
<td>.001<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0194599812451840">*</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Drummond et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-0194599812451840">19</xref></sup></td>
<td>98</td>
<td>0.52 (0.53)</td>
<td>0.54 (0.92)</td>
<td>.387</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Iesato et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-0194599812451840">20</xref></sup></td>
<td>36</td>
<td>0.18 (0.17)</td>
<td>0.10 (0.12)</td>
<td>.014<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0194599812451840">*</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ishida et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-0194599812451840">22</xref></sup></td>
<td>40</td>
<td>0.23 (0.25)</td>
<td>0.16 (0.19)</td>
<td>.042<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0194599812451840">*</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Kohler et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-0194599812451840">15</xref></sup></td>
<td>48</td>
<td>0.31 (0.16)</td>
<td>0.28 (0.13)</td>
<td>.2008</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Partuno et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0194599812451840">23</xref></sup></td>
<td>16</td>
<td>0.80 (0.30)</td>
<td>0.47 (0.40)</td>
<td>.006<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0194599812451840">*</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Partuno et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-0194599812451840">23</xref></sup> (APAP)</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>0.65 (0.30)</td>
<td>0.40 (0.38)</td>
<td>.02<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0194599812451840">*</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Steiropoulos et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-0194599812451840">24</xref></sup></td>
<td>20</td>
<td>0.72 (0.54)</td>
<td>0.55 (0.47)</td>
<td>.14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Yokoe et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-0194599812451840">21</xref></sup></td>
<td>17</td>
<td>0.29 (0.08)</td>
<td>0.11 (0.03)</td>
<td>.00006<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0194599812451840">*</xref>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>All studies</td>
<td>325</td>
<td>0.43 (0.39)</td>
<td>0.35 (0.46)</td>
<td>.002<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn5-0194599812451840">*</xref>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table-wrap-foot>
<fn id="table-fn4-0194599812451840">
<p>Abbreviations: APAP, automatic positive airway pressure; CRP, C-reactive protein.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="table-fn5-0194599812451840">
<label>*</label>
<p><italic>P</italic> &lt; .05.</p>
</fn>
</table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
<fig id="fig2-0194599812451840" position="float">
<label>Figure 2.</label>
<caption>
<p>Meta-analysis and forest plot of all studies included. Calculations based on random effects model. CI, confidence interval; CRP, C-reactive protein.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0194599812451840-fig2.tif"/>
</fig>
<sec id="section14-0194599812451840">
<title>Sensitivity Analysis—Study Type</title>
<sec id="section15-0194599812451840">
<title>Randomized controlled trials</title>
<p>The total standard mean difference between the randomized controlled studies is not significant, with a corresponding value of −0.674 (−1.740, 0.391; <italic>P</italic> = .215) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0194599812451840"><bold>Figure 3</bold></xref>). As such, among the 2 studies with the “highest level of evidence,” CPAP does not lead to a significant reduction in CRP.</p>
<fig id="fig3-0194599812451840" position="float">
<label>Figure 3.</label>
<caption>
<p>Sensitivity analysis and forest plot based on all included randomized controlled trials. Calculations based on random effects model. CI, confidence interval; CRP, C-reactive protein.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0194599812451840-fig3.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section16-0194599812451840">
<title>Case-controlled/case-series trials</title>
<p>The total standard mean difference between the case-controlled studies is significant, with a corresponding value of −1.068 (−1.641, −0.495; <italic>P</italic> = .000) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0194599812451840"><bold>Figure 4</bold></xref>). The total standard mean difference between the case-series studies is significant, with a corresponding value of −0.354 (−0.606, −0.101; <italic>P</italic> = .006) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-0194599812451840"><bold>Figure 5</bold></xref>). As such, among the studies with “lower-level evidence,” CPAP does lead to a significant reduction in CRP levels.</p>
<fig id="fig4-0194599812451840" position="float">
<label>Figure 4.</label>
<caption>
<p>Sensitivity analysis and forest plot based on all included case-controlled controlled trials. Calculations based on random effects model. CI, confidence interval; CRP, C-reactive protein.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0194599812451840-fig4.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig5-0194599812451840" position="float">
<label>Figure 5.</label>
<caption>
<p>Sensitivity analysis and forest plot based on all included case series. Calculations based on random effects model. CI, confidence interval; CRP, C-reactive protein.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0194599812451840-fig5.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section17-0194599812451840">
<title>Sensitivity Analysis—Intervention Type</title>
<sec id="section18-0194599812451840">
<title>CPAP/APAP</title>
<p>The total standard mean difference between the CPAP studies is significant, with a corresponding value of −0.720 (−1.072, −0.369; <italic>P</italic> = 0.000) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-0194599812451840"><bold>Figure 6</bold></xref>). The total standard mean difference between the APAP studies is not significant, with a corresponding value of −0.251 (−0.517, 0.015; <italic>P</italic> = .065) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-0194599812451840"><bold>Figure 7</bold></xref>). As such, although CPAP treatment does significantly lower CRP levels, treatment with APAP does not.</p>
<fig id="fig6-0194599812451840" position="float">
<label>Figure 6.</label>
<caption>
<p>Sensitivity analysis and forest plot based on all included continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) studies. Calculations based on random effects model. CI, confidence interval; CRP, C-reactive protein.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0194599812451840-fig6.tif"/>
</fig>
<fig id="fig7-0194599812451840" position="float">
<label>Figure 7.</label>
<caption>
<p>Sensitivity analysis and forest plot based on all included automatic positive airway pressure (APAP) trials. Calculations based on random effects model. CI, confidence interval; CRP, C-reactive protein.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0194599812451840-fig7.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section19-0194599812451840">
<title>Sensitivity Analysis—Population Type</title>
<sec id="section20-0194599812451840">
<title>BMI &lt;30</title>
<p>The total standard mean difference between the studies with an average BMI &lt;30 is significant, with a corresponding value of −0.455 (−0.678, −0.232; <italic>P</italic> = .000) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig8-0194599812451840"><bold>Figure 8</bold></xref>). As such, the analysis reveals that CPAP treatment leads to a significant reduction in CRP in patients with a BMI &lt;30.</p>
<fig id="fig8-0194599812451840" position="float">
<label>Figure 8.</label>
<caption>
<p>Sensitivity analysis and forest plot based on all included trials with average body mass index (BMI) &lt;30. Calculations based on random effects model. CI, confidence interval; CRP, C-reactive protein.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0194599812451840-fig8.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="section21-0194599812451840">
<title>Duration of treatment</title>
<p>The total standard mean difference between the studies with a CPAP duration of ≤3 months is significant, with a corresponding value of −0.559 (−0.826, −0.291; <italic>P</italic> = .000) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-0194599812451840"><bold>Figure 9</bold></xref>). As such, the analysis reveals that CPAP treatment leads to a significant reduction in CRP in patients treated for ≤3 months.</p>
<fig id="fig9-0194599812451840" position="float">
<label>Figure 9.</label>
<caption>
<p>Sensitivity analysis and forest plot based on all included trials with treatment ≤3 months. Calculations based on random effects model. CI, confidence interval; CRP, C-reactive protein.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0194599812451840-fig9.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section22-0194599812451840">
<title>Assessment of Bias</title>
<p>Publication bias was assessed both mathematically using Egger’s regression intercept (<italic>P</italic> = .000) and graphically using a precision funnel plot with Duval and Tweedie’s trim and fill (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-0194599812451840"><bold>Figure 10</bold></xref>). Five possible unpublished studies were “found” (black dots), shifting the standard mean difference to −0.232 (−0.473, 0.009). This suggests that publication bias is likely and that if these studies were “added,” they would likely negate our original results on the effectiveness of CPAP at lowering CRP levels.</p>
<fig id="fig10-0194599812451840" position="float">
<label>Figure 10.</label>
<caption>
<p>Precision funnel plot with imputed values of “missing” studies in black.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0194599812451840-fig10.tif"/>
</fig>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section23-0194599812451840" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>The limitations of meta-analysis, especially pertaining to observational studies, include selection bias and confounding factors. Although the primary reviewers attempted to lessen the potential of patient selection bias through the use of the inclusion/exclusion criteria as outlined, this itself may represent a source of selection bias. One example of this was the exclusion of 17 articles that were not written in English. Although unavoidable, given the language limitations of the 2 reviewers, the exclusion of these articles may potentially weigh results in favor of one outcome over another. The consequence of limiting selection bias is the inclusion of many possible confounding factors. Assessment of publication bias using Egger’s regression was significant, suggesting that there is likely publication bias. This is further illustrated in the precision funnel plot by the lack of smaller, less precise studies to the right of the mean. When these studies are imputed to the analysis, the reduction in CRP is no longer significant. In addition, the meta-analysis included multiple case-controlled studies and case-series studies, each with the possibility of a high degree of experimental bias. As such, our results, although significant, are overshadowed by the inherent limitations and number of studies available for analysis.</p>
<p>As the included studies had varied protocols (with respect to inclusion/exclusion criteria, as well as diagnostic definition of OSAHS), the random effects model was used. This model assumes that the studies were drawn from populations that differ from each other in parameters that may have a direct effect on the outcomes and that any observed differences will be due to random error or true variation in effect. This method is considered the standard choice for outcomes related to medical decision making as conclusions may be extrapolated beyond the study.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-0194599812451840">25</xref></sup> Another limitation to our study is the controversy over the relationship between CRP and OSAHS.</p>
<p>The main controversy surrounding the relationship between CRP and OSAHS is whether a relationship actually exists at all. Numerous studies suggest that elevated CRP levels in OSAHS patients are secondary to obesity and not related to the OSAHS diagnosis, regardless of the severity of the disease.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-0194599812451840">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-0194599812451840">27</xref></sup> These studies have demonstrated that CRP levels strongly correlate with the amount of visceral and total body fat, as well as indicators of obesity such as waist circumference, waist-to-hip ratio, and BMI. In a study by Rexrode et al,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-0194599812451840">28</xref></sup> the authors concluded that women with a BMI in the upper quartile have an odds ratio of CRP elevation above the 75th percentile of 12.2. In addition, obesity itself is a risk factor for OSAHS. Therefore, any elevation of CRP noted in obese OSAHS patients may be a reflection of chronic inflammation due to obesity and not related to OSAHS-induced chronic hypoxia, as studies suggest that nonobese patients with OSAHS may not have statistically increased levels of systemic inflammatory markers.</p>
<p>Recent studies, however, suggest that CRP elevation may be independent from visceral obesity in patients with OSAHS. In a study by Punjabi and Beamer,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0194599812451840">6</xref></sup> the authors suggest that, in the absence of hypertension, diabetes, and cardiovascular disease, CRP is related to the degree of OSAHS <italic>with and without</italic> taking into account age and various parameters of obesity. In addition, Liu et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-0194599812451840">13</xref></sup> showed that in a population of 111 healthy males, CRP is associated with OSAHS severity independent of BMI. These results suggest that factors other than adiposity may be responsible for the proinflammatory state seen in OSAHS. In addition, they suggest that CRP levels can be evaluated both in and between studies, irrespective of the average BMI of the study population.</p>
<p>For the purposes of this study, we are assuming the latter hypothesis, that CRP is elevated in patients with OSAHS. Although we acknowledge that our study population is, by definition, obese (BMI &gt;30), the average pretreatment CRP levels are higher than those expected in obese patients free from OSAHS. In addition, the posttreatment BMI is unchanged. As a tool for the noninvasive treatment of OSAHS, CPAP can offer significant benefits. Studies show that depression decreases and quality of life increases in patients who use CPAP.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-0194599812451840">14</xref></sup> In addition, compliance with therapy can result in significant reduction in systolic/diastolic hypertension, particularly in drug-resistant patients. Yet, although CPAP can improve OSAHS symptoms and sequelae, there is little agreement as to its effect on CRP levels. Assuming that OSAHS is an independent variable that is associated with elevated CRP levels, further controversy exists as to whether CPAP can reduce these levels.</p>
<p>Our initial literature search returned 136 articles. After exercising the exclusionary criteria, 10 studies remained for analysis, consisting of a total of 325 patients. The results of our meta-analysis suggest that CPAP is effective in reducing CRP in patients treated for OSAHS. Furthermore, because we analyzed our data using the random effects model, these results suggest that despite the variance among study protocol and patient population, our results may represent the true response of CRP levels to CPAP treatment.</p>
<p>A sensitivity analysis of the included studies suggests that all case studies, case-controlled series, CPAP studies, studies treating patients less than 3 months, and studies with participants with a mean BMI &lt;30 yielded significant total standard mean differences. As discussed, these studies have a high risk of bias and a low level of evidence. As a result, the strength of our conclusion is somewhat limited by the quantity of quality studies available. Although BMI did not significantly change within each respective study, our results suggest that CRP levels in patients with a BMI &lt;30 may respond better to CPAP therapy. In addition, patients treated with CPAP may have a greater reduction in CRP than those treated with APAP, and it may require as little as 3 months to observe these results.</p>
<p>When all studies are included, CPAP treatment appears to significantly lower CRP levels by 0.11 mg/dL, or 17.8%. The actual clinical significance of this witnessed decrease remains in question. Even if there is a significant reduction in CRP level, the mean posttreatment levels suggest that patients remain at high risk for cardiovascular morbidity (&gt;3 mg/L as defined by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention guidelines).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-0194599812451840">29</xref></sup> There is ample evidence that CPAP treatment decreases hypertension and improves insulin sensitivity as well as overall cardiac function. Therefore, patients may be getting benefit from CPAP that is not accurately reflected in CRP. This may suggest a mechanism of improvement that is independent from CRP production. These mechanisms may be peripheral such as improved quality of life/daytime wakefulness, leading to further daytime activity and improved cardiac output during exercise, or more central mechanisms such as reduced sympathetic activity during sleep and wakefulness.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section24-0194599812451840" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<p>Although the quantity of randomized controlled studies is lacking, treatment with CPAP appears to have a significant effect on decreasing CRP levels in patients treated for OSAHS, as determined by pre- and posttreatment serum levels. Unfortunately, there still exists debate as to the true relationship between CRP and OSAHS, as well as the clinical significance of any reduction. Closely following patients for improvement in sleep study indices and clinical symptomatology remains the mainstay of treatment. Further research is needed to determine those who will have the greatest reduction with CPAP treatment, as well as to understand the interplay between cardiac risk factor reduction and reduction of CRP as it relates to patients with OSAHS.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section25-0194599812451840">
<title>Author Contributions</title>
<p><bold>Michael Friedman</bold>, study design, data collection/interpretation, drafting/revision, presentation; <bold>Christian G. Samuelson</bold>, study design, data interpretation, drafting/revision, presentation; <bold>Craig Hamilton</bold>, study design, data interpretation, drafting/revision; <bold>Michelle Fisher</bold>, study design, data collection/interpretation, drafting; <bold>Kanwar Kelley</bold>, study design, data interpretation, drafting; <bold>Ninos J. Joseph</bold>, study design, statistical analysis; <bold>Pa-Chun Wang</bold>, study design, statistical analysis, drafting; <bold>Hsin-Ching Lin</bold>, study design, statistical analysis, data interpretation, drafting.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section26-0194599812451840">
<title>Disclosures</title>
<p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> Michael Friedman is a recipient of a grant for a study on nasal irrigation as treatment for sinonasal symptoms for TriCord Pharmaceuticals and is a member of the speaker’s bureau for GlaxoSmithKline.</p>
<p><bold>Sponsorships:</bold> None.</p>
<p><bold>Funding source:</bold> This study was funded in its entirety by the principal investigator (Michael Friedman, MD).</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="presented-at">
<p>Sponsorships or competing interests that may be relevant to content are disclosed at the end of this article.</p>
<p>This article was presented at the 2011 AAO-HNSF Annual Meeting &amp; OTO EXPO; September 11-14, 2011; San Francisco, California.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0194599812451840">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pepys</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hirschfield</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>C-reactive protein: a critical update</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>1805</fpage>-<lpage>1812</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0194599812451840">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Fanfulla</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grassi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Taurino</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>D’Artavilla Lupo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trentin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The relationship of daytime hypoxemia and nocturnal hypoxia in obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source>Sleep</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>249</fpage>-<lpage>255</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0194599812451840">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Nieto</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lind</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Association of sleep-disordered breathing, sleep apnea, and hypertension in a large community-based study. Sleep Heart Health Study</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>283</volume>:<fpage>1829</fpage>-<lpage>1836</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0194599812451840">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Peppard</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Palta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Skatrud</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Prospective study of the association between sleep-disordered breathing and hypertension</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>342</volume>:<fpage>1378</fpage>-<lpage>1384</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0194599812451840">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Haack</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mullington</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Elevated inflammatory markers in response to prolonged sleep restriction are associated with increased pain experience in healthy volunteers</article-title>. <source>Sleep</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>1145</fpage>-<lpage>1152</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0194599812451840">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Punjabi</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beamer</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>C-reactive protein is associated with sleep disordered breathing independent of adiposity</article-title>. <source>Sleep</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>-<lpage>34</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0194599812451840">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kapsimalis</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Varouchakis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Manousaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Association of sleep apnea severity and obesity with insulin resistance, C-reactive protein, and leptin levels in male patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source>Lung</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>186</volume>:<fpage>209</fpage>-<lpage>217</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0194599812451840">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shamsuzzaman</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Winnicki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lanfranchi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Elevated C-reactive protein in patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>2462</fpage>-<lpage>2464</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0194599812451840">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>IY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Endothelial dysfunction and C-reactive protein in relation with the severity of obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source>Sleep</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>997</fpage>-<lpage>1001</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0194599812451840">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Saletu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nosiska</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kapfhammer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Structural and serum surrogate markers of cerebrovascular disease in obstructive sleep apnea (OSAHS): association of mild OSAHS with early atherosclerosis</article-title>. <source>J Neurol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>253</volume>:<fpage>746</fpage>-<lpage>752</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0194599812451840">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Increased serum levels of C-reactive protein and matrix metalloproteinase-9 in obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source>Chin Med J (Engl)</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>120</volume>:<fpage>1482</fpage>-<lpage>1486</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-0194599812451840">
<label>12.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zouaoui Boudjeltia</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Meerhaeghe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Doumit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Sleep apnoea-hypopnoea index is an independent predictor of high-sensitivity C-reactive protein elevation</article-title>. <source>Respiration</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>243</fpage>-<lpage>346</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-0194599812451840">
<label>13.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Lui</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>C-reactive protein is associated with obstructive sleep apnea independent of visceral obesity</article-title>. <source>Chest</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>135</volume>:<fpage>950</fpage>-<lpage>956</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-0194599812451840">
<label>14.</label>
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>Sleep Apnea and Snoring: Surgical and Non-Surgical Therapy</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Saunders</publisher-name>; <year>2009</year>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-0194599812451840">
<label>15.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kohler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pepperell</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Packwood</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of continuous positive airway pressure on systemic inflammation in patients with moderate to severe obstructive sleep apnoea: a randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Thorax</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>67</fpage>-<lpage>73</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-0194599812451840">
<label>16.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Togeiro</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ribeiro-Filho</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Continuous positive airway pressure therapy improves hypoadiponectinemia in severe obese men with obstructive sleep apnea without changes in insulin resistance</article-title>. <source>Metab Syndr Relat Disord</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>537</fpage>-<lpage>542</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-0194599812451840">
<label>17.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Dorkova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Petrasova</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Molcanyiova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Popovnakova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tkacova</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of continuous positive airway pressure on cardiovascular risk profile in patients with severe obstructive sleep apnea and metabolic syndrome</article-title>. <source>Chest</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>134</volume>:<fpage>686</fpage>-<lpage>692</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-0194599812451840">
<label>18.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Drager</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bortolotto</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Figueiredo</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lorenzi</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of continuous positive airway pressure on early signs of atherosclerosis in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>176</volume>:<fpage>706</fpage>-<lpage>712</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-0194599812451840">
<label>19.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Winck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guimaraes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Long term effect of autoadjusting positive airway pressure on C-reactive protein and interleukin-6 in men with obstructive sleep apnoea syndrome</article-title>. <source>Arch Bronconeumol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>577</fpage>-<lpage>584</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-0194599812451840">
<label>20.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Iesato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tatsumi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saibara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Decreased lipoprotein lipase in obstructive sleep apnea syndrome</article-title>. <source>Circ J</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>1293</fpage>-<lpage>1298</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-0194599812451840">
<label>21.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yokoe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Minoguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matsuo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Elevated levels of C-reactive protein and interleukin-6 in patients with obstructive sleep apnea syndrome are decreased by nasal continuous positive airway pressure</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>107</volume>:<fpage>1129</fpage>-<lpage>1134</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-0194599812451840">
<label>22.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ishida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yanagihara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Appropriate use of nasal continuous positive airway pressure decreases elevated C-reactive protein in patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source>Chest</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>136</volume>:<fpage>125</fpage>-<lpage>129</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-0194599812451840">
<label>23.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Patruno</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Costantino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Murgia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Selmi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Malliani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Montano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Fixed and autoadjusting continuous positive airway pressure treatments are not similar in reducing cardiovascular risk factors in patients with obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source>Chest</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>131</volume>:<fpage>1393</fpage>-<lpage>1399</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-0194599812451840">
<label>24.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Steiropoulos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tsara</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nena</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of continuous positive airway pressure treatment on serum cardiovascular risk factors in patients with obstructive sleep apnea-hypopnea syndrome</article-title>. <source>Chest</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>132</volume>:<fpage>843</fpage>-<lpage>851</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-0194599812451840">
<label>25.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>DerSimonian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Meta-analysis in clinical trials</article-title>. <source>Control Clin Trials</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>177</fpage>-<lpage>188</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-0194599812451840">
<label>26.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nolan</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hannigan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McNicholas</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Cardiovascular risk markers in obstructive sleep apnoea syndrome and correlation with obesity</article-title>. <source>Thorax</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>509</fpage>-<lpage>514</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-0194599812451840">
<label>27.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>Obesity, and not obstructive sleep apnea, is responsible for increased serum hs-CRP levels in patients with sleep-disordered breathing in Delhi</article-title>. <source>Sleep Med</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>149</fpage>-<lpage>156</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-0194599812451840">
<label>28.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Rexrode</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pradhan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Manson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buring</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ridker</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Relationship of total and abdominal adiposity with CRP and IL-6 in women</article-title>. <source>Ann Epidemiol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>674</fpage>-<lpage>682</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-0194599812451840">
<label>29.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rifai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tracy</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group>. <article-title>CDC/AHA workshop on markers of inflammation and cardiovascular disease: application to clinical and public health practice: report from the laboratory science discussion group</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>545</fpage>-<lpage>549</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>