<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JPE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjpe</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Planning Education and Research</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0739-456X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-6577</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0739456X11431872</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0739456X11431872</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Separate Societies: Poverty and Inequality in U.S. Cities</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Scally</surname><given-names>Corianne P.</given-names></name>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0739456X11431872">University at Albany, State University of New York</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>32</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>251</fpage>
<lpage>252</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>William W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blakely</surname><given-names>Edward J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <source>Separate Societies: Poverty and Inequality in U.S. Cities</source>, <edition>2nd ed.</edition> <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Temple University Press</publisher-name>, <year>2010</year>. <page-count count="255"/> pp. <price>$79.50</price> (hardback); <price>$30.95</price> (paperback). ISBN <isbn>978-1-43990-291-2</isbn> (hardback); <isbn>978-1-43990-292-9</isbn> (paperback)</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">Association of Collegiate Schools of Planning</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>America’s inner cities were still smoldering when the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0739456X11431872">National Advisory Commission on Civil Disorders (1968)</xref>, or Kerner Commission, reported its findings on the cause of the series of riots that devastated the nation’s urban centers. They found that the United States was “moving toward two societies, one black, one white—separate and unequal” (p. 1). Active racial discrimination and unrelenting poverty were dividing the nation into those privileged by skin color and wealth and those locked out of opportunity. To address this increasing polarization, the Kerner Commission recommended a series of federal interventions to eliminate discrimination and equalize education, employment, and housing opportunities for blacks. Barely twenty years later, William Julius <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0739456X11431872">Wilson (1987)</xref> identified a persistent underclass concentrated in U.S. urban neighborhoods: racially segregated, socially isolated and disorganized, unskilled and unemployed, and cut off from a deindustrializing economy and globalizing labor market. The Kerner Commission’s fears had quickly become reality.</p>
<p>Goldsmith and Blakely entered the fray soon thereafter with their Paul Davidoff Award–winning first edition of <italic>Separate Societies: Poverty and Inequality in U.S. Cities</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0739456X11431872">1992</xref>). They, too, found a country firmly stratified by wealth, race, gender, occupation, and geography and expressed concern about the increasing consequences of footloose capital on those being left behind without the ability to succeed. As they noted, underemployment of the poor (most of whom were indeed working, contrary to public opinion) was not only threatening individual livelihoods but national productivity in a global economy. To address such inequalities, Goldsmith and Blakely advocated for an about-face in public policies of the 1970s and 1980s that had retrenched social support programs while failing to adequately regulate restructuring capital and labor markets. They stressed the need for politically palatable universal policies, including a national industrial policy supporting labor, improving public education and its linkages to employment, and providing sufficient family supports through a destigmatized cash assistance program to all households regardless of need. To achieve such changes, Goldsmith and Blakely considered multiple sites of political pressure that could turn the tide: major corporate leaders, a reinvigorated New Deal Democratic coalition, the suburbs, or the central cities. They concluded that cities remained key to building a coalition of antipoverty interests, as they remained closest to the problems and capable of the most innovative (even radical) solutions.</p>
<p>With this second edition of <italic>Separate Societies</italic>, Goldsmith and Blakely update their arguments from twenty years ago with new data and analyses of contemporary trends of increasing inequalities. They continue to find two “separate societies” in the United States—“one rich and the other poor, one suburban and the other urban, one white and the other minority” (p. 77). The structure of the book has changed little. The Foreword previously supplied by planning practitioner Harvey Gantt is replaced by one from President Bill Clinton, who affirms the authors’ findings despite his administration’s attempts to address urban inequalities. In a substantially revised first chapter, Goldsmith and Blakely put contemporary poverty in context of political, demographic, and economic shifts over the past twenty years. They make a strong case for structural causes of poverty, rejecting more pathological or incidental causes, highlighting how deindustrialization, technological innovation, and globalization have diminished domestic job opportunities for those with low skills in both cities and their surrounding suburbs and regions. The authors present their first round of evidence in chapter 2 on “Separate Assets,” tracing the historically inequitable distribution of wealth by income group, race, gender, age, family type, and occupation across the United States with numerous data. They tell the now familiar tale of persistent underemployment and unemployment in a rapidly globalizing, technological world where the bottom rung of the economic ladder is not just out of reach but “sawed off and shipped overseas” (p. 79). Meanwhile, poor, minority workers remain concentrated in low-skilled, low-wage jobs with no means of promotion.</p>
<p>Chapter 3, “Separate Opportunities,” and chapter 4, “Separate Places,” detail two factors contributing to persistent poverty and inequality. Goldsmith and Blakely distill how globalization has provided differential opportunities for U.S. cities to either compete in an international race to the economic bottom or create environments more conducive to domestic labor needs. Industrial restructuring has cut profits, relocated jobs, depressed wages, strengthened demand for skilled labor, increased vulnerability to global capital and debt, and weakened political power. The American metropolitan landscape has changed as a result of these poorly regulated external forces, as well as intraregional spatial inequalities in housing, education, jobs, immigration, and incarceration. Concentrations of disenfranchised populations remain in city centers but have expanded into the inner-ring suburbs and even some peripheral ones, calling into question former urban–suburban distinctions and suggesting the foundations of a new antipoverty coalition.</p>
<p>On the basis of the evidence presented, Goldsmith and Blakely lay out their vision for “rebuilding the American city,” the title of their final chapter. Discouraged with the lack of federal response, private sector support, and suburban advocacy they had hoped for in their first book, they renew their discussion of building power at the local level to influence federal action. Recalling the successes of the federal Community Action Program in directly funding the political mobilization of community organizations, Goldsmith and Blakely advocate for neighborhoods to organize to demand poverty solutions. Cognizant of repeated local and state efforts to vilify the “undeserving” poor and exclude them from targeted, means-based programs meant to assist them, the authors find greater hope in universal policies like Social Security that lift all boats regardless of need. As they did in 1992, the authors point to three areas for change: a coordinated national industrial policy that saves businesses money while promoting domestic labor, enhanced education programs to better prepare the future labor force, and universal family supports to weather economic fluctuations.</p>
<p>The greatest disappointment of this book is the missed opportunity for a more substantial update. On one hand, perhaps Goldsmith and Blakely believe that circumstances have not changed enough to warrant more contemporary analysis and recommendations—a disheartening and discouraging consideration. On the other hand, while the plight of the poor has become even grimmer, the past twenty years of economic, demographic, and geographic shifts, along with research on policies to address poverty and inequality, deserve greater attention than they give it. Perhaps because of their emphasis on federal solutions, Goldsmith and Blakely overlook recent community-based attempts to address poverty and inequality by decommodifying labor and capital—such as local credit unions, employee-owned businesses, and community land trusts—although they continue to include twenty-year-old examples of mayoral–neighborhood partnerships designed to reach similar ends. They also dismiss the efficacy of regional, metropolitan, multilocal, or statewide coalitions in advocacy despite their recognition of the importance and interest of suburbs in fighting poverty. Finally, the authors continue to prefer universal policies and give too brief (although some) consideration to how legacies of discrimination and disenfranchisement would be addressed through such policies.</p>
<p>Despite these shortcomings, <italic>Separate Societies</italic> remains a classic text, offering a solid overview of social and economic theories on the roots of poverty and inequality, and providing timely and comprehensive data. Goldsmith and Blakely do this admirably without relying too heavily on the jargon of the sociologists, geographers, economists, regional scientists, and others from whom they draw. As such, it remains an important tome on social, economic, and political stratification in the United States for both those new to the material and those relatively familiar with it. While not comprehensive in the policy prescriptions or advocacy processes they propose, the authors provide much food for thought to inspire yet another generation of policymakers, planners, and scholars in their pursuit of ending poverty in the United States.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0739456X11431872">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>William</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blakely</surname><given-names>Edward</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <year>1992</year>. <source>Separate societies: Poverty and inequality in U.S. cities</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Temple University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0739456X11431872">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab>National Advisory Commission on Civil Disorders</collab>. <year>1968</year>. <source>Report of the National Advisory Commission on Civil Disorders</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Advisory Commission on Civil Disorders</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0739456X11431872">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>William J.</given-names></name>
</person-group> <year>1987</year>. <source>The truly disadvantaged: The inner city, the underclass, and public policy</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>