<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CON</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spcon</journal-id>
<journal-title>Convergence</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1354-8565</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1748-7382</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1354856512439509</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1354856512439509</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Articles</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>French videogaming</article-title>
<subtitle>What kind of culture and what support?</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name>
<surname>Dauncey</surname>
<given-names>Hugh</given-names>
</name>
<aff id="aff1-1354856512439509">Newcastle University, UK</aff>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-1354856512439509"/>
</contrib>
<bio>
<title>Biography</title>
<p>
<bold>Hugh Dauncey </bold>is Senior Lecturer in French Studies, Newcastle University, UK. His research focuses on French public policy in the field of popular culture, and the French media. Particular focuses are music and sport, and new technologies. He is the author of numerous articles and chapters dealing with the ‘exceptional’ nature of French policy approaches to popular culture and works closely with individual colleagues in France and as an associate research member of the Université de Paris 1 Sorbonne-CNRS IDHE-LGF research laboratory. He has recently co-edited (with Ph Le Guern) a volume examining contrasting French and British approaches to the academic study of popular music: <italic>Stereo: Comparative Perspectives on the Sociological Study of Popular Music in France and Britain </italic>(Ashgate, 2010) and is currently working on a number of studies of the increasing trend in France towards understanding ‘popular culture’ as a valid part of French cultural heritage.</p>
</bio>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1354856512439509">Hugh Dauncey, School of Modern Languages, Room 3.4 Old Library Building, Newcastle University, Newcastle upon Tyne, NE1 7RU, UK Email: <email>hugh.dauncey@newcastle.ac.uk</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>11</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>18</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>385</fpage>
<lpage>402</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>This article discusses developments in French public policy towards videogaming in the 2000s, and explains them by locating them within the context of French cultural policy during the Fifth Republic (especially since the 1980s), and evolving interpretations of what kinds of activities can contribute to France’s ‘cultural presence’ in the world.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Cultural industries</kwd>
<kwd>culture</kwd>
<kwd>democratisation</kwd>
<kwd>France</kwd>
<kwd>history of 21st-century cultural policy</kwd>
<kwd>popular culture</kwd>
<kwd>public policy</kwd>
<kwd>videogames</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="section1-1354856512439509">
<title>A popular leisure activity – what view from the French state?</title>
<p>In March 2006 French Culture and Communications Minister Renaud Donnedieu de Vabres awarded the prestigious decoration of<italic> Chevalier de l’ordre des Arts et des Lettres</italic> to the French videogames authors Michel Ancel (<italic>Rayman, Beyond Good and Evil, King Kong)</italic> and Frederick Raynal (<italic>Alone in the Dark, Resident Evil</italic>), and the Japanese creator of games for Nintendo, Shigeru Miyamoto. Honouring – by making them ‘Knights of Arts and Letters’ – representatives of a leisure practice frequently looked down on in France by many representatives of elite culture was a political and cultural symbol that the state wanted to redraw the conceptual, legal, financial and industrial boundaries of videogaming, and particularly, to signal that for the Ministry of Culture, video was truly ‘cultural’, rather than mere software. Other – commercial – signals of the significance of videogaming had come two years earlier, when figures revealed that in 2004, after a 10% rise over 2003, French consumer purchases in interactive leisure products had exceeded €1 billion, including more than 33 million items of software, or two for every French household. Also in 2004, the interactive leisure industry grew to employ more French citizens – 12,000 plus – than cinema, long-considered France’s prime cultural product after literature. And statistics revealed that literature itself was also being overtaken by videogaming: the most popular cultural product sold in France in 2004 was not <italic>The Da Vinci Code</italic> (800,000 copies), but the more than million-selling <italic>GTA San Andreas</italic>! After the French state’s realisation of the importance of comic-books (‘bandes dessinées’) in the 1980s and popular music (‘musiques amplifiées/actuelles’) in the 1990s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47-1354856512439509">Teillet, 2008</xref>) it was the turn of videogames to warrant attention of governments anxious to promote France’s economic and cultural independence.</p>
<p>Donnedieu de Vabres’ honouring of the videogame creators in 2006 marked a significant shift in attitudes from only a few years earlier, when it had seemed that traditional prejudices in favour of high culture were still dominant. In October 2002, Jean-Claude Larue, speaking as former member of the <italic>Conseil supérieur de l’audiovisuel</italic> (the regulatory body for audiovisual and communications industries) and then chair of the <italic>Syndicat des éditeurs de logiciels de loisirs</italic> (a videosoftware trade association) had made a dyspeptic and despairing assessment of videogaming’s chances of establishing itself as a cultural form which could co-exist in the ecological system of French culture on an equal footing with other more politically favoured activities:<disp-quote>
<p>I’ve tried in vain to convince two Presidents of the Republic and six successive Ministers of Culture that multimedia products and videogames are revolutionary and the preferred media of young people, and that French video industry is internationally recognised for its quality, but that if we leave it exposed to the winds of free trade, it will be the winds from America which will blow strongest. With fourteen recent business failures in the sector we are experiencing a massacre of French firms in a climate of general indifference. Even the Brin-Buisson Commission’s study of the effects of pirate copying neglected to look at videogames. It’s an aberration that while solutions have been found to help the film industry with appropriate labour legislation and subsidies, and the music industry is protected by minimum quotas of French songs on radio, nothing – but nothing – has been done for video. The intellectuals don’t like it. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1354856512439509">Rive, 2002 [translated by the author]</xref>)</p>
</disp-quote>Despite enduring scepticism from some quarters and, as we shall see, some remaining difficulties for the sector, by the end of the 2000s, the increasing importance being accorded to videogames by the cultural establishment and by policy-makers in culture and industry was further evidenced by the <italic>MuseoGames</italic> exhibition organised from July 2010 to March 2011 by the normally conservative and traditionalist <italic>Musée national des arts et métiers</italic>, a prestigious state-funded museum attached to the <italic>Conservatoire national des arts et métiers</italic> (CNAM) founded in 1794 as a means of fostering France’s scientific and industrial strength. Typically, the CNAM and its associated museum focus on ‘hard’ science and technology, and showcasing videogames reflected new ambitions within the Ministry of Culture to promote the ‘heritigisation’ of gaming, both as technology and as cultural practice and form. Symbolic and rhetorical approval of the entry of videogames into the pantheon of ‘heritage’ was given by the visit of Culture Minister Frédéric Mitterrand in June 2010, as <italic>MuseoGames</italic> was pre-presented to the press.</p>
<p>Since the late 1980s, French videogame companies have been – despite occasional periods of difficulty – major players in the videogames industry worldwide. The two most important companies in the 2000s have been Infogrames/Atari and Ubisoft. Although Infogrames/Atari (founded 1983) was an astonishing success story during the late 1980s, 1990s and early 2000s, buying up British and American companies to produce rapid growth in market penetration, it encountered significant financial difficulties after 2002. In 2006 it employed a workforce of 1200 with a turnover of €600 million. Ubisoft (founded 1986), however, by pursuing an arguably less ambitious and risky strategy – for example working with US and Canadian subsidiaries to attack the US market rather than purchasing debt-laden American companies – has consistently resisted take-overs to remain France’s most successful independent videogames producer. Although approximately 20% of Ubisoft is held since late 2004 by the US-owned Electronic Arts, the company remains essentially a prudently managed and financed family business, which has nevertheless maintained a top-ten ranking in world videogames sales, and in 2006 employed 3000 people for a turnover of €540 million (which by 2009 had doubled to reach over €1 billion).</p>
<p>Since the late 1990s French governments are increasingly aware of the scale and international importance of their national videogames sector, and have taken a growing interest in fostering new initiatives and supporting existing industry leaders. Developments in public policy towards the French videogames industry have involved a number of traditional policy sectors such as trade, commerce, and industry, but have also, notably, required the French state to consider the ‘cultural’ status it accords to videogaming. New-found government interest in the financial importance of the videogames industry has led to attempts to support its activities which essentially follow well-worn policies of neo-Colbertist (neo-dirigiste, interventionist and on occasions seemingly ‘protectionist’) French industrial policy, but within the context of French-inspired notions of ‘cultural exception’ in world trade, there have also been attempts to encourage the videogames industry using mechanisms developed by France in previous decades to defend cultural forms and practices such as cinema and music against Americanisation and globalisation. The videogames sector has found itself at the centre of a debate over culture, technology, industry and commerce in which videogaming has been the focus of conflicting and antagonistic discourses around the nature of ‘culture’, and what precisely the French state actually considers to be part of France’s culture. In essence, as videogaming is a form of cultural activity long considered in France to be part of ‘popular culture’, and as such ignored by France’s intellectual and governing elites, redefining it as ‘culture’ in order to afford the sector the same advantages as those enjoyed by the nobler ‘arts’ of film and music has proved problematic. Videogaming as ‘culture’ questions established hierarchies of cultural value in France and challenges the flexibility of more ‘inclusive’ and ‘pluralist’ cultural policies, which have been developed since the early 1980s. Simultaneously, the view that videogaming is important as ‘technology’ has contributed to France’s traditional and on-going insecurity over her scientific and technological ‘independence’.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1354856512439509">
<title>French cultural policy, popular culture and videogaming</title>
<p>Videogames and videogaming have recently become increasingly ‘respectable’ (but still controversial) in the heavily hierarchised and essentially enduringly elitist world of French culture. Although many in France may privately deplore a pastime that can still be seen as part of what was famously described by one leading right-wing cultural commentator as ‘the defeat of thought’ in France (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1354856512439509">Finkielkraut, 1987</xref>), there is a significant trend of ‘institutionalisation’ of this newer cultural practice and its artefacts by official organisations that has allowed others to describe it as finally becoming part of France’s cultural ‘heritage’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-1354856512439509">Jacquinot-Delaunay, 2008</xref>). Here we set the context of debates over the cultural status of videogaming in the 2000s by briefly discussing the main themes and discourses of French cultural policy since 1958 and the creation by de Gaulle and Malraux of contemporary state attitudes towards culture.</p>
<sec id="section3-1354856512439509">
<title>Cultural elitism, democratisation, exception, dirigisme</title>
<p>Recent relative acceptance of a leisure activity with the mass appeal of videogaming continues a tendency of ‘democratisation’ in French cultural politics originating in the late 1960s and 1970s and given official backing by the innovative approach to cultural policies implemented by Jack Lang as socialist Minister of Culture during the 1980s. Lang’s left-wing ‘pluralist’ thinking on culture and cultural policy broke with dominant doctrines developed by André Malraux, appointed to head the newly-formed Ministry of Culture by President de Gaulle in 1958 to guide the Fifth Republic’s ‘democratisation’ of culture. Malraucian policies were more concerned with a ‘top-down’ opening of elite culture to the masses than with reassessment of how cultural activities should be defined and what kinds of culture should be recognised as worthy of state support. After the cultural and social upheavals of May 1968, there was some recognition during the 1970s of the need for more inclusive views on regional cultures and languages, popular traditions and arts, but it was the changes implemented in the 1980s by Lang which created conditions in which the videogaming industry could possibly be considered eligible for state support principally as ‘culture’ rather than leisure, or technology.</p>
<p>The idea that culture should be encouraged and supported by the state is of course a central feature of French approaches to cultural policy. To use the term coined by Fumaroli in his key study of the traditions of state interest in the arts, the French state in the early decades of the Fifth Republic was a ‘cultural state’, inheriting an interventionist and dirigist involvement in culture from the Vichy Regime, whose policies were in turn inspired by the <italic>Kulturkampf</italic> of Bismarckian Germany and inter-war manipulations of culture undertaken by Nazi Germany and Fascist Italy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24-1354856512439509">Fumaroli, 1991</xref>). As well as deploring the state interference in what should ideally be the ‘private sphere’ of cultural activities, Fumaroli’s neo-liberal critique of the French state’s promotion of culture targeted the increasing domination of culture by the mass audiovisual media, a process encouraged by the action of successive ministers of culture since Malraux. Published in 1991, Fumaroli’s polemic contributed to the ongoing debate on culture that had been exercising French intellectuals since the early 1980s and the shock of Jack Lang’s policies of cultural pluralism and inclusion. This debate coalesced politically and culturally conservative criticisms of the Left’s more recent stewardship of culture with wider concerns over the quality of French culture threatened by the mass media and distorted by government instrumentalisation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45-1354856512439509">Schneider, 1993</xref>), the importance of intellectuals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1354856512439509">Lévy, 1987</xref>) and, increasingly during the 1990s, generalised anxieties about the threat to French culture posed by globalisation.</p>
<p>Another perspective on ‘cultural policy’ that arose around the same time was that of Philippe Urfalino, who provided a slightly more measured analysis than that of Fumaroli, concentrating arguably more on public policy than on moral-panic concerns about declining standards (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48-1354856512439509">Urfalino, 1996</xref>). One of the key distinctions drawn by Urfalino in his discussion of the relationship between the French state and culture is that between general ‘public policies relating to culture’ and ‘la politique culturelle’ (say ‘Cultural Policy’) itself, invented by Malraux and continuing with greater or lesser success ever since. In this perspective – which usefully informs understanding of the precarious relationship enjoyed by videogaming with the Ministry of Culture – French Cultural Policy is the idea and associated political and other actions that ‘culture’ can be harnessed by the state to change society. This grand ambition for culture is clearly Malraucian, and is the somewhat problematic legacy of the founding period of Fifth Republic ‘cultural policy’ for subsequent action in favour of and via the ‘arts’. Debates in the 1990s struggled with the idea of videogames participating in any way in a national ‘Cultural Policy’, although increasingly, space seemed to be being made for them as a legitimate beneficiary of support for ‘culture’.</p>
<p>Within these discussions in the 1990s the traditional notion of French ‘cultural exceptionalism’ (understood as France’s distinctive and unique contribution to world culture in literature, the arts and philosophy) and the cultural and economic policies associated with fostering it and promoting it internationally has often become confused with debates over the status of cultural products and services in general in international commerce. State support for activities considered as culturally important has often become progressively conflated with the concept of the ‘cultural exception’, or the need for ‘culture’ to be treated differently in international trade from other goods or services. Within the framework of the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) and – more specifically from 1995 – the General Agreement on Trade in Services (GATS) what is ‘culture’ and what ‘protection’ should be afforded to (French/Francophone and European) cultural activities became central themes of French politics during the mid and late 1990s, and in the 2000s were supplemented by the concept of ‘cultural diversity’ as another principle of French state intervention in culture. Negotiations on trade in audio-visual products within GATS included debates launched notably by France and Canada, that the audiovisual sector needed to be treated differently from other goods and services, allowing the notion of ‘cultural exception’ to come strongly to the fore.</p>
<p>It is against this backdrop of cultural policies defined and refined since the late 1950s that the videogaming industry in the late 1990s and 2000s fought to obtain the support of the state as culture rather than leisure, as art rather than technology, and thus to benefit from the measures afforded to activities deemed to contribute to France’s cultural specificity and cultural diversity. Despite the gradual drift of policy towards recognising the validity of popular culture (rock and pop music gained such approval from the 1980s), as Jean-Claude Larue suggested in 2002 (quoted in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44-1354856512439509">Rive, 2002</xref>), videogames have often struggled to overcome the enduring elitism of the French cultural establishment.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1354856512439509">
<title>André Malraux’s ‘democratisation’ of elite culture</title>
<p>Although the French state’s interventionism in culture predates the creation of the Fifth Republic in 1958, it was Malraucian thinking which set the mould for much contemporary policy. In terms of the nature of government interaction with culture, the Gaullist regime applied the same ‘voluntarist’ approach as it did in politics, economics and social issues, and notwithstanding gradual liberalisation of the French state’s traditionally dirigist management of other issues in subsequent decades, the mechanisms of policy remain marked by the belief that the state can and must take on a strong role in culture. And in terms of the content of policy, although popular culture has increasingly gained recognition, much of the reluctance to accept videogaming as ‘culture’ stems from enduring elitist mindsets dating from the 1950s and 1960s.</p>
<p>In addition to creating the structures of the Ministry of Culture out of the disparate organisations which contributed to the weak management of culture during the essentially culturally non-interventionist Fourth Republic, the founding action of the Malraux years – 1959–1969 – has been neatly summarised as heritage, creation and democratisation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1354856512439509">Looseley, 1995</xref>). These initiatives to conserve, create and render culture more accessible operated within a system of national pride in French civilisation (French ‘cultural exceptionalism’) and a quasi-mystical understanding – shared arguably by both Malraux and de Gaulle – of the power of culture to influence society for the better: heritage was essentially concerned with the legacy of French culture; French creativity was to be encouraged wherever possible; and French society in its entirety was to be exposed to the transcending genius of (high) cultural forms. Looseley’s sensitive reading of Malraucian declarations on the significance of culture concludes that he saw in it almost a humanist alternative to religion, capable of making sense of an absurd world for ordinary people. But despite the power of culture to unite and inspire, it was, for Malraux, threatened by exploitation by the new cultural industries of the dawning consumer age, and it was therefore the responsibility of the state to defend (high) culture against the ‘dream factories’ of television and other mass-cultural forms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1354856512439509">Looseley, 1995</xref>: 36). Malraux’s concerns were typical of the dominant elitist interpretation of culture which prevailed in France at the time: it was high culture which had to be conserved, creation in high culture which had to be encouraged, and high culture which was to be rendered more accessible to the masses.</p>
<p>Such views are still firmly entrenched in the French intelligentsia, and have obstructed attempts by videogaming to acquire greater cultural recognition. One field of more ‘modern’ culture which did receive support from Malraux was cinema, which was helped from 1960 by a restructuring of the ‘avances sur recettes’ system initiated during the Fourth Republic to pump-prime the cinema industry through a system of competitive grants made available to directors planning their first film, or to more established film-makers before or after the making of their films. But the events of May 1968 suggested that more attention should be paid to the wider and more popular cultural aspirations of younger generations of French citizens, and Malraux’s resignation in 1969 began a 12-year period in which the Ministry of Culture grappled uncertainly with its role during the rapid socioeconomic and sociocultural changes of the 1970s. The ever-rising importance of the cultural industries and questioning of the success of classical policies of democratisation of high culture led to growing recognition of the need for wider, more inclusive and pluralist definitions of ‘culture’, theorised notably by intellectuals such as Michel de Certeau (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-1354856512439509">de Certeau and Giard, 1974</xref>) and Pierre Bourdieu (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1354856512439509">Bourdieu, 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1354856512439509">Bourdieu and Darbel, 1966</xref>) but implemented ineffectually by no fewer than nine short-lived ministers of culture.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1354856512439509">
<title>Jack Lang and ‘le tout-culturel’: The cultural industries</title>
<p>It was in 1981 that culture regained a strong champion with a clear vision in the person of the socialist Culture Minister Jack Lang. Between 1981 and 1986, his action was to be crucial in radically altering the perspectives of the French state on culture, and since the 1980s, French cultural policy remains indelibly marked by the pluralist and popular cultural imprint of Lang’s revolution. The new understandings of which kinds of culture were deserving of state support elaborated by Lang ultimately allowed popular music, comic-books, cuisine, fashion and other mass-cultural forms to benefit from state aid: French culture was interpreted in its widest sense (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43-1354856512439509">Rigby, 1991</xref>).</p>
<p>In a speech to the National Assembly in November 1981, Lang openly recognised the legitimacy of the cultural industries, and in a somewhat surprising break from traditionally elitist French attitudes towards culture on left and right and also from the socialist and communist Left’s innate distrust of capitalism, called for the state to work closely and co-operatively with the private sector in fostering all cultural forms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30-1354856512439509">Lang, 1981</xref>). A second – related – tenet of Lang’s reorientation of thinking on culture was that ‘there can be as much culture in the styling of a dress, in the design of an object or in the structure of a television commercial as there is in musical composition, graphical art or architecture’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-1354856512439509">Lang, 1982</xref>); it was this interpretation of culture – validating the ‘artistic’ content of ‘industrial’ culture – which gave rise to the generally pejorative expression of ‘le tout-culturel’ (‘all-is-culture’). Videogaming’s claims in the 2000s to ‘cultural’ status base themselves in large part on the redrawing of the boundaries of ‘culture’ effected by Lang in the 1980s, and also depend for their success on a second aspect of Lang’s influence: systematic state encouragement for the commercial, industrial and technological infrastructures which support these activities. The real drive to foster France’s cultural industries came from 1983 onwards, with considerable rises in the volume of state funding for the new technologies of the growing audiovisual revolution (audio, video, computing, cinema) and new government agencies such as the<italic> Mission économie culturelle et communication</italic> or state-initiated lobby associations such as OCTET, which had a specific brief to assist new technologies and partnerships in video and animation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-1354856512439509">Lang, 1983</xref>).</p>
<p>Various commentators have identified the lack of an overall coherent doctrine underlying Lang’s redefinitions of culture and of cultural policy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-1354856512439509">Gentil and Poirrier, 2006</xref>: 21) or the shaky theoretical underpinnings of some of his conceptualisations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35-1354856512439509">Looseley, 1995</xref>: 127–28), and France’s Lang-inspired move towards a more pluralistic cultural democracy raised opposition from cultural conservatives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-1354856512439509">Finkielkraut, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34-1354856512439509">Lévy, 1987</xref>), but there is no denying the huge importance of the socialists’ programme for culture and the economy in the 1980s and well-beyond. Increasingly during the mid and later 1980s, concepts of ‘le tout-culturel’ linked culture and commerce in the general defence of France’s ‘exceptional’ place in the international system and in the protection of the French language and of the products and services of French ‘cultural industries’ whose survival was increasingly threatened by global English and by the Americanisation (or globalisation) of culture, mainly vehicled by US media businesses or American-dominated international conglomerates.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1354856512439509">
<title>French cultural exception, cultural exclusion, popular culture</title>
<p>The idea of the ‘French exception’ has long characterised not only French thinking about France and the presumed singularity of her historical development and political, social and cultural model, but also academic studies of France (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-1354856512439509">Chafer and Godin, 2004</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-1354856512439509">2010</xref>). A concept closely – and sometimes confusingly – linked to that of France’s ‘exception’ is that of ‘cultural exception’, meaning either the specificity of French culture and cultural traditions or/and the necessity for culture in general (and French culture in particular, because of its specificity) to be accorded certain advantages in international trade. The ideas of the ‘French exception’ and of ‘l’exception culturelle’ are of course closely related, as in many ways, the notion of a special approach to and treatment of ‘culture’ is based on and within the traditional framework of thinking on how France differs from other western European democracies, especially from ‘Anglo-Saxon’ ones. Increasingly, in terms of French culture, France’s ‘difference’ is perceived internally with apprehension, with fears that French civilisation is under attack, besieged linguistically by global English and culturally by worldwide free trade in cultural products and services. The need for culture in general to be protected by an exceptional status in commerce came to the fore during the Uruguay round of multilateral trade negotiations between 1987 and 1993, as France battled for exemptions for cinema (which happened to be her main cultural export) and the audiovisual industries, and in 1994, in a well-known example of ‘special measures’, the French state legislated to support both the French language and the French music industry by imposing a quota of French-language songs on radio play-lists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-1354856512439509">Dauncey, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-1354856512439509">Hare, 2003</xref>). French cinema had as early as the pre-war period and during the Fourth Republic benefited from support against perceived Hollywood hegemony, and Malraucian improvements to the film industry’s ‘avances sur recettes’ system in the 1960s similarly supported France’s indigenous industry and diffusion of French culture and language abroad through cinema, but in the 1990s it became clearer to the French state that the whole range of audiovisual forms and technologies needed support.</p>
<p>Also during the mid-1990s, buoyed by its new legitimacy as champion of France’s identity, cultural policy also refocused on its role as a catalyst of social harmony. The presidential election of 1995 produced the notion of France’s ‘social fracture’: rather than being a society where citizens enjoyed Republican equality and fraternity, France’s politicians, social commentators and intellectuals identified glaring inequalities of all kinds. Elected in 1995, President Chirac encouraged the use of cultural policy to reduce the divide between France’s ‘haves’ and ‘have-nots’, and the action of Culture Minister Philippe Douste-Blazy included measures to reduce ‘exclusion culturelle’ based in part on an influential official report on cultural policy which asserted the enduring relevance of the French state’s interventionist understanding of culture as a ‘public service’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41-1354856512439509">Rigaud, 1995</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42-1354856512439509">1996</xref>). Indeed, the Rigaud Report of 1996 called for a ‘refounding’ of cultural policy, which would inject new coherence into public policy towards the cultural industries. This was delayed by the change of government in 1997, but new Culture Minister Catherine Trautmann pursued similar objectives to guarantee to citizens ‘the greatest possible freedom in the choice of cultural practices’, through a voluntarist and ‘republican’ cultural policy. However, despite this apparent strength of political will and the arrival of a new banner-concept in the form of ‘cultural diversity’, policy in the 2000s seemed weakened and lacking in its former senses of purpose.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section7-1354856512439509">
<title>Cultural diversity, new cultures: Cultural policy in crisis?</title>
<p>Official discourses and academic studies of French cultural policy have, since the 1990s and particularly in the new millennium, become interested in the semantic differences between ‘exception’ and ‘diversity’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-1354856512439509">Creton et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36-1354856512439509">Mattelart, 2007</xref>). The original terms in which French mistrust of free trade in cultural goods and services was couched during the Uruguay Round came to be seen as doing a disservice to wider cultural and political ambitions of policy. It was thus that the more semantically neutral vocabulary of ‘diversité culturelle’ began to be employed. Under Chirac, and under Sarkozy since 2007, France has continued to espouse the rhetoric of a ‘different’ approach to culture. Whereas traditional discourses of ‘exception culturelle’, which had evolved during the 1990s, emphasised – rather negatively – the need for French culture to resist the Americanising and globalising forces of international trade, ‘diversité culturelle’ arguably refocused the debate towards more positive interpretations of cultural policy. Official declarations now state that its objectives are to protect France’s national cultural heritage and to democratise access to it, and, within the encouragement of creativity, to foster ‘cultural diversity’. It was during the late 1990s, that, with active French support and of other non ‘Anglo-Saxon’ cultures/countries, the concept was developed in Unesco. In June 1999, the Unesco conference on ‘La culture: une marchandise pas comme les autres?’ prepared what became, in November 2001, the <italic>Unesco Universal Declaration on Cultural Diversity</italic>, and the subsequent <italic>Unesco</italic> <italic>Convention on the Protection and Promotion of the Diversity of Cultural Expression</italic> was adopted in October 2005, and ratified by France in July 2006.</p>
<p>It is within the context of ‘cultural exception’ in GATT/GATS and ‘cultural diversity’ for Unesco that wider interpretations of culture now meet the specific position of videogaming: French cultural pluralism in the early 2000s reflected an increasingly instrumentalist and commercial understanding of the importance of the cultural industries. The application of ‘cultural diversity’ by the French state has meant that what is encouraged by cultural policy is now more varied, heterogeneous, and innovative, and arguably, more ‘popular’ than ever. Realising that past supportive interventionism may have stifled creativity as well as allowing certain forms of production – those best understood by ministry officials, or which respond best to centralised support – to flourish, ‘cultural diversity’ aims to foster all activities, in an environment which provides more flexible support and freedom from regulation, intended to inject new entrepreneurial dynamism into France’s cultural industries.</p>
<p>Although its very ambiguity can be useful to policy-makers, numerous studies criticised the conceptual weakness of ‘cultural diversity’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1354856512439509">Benhamou, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40-1354856512439509">Regourd, 2004</xref>) and during the 2000s there has been ongoing debate in France about the content and direction of cultural policy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1354856512439509">Abirached, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-1354856512439509">Djian, 2005</xref>). After the ‘heroic’ periods of the 1960s and the 1980s, the Ministry of Culture seems to have lost its glamour as a ministry of ‘democratisation’ under Malraux or as a ministry of ‘fun’ under Lang. The success of cultural policy in pluralising the definition of what is culture and in justifying the intervention of the state in cultural activities has – by demonstrating the importance of technology, industry and commerce in modern culture – paradoxically undermined the <italic>raison d’être</italic> of a strong and influential autonomous Ministry of Culture. It is in this context of long-term achievements in favour of popular culture and a somehow failing vision for the Ministry of Culture itself that videogaming has fought to define its status in the 2000s. As will be seen, it has benefited from the new directions of institutional redefinition of culture but also suffered from the lack of a continuing clear sense of purpose within the political institution of culture.</p>
<p>The gradual move towards considering videogames as culture has been driven both by ‘top-down’ technocratic redefinitions of culture within the on-going evolution of cultural policy, and by ‘bottom-up’ pressure from those involved in the conception and creation of games. Bodies such as <italic>les e.créateurs</italic> (a ‘forum for producers of digital content’) working in partnership with other trade associations such as the <italic>Agence française pour le jeu vidéo</italic> (AFJV) or the APOM (which became the <italic>Syndicat national du jeu vidéo</italic> SNJV in July 2008) have consistently lobbied in favour of state recognition of the specifically ‘cultural’ (rather than technological or industrial) dimensions of the creation of videogames. Thus, even after Donnedieu de Vabre’s gesture in 2006, the APOM/SNJV still placed ‘obtaining the recognition of videogames as a form of cultural expression in their own right’ at the very top of their list of objectives for 2006–2008 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1354856512439509">APOM, 2008</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section8-1354856512439509">
<title>Videogames policy: Commerce, culture and technology</title>
<p>Visiting the Parisian Darkworks videogames studio in November 2002, the middle-aged and rather boring centre-right Prime Minister Jean-Pierre Raffarin confided to journalists a surprising personal interest in gaming: <italic>‘Je suis un praticien modeste, mais il m’arrive de pratiquer’ </italic>(‘I don’t play much, but I do sometimes’). Raffarin’s newly-installed government had been quickly lobbied by the videogames industry, which was suffering a downturn, and in April 2002, outgoing socialist Minister of Culture and Communication, Catherine Tasca, had received the Diberder Report on creativity in the multimedia and video industries which drew mixed conclusions on the health of this next ‘coming’ audiovisual cultural industry. Responding to industry concerns, Raffarin at Darkworks underlined his government’s belief in the importance of the videogames industry, one of the sectors of cultural/industrial/technological activity in which ‘French creativity, innovation and excellence’ had been best demonstrated in recent years, and where ‘French talent in design and engineering’ had become internationally recognised. Here we shall discuss the debates, issues and policies that have surrounded the French state’s recent attempts to define an appropriate cultural, industrial and technological status for videogaming. Much of the discussion – as often in France – was structured by a series of official reports.</p>
<sec id="section9-1354856512439509">
<title>New leisure cultures, technologies and intellectual property</title>
<p>Raffarin’s use in his Darkworks speech of the expression ‘French touch’ to describe how French videogames were seen worldwide as quality French products explicitly linked video with the ongoing cultural/commercial successes of French electronica music exemplified by artists such as Air and Daft Punk. Indeed, for Raffarin, videogames were an important aspect of his government’s ambition to build a ‘République numérique’ (a digital Republic) within a ‘société de l’information et de l’innovation’ (an information and innovation society) where technical innovation and increased accessibility of communications technologies would, despite perceived weakness of French Web activities, reduce ‘la fracture numérique’ (the digital divide) and stimulate France’s technological competitivity. The parallel was clear between the popularity of music and that of video, with the difference that video was believed able to defend French culture by content, technology and an education of citizens towards digital society. Raffarin’s comparison acknowledged how videogaming in France had become a major leisure activity as well as acquiring claims to the status of ‘culture’. Here it is necessary to briefly set out two main strands in French debates over the cultural status of this new popular cultural form. Underlying much of the French state’s interest in redefining video as culture, but often understated or taken for granted in debates or official declarations is firstly the idea of France’s technological independence: mastering the range of audiovisual and computer technologies by French businesses is important for France’s scientific and industrial survival. Secondly, a central problem of clear policy for supportive state interest in video is the problem of intellectual property rights: who is the ‘author’/’creator’ of a videogame?</p>
<p>The French state in the Fifth Republic has traditionally held dirigist attitudes towards encouraging innovative technologies, even in more flexible neo-Colbertist incarnations of technology policy prevailing since the late 1980s: were it not for the strong popular-cultural handicap of the cultural form and practice, the lack of a higher priority for video technologies in recent decades might seem more surprising. Nonetheless, French state interest in communication technologies and in the computerisation – in the widest senses of the term – of society stretch back as far as the 1960s, when Servan-Schreiber rang alarm bells about France’s technological weakness vis-à-vis the USA by coining the phrase ‘the American challenge’, and in the late 1970s the Nora–Minc report entitled ‘The Computerisation of Society’ laid the foundation stone of state-led plans to ‘modernise’ France’s information and communication technologies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38-1354856512439509">Nora and Minc, 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46-1354856512439509">Servan-Schreiber, 1965</xref>). French governments have realised – belatedly, because of cultural prejudices against popular culture – that videogaming places ordinary children and citizens in contact with hardware and software allowing them to access the skills and knowledge of the information society: awareness of terminals, consoles, input devices; familiarity with software and an introduction to the interlinking of technologies (computers, consoles, televisions and so on). Intervention in favour of ‘modernising’ audiovisual/communication technologies has been considerable in recent decades: in the 1970s the <italic>Direction générale des télécommunications</italic> (DGT) provided top-down modernisation of the telephone system; in the 1980s the French state forced the population to enter the videotext age with the supply-led Minitel teletext system and its ‘electronic phonebook’; in the early 1990s the state’s neo-dirigist preoccupations with the information superhighway and with France’s perceived backwardness towards the Web took France closer towards the wired society (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-1354856512439509">Dauncey, 1997</xref>). In many ways, the French state sees videogaming as a catalyst for early adoption of new technologies and new communications practices, introducing skills to households in a ‘ludic’ demand-led form, rather than by ‘need’ or top-down imposition, but perhaps because of its perceived ‘triviality’ as youth popular culture and moral panics over its content and social/psychological effects, governments still held back from adopting it wholeheartedly.</p>
<p>Another problem for the state in espousing video as a cultural product to be supported by policies predicated on its clear ‘artistic’ nature was the vexed issue of intellectual property rights and copyright. French law moved slowly during the 2000s to resolve the legal ambiguities of videogames, hesitating between a view which prioritises the importance of the software (in which case the rights belong to the employers of the programmers) and an interpretation which emphasises the ‘creative’ dimensions of plot, imagery, sound (in which case the rights devolve to the game inventers). A ruling in 2008 stated that videogames are works of collaborative culture (‘oeuvres audiovisuelles de collaboration’), and although stressing their ‘artistic’ nature, it clouded the issue of copyright by emphasising the shared responsibility of their creation, and in 2010, a clear-cut solution to the question still remained to be found. While French law hesitates in finding a satisfactory status for videogames, programmers and creators are tempted to leave France in search of more favourable legal conditions for their work.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section10-1354856512439509">
<title>The <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1354856512439509">Le Diberder Report (2002)</xref>: Beginnings of state interest</title>
<p>Commissioned in 2001 from Alain and Frédéric Le Diberder, while the socialist Catherine Tasca was still Minister of Culture and Communication, this investigation into France’s videogames industry was, significantly, requested by the <italic>Conseil supérieur de la propriété littéraire et artistique</italic> (CSPLA – a ‘high council of literary and artistic property’, created to reflect on French intellectual property rights in a digitised, globalised world), and partly funded by the <italic>Centre national de la cinématographie</italic> (CNC – the body organising long-running state support for that more senior cultural industry, film). This first official report into video – a snapshot of activities in 2001 – thus approached the industry from the perspective of literary and artistic property rights and was closely linked to cinema (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-1354856512439509">Le Diberder and Le Diberder, 2002</xref>). Moreover, the CSPLA had been created especially to consider how France’s cultural influence in a wired world could be protected and furthered. The report stressed how the videogames sector had developed over a period of 30 years into what it described as ‘cultural industry on a world scale’ within which France’s specific strength was to contribute products for all aspects of the cultural practice except that of console manufacturing. In other words, French businesses were strong in devising games (<italic>‘la création’</italic>), publishing them (<italic>‘l’édition’</italic>), manufacturing console and computer accessories, manufacturing middleware (videogame creation tools), engaging in specialist retailing, and commenting on videogames through a burgeoning specialist press. The report proudly emphasised how France’s videogames industry was alone amongst French cultural industries to export more than three-quarters of its production, to regularly release products which were world-wide successes, and even – sweet revenge of French capitalism – to buy out foreign businesses! The maturity of the sector was demonstrated up-stream of industry itself, by trade organisations such as the <italic>Syndicat des éditeurs de logiciels de loisirs</italic> (SELL, created 1995), and the more recent <italic>Association des producteurs d’oeuvre multimédia </italic>(APOM – set up in 2002), and down-stream of industrial activities, various private and public training schemes varying from courses at HE <italic>Instituts universitaires de technologie</italic> to diplomas at highly prestigious university-level <italic>grandes écoles</italic> which had developed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-1354856512439509">de Linares, 2004</xref>) to deal with computing aspects or graphic design (particularly the state ENJMIN – <italic>Ecole nationale du jeu des médias interactifs numériques</italic>).</p>
<p>The Report drew attention to two principal difficulties of the French videogames industry, firstly the lack of well-tried funding structures specialising in providing finance, and secondly, the absence of appropriate legal frameworks for the creation of videogames as <italic>‘produits culturels’</italic>. It is these problems that developments throughout the 2000s have addressed, as the French state has intervened to support the industry financially, and to negotiate compromise over the intellectual property rights of game creators. But in addition to these perceived structural, financial and legal handicaps suffered by French videogame producers as they compared their lot with other cultural industries such as film and music, in the early 2000s economic slowdown hit the sector hard. For producers of games such as Infogrames/Atari or Ubisoft – the ‘national champion’ French companies – the games industry is notoriously cyclical, profitability dependent on occasional release of new consoles and new killer games as much as on the inherent quality of ‘French Touch’ games. The Le Diberder report was commissioned and published as the industry took a downwards turn and French production faced ever stronger competition from US, Japanese and new producers in the Far East or Eastern Europe. Numerous French producers of games went bankrupt – Kalysto, Cryo, Gamesquad – leading to a strong industry appeal to the state for support (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1354856512439509">APOM, 2003</xref>), which was answered initially by the government’s launch of a ‘national support plan’ in April 2003.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section11-1354856512439509">
<title>The ‘National Support Plan’ (2003) and the <italic>Fries Report</italic> (2004)</title>
<p>After Darkworks in 2002, Prime Minister Raffarin’s next major declaration in favour of videogames came at the inauguration of a new digital exhibition hall at France’s flagship Futuroscope science park in April 2003 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39-1354856512439509">Raffarin, 2003</xref>). Ironically, the speech was made in Poitiers, scene of the infamous 1980s ‘battle of Poitiers’ when imported Japanese VCRs were stockpiled by French Customs authorities in an attempt to protect the national home electronics industry (another battle of Poitiers in 732 saved French civilisation from Moorish invasion). Presenting the videogames industry as part of his government’s ambition to use multimedia technologies to reduce social inequalities, one of Raffarin’s soundbites was ‘Le ludique est une voie d’entrée à la République numérique’ (‘Videogaming is a doorway into the digital Republic’). He announced measures partially addressing the problems identified by the<italic> Diberder Report</italic> and taken up by APOM in its pleas for government aid. Firstly, stressing ‘scientific research’ dimensions of the creation of videogames linked such initiatives increasingly closely to the ‘Plan Innovation’ for industrial technologies and enabled tax breaks and financial aid through the recently-created <italic>Réseau pour la recherche et l’innovation en audiovisuel et multimédia</italic> (RIAM), and equally importantly, enhanced support for videogames through the <italic>Fonds d’aide à l’édition multimédia</italic> (FAEM) run by the CNC (a linkage with ‘high culture which was itself significant) was announced. Secondly, Raffarin’s measures suggested that the legal and artistic status of videogames and the entire game-producing profession could progressively be reviewed, aligning creation of videogames more closely with films and music, and officially accepting them as <italic>‘oeuvres culturelles’</italic>. However, there were still obstacles in the way of the recognition of videogames as art: one of Raffarin’s advisors had stated in 2002 how the Ministry of Culture was reticent to accept as ‘culture’ vulgar games of sport or action, many of which were – <italic>quelle horreur!</italic> – in English (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-1354856512439509">Guillemin, 2002</xref>), and this view seemed as yet relatively unshaken. And copyright law was mired in difficulties.</p>
<p>In order to advance government thinking on what seemed essentially more a series of proposals than a concrete, implemented plan, two further official reports were commissioned (from Fabrice Fries on game creation, and from Michel Averous on the training of game designers) which addressed the legal and financial needs of some more ‘artistic’ dimensions of videogaming. The Fries report was delivered to the Industry Ministry in January 2004 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-1354856512439509">Fries, 2004</xref>). It had been <italic>‘création’</italic> which specifically caught the governments’ attention since the early 2000s, because although major French publishers and distributors of videogames such as Infogrames and Ubisoft (which often have in-house creative studios) regularly underwent troubled periods, they always managed to survive, whereas many smaller creative studios suffered drastically from international competition. And it was <italic>‘création’</italic> around which crystallised major cultural debates over the intrinsic nature of videogames as ‘art’ or mass entertainment/leisure, as ‘culture’ or computing. One measure recommended by the Averous Report of January 2004 was precisely the creation of the ENJMIN in the town – which already concentrated expertise in <italic>bandes dessinées</italic> and other video-related arts and technologies – of Angoulême, thereby mirroring state support of training for cultural forms such as art, comic-strips, music, cuisine and dance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1354856512439509">Averous, 2004</xref>). The Fries Report also confirmed one of the financial measures – with a strong cultural subtext – initiated by Raffarin in April 2003: by authorising the creation of videogames to be more supportively funded in the same way as films through the CNC/FAEM, video production was given state support and the debate over video as art/culture, technology or industry could continue, with an increasing tendency to see gaming properly as culture.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section12-1354856512439509">
<title>The <italic>Assemblée Nationale</italic> conference (2006): Ongoing debate</title>
<p>In late 2005 the Ubisoft studios in the Parisian suburb Montreuil and those of Quantic Deams in Paris itself received a stream of high-level political visitors: new centre-right Prime Minister Dominique de Villepin, Culture Minister Renaud Donnedieu de Vabres and Industry Minister Dominique Loos all voiced their support for two of France’s flagship video companies, and more specifically, publicised government lobbying in favour of tax credits for videogame production. Initially contained within Raffarin’s ‘plan’ for the videogame industry and eventually forwarded to the European Commission (EC) for approval in late 2005, the application to use a ‘crédit d’impôt’ (tax credit) was based on recognition of the cultural nature of videogames and their eligibility for more generous treatment by competition regulation. Although Unesco had been able to recognise videogames as a valid element of ‘cultural diversity’, the EC was less easily satisfied, only eventually agreeing to France’s request – for some categories of more especially ‘cultural’ games – in 2007, after Donnedieu de Vabres had made special representations to Competition Commissioner Nellie Kroes in October 2006.</p>
<p>Throughout 2005, 2006 and 2007 discussions continued within France over the status of videogames, while awaiting the EC’s contribution to the French debate. One event encapsulating many of the problems of the sector was the wide-ranging conference hosted in September 2006 by the National Assembly on policy choices for the videogames industry. As well as ‘moral panic’ discussions of the feared negative effects of videogame violence on children, risks of addiction, potential needs for greater regulation of game content, or on the contrary, the positive educational capacities of video and possibilities of socialisation through gaming, sociologists of culture nevertheless pointed out how videogaming was struggling to acquire the cultural status within French society that it deserved. Despite Lang’s work in the 1980s to render the ‘cultural’ more pluralist, the National Assembly conference underlined how prejudices about the age of gamers (assumed to be immature adolescents, but often adult), ideologically questionable content (assumed to be violent or pornographic but often artistic or cultural) and methods of production which fit badly with traditionally understood practices of artistic creation (automation, programming, team-work) were holding videogaming back from recognition as art by more traditional elements of the cultural establishment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1354856512439509">Brizé, 2006</xref>).</p>
<p>Culture and Communications Minister Donnedieu de Vabres’ contribution to the conference was however as clear as his other declarations on the value of videogaming as art since his appointment in 2005, drawing precise parallels between the artistic nature of cinema and the ‘intelligence, innovation and creativity’ of video (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-1354856512439509">Donnedieu de Vabres, 2006</xref>). He was also at pains to illustrate how video in France was closely involved in crossovers with artistic forms such as film, architecture or graphic art, helping stimulate a network of French creativity. Other participants emphasised how the breakdown of costs in producing a videogame in France (25% for programming, 15% for scenario, 55% for visuals and 5% for soundtrack) suggested the gaming industry was (proportionately) more ‘art’ than computing/technology. While France waited for the EC ruling on the tax credit for videos, the conference concluded that one of the remaining hindrances to clear policy on videogames was the still enduring lack of a precise legal definition in French law of their nature either as ‘work of art’ or mere software.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section13-1354856512439509">
<title>The Besson Report (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-1354856512439509">2008</xref>): Planning the digital economy</title>
<p>France’s request for EC approval of tax credit support for the video industry was only agreed by Brussels in mid December 2007, and the <italic>crédit d’impôt jeu vidéo</italic> (CIJV) was quickly voted by the National Assembly, entering application on 30 May 2008. Also during early 2008, the FAEM became the <italic>Fonds d’aide au jeu vidéo</italic> (FAJV), now run by the Ministry of the Economy, Industry and Employment in partnership with the CNC. The interventionism in the videogame industry of the second Chirac presidency (2002–2007) was thus being adopted by the centre-right Fillon government of president Nicholas Sarkozy with few substantive changes. The ‘lobbying’ undertaken by Donnedieu de Vabres in favour of videogames being accepted – at least tacitly – as properly part of the attributions of the Ministry of Culture and Communications seemed to have borne fruit, as the new minister Christine Albanel declared at the <italic>Assises du jeu vidéo</italic> colloquium in April that there was no longer any doubt about video being seen as culture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1354856512439509">Albanel, 2008</xref>). In suggesting future reforms to stimulate the video industry, Albanel however insisted on the need for continued thought on the legal status of games and their creators, in order to allow – through clear identification of ‘authors’ – videogames to enjoy the same levels of ‘artistic’ individuality as songs, books and other works of artistic creation. In a speech delivered to the same colloquium, the new discourse of videogames as truly part of cultural policy was reinforced by Véronique Cayla (director of the CNC): stressing the dual nature of videogames as industry and art, Cayla underlined how much the sector should now be considered largely in the same way as cinema. Further, she underlined how important had been the approval by the European Commission of the principle of ‘crédit d’impôt’ in terms of recognition of the legitimacy of cultural policy favouring digital arts.</p>
<p>In October 2008, Secretary of State for the digital economy Eric Besson presented his report on France’s preparations to be a fully digital society by 2012 (the end of Sarkozy’s presidency). Plans for the videogames industry were naturally included in this ambitious programme, but of the six measures proposed, only one – facilitating a clearer legal definition of videogames and employment in the sector – was arguably of major significance. Apart from ‘Action no. 57’ which called for this clarification of the legal framework within which the videogames industry was felt to be struggling, five other rather vaguer ‘actions’ proposed stronger links between the French video sector and the European Audiovisual Observatory, sensitising students to the employment opportunities existing in French videogame studios, creating decentralised regional financial support for videogames businesses, encouraging work on ‘intelligent-gaming’, encouraging the private sector to make more use of videogames techniques and fostering work in the public sector on Web 2.0 technologies and serious-gaming. These somewhat nebulous plans were generally perceived by industry as underwhelming, and the ongoing issue of how to define a videogame and the work of its creators was a serious problem. In summary: if all videogames could legally be recognised in French law as cultural products like books, music, paintings and other artistic works, then this would have a number of implications in terms of reduced VAT ratings, pricing, advertising, marketing and state support. Secondly, related to the status of the product itself, definition of inventors of videogames as ‘artists’ or ‘authors’ would entail complicated and costly applications of artistic property rights, royalties and a reconceptualisation of the whole profession to bring employment contracts into line with other ‘artistic’ sectors. The question of employment in the cultural sector was, during the mid 2000s, a particularly inflammatory issue as economically neo-liberal governments attempted to dismantle some of the anachronistic subsidies to the arts inherited from Malraux in the form of generous pension and unemployment allowances for ‘occasional’ culture-workers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37-1354856512439509">Menger, 2005</xref>). Significantly, the Besson report suggested that thinking on these problems should be coordinated by the <italic>Conseil supérieur de la propriété littéraire et artistique</italic> (CSPLA, set up in 2001), as part of its brief to enhance France’s worldwide cultural presence in audiovisual and communications technologies.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="section14-1354856512439509">
<title>Rhetoric and irresolution: Whither videogames policy now?</title>
<p>Early 2008 marked something of a watershed for public policy regarding videogames: the CIJV was introduced; Culture Minister Albanel produced more rhetorical support for the sector’s activities to gain recognition as ‘culture’, in response to the dual push and pull in favour of such a definition coming from producers, creators, artists in the profession on the one hand and from government on the other hand, keen to use a ‘cultural’ categorisation of videogames to best advantage in terms of state aid; and the head of the CNC optimistically anticipated success for the videogames sector within structures that had worked so well in the past for cinema.</p>
<p>In 2009 and 2010, however progress seemed slow by comparison with the advances made between 2006 and 2008. A change of leadership in the Ministry of Culture, where Frédéric Mitterrand replaced Albanel in June 2009 strengthened the discursive and symbolic support for videogames <italic>qua</italic> culture and for some concomitant policy in favour of the sector, but some problems remained in the way of what might be termed the progressive ‘normalisation’ of videogames within French cultural policy overall.</p>
<p>In terms of favourable rhetoric and minor policy initiatives, one of Mitterrand’s early actions as Culture Minister was his participation in the <italic>Festival du Jeu vidéo</italic> in September 2009, where he announced an <italic>Observatoire du jeu vidéo</italic> by the CNC (set up in spring 2010 and producing initial studies in July 2010) charged with providing government with a better understanding of the complexities of the sector. He also publicly supported video as ‘culture’ in April 2010 at the <italic>Studio national des arts contemporains</italic> (SNAC), where – despite the growing impression of ‘more haste less speed’ in policy – he underlined new overt state support for ‘création’ in videogames. The SNAC speech conveniently summarised ongoing and future policy in favour of videogames within the sector’s apparent ‘normalisation’ as a domain of cultural policy by its attachment to the <italic>Centre national du cinéma et de l’image animée</italic> (and planned extension of the long-standing form of state support to the film industry via ‘avances sur recettes’ tax-breaks to cover video) and also mooted the creation of a ‘Bureau export’ for French video similar to existing structures in cinema and popular music. The idea of such an export bureau showed how much it was now felt that videogaming could now respectably be allowed to represent France abroad culturally, as well as commercially.</p>
<p>But areas of irresolution still remained which seemed to some lobbyists in the industry to reflect enduring reservations over videogaming’s status. Firstly, uncertainty continued over the precise legal status in French law of videogames. Secondly, questions were raised about the extent to which the CIJV was actually benefiting the whole range of games, studios and producers, as the CNC seemed to be applying rather narrowly restrictive criteria in its selection of eligible projects. Indeed, in privileging such aspects as originality, innovation and quality, the selection process seemed to reflect elitist and ‘auteurist’ understandings of state funding of (popular) culture rather than the more pluralist and diverse approaches that seemed to have been promised. Although Véronique Cayla of the CNC has suggested that an effective compromise between support for commercially successful products and services and aid for ‘auteurist quality’ can be found (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1354856512439509">Cayla, 2008</xref>), concerns amongst industry lobbyists remained (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49-1354856512439509">Villedieu, 2009</xref>).</p>
<p>Another potential development which alarmed creators and producers of games was the apparent refocusing of government attention towards ‘Serious Gaming’ within the framework of planning for France’s planning for a digital 2012. The promise in mid 2009 by junior minister for the Digital Economy Nathalie Kosciusko-Morizet of €30 million to encourage French Serious Gaming production was welcomed, but studios and trade organisations rang alarm bells about the counter-productive effects of distinguishing between videogames ‘deserving’ of support, and by default, other games, to be pejoratively classified as ‘leisure’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-1354856512439509">Gaume, 2010</xref>). Elsewhere, in terms of government interest in gaming as technology, financial rigour caused cuts in late 2010 of state support to ‘jeunes entreprises innovantes’ (JEI, or small, recent startups with high-tech innovation activities) hitting the videogames sector hard.</p>
<p>All in all, France’s videogames industry in the 2000s was an intriguing example of the intricacies and complexities of French public policy towards the cultural industries. Debate and action since the early 2000s enabled some progress to be made in favour of maintaining video’s contribution to ‘cultural diversity’ and to France’s ‘cultural exceptionalism’ but overall the reactivity of the state seemed insufficient to redraw the framework in time to fully safeguard French strengths and successes. But the ‘normalisation’ of videogames within cultural policy appeared set to slowly continue, as politicians and intellectuals seemed increasingly accepting of its validity: at SNAC in April 2010 Mitterrand emphasised that the cinema blockbuster of early 2010 – James Cameron’s <italic>Avatar</italic> – was also an Ubisoft videogame, partnership between film and videogames proving their artistic ‘maturity’, echoing the view expressed in June 2009 by Jacques Attali – one of France’s leading public intellectuals – that videogames were to become the future of cinema itself (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1354856512439509">Attali, 2009</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Abirached</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Le Théâtre et le Prince</source>. <publisher-loc>Arles</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Actes Sud</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Albanel</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <comment>Discours de clôture des Assises du jeu vidéo. Culture Ministry, 4 April. Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.culture.gouv.fr/culture/actualites/index-com.html">http://www.culture.gouv.fr/culture/actualites/index-com.html</ext-link> <comment>(accessed October 2008)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">APOM</collab> (<year>2003</year>) <source>10 propositions au premier ministre pour le développement durable de l’industrie des loisirs électroniques en France</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>APOM</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<collab collab-type="author">APOM</collab> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Bilan d’activités 2002–2007</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>APOM</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Attali</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Le jeu vidéo est l'avenir du cinéma, website Slate.fr, 9 June</article-title>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.slate.fr/story/6303/lavenir-du-cin%C3%A9ma">http://www.slate.fr/story/6303/lavenir-du-cin%C3%A9ma</ext-link> <comment>(accessed 10 November 2010)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Averous</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Rapport sur les jeux vidéo</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Documentation française</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Benhamou</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>L’Exception culturelle: Exploration d’une impasse</article-title>. <source>Esprit</source> <issue>May</issue>: <fpage>85</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Besson</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <source>France Numérique 2012</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Premier ministre/Secrétariat d’Etat à la Prospective, Documentation française</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bourdieu</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1979</year>) <source>La Distinction: Critique sociale du jugement</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Minuit</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bourdieu</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Darbel</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1966</year>) <source>L’Amour de l’art. Les musées d’arts européens et leurs public</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Minuit</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Brizé</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <comment>Synthèse du colloque au Palais Bourbon: ‘Quelle politique pour les jeux vidéo’. AFJV, 11 septembre 2006. Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.afjv.com/press0609/060927_synthese_politique_jeux_video.htm">http://www.afjv.com/press0609/060927_synthese_politique_jeux_video.htm</ext-link> <comment>(accessed October 2008)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cayla</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Quels leviers pour l’industrie française sur un terrain de jeu mondialisé? Speech made at the conference</article-title>. <source>Jeu vidéo: Le nouvel âge</source>, <issue>4 April</issue> <comment>2008</comment>. <comment>Paris: CNC/Documentation française</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr13-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chafer</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Godin</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2004</year>) <source>The French Exception</source>. <publisher-loc>New York and Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Berghahn</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr14-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chafer</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Godin</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2010</year>) <source>The End of the French Exception? Decline and Revival of the French Model</source>. <publisher-loc>Basingstoke and New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr15-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Creton</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Palmer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sarrazac</surname>
<given-names>J-P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Arts du spectacle, métiers et industries culturelles. Penser la généalogie</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sorbonne Nouvelle</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr16-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dauncey</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>A cultural battle: French Minitel, the internet and the superhighway</article-title>. <source>Convergence</source> <volume>3</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>72</fpage>–<lpage>89</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr17-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dauncey</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The French music industry: Structures, challenges and responses</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Dauncey</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cannon</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Popular Music in France from Chanson to Techno: Culture, Identity, Society</source>. <publisher-loc>Aldershot</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr18-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>De Certeau</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Giard</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1974</year>) <source>La Culture au pluriel</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Union générale d’édition</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr19-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>De Linares</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Grandes écoles pour jeux vidéo</article-title>. <source>Le Nouvel Observateur</source> <volume>2062</volume>(<issue>13 May</issue>).</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr20-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Djian</surname>
<given-names>J-M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Politique culturelle: La fin d’un mythe</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Gallimard</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr21-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Donnedieu de Vabres</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <comment>Quelle politique pour les jeux vidéo? Text of speech to the National Assembly conference, 11 September 2006. Culture Ministry. Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.culture.gouv.fr/culture/actualites/conferen/donnedieu/colloquejv.html">http://www.culture.gouv.fr/culture/actualites/conferen/donnedieu/colloquejv.html</ext-link> <comment>(accessed October 2008)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr22-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Finkielkraut</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <source>La Défaite de la pensée</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Gallimard</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr23-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fries</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Propositions sur la régulation et le développement du marché de la vidéo en France</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ministère de l’Economie, des Finances et de l’Industrie, Documentation française</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr24-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fumaroli</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <source>L’Etat culturel: Essai sur une religion moderne</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Fallois</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr25-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gaume</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Interview bilan 2009 avec N Gaume (SNJV). Gamekult website</article-title>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gamekult.com/actu/interview-bilan-2009-n-gaume-snjv-A0000081941.html">http://www.gamekult.com/actu/interview-bilan-2009-n-gaume-snjv-A0000081941.html</ext-link> <comment>(accessed 25 November 2010)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr26-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gentil</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Poirrier</surname>
<given-names>Ph</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) (<year>2006</year>) <source>La Politique culturelle en débat: Anthologie 1955–2005</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Documentation française</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr27-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Guillemin</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Jeux vidéo: Raffarin débloque une aide d’urgence d’un million d’euros</article-title>. <comment>ZDNet. Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.zdnet.fr/actualites/informatique/0,39040745,2126073,00.htm">http://www.zdnet.fr/actualites/informatique/0,39040745,2126073,00.htm</ext-link> <comment>(accessed October 2008)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr28-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hare</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Popular music on French radio and television</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Dauncey</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cannon</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Popular Music in France from Chanson to Techno: Culture, Identity, Society</source>. <publisher-loc>Aldershot</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ashgate</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr29-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jacquinot-Delaunay</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Prendre le risque de comprendre</article-title>. <source>MédiaMorphoses</source> <volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>2</fpage>–<lpage>3</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr30-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1981</year>) <comment>In Discours de Jack Lang. vol. 1 July 1981–September 1982: 95. (Ministry of Culture, unpublished documents)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr31-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>Press conference address 26 June 1982. In Discours de Jack Lang</article-title>. <volume>vol. 1</volume> <comment>July 1981–September 1982: 95. (Ministry of Culture, unpublished documents)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr32-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Les Orientations nouvelles de la politique des industries de la culture</article-title>. <comment>Dossier d’information</comment>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ministère de la culture</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr33-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Le Diberder</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Le Diberder</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <source>La création de jeux vidéo en France</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ministère de l’industrie/Documentation française</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr34-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lévy</surname>
<given-names>B-H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1987</year>) <source>Eloge des intellectuels</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Grasset</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr35-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Looseley</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <source>The Politics of Fun: Cultural Policy and Debate in Contemporary France</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford and New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Berg</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr36-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mattelart</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Diversité culturelle et mondialisation</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>La Découverte</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr37-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Menger</surname>
<given-names>P-M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <source>Les intermittents du spectacle: Sociologie d’une exception</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Editions EHESS</publisher-name>.
</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr38-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nora</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Minc</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1978</year>) <source>L’Informatisation de la société</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Documentation française</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr39-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Raffarin</surname>
<given-names>J-P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>10 Propositions pour l’avenir de l’industrie du jeu vidéo. Prime Minister’s office internet archives</article-title>. <comment>Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.internet.gouv.fr/archives/article5ab9.htm">http://www.internet.gouv.fr/archives/article5ab9.htm</ext-link> <comment>(accessed October 2008)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr40-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Regourd</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>L’Exception culturelle</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>PUF</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr41-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rigaud</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1995</year>) <source>L’Exception culturelle: Culture et pouvoirs sous la Vième République</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Grasset</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr42-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rigaud</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Pour une refondation de la politique culturelle</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Documentation française</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr43-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rigby</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1991</year>) <source>Popular Culture in France: A Study of Cultural Discourse</source>. <publisher-loc>London and New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr44-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rive</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Plans sociaux Infogrames: le tatou in the dark</article-title>. <source>L’Humanité</source> <issue>12 October</issue>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr45-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Schneider</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1993</year>) <source>La Comédie de la culture</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Le Seuil</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr46-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Servan-Schreiber</surname>
<given-names>J-J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1965</year>) <source>Le Défi américain</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Grasset</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr47-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Teillet</surname>
<given-names>Ph</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Politiques culturelles et musiques populaires/actuelles/amplifiées</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Dauncey</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Le Guern</surname>
<given-names>Ph</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (eds) <source>Stéréo: Sociologie comparée des musiques populaires France/GB</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IRMA/Mélanie Séteun</publisher-name>, pp. <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr48-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Urfalino</surname>
<given-names>Ph</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>L’Invention de la politique culturelle</source>. <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>la Documention française</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr49-1354856512439509">
<citation citation-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Villedieu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Intervention de J Villedieu – Digiworld Summit 2009</article-title>. <comment>SNJV website. Available at</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.snjv.org/fr/positions-reactions-trib/intervention-digiworld.html">http://www.snjv.org/fr/positions-reactions-trib/intervention-digiworld.html</ext-link> <comment>(accessed 30 November 2010)</comment>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>