<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JMI</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjmi</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journal of Management Inquiry</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1056-4926</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-6542</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1056492611430299</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1056492611430299</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Editor’s Choice</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Editor’s Introduction</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Washington</surname><given-names>Marvin</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1056492611430299">1</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1056492611430299"><label>1</label>University of Alberta, Edmonton, Canada</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>4</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>21</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<fpage>127</fpage>
<lpage>127</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This is an amazing essay! Normally when we write an editor’s introduction, we try to provide a synopsis of the article, or we link the essay to previous research both in the field and specifically in past editions of the <italic>Journal of Management Inquiry (JMI).</italic> With this essay, I feel doing that would trivialize the article. Often, we hear people introduce a guest speaker or lecture with the phrase “this person needs no introduction.” I feel similar about this article. This article needs no introduction. It is a great essay examining how the second author takes his academic scholarship to a very personal and practical issue that requires great courage and compassion. This article is also a great reminder that many of us create wonder myths and ceremonies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1056492611430299">Meyer &amp; Rowan, 1977</xref>) about our own settings, universities, and the academy in general to not connect what we do as scholars to who we are and how we can have an impact. Last, this article is a call to action: a call to discover what we as scholars can care about and how we can use our skills and gifts as academics to create a better society, not only as a collective endeavor but also, similar to Hansen’s work on death penalty cases in Texas, as a series of individual projects. With this last call to action, I have my own call to action. What are your “dare to care stories?” We at <italic>JMI</italic> invite you to submit your dare to care stories as a way of starting a dialogue and encouraging others to dare to care. Specifically, email me with your dare to care stories (<email>washingt@ualberta.ca</email>). Most of these will go on our website as we create a dialogue and continue to encourage others to care; however, some of these stories could end up in further essays in <italic>JMI</italic> as we, the editors of <italic>JMI</italic>, want to continue the trend of providing scholars with a place to connect the passion in their lives with their academic scholarship!</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>Reference</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1056492611430299">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rowan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group> (<year>1977</year>). <article-title>Institutionalized organizations: Formal structure as myth and ceremony</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Sociology</source>, <volume>83</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>340</fpage>-<lpage>363</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>