<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">NCP</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spncp</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nutr Clin Pract</journal-id>
<journal-title>Nutrition in Clinical Practice</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0884-5336</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1941-2452</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0884533612443713</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0884533612443713</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Invited Commentary</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>The Place of Nutrition in Critical Care of the Chest</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Van Way</surname><given-names>Charles W.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>
<degrees>MD, FACS, FCCP, FCCM, FASPEN</degrees>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0884533612443713">University of Missouri-Kansas City, School of Medicine, Kansas City, Missouri</aff>
</contrib-group>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-0884533612443713">Charles W. Van Way III, MD, FACS, FCCP, FCCM, FASPEN, Sosland/Missouri Endowed, Chair of Trauma Services, University of Missouri-Kansas City, School of Medicine, 2411 Holmes Street, MG-C01, Kansas City, MO, USA; e-mail: <email>cvanway@kc.rr.com</email>.</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>6</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>27</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<issue-title>Cardiovascular and Critical Illness</issue-title>
<fpage>320</fpage>
<lpage>322</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 American Society for Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">The American Society for Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>On reading the excellent reviews in this issue, I found myself somewhat discouraged. Now, I should be clear about this. My background is in chest surgery. But my interest in nutrition is viewed by other chest surgeons as . . . shall we say, a harmless eccentricity. Nutrition is simply not viewed by heart surgeons and cardiologists as nearly as important as, for example, sewing in grafts or placing stents in the coronary arteries. That’s why I tend to feel discouraged. And yet, we have learned a great deal about the relationship between heart and lung disease, their treatment, and nutrition. It is now crystal clear that preoperative nutrition status can affect outcome and that feeding following operation can improve survival.</p>
<p>As noted in the article by Cresci et al,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0884533612443713">1</xref></sup> diseases of the heart and lung are hugely important as a cause of disability and death. Their economic importance is large, as well. According to an estimate, which is admittedly a bit old, from the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality, heart and lung disease together consume about 14% of total healthcare expenditures.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-0884533612443713">2</xref></sup> Being as those expenditures are around $2.1 trillion, that makes heart and lung disease treatment about the size of the gross domestic product of, say, Denmark. If such treatment were a country, it would be around 30th in the world.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-0884533612443713">3</xref></sup></p>
<p>The importance of nutrition in treating patients with heart and lung disease falls broadly into 3 categories. First, as noted above, malnutrition adversely affects outcome. Cresci et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0884533612443713">1</xref></sup> review this and point out that such established measures of inadequate nutrition as low body mass index (BMI), recent weight loss, and low serum albumin all correlate inversely with mortality. The good news here is that screening for malnutrition is universal in hospitalized patients. The Joint Commission mandates it, and all hospitals have to do it. But the bad news is that such screening can easily be ignored. Very few cardiac surgeons, for example, will cancel or delay a case because the serum albumin is low, nor will cardiologists delay a catheter procedure because the patient lost weight recently. Furthermore, early postoperative nutrition is far from universal. Most cardiac surgery patients are able to eat on day 2 or 3, and that’s felt to be “good enough.” And the treatment of patients with heart failure emphasizes diuresis, with nutrition often regarded as an unnecessary fluid load.</p>
<p>Second, specific barriers to the administration of nutrition occur in heart and lung disease. A major issue is the use of vasoactive drugs, a problem reviewed by Allen.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0884533612443713">4</xref></sup> Patients on pressors may have lowered blood flow to the intestines and liver and hence be only marginally able to absorb and process nutrients. Because the normal response to being fed is a marked increase in blood flow to the small intestine in particular, this may greatly interfere with nutrition. Patients who require pressors are among the most sick and most likely to have nutrition deficiencies either preexisting or going forward. Most clinicians feel that the unstable patient should not be fed and frequently interpret that as meaning the patient should be off all drugs. However, the American Society for Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition (A.S.P.E.N.) guidelines (and others) emphasize that, if the patient is reasonably stable, there is no contraindication to feeding even if 1 or 2 vasoactive drugs are being used. And as noted in Allen’s review, studies of nutrition in patients on pressors have shown the safety and efficacy of this recommendation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-0884533612443713">4</xref></sup></p>
<p>Related to the use of pressors is the question of when and if the patient is no longer in shock. Muller et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0884533612443713">5</xref></sup> have reviewed hemodynamic monitoring. The basic information obtained is pulmonary artery occlusion pressure, which allows approximation of left ventricular end-diastolic pressure, and cardiac output. From these can be calculated a number of helpful pieces of information, including stroke volume, stroke work, stroke work index, and, with the addition of blood oxygen values, oxygen delivery and consumption. All of these allow very precise titration of resuscitation for an unstable patient. This technique, now about 40 years old, has had varied acceptance over the years. After the initial development of the Swan Ganz pulmonary artery catheter, there was extensive use in critical care. Unfortunately, the pulmonary artery catheter has its own sets of complications. Passing through the heart, with its tip in a branch of the pulmonary artery, these catheters can introduce infection, cause thrombosis, or lead to other problems. Its routine use has been found by several sizable studies to be unnecessary and possibly harmful. Beginning 10–15 years ago, its use has dropped dramatically. Still, there are patients in whom it may be very beneficial. As Muller and colleagues point out, emphatically and correctly, the pulmonary artery catheter is only valuable if findings derived from it are incorporated into treatment, preferably through algorithms to guide therapy. Emerging technologies, notably arterial waveform analysis and ultrasonography, have a great deal of promise to obtain equivalent data, and it may be possible in the near future to obtain needed information without the indwelling pulmonary artery catheter.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-0884533612443713">5</xref></sup></p>
<p>As with other critically ill patients, ventilator support is associated with difficulties in feeding. Most of us are all too familiar with these difficulties. Gastric feeding presents a particular hazard to patients on ventilators, because it is critical to avoid aspiration. Yet placement of a jejunal tube may be difficult in a patient who cannot go to the radiology department. Clinicians are often reluctant to place a central line and initiate parenteral nutrition (PN), with the result that patients are not fed at all. Although it is generally true that enteral nutrition is superior to PN, it is also true that either is preferable to no feeding at all.</p>
<p>One particular problem, a result of our advancing technology, is use of the ventricular assist device (VAD). The intra-aortic balloon assist device has been used for 30 years, but it should be viewed as a mechanical pressor drug and is only used for a few days, at most. But now, patients may have a VAD implanted and left in place for weeks or months. In suitable patients, it may be a “bridge to transplant”; in other patients, it may be a life-extending technology. Montgomery et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-0884533612443713">6</xref></sup> reviewed the nutrition needs of patients on the VAD. They point out that the patients whose heart failure has progressed to the point of needing ventricular assist are often malnourished. Furthermore, the presence of the device itself interferes with normal eating. Notably, in one study, the group having the lowest BMI (&lt;22.9) had the highest mortality.</p>
<p>Third, very specific nutrition problems relate to cardiac disease. The best example is the B vitamin complex. Most of us learned about “beriberi heart” during our training. So-called wet beriberi, caused by deficiency of thiamin (vitamin B<sub>1</sub>), is characterized by tachycardia, peripheral edema, and congestive failure. This subject is reviewed by Azizi-Namini et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0884533612443713">7</xref></sup> They present the case for the use of thiamin and other members of the B complex in the routine treatment of congestive failure.</p>
<p>This is an easy recommendation in the case of thiamine. Because published studies vary widely, the true incidence of thiamin deficiency is difficult to assess. The only consensus across all studies is that, however common or uncommon it may be, it’s bad for you. But there have been prospective studies showing benefit of thiamine treatment in heart failure. The case for the other members of the B complex is less persuasive. These include riboflavin (B<sub>2</sub>), niacin (B<sub>3</sub>), pantothenic acid (B<sub>5</sub>), pyridoxine (B<sub>6</sub>), biotin (B<sub>7</sub>), and folic acid (B<sub>9</sub>). Although none of these has been shown to be specifically beneficial, a number of them have been found relatively deficient in patients with heart failure. It can reasonably be concluded that, although vitamin supplementation is commonly administered to all other chronically ill patients, supplementation may be an especially good thing for patients with heart failure. Pending the availability of better studies, it is probably reasonable to use a broad supplement of the B complex rather than confining supplementation to thiamine alone.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-0884533612443713">7</xref></sup></p>
<p>Protein-losing enteropathy is a specific problem that may follow completion of the Fontan operation, a staged procedure for infants and children with single ventricle. O’Leary et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-0884533612443713">8</xref></sup> have reviewed the management of this particularly difficult complication. Because the Fontan operation is associated with a postoperative rise in the central venous pressure, some patients may develop enteropathy, presumably on the basis of increased splanchnic venous pressure.</p>
<p>It may be appropriate to point out, as a surgeon, that our view of “optimal” nutrition status is still evolving. There has been, for a very long time, a suspicion among surgeons that patients who are overweight by the usual definition might even fare better than normal-weight or undernourished patients following surgery. Despite several studies on this point, data have not been conclusive. There is increasing evidence, however, that patients who are underweight are subject to a much larger risk of mortality following operation and that obesity is not harmful, as it was once thought to be. A recent study by Turrentine et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-0884533612443713">9</xref></sup> drew data from the National Surgery Quality Improvement Program (NSQIP). The NSQIP calculates operative risk of mortality from 30 preoperative variables, with an accuracy that has been well validated by other studies. Turrentine and colleagues compared BMI with the calculated operative risk for 189,533 patients undergoing general or vascular surgical procedures. Cardiac procedures were not included, although pulmonary and vascular operations were in the analysis. The highest risk was in the first quintile of BMI (&lt;23.1 kg/m<sup>2</sup>). None of the other quintiles were significantly different from the third or “reference” quintile (26.3–29.7). In particular, the fifth quintile (&gt;35.2) had less than half the mortality risk than the first quintile (1% vs 2.8%) and was not significantly different from the third or fourth quintile. The second quintile (23.1 to &lt;26.3) had a higher risk than the reference quintile (1.8% vs 1.5%) but not significantly so. In short, an optimum weight for the surgical patient may be somewhat higher than the usually cited range of normal (18.5–24.9 kg/m<sup>2</sup>).</p>
<p>In a study of cardiac surgery patients, Reeves et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-0884533612443713">10</xref></sup> studied 4372 patients undergoing coronary artery bypass grafting. The categories they used were as follows: underweight, BMI &lt;20 kg/m<sup>2</sup>; normal, 20–25 kg/m<sup>2</sup>; overweight, 25–30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>; obese, 30–35 kg/m<sup>2</sup>; and severely obese, &gt;35 kg/m<sup>2</sup>. The risk of death was 4 times higher in the underweight group (6.8%) than in normal-weight group (0.9%). Overweight (0.8%) or obese (0.8%, 0.6%) patients were no different from the normal-weight group. The odds ratios were 4.12, 1.0, 1.31, and 1.12 (underweight, normal, overweight, and obese), with only the underweight group being significantly different. This study was also cited by Cresci et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-0884533612443713">1</xref></sup></p>
<p>In short, it is clear that the preoperative screening of patients who are to have heart or lung surgery should emphasize detection and treatment of underweight and malnutrition. Furthermore, it is strongly suggested that for screening purposes, the threshold for underweight should be reset to between 20 and 23 kg/m<sup>2</sup>.</p>
<p>The syndrome of cardiac cachexia resulting from chronic heart failure has been known for years. Its development in a patient is considered an ominous prognostic sign. A recent study by Cai et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-0884533612443713">11</xref></sup> found that the survival rate of patients over a 30-month period with an initial BMI below 25 kg/m<sup>2</sup> was significantly lower than patients with a BMI over 25 kg/m<sup>2</sup>, as measured both by univariate analysis and by Kaplan-Meier survival curves. This suggests an even stronger relationship between underweight and mortality in patients with chronic heart failure.</p>
<p>We know that 30%–50% of hospitalized patients have inadequate nutrition or frank malnutrition. Both typically worsen during hospitalization. But unfortunately, clinicians often simply put off doing something about either problem. This has been especially true in care of the patient with heart or lung disease. Nutrition care has not historically been a large part of cardiothoracic surgery, cardiology, or pulmonary medicine. We need to change that and to make it as important as any other factor that determines patient outcomes.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>This work acknowledges the support of the Sosland Family Fund, Kansas City, Missouri.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<p>Financial disclosure: none declared.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-0884533612443713">
<label>1.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cresci</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hummell</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raheem</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Nutrition intervention in the critically ill cardiothoracic patient</article-title>. <source>Nutr Clin Pract</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>323</fpage>-<lpage>334</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-0884533612443713">
<label>2.</label>
<citation citation-type="gov">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Olin</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rhoades</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <source>The Five Most Costly Medical Conditions, 1997 and 2002: Estimates for the U.S. Civilian Non-Institutionalized Population</source>. <comment>Statistical Brief 80</comment>. <publisher-loc>Rockville, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality</publisher-name>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://meps.ahrq.gov/mepsweb/data_files/publications/st80/stat80.pdf">http://meps.ahrq.gov/mepsweb/data_files/publications/st80/stat80.pdf</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed February 27, 2012</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-0884533612443713">
<label>3.</label>
<citation citation-type="web"><collab>List of countries by GDP (nominal)</collab>. <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_countries_by_GDP_(nominal)">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_countries_by_GDP_(nominal)</ext-link></comment>. <access-date>Accessed February 27, 2012</access-date>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-0884533612443713">
<label>4.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Vasoactive substances and their effects on nutrition in the critically ill patient</article-title>. <source>Nutr Clin Pract</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>335</fpage>-<lpage>339</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-0884533612443713">
<label>5.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kennard</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fecher</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>TZ</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Hemodynamic monitoring in the intensive care unit</article-title>. <source>Nutr Clin Pract</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>340</fpage>-<lpage>351</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-0884533612443713">
<label>6.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garnick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spadafore</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boldea</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Nutrition assessment, care, and considerations of the ventricular assist device patients</article-title>. <source>Nutr Clin Pract</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>352</fpage>-<lpage>362</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-0884533612443713">
<label>7.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Azizi-Namini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keith</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The role of B vitamins in the management of heart failure</article-title>. <source>Nutr Clin Pract</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>363</fpage>-<lpage>374</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-0884533612443713">
<label>8.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Driscoll</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>O’Leary</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Protein losing enteropathy and the Fontan operation</article-title>. <source>Nutr Clin Pract</source>. <year>2012</year>;<fpage>375</fpage>-<lpage>384</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-0884533612443713">
<label>9.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Turrentine</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hanks</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schirmer</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stukenborg</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>The relationship between body mass index and 30-day mortality risk, by principal surgical procedure</article-title>. <source>Arch Surg</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>147</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>236</fpage>-<lpage>242</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-0884533612443713">
<label>10.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ascione</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chamberlain</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Angelinni</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Effect of body mass index on early outcomes in patients undergoing coronary artery bypass surgery</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>668</fpage>-<lpage>676</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-0884533612443713">
<label>11.</label>
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>He</surname><given-names>ZX</given-names></name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Body mass index and rest myocardial perfusion defect predicts cardiac death in patients with chronic heart failure</article-title>. <source>Int J Cardiovasc Imaging</source>. <year>2012</year> <month>Feb</month> <day>12</day>. [<comment>Epub ahead of print</comment>]</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>