<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JMQ</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjmq</journal-id>
<journal-title>Journalism &amp; Mass Communication Quarterly</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1077-6990</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">XXXX-XXXX</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1077699012455999</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1077699012455999</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Ideology and Framing</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Suppressing Allied Atrocity Stories</article-title>
<subtitle>The Unwritten Clause of the World War II Censorship Code</subtitle>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<name><surname>Slattery</surname><given-names>Karen</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1077699012455999">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name><surname>Doremus</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-1077699012455999">2</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-1077699012455999"><label>1</label>Marquette University, Milwaukee, WI, USA</aff>
<aff id="aff2-1077699012455999"><label>2</label>University of Wisconsin–Milwaukee, Milwaukee, WI, USA</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="corresp1-1077699012455999">Karen Slattery, Marquette University, Diederich College of Communication, Department of Journalism, 1131 West Wisconsin Avenue, Milwaukee, WI 53223, USA Email: <email>karen.slattery@marquette.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>89</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<fpage>624</fpage>
<lpage>642</lpage>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© 2012 AEJMC</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="society">Association for Education in Journalism &amp; Mass Communication</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Wartime journalists can be torn between loyalty to the ideal of truth and loyalty to their nation. During World War II, American journalists working in the Office of Censorship reached beyond the domestic self-censorship code to stop the publication of news of Allied atrocities. The press had agreed to suppress stories related to military security, but not to cover up military misconduct. The resulting conflict proved difficult for journalists and journalists working for the government to resolve.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Office of Censorship</kwd>
<kwd>wartime</kwd>
<kwd>press censorship</kwd>
<kwd>Allied atrocities</kwd>
<kwd>World War II</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The First Amendment, which prohibits laws abridging press freedom, was written because the nation’s founders, and their intellectual forbearers, wanted journalism to be a check on the abuse of power by public officials.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-1077699012455999">1</xref></sup> Scholars and others have long argued that a free press must be responsible,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-1077699012455999">2</xref></sup> and professional journalists have embraced a commitment to truth-telling, as expressed in the 1922 “Canons of Journalism” and subsequent codes of ethics.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-1077699012455999">3</xref></sup> In 1947, the Hutchins Commission called for truthful and complete reporting.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-1077699012455999">4</xref></sup> These statements suggest journalists are obliged to accurately and comprehensively report news that serves the public interest.</p>
<p>However, the loyalty to truth may conflict with loyalty to country when the nation is at war. Threats to national security may lead the press and the public to conclude that the journalist’s commitment to accurate and comprehensive reporting must be restrained.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-1077699012455999">5</xref></sup> Such was the case in World War II, when the American press cooperated with the federal government at home and military in battle zones to restrict reporting for security reasons.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-1077699012455999">6</xref></sup></p>
<p>This study focuses on the nation’s domestic Office of Censorship and the problem of reporting atrocities committed by U.S. and Allied soldiers. It shows that accounts of Allied atrocities were not matters of military security under the censorship agreement between the Office of Censorship and the military. But, as the evidence of the atrocities reached the United States, the military pressured the Office of Censorship to formally agree to restrict such news. The censors resisted the pressure and reached an uneasy compromise.</p>
<p>The goal of this study is to understand how the journalists serving in the Office of Censorship wrestled with the problem of reporting actions of Allied soldiers who violated international law. World War II is of particular interest because it has been considered a paradigm of a “just war,” which requires that the war be the nation’s last resort and its targets appropriate, and that the nation’s soldiers minimize destruction, death, and injury.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-1077699012455999">7</xref></sup> The 1929 Geneva Conventions, to which the United States was a signatory, codified a number of guidelines for battle: prohibitions included killing the wounded, bombing hospitals, and desecrating enemy dead. Such actions violate “just war” principles.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8-1077699012455999">8</xref></sup></p>
<p>Government propaganda and press censorship shaped the narrative of the “Good War”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9-1077699012455999">9</xref></sup> that has long colored public perception of World War II.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10-1077699012455999">10</xref></sup> Parts of the narrative have been called into question,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11-1077699012455999">11</xref></sup> as scholars have begun examining the role of the press in constructing cultural myths surrounding armed conflicts.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12-1077699012455999">12</xref></sup> Some have grounded their research in the concept of mythmaking, a necessary cultural process, according to Jung, Neumann, and others.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13-1077699012455999">13</xref></sup> Storytellers use archetypal figures to interpret phenomena and events and make sense of their lives. Mythic stories reflect patterns of experience and are peopled with heroes and villains who struggle over good and evil; the soldier as hero is a familiar archetype. Myths embody and transmit cultural values, and in doing so, the mythic stories help to establish cultural and political identity.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14-1077699012455999">14</xref></sup></p>
<p>Lule situates news within the context of cultural mythmaking to the extent that news tells “the great stories of humankind for humankind.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15-1077699012455999">15</xref></sup> News narratives are told within the context of similar stories and become part of a larger symbolic system that is a model for and of culture.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16-1077699012455999">16</xref></sup> Because values and behaviors are embedded in news stories, and news has the power to influence how readers think about and react to events, it is critical to understand the forces shaping these narratives. Stories based on incomplete information or misinformation, in time, may lead to choices that are damaging to a nation’s best interests.</p>
<sec id="section1-1077699012455999">
<title>Literature Review</title>
<p>Press censorship is often tolerated when the nation’s security is threatened.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17-1077699012455999">17</xref></sup> As Smith has pointed out, officials typically argue that safety is a higher law than the Constitution.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18-1077699012455999">18</xref></sup> Sweeney has noted that the tension among the military, the government, and the free press over wartime censorship has never been fully resolved.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19-1077699012455999">19</xref></sup></p>
<p>Historians have examined mechanisms put into place by the Wilson administration during the Great War,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20-1077699012455999">20</xref></sup> which, in turn, set the stage for press censorship during World War II. The World War I Committee on Public Information both generated wartime propaganda and managed press self-censorship. Those functions were separated during World War II; the U.S. Office of Censorship oversaw press self-censorship, while the U.S. Office of War Information produced propaganda to maintain morale. The director of the Office of Censorship, Byron Price, believed that limiting his agency’s news-related functions to censorship led to more cooperation and trust between the stateside press and his office on wartime press restrictions.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21-1077699012455999">21</xref></sup></p>
<p>Sweeney and McDaniel have provided overviews of the agency and its functions,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22-1077699012455999">22</xref></sup> while Washburn has detailed the relationship between the Office of Censorship and military during the development of the atomic bomb.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23-1077699012455999">23</xref></sup> Theodore Koop,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24-1077699012455999">24</xref></sup> Frank Clough,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25-1077699012455999">25</xref></sup> and Byron Price described the Office of Censorship,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26-1077699012455999">26</xref></sup> its philosophies, and its decisions from the perspective of insiders in accounts of their efforts as press censors. While these studies and reports are replete with stories about how the civilian censors handled difficulties between the wartime press and the military, they have failed to systematically address the problem related to reporting news of Allied atrocities. Sweeney and Knightley reported that no such stories appeared in the wartime press,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27-1077699012455999">27</xref></sup> while Smith has noted that stories of Allied atrocities were “usually rejected either by the censors or the journalists themselves.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28-1077699012455999">28</xref></sup> Censors failed to mention the problem in the <italic>Report on the Office of Censorship</italic>,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29-1077699012455999">29</xref></sup> or in their postwar writings and speeches.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30-1077699012455999">30</xref></sup></p>
<p>This study fills the gap in the literature surrounding the policy of the Office of Censorship on the publication of Allied atrocity stories, a policy that censors and others privately referred to as the “unwritten clause” of the censorship <italic>Code</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31-1077699012455999">31</xref></sup> It seeks to answer the following questions: How did civilian censors, working on behalf of and with the consent of the American news media, grapple with the issue of reporting Allied atrocities, particularly acts committed by Americans in the Pacific theater of war? What pressures did the military and government apply on censors to keep the domestic press from reporting such stories? How did they respond, and what normative rationales did they offer in their response? Answers to these questions help clarify how the journalists who staffed the Office of Censorship viewed their wartime obligations, and further an understanding of the larger problem of press censorship during war.</p>
<p>This study lays out the philosophies behind the practices and details how censors squared off with the military over publishing news about Allied war crimes. That story has been buried in government files. Sources for this study are the records of the Office of Censorship housed in the National Archives in Maryland and the Byron Price papers located at the Wisconsin State Historical Society in Madison, Wisconsin. The authors drew on memoranda, telegrams, letters, records of phone conversations, and other documents. The archival material reveals how the censors reacted to the reports of American atrocities arriving from the South Pacific and indicates that the stories gradually emerged as an unanticipated threat to the consensus on the restriction of wartime news.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="section2-1077699012455999">
<title>Voluntary Press Censorship in World War II</title>
<p>Stateside journalists saw themselves as patriotic and press self-censorship as an instrument of war.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32-1077699012455999">32</xref></sup> By withholding some information from the public, the press put concerns about international crisis ahead of its professional devotion to truth. The press and the government struck the domestic censorship bargain shortly after Congress declared war against Germany and Japan. President Franklin Roosevelt created the Office of Censorship and named Associated Press (AP) newsman Byron Price as its director on December 16, 1941.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33-1077699012455999">33</xref></sup> Resisting pressure from aides for statutory censorship, the president set up a system for the domestic press to censor itself.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34-1077699012455999">34</xref></sup></p>
<p>In negotiating voluntary press censorship with the government and military, Censorship Director Byron Price secured limits to the type of material that the stateside press would censor. Price was steeped in the tradition of the free press; he was the AP executive editor when he agreed to head the Office of Censorship. Having been a World War I infantry officer in France,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35-1077699012455999">35</xref></sup> he believed that some material should be censored during conflict.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36-1077699012455999">36</xref></sup> Price worked with the government and military early in the war to craft the <italic>Code of Wartime Practices for the American Press</italic>, a guidebook for editors and publishers that limited censorship to information related to military security. The <italic>Code</italic> asked journalists to refrain from publishing information about enemy attacks, domestic fortifications, factory production, weather conditions, and military and presidential movements. A similar code was created for American broadcasters. Both were revised four times during the war.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37-1077699012455999">37</xref></sup> Journalists were told to keep a question in mind when editing stories: “Is this information I would like to have if I were the enemy?”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38-1077699012455999">38</xref></sup></p>
<p>Price staffed the Office of Censorship’s Press Division with journalists who took leaves of absence to work in Washington but remained on the payrolls of the news organizations that loaned them to the agency.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39-1077699012455999">39</xref></sup> Despite their efforts, there were occasional “busts,” or instances when press coverage revealed restricted information. The Office of Censorship would then send a written inquiry about the incident. If the offender offered no response, the news organization received a visit from an emissary, usually another editor or publisher from the area.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40-1077699012455999">40</xref></sup> Most often, however, the papers replied promptly. Price said most of the violations were inadvertent and the journalists were apologetic.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41-1077699012455999">41</xref></sup></p>
<p>Price believed that the military and government were responsible for censoring themselves. He therefore adopted the principle of “appropriate authority,” which said that information released by official sources was presumed cleared for publication even if it violated the <italic>Code</italic>. The principle of “prior publication” held that if a story crossed the <italic>Code</italic>, but was published elsewhere, the domestic press could use the information. If it was available to the enemy, Price reasoned, the American public should not be kept in the dark. He also refused to restrict editorial opinion and criticism of the government as had been done in the First World War.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42-1077699012455999">42</xref></sup></p>
<p>Undergirding the chief censor’s actions was an intense allegiance to the First Amendment and an aversion to government restrictions on free speech; his goal was to keep the press as free as possible during the war. Censorship, Price said, was to be impartial, transparent in its administration, addressed to secrets of military value to the enemy, and limited in its scope to factual information.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43-1077699012455999">43</xref></sup> In effect, Price had made a compact with his fellow journalists: observe voluntary censorship by self-policing and avoid mandatory controls imposed by law.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44-1077699012455999">44</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section3-1077699012455999">
<title>Atrocity Stories</title>
<p>Press accounts of atrocities by the United States and Allies became an increasingly difficult problem for censors as the war unfolded. In North Africa and Europe, Americans and their opponents waged a “war of rules” in which the Geneva Conventions were generally observed, though violations did occur, particularly as the Allies approached German soil.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45-1077699012455999">45</xref></sup> In contrast, the fighting against Japan was notoriously brutal, and it was the Japanese who took the lead in making it so.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn46-1077699012455999">46</xref></sup> On Bataan, in the Philippines, in 1942, the Imperial Army tortured and mutilated its enemies. Dismembered corpses were left out in the open to be found, presumably for purposes of intimidation.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47-1077699012455999">47</xref></sup> On Guadalcanal, wounded and captured Japanese killed Americans with hidden weapons. If severely injured, a Japanese soldier was likely to commit suicide or be killed by others around him. The Japanese seemed to have no fear of death; in fact, they appeared to embrace it. Cornered, or in a hopeless situation, Japanese soldiers made banzai charges into enemy fire. They were trained to prefer death to dishonor.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn48-1077699012455999">48</xref></sup></p>
<p>The American response was to dehumanize the enemy. According to Linderman, American soldiers viewed the Japanese as impossible to understand; they were “inscrutable,” “inhuman,” “crazy,” “demented,” and “fearless.” They were referred to as “little, yellow monkeys,” “rats,” “mad dogs,” “jungle animals,” “snakes,” and “ghosts.” A pestilence to be obliterated, they slithered through the jungle and burrowed into island caves and bunkers.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn49-1077699012455999">49</xref></sup></p>
<p>These attitudes were compounded by a virulent and deep-seated racial antagonism toward the Japanese. In the eyes of American soldiers, the Japanese were well below Germans and Italians on the subjective scale of “humanness.” European enemies were viewed as “men just like us,” observed Harrison, while the Japanese were subhuman.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn50-1077699012455999">50</xref></sup> American propagandists portrayed the Japanese as insects and vermin;<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn51-1077699012455999">51</xref></sup> frontline soldiers and military leaders alike spoke of them as a species entirely different from human beings.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn52-1077699012455999">52</xref></sup> Accordingly, the cold-blooded murder and desecration of the dead were most prevalent in the Pacific theater.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn53-1077699012455999">53</xref></sup> American soldiers executed prisoners and the rare Japanese soldier who attempted to surrender.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn54-1077699012455999">54</xref></sup> Allied soldiers often collected Japanese body parts.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn55-1077699012455999">55</xref></sup> They extracted gold teeth (before and after death), cut off ears, and boiled heads for souvenir skulls. The trophies were mounted on military vehicles, or mailed home to wives, girlfriends, relatives, and even public officials.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn56-1077699012455999">56</xref></sup> Many soldiers and civilians condemned such violations of the rules of “civilized” warfare. But war crimes happened, as callousness and bitterness gradually debased American soldiers in the brutal Pacific war.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn57-1077699012455999">57</xref></sup> Allied war crimes in the Pacific were sufficiently well known as to attract the serious concern of military authorities.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn58-1077699012455999">58</xref></sup></p>
<p>The censorship system in place during the Second World War was partially to blame for the difficulties that arose over the Allied atrocity stories. The Office of Censorship was responsible for overseeing voluntary censorship stateside, and, while censors made suggestions to editors, publishers, and broadcasters, they lacked the legal authority to tell them what information to withhold. Border censorship, meanwhile, was statutory. Cable and postal censors in the Office of Censorship were responsible for seeing that print publications and other communications leaving the country, including newspapers, did not harm military security.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn59-1077699012455999">59</xref></sup> Military field censors had absolute authority to censor news stories originating in the war zone; accredited journalists submitted their dispatches for clearance.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn60-1077699012455999">60</xref></sup></p>
<p>As will be shown, Price and his staff initially argued they had no standing to censor stories of atrocities committed by U.S. and Allied soldiers because that kind of information was not a matter of military security under the <italic>Code</italic>. The military, embarrassed by the disclosures, repeatedly pressured the Office of Censorship for a remedy. Like the military, Price and his staff recognized the problems that the stories could create for the services, but they believed it was the military’s job to censor itself. Price adopted a behind-the-scenes strategy to help curtail the publication of Allied atrocity stories, but the strategy was not entirely successful.</p>
<p>Atrocity stories came from three sources. The first was interviews with service members who returned from war zones. The military censored everything that originated in combat areas, from soldiers’ letters to journalists’ dispatches, in an effort to remove anything that might be of use to the enemy or potentially embarrassing. The War Department warned returning personnel against speaking to the stateside press without clearance from a local public relations officer (PRO).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn61-1077699012455999">61</xref></sup> However, the military lacked the authority to censor the press once the statements were made to reporters; in some cases the comments revealed violations of the Geneva Conventions.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn62-1077699012455999">62</xref></sup></p>
<p>A revised edition of the <italic>Code</italic>, issued on July 15, 1942, added a provision asking journalists to submit stories containing interviews with returnees to either the Office of Censorship in Washington or a local military PRO for clearance. The request fell under the “Notes on Rumors” section of the <italic>Code</italic> that discouraged publishing stories related to “enemy claims of ship sinkings and other damage to our forces.” The clause also urged caution “in handling so-called ‘atrocity’ stories.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn63-1077699012455999">63</xref></sup> Early in the war, the military had asked the Office of Censorship to encourage suppression of enemy atrocity stories to avoid, among other things, reprisal against Japanese nationals in the United States. Censors tried to comply, but abandoned the plan when the government and military could not decide if publishing stories of enemy atrocities would help or hurt the American cause.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn64-1077699012455999">64</xref></sup> The reference to “so-called atrocities” was dropped from the <italic>Code</italic>’s later editions.</p>
<p>A second source of Allied atrocity stories included letters and graphic photos from the front that recipients shared with the news media. The third edition of the <italic>Code</italic>, issued on February 1, 1943, urged journalists to be judicious when publishing letters from the war zone. They were advised that those letters were edited by field censors for private rather than public consumption, and might contain information that the military would not want published.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn65-1077699012455999">65</xref></sup></p>
<p>The third source of the information was souvenirs, usually Japanese body parts, that indicated a failure of military discipline. The stories about the souvenirs arriving in the United States, sometimes via the mail, did not necessarily seem objectionable to the press because the <italic>Code</italic> did not specifically address the subject and the items had been passed by field censors.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn66-1077699012455999">66</xref></sup></p>
<p>The military, vexed by the stories that were printed, thought that Price should add a blanket provision to the <italic>Code</italic> asking the press to refrain from publishing all stories about atrocities committed by U.S. and Allied soldiers, or issue a Special Request or Confidential Memo to journalists, as his office did in other cases.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn67-1077699012455999">67</xref></sup> The Office of Censorship, however, steadfastly refused to formally ask the press to black out stories related to Allied atrocities. The staff clearly recognized the problem, but believed the military had its own duty to keep soldiers in line. Jack Lockhart, deputy director of the Press Division, argued it would be difficult for press censors to claim the stories were domestically dangerous if military censors allowed “certain souvenirs” to leave the war zone.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn68-1077699012455999">68</xref></sup> Press censors insisted that they did not want to be accused of helping the military hide misconduct. Assuming responsibility for keeping the stories out of the media, they argued, would undermine their covenant with the stateside journalists and threaten voluntary censorship, which depended on the good will of American journalists if it was to work.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn69-1077699012455999">69</xref></sup></p>
<p>At the same time, the Office of Censorship staff members reached beyond the <italic>Code</italic> to discourage the publication of Allied atrocity stories when they knew about them ahead of time. They also contacted offending journalists after accounts of U.S. or Allied atrocities were distributed in order to discourage them from publishing additional stories. Censors repeatedly told the military that this unofficial practice, also called the “unwritten clause” of the <italic>Code</italic>, was as far as they were willing to go.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn70-1077699012455999">70</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section4-1077699012455999">
<title>Pressure on the Censors</title>
<p>The publication of atrocity stories prompted complaints to government officials. In the summer of 1943, Texas Congressman George Mahon wrote to President Roosevelt and the Office of War Information,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn71-1077699012455999">71</xref></sup> asking what was being done to suppress stories like one in the <italic>Dallas News</italic>, about a Marine, a taxidermist in civilian life, who sent family members a string of beads made out of Japanese teeth.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn72-1077699012455999">72</xref></sup> Mahon wrote that he also knew of a state official who had received pictures showing “various stages in the cooking of Japanese heads, the scraping of the heads and finished skull [<italic>sic</italic>] for souvenirs.” Saying he was writing on behalf of the West Texas prisoners of war, Mahon worried the American soldiers would be tortured and killed if the Japanese learned how their own men had been treated. General George Strong responded that such occurrences were “shocking to our sensibilities and . . . unworthy of a civilized people.” He agreed that the news accounts could lead to enemy reprisals against American POWs.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn73-1077699012455999">73</xref></sup> Captain Leland Lovett, director of the Navy’s Office of Public Relations, told the lawmaker that such reports reflected isolated instances and that servicemen “are instructed to abide scrupulously by the terms of the Geneva Convention in treatment of enemy prisoners or dead.” He pointed out that the Navy had no censorship authority in these matters and told the lawmaker that he would ask the Office of Censorship to request that the press refrain from publishing such reports or pictures. “This is the soundest solution and should bring desired results,” he said.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn74-1077699012455999">74</xref></sup></p>
<p>The Office of Censorship resisted the idea. Lockhart told Price that he feared that a formal request to the press would backfire, “leading to the belief that we were covering up widespread inhuman and sadistic behavior.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn75-1077699012455999">75</xref></sup> Responding to Congressman Mahon, Lockhart said that the press had been patriotic and cooperative when censors discouraged individual editors and broadcasters from publishing atrocity stories. He added that when such information got into print it was suppressed at the nation’s borders and was unlikely to be read by the Japanese.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn76-1077699012455999">76</xref></sup></p>
<p>Several months later, Colonel Gilbert Jacobus of the War Department alerted the Office of Censorship to a <italic>Washington Post</italic> picture of a sailor home on leave. In the background were three human skulls. Jacobus said that the War Department had instructed commanders in the South and Southwest Pacific to suppress these kinds of stories, and he asked Price to cooperate in controlling that type of information.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn77-1077699012455999">77</xref></sup> The archives have no record of any response.</p>
<p>At the end of January 1944, the U.S. and British governments released the news of the Japanese atrocities committed against the Allies at Bataan and Corregidor in the Philippines. When the news of the “March of Death,” based on eye-witness accounts,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn78-1077699012455999">78</xref></sup> was made public, Price issued a short Note to Editors and Broadcasters stating that interviews with civilians or service men from combat zones that “disclos[ed] atrocities,” should be submitted to local PROs or the Office of Censorship for clearance. He said that the purpose of the reminder was to make sure nothing was printed that revealed “guerilla activities or escape routes or identifying data” that could lead to reprisal against people in enemy territory.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn79-1077699012455999">79</xref></sup> The timing of the note, as well as a letter from the Director of War Information to the Chairman of the Joint Chief of Staff in the Office of Censorship file,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn80-1077699012455999">80</xref></sup> suggests that the note was related to news of enemy atrocities; there is no indication that Price believed that the note would serve to satisfy the military that the Office of Censorship was taking steps to black out stories related to Allied atrocities.</p>
<p>The Office of Censorship, meanwhile, remained wary on that issue. On January 31, 1944, censor Bill Mylander learned that the military’s Joint Security Control drafted a policy giving the services tighter control over the handling of atrocity stories, either enemy or Allied, told by its personnel. The proposal, which Mylander described as a “nightmare,” required that any statement or story involving atrocities be forwarded by local PROs “to either the War or Navy Departments for clearance—not the Office of Censorship.” The interviews would have to be accompanied by sworn affidavits swearing to the truthfulness of any atrocity claim.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn81-1077699012455999">81</xref></sup> Lockhart observed that the policy would confuse editors or publishers who had the option of submitting stories of interviews with returnees to either local PROs or the Office of Censorship.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn82-1077699012455999">82</xref></sup></p>
<p>In mid-February, censor Mil Petty suspiciously noted that, for the third time, the Army had asked the Office of Censorship a hypothetical question: What would censors do if a newspaper printed a story about a local store that displayed a Japanese skull in its windows? Censors had explained and re-explained their strategy to the military, saying they would encourage suppression if they “had a crack at the story before it got into print, although there was no code application.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn83-1077699012455999">83</xref></sup></p>
<p>Several days later, Major General A. D. Surles, the director of the War Department’s Bureau of Public Relations, sent a letter to Price indicating that the military would be handling all stories on atrocities committed by or against American and Allied soldiers. Surles said that it was his understanding that censors would put a hold on such stories unless the War Department issued a release.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn84-1077699012455999">84</xref></sup></p>
<p>The proposal astounded Lockhart, who said that he opposed ceding press censorship to the military.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn85-1077699012455999">85</xref></sup> Price responded immediately, calling Surles’s understanding “entirely incorrect.” He told Surles that there was nothing in the <italic>Code</italic> about atrocities and argued that voluntary censorship would collapse if censors started deviating from “the single principle of keeping information from the enemy.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn86-1077699012455999">86</xref></sup> Price’s quick and clear response, and the fact that he reported directly to President Roosevelt alone,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn87-1077699012455999">87</xref></sup> were apparently enough to keep the military at bay.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn88-1077699012455999">88</xref></sup></p>
<p>Service members continued to worry. In January of 1945, Lieutenant Ray Neumann, on staff at Censorship’s cable office, said he and others were concerned about Allied atrocity stories in newspapers leaving the United States. Arguing that military security extended to matters related to prisoners of war, Neumann asked Lockhart to create a code provision that prohibited publication of information that would lead to reprisal against U.S. soldiers. He insisted that if such information “results in harm, I don’t think the free press should carry weight.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn89-1077699012455999">89</xref></sup></p>
<p>Lockhart acknowledged the possible danger, but said that the “acts which our soldiers and sailors may commit against Japanese living or dead . . . are not primarily matters of military security and so are not included in the <italic>Code</italic>.” Lockhart admitted that some of the stories were not suppressed at the border because there was no provision in the <italic>Code</italic> to cover them, a statement that contradicted information given earlier to Congressman Mahon. Lockhart also reasoned that some of the stories had circulated widely in the domestic news media, so it was a matter of time before the Japanese learned of them.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn90-1077699012455999">90</xref></sup></p>
<p>Some in the media joined public officials, ordinary citizens, and the military in complaining when stories about U.S. or Allied atrocities found their way into print or broadcast. One complaint to reach a censor’s desk came from the president of a company that operated a Tennessee radio station. Edwin Craig said parents of POWs were upset about atrocity stories in the news, including one about “an American soldier’s father in Louisiana receiving the skull of dead Jap[anese] soldier” and “a Chicago policeman who received a similar souvenir.” Craig argued that these reports were dangerous to “every American soldier in a Jap[anese] prison camp and everyone who faces the possibility of capture,” and he wondered why they were allowed to circulate.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn91-1077699012455999">91</xref></sup> Price gave Craig the same answer he gave the military: that voluntary censorship was based on the “single principle of keeping information [of potential military value] from the enemy,” and any deviation from that principle would threaten voluntary censorship.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn92-1077699012455999">92</xref></sup></p>
<p>While Price did not point his finger at the military’s shortcomings in his letter to Craig, his staff members did just that among themselves. John Fetzer told Price that the Army and Navy field censors were under strict orders to see that nothing left the war zone that could be construed as “possible American atrocity materials,” noting that “the stories [referred to in the complaint] are the result of military failure to withhold shipments of certain portions of Japanese anatomies.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn93-1077699012455999">93</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section5-1077699012455999">
<title>Cautions to Journalists</title>
<p>While unwilling to add a clause to the <italic>Code</italic> related to Allied atrocities, censors discouraged the publication of such stories by citing the same reasons given by the military, the government, and citizens themselves when objecting to the press accounts of Allied misconduct. Japanese reprisal was often cited as the reason to withhold the stories. Lockhart raised the issue when he contacted the <italic>Lynchburg News</italic> about its story on a USO performer who proudly explained that she had been able to knock a tooth out of the skull of a dead Japanese soldier while she was on tour in the Pacific. He urged the paper’s editor to consider what might happen to soldiers or USO workers if captured. American papers, he said, would be following a “patriotic and humane policy in refusing to publicize such acts.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn94-1077699012455999">94</xref></sup></p>
<p>Lockhart expressed concern about the welfare of a soldier when he contacted the editor of the <italic>Houston Press</italic> about his paper’s decision to run a picture and story of Mrs. Cary Moss and her baby playing with a string of Japanese teeth sent home by the baby’s father. Lockhart urged the editor to hold back any more stories that “reveal any action of our men which is not clearly countenanced by rules of war.” He said that blacking out such stories would help soldiers like Sergeant Moss avoid discipline for breaking military regulations.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn95-1077699012455999">95</xref></sup> The editor responded his paper had erred.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn96-1077699012455999">96</xref></sup></p>
<p>When the city editor of the <italic>Washington Star</italic> asked whether it was acceptable to run a story about a Japanese skull and other souvenirs, Phil Adler replied that there was no <italic>Code</italic> objection, but “FYI and off the record, the War Department wanted to discourage every mention of skulls as souvenirs.” He told the editor that <italic>Life</italic> had run a photo showing a Japanese skull and the incident had “cost several officers their commission.” The editor replied that he understood and would not use anything on “Japanese skulls, ears, teeth or such” in future stories.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn97-1077699012455999">97</xref></sup></p>
<p>The <italic>Code</italic> urged journalists to use caution with letters from the war zone because they were censored for private reading only. When questioned about the appearance of a letter from a soldier who said he had been instructed to take no prisoners of war, the publisher of the <italic>Melvin Enterprise</italic> told Lockhart that he did not want to print anything that would “endanger the life [<italic>sic</italic>] of our boys or allies.” He said that he wished the government would censor the letters for public consumption because parents wanted to see the letters in print.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn98-1077699012455999">98</xref></sup></p>
<p>Lockhart contacted the editor of a mimeographed news publication of the Southwestern Power Association after he published a serviceman’s letter to his wife telling her not to “be surprised if you receive a little bottle of ears, pickled ears.” Lockhart pointed out that both enemy agents and general readers were likely to assume “that men in the South Pacific are collecting ears.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn99-1077699012455999">99</xref></sup> The editor said he believed that correspondence had been censored in the war zone, and promised to check with the Office of Censorship before printing additional letters.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn100-1077699012455999">100</xref></sup></p>
<p>Journalists were inclined to cooperate with Censorship’s efforts to discourage the publication of Allied atrocity stories. Lockhart wrote to the editor of the <italic>Red Lion Bugle</italic> who had printed a picture of a Fiji scout holding the severed head of a Japanese soldier with a story about American Marines trading cigarettes and clothing to islanders who offered proof of such slayings. Lockhart said that the story could be seen as saying that the Marines paid native islanders for killing Japanese soldiers.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn101-1077699012455999">101</xref></sup> The editor responded that he was a World War I veteran and had a son in the present conflict and would not print future stories that the enemy might use as propaganda.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn102-1077699012455999">102</xref></sup></p>
<p>While most journalists accepted the arguments for suppressing stories of Allied misconduct, some needed additional convincing. In one instance, censor Jim Warner tried to discourage a <italic>Washington Star</italic> journalist from profiling a pilot who deliberately bombed a German hospital in retaliation for the bombing of a U.S. hospital in Italy. Warner said he was trying to keep stories out of print that suggested that “our people did not obey the laws of war, for fear it would incite enemies to further excess.” The journalist agreed but argued it was a good story. Warner responded, “There are lots of good stories kicking around that would be better left untold until after the war.” He offered to review the story after it was written, but thought the journalist would drop it.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn103-1077699012455999">103</xref></sup></p>
<p>Stories about U.S. and Allied misconduct were noticed in Japan. The <italic>Nippon Times</italic> called the practice of collecting skulls “sickening barbarism.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn104-1077699012455999">104</xref></sup> News that an American serviceman sent President Roosevelt a letter opener carved from the bone of a Japanese soldier drew loud criticism from the Catholic Archbishop of Tokyo. According to the Vatican News Service, the Archbishop asked for respect for “laws of humanity, even in total war.” His remarks appeared following a story in Drew Pearson’s column in June 1944. FDR ordered the letter opener returned to the sender with the suggestion that it be buried.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn105-1077699012455999">105</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
<sec id="section6-1077699012455999">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>During and after the war, Price and his staff praised the press for cooperating with the government to conceal information from the enemy and keep the press as free as possible during the war.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn106-1077699012455999">106</xref></sup> But at the same time they congratulated the press for keeping the military’s wartime secrets, they harbored one of their own. No one from the Office of Censorship, during or after the war, sought to publicize the problem they had faced over stories of U.S. and Allied atrocities. In doing so, they neglected to share an important part of the Office of Censorship history, one that offers insight into how the journalists in the agency viewed their wartime obligations.</p>
<p>The story of the “unwritten clause” of the censorship <italic>Code</italic> can be interpreted in two ways. Discouraging the press from printing stories of Allied atrocities could be seen as an effort by censors to avoid harm to the war effort. Furthermore, the practice appeared to fend off military pressure for additional restrictions on information. On the other hand, the censors’ efforts to black out the stories were ad hoc and, perhaps, half-hearted. Their refusal to issue a blanket prohibition of such stories could be viewed as putting the general principle of truth ahead of concern for the nation’s war effort. The evidence indicates that censors did not want to be accused of participating in a cover up of military misconduct.</p>
<p>Why did Price and his staff withhold this piece of the press censorship story? They might have felt that the war-weary Americans did not care to hear about the Office of Censorship’s difficulties after the war, or they may have wanted to avoid raising the specter of Allied war crimes at a time when international war crime tribunals were under consideration. Finally, they may not have wanted to openly admit that they had violated one of Price’s own wartime precepts, that is, censors “should be frank with the public.”<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn107-1077699012455999">107</xref></sup></p>
<p>Whatever the reasoning, journalists in the Office of Censorship supported the national narrative of the “Good War” when they held back the story of the pressures they faced over news related to Allied atrocities. Their actions also helped forestall an honest and intelligent examination of the constraints that challenge a wartime press. The failure to debrief after World War II reflects a missed opportunity to refine the approach of the news media to the reporting of American misconduct in wartime. In the absence of a consensus, journalists lacked a clear vision on how to react when later atrocity stories emerged. The Vietnam My Lai massacre is one example.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn108-1077699012455999">108</xref></sup></p>
<p>The fact that Price was able to stave off military threats of further restrictions to press freedom during World War II should not be viewed by the press or by citizens as comforting. New wars bring new threats, to the government and to civil liberties. The time to negotiate media policy is not when the nation is at war, but rather when the country is at peace. During those periods, as Blasi has observed, it is also in the national interest to work toward ensuring that the First Amendment views of the citizenry are robust enough to survive the paranoid, emotional times.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn109-1077699012455999">109</xref></sup></p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors thank Marquette University’s J. William &amp; Mary Diederich College of Communication for project funding and Professor Jeffery A. Smith for his suggestions.</p>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="conflict">
<label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label>
<p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
<label>Funding</label>
<p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<notes>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-1077699012455999">
<label>1.</label>
<p>Vincent Blasi, “The Checking Value in First Amendment Theory,” <italic>American Bar Foundation Research Journal</italic> 2 (3, 1977): 521–649; Jeffery A. Smith, <italic>Printers and Press Freedom: The Ideology of Early American Journalism</italic> (New York: Oxford University Press, 1988).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-1077699012455999">
<label>2.</label>
<p>Elizabeth Blanks Hindman, “First Amendment Theories and Press Responsibility: The Work of Zechariah Chafee, Thomas Emerson, Vincent Blasi, and Edwin Baker,” <italic>Journalism Quarterly</italic> 69 (1, 1992): 48–64.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-1077699012455999">
<label>3.</label>
<p>See, e.g., American Society of Newspaper Editors, “Canons of Journalism” (1922), accessed August 15, 2011, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://asne.org/kiosk/archive/principl.htm">http://asne.org/kiosk/archive/principl.htm</ext-link>; Society of Professional Journalists, “SPJ Code of Ethics” accessed April 21, 2012, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.spj.org/ethicscode.asp">http://www.spj.org/ethicscode.asp</ext-link>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-1077699012455999">
<label>4.</label>
<p>Commission on Freedom of the Press, <italic>A Free and Responsible Press</italic> (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1947).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-1077699012455999">
<label>5.</label>
<p>Vincent Blasi, “The Pathological Perspective and the First Amendment,” <italic>Columbia Law Review</italic> 85 (April 1985): 449–514.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-1077699012455999">
<label>6.</label>
<p>See Michael S. Sweeney, <italic>Secrets of Victory: The Office of Censorship and the American Press and Radio in World War</italic> II (Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 2001); Patrick S. Washburn, “The Office of Censorship’s Attempt to Control Press Coverage of the Atomic Bomb during World War II,” <italic>Journalism Monographs</italic> 120 (April 1990); Alvin William McDaniel, Jr., “The War on Words: The Office of Censorship in World War II” (master’s thesis, University of the Pacific, 1972); Theodore Koop, <italic>Weapon of Silence</italic> (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1946); Byron Price, “Memoir,” Price Papers, Boxes 4 and 5, Wisconsin State Historical Society (WHi); Robert E. Summers, comp., <italic>Wartime Censorship of Press and Radio</italic> (New York: H. W. Wilson, 1942).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-1077699012455999">
<label>7.</label>
<p>Michael Walzer, <italic>Just and Unjust Wars</italic> (New York: Basic Books, 1992).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn8-1077699012455999">
<label>8.</label>
<p>Convention for the Amelioration of the Condition of the Wounded and Sick in Armies in the Field, Articles 6, 9, Geneva, 27 July 1929, accessed January 14, 2011, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.icrc.org/ihl.nsf/FULL/300">http://www.icrc.org/ihl.nsf/FULL/300</ext-link>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn9-1077699012455999">
<label>9.</label>
<p>Richard W. Steele, “News of the ‘Good War’: World War II News Management,” <italic>Journalism Quarterly</italic> 62 (winter 1985): 707–17, 783.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn10-1077699012455999">
<label>10.</label>
<p>Tom Brokaw, <italic>The Greatest Generation</italic> (New York: Random House, 2004) and <italic>Saving Private Ryan</italic>, directed by Steven Spielberg (1998; Universal City, CA: DreamWorks, Paramount Pictures, 1999).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn11-1077699012455999">
<label>11.</label>
<p>John E. Bodnar, <italic>The “Good War” in American Memory</italic> (Baltimore, MD: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2010); Michael C. Adams, “The ‘Good War’ Myth and the Cult of Nostalgia,” <italic>Midwest Quarterly</italic> 40 (autumn 1988): 59–74.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn12-1077699012455999">
<label>12.</label>
<p>Ana C. Garner and Karen Slattery, “Mobilizing Mother: From Good Mother to Patriotic Mother in World War I,” <italic>Journalism and Communication Monographs</italic> 14 (1, 2012); Ana C. Garner and Karen Slattery, “The World War II Patriotic Mother: A Cultural Ideal in the US Press,” <italic>Journalism Studies</italic> 11 (April 2010): 143–57.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn13-1077699012455999">
<label>13.</label>
<p>Carl G. Jung, <italic>Memories, Dreams, Reflections</italic>, ed. Aniela Jaffe (New York: Vintage Books, 1965); Jolande Jacobi, <italic>Complex/Archetype/Symbol in the Psychology of C. G. Jung</italic> (New York: Pantheon Books, 1959); Erich Neumann, <italic>The Fear of the Feminine and Other Essays on Feminine Psychology</italic>, trans. Boris Matthews, Esther Doughty, Eugene Rolfe, and Michael Cullingworth (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1994); Anthony Stevens, <italic>Archetypes: A Natural History of the Self</italic> (New York: Quill, 1982).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn14-1077699012455999">
<label>14.</label>
<p>Barry B. Powell, <italic>Classical Myth</italic> (Upper Saddle River, NJ: Pearson/Prentice Hall, 2001).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn15-1077699012455999">
<label>15.</label>
<p>Jack Lule, <italic>Daily News, Eternal Stories: The Mythological Role of Journalism</italic> (New York: Guilford, 2001), 15.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn16-1077699012455999">
<label>16.</label>
<p>Lule, <italic>Daily News, Eternal Stories.</italic></p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn17-1077699012455999">
<label>17.</label>
<p>Phillip Knightley, <italic>The First Casualty: The War Correspondent as Hero and Myth-Maker from the Crimea to Iraq</italic> (Baltimore, MD: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2004).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn18-1077699012455999">
<label>18.</label>
<p>Jeffery A. Smith, <italic>War and Press Freedom: The Problem of Prerogative Power</italic> (New York: Oxford University Press, 1999).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn19-1077699012455999">
<label>19.</label>
<p>Michael S. Sweeney, <italic>The Military and the Press: An Uneasy Truce</italic> (Evanston, IL: Northwestern University Press, 2006).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn20-1077699012455999">
<label>20.</label>
<p>Stephen Vaughn, <italic>Holding Fast the Inner Lines: Democracy, Nationalism, and the Committee on Public Information</italic> (Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1980); James R. Mock and Cedric Larson, <italic>Words That Won the War: The Story of the Committee on Public Information 1917–1919</italic> (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1939); U.S. Committee on Public Information, <italic>The Creel Report: Complete Report of the Chairman of the Committee on Public Information 1917: 1918: 1919</italic> (New York: Da Capo Press, 1972); James R. Mock, <italic>Censorship 1917</italic> (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1941).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn21-1077699012455999">
<label>21.</label>
<p>Byron Price, “How Far Censorship?,” <italic>American Forum of the Air</italic> 5 (February 14, 1943): 1–7, Price Papers, Box 2, Folder 6, WHi; Byron Price, “Memoir,” Boxes 4 and 5.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn22-1077699012455999">
<label>22.</label>
<p>Sweeney, <italic>Secrets of Victory</italic>; McDaniel, “War on Words.”</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn23-1077699012455999">
<label>23.</label>
<p>Washburn, <italic>“</italic>Office of Censorship’s Attempt to Control Press Coverage.”</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn24-1077699012455999">
<label>24.</label>
<p>Koop, <italic>Weapon of Silence.</italic></p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn25-1077699012455999">
<label>25.</label>
<p>Frank C. Clough, “Operations of the Press Division of the Office of Censorship,” <italic>Journalism Quarterly</italic> 20 (September 1943): 220–24.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn26-1077699012455999">
<label>26.</label>
<p>Price, “Memoir,” Boxes 4 and 5; Byron Price, “Governmental Censorship in Wartime,” <italic>American Political Science Review</italic> 36 (October 1942): 837–49; Byron Price, “Nation’s Press Has Complied with the Censorship Code,” <italic>Journalism Quarterly</italic> 20 (December 1943): 318–19; Byron Price, “The American Way,” in <italic>Journalism in Wartime: A Symposium of the School of Journalism, University of Missouri</italic>, ed. Frank Luther Mott (Washington, DC: American Council on Public Affairs, 1943), 29–33; Byron Price, “Censorship an Evil of War,” <italic>Vital Speeches of the Day</italic>, December 15, 1942, 158–60; Byron Price, “Address before the NAB War Conference,” Price Papers, Box 2, WHi; National Association of Broadcasters, “Do We Have Freedom of Speech in the United States? A Panel Discussion at the 24th Annual NAB Convention,” <italic>Information Bulletin—Convention</italic> 14 (October 23, 1946): 1–16. In addition, a volume of the texts of seventeen speeches Price gave during the war can be found in Price Papers, WHi.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn27-1077699012455999">
<label>27.</label>
<p>Sweeney, <italic>Secrets of Victory</italic>, 104; Phillip Knightley, <italic>The First Casualty: The War Correspondent as Hero and Myth-Maker from the Crimea to Iraq</italic> (Baltimore, MD: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2004).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn28-1077699012455999">
<label>28.</label>
<p>Smith, <italic>War and Press Freedom</italic>, 163</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn29-1077699012455999">
<label>29.</label>
<p><italic>A Report on the Office of Censorship</italic> (Washington, DC: Government Printing Office, 1945).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn30-1077699012455999">
<label>30.</label>
<p>Koop, <italic>Weapon of Silence</italic>; Price, “Memoir,” Boxes 4 and 5.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn31-1077699012455999">
<label>31.</label>
<p>J. E. Warner to Jack Lockhart, “Memorandum,” September 18, 1943, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, January 1943 folder, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn32-1077699012455999">
<label>32.</label>
<p>Sweeney, <italic>Secrets of Victory</italic>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn33-1077699012455999">
<label>33.</label>
<p>Sweeney, <italic>Secrets of Victory</italic>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn34-1077699012455999">
<label>34.</label>
<p>Price, “American Way,” 29.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn35-1077699012455999">
<label>35.</label>
<p>Sweeney, <italic>Secrets of Victory</italic>, 38.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn36-1077699012455999">
<label>36.</label>
<p>Price, “Memoir,” Box 4, Folder 10, p. 204.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn37-1077699012455999">
<label>37.</label>
<p>See U.S. Office of Censorship, <italic>Code of Wartime Practices for the American Press</italic> (Washington, DC: Government Printing Office, 1942); U.S. Office of Censorship, <italic>Code of Wartime Practices for the American Press</italic>, edition of June, 15, 1942 (Washington, DC: Government Printing Office, 1942); U.S. Office of Censorship, <italic>Code of Wartime Practices for the American Press</italic>, edition of February 1, 1943 (Washington DC: Government Printing Office, 1943); U.S. Office of Censorship, <italic>Code of Wartime Practices for the American Press</italic>, edition of December 1, 1943 (Washington, DC: Government Printing Office, 1943); U.S. Office of Censorship, <italic>Code of Wartime Practices for American Broadcasters</italic> (Washington, DC: Government Printing Office, 1942); U.S. Office of Censorship, <italic>Code of Wartime Practices for American Broadcasters</italic>, edition of June 15, 1942 (Washington, DC: Government Printing Office, 1942); U.S. Office of Censorship, <italic>Code of Wartime Practices for American Broadcasters</italic>, edition of February 1, 1943 (Washington DC: Government Printing Office, 1943); U.S. Office of Censorship, <italic>Code of Wartime Practices for American Broadcasters</italic>, edition of December 1, 1943 (Washington, DC: Government Printing Office, 1943); and U.S. Office of Censorship, <italic>Code of Wartime Practices for the American Press and Radio</italic>, edition of May 15, 1945 (Washington, DC: Government Printing Office, 1945). All can be found in Price Papers, Box 3, File 4 and Box 5, File 15, WHi.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn38-1077699012455999">
<label>38.</label>
<p>U.S. Office of Censorship, <italic>Code of Wartime Practices for the American Press</italic>, 1942, 1.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn39-1077699012455999">
<label>39.</label>
<p>Price, “Memoir,” Box 4, Folder 10, p. 221.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn40-1077699012455999">
<label>40.</label>
<p>Michael S. Sweeney, “Censorship Missionaries of World War II,” <italic>Journalism History</italic> 27 (spring 2001): 4–13.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn41-1077699012455999">
<label>41.</label>
<p>Price, “Memoir,” Box 4, Folder 10, pp. 295, 305.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn42-1077699012455999">
<label>42.</label>
<p>Price, “Memoir,” Box 4, Folder 11, p. 319.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn43-1077699012455999">
<label>43.</label>
<p>Price, “Governmental Censorship in Wartime.”</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn44-1077699012455999">
<label>44.</label>
<p>Price, “American Way.”</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn45-1077699012455999">
<label>45.</label>
<p>Gerald F. Linderman, <italic>The World within War: America’s Combat Experience in World War II</italic> (New York: Free Press, 1997).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn46-1077699012455999">
<label>46.</label>
<p>Simon Harrison, “Skull Trophies of the Pacific War: Transgressive Objects of Remembrance,” <italic>Journal of the Royal Anthropological Institute</italic> 12 (December 2006): 817–36, 824; John W. Dower, <italic>War without Mercy: Race and Power in the Pacific War</italic> (New York: Pantheon Books, 1986), 41–44.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn47-1077699012455999">
<label>47.</label>
<p>Linderman, <italic>World within War</italic>, 147.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn48-1077699012455999">
<label>48.</label>
<p>Linderman, <italic>World within War</italic>, 149–64.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn49-1077699012455999">
<label>49.</label>
<p>Linderman, <italic>World within War</italic>, 161–73.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn50-1077699012455999">
<label>50.</label>
<p>Harrison, “Skull Trophies of the Pacific War.”</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn51-1077699012455999">
<label>51.</label>
<p>Michael Burleigh, <italic>Moral Combat: Good and Evil in World War II</italic> (New York: Harper, 2011), 386.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn52-1077699012455999">
<label>52.</label>
<p>Dower, <italic>War without Mercy</italic>, 78–85</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn53-1077699012455999">
<label>53.</label>
<p>Linderman, <italic>World within War</italic>, 180.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn54-1077699012455999">
<label>54.</label>
<p>Linderman, <italic>World within War</italic>, 177–80.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn55-1077699012455999">
<label>55.</label>
<p>Skulls were missing from 60% of the Japanese remains repatriated from the Marianas Islands, and from many of those found on Iwo Jima long after the war by a Japanese priest (Harrison, “Skull Trophies of the Pacific War,” 828), but there is a complete lack of forensic evidence that body parts were collected as trophies in Europe (Harrison, “Skull Trophies of the Pacific War,” 826).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn56-1077699012455999">
<label>56.</label>
<p>Linderman, <italic>World within War</italic>, 180–82.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn57-1077699012455999">
<label>57.</label>
<p>Linderman, <italic>World within War</italic>, 182.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn58-1077699012455999">
<label>58.</label>
<p>The Commander of the Pacific Fleet ordered “stern disciplinary action” against the collection of enemy body parts in 1942, during the early weeks of the Battle of Guadalcanal (Harrison, “Skull Trophies of the Pacific War,” 827). See also an October 1943 communiqué from the Army Chief of Staff to Gen. Douglas MacArthur, expressing concern over reports of U.S. soldiers boiling Japanese skulls for souvenirs and extracting gold teeth from the heads of dead Japanese soldiers. James J. Weingartner, “Trophies of War: US Troops and the Mutilation of Japanese War Dead,” <italic>Pacific Historical Review</italic> 61 (February 1992): 53–67.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn59-1077699012455999">
<label>59.</label>
<p>Border censors charged with reading printed material leaving the country often alerted the Press Censorship Division to published news stories that violated the <italic>Code</italic>. Frank C. Clough, “Operations of the Press Division of the Office of Censorship.”</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn60-1077699012455999">
<label>60.</label>
<p>Knightley, <italic>First Casualty</italic>.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn61-1077699012455999">
<label>61.</label>
<p>“Welcome Home,” <italic>War Department Pamphlet</italic>, No. 20–10 (Washington, DC, March 1944).</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn62-1077699012455999">
<label>62.</label>
<p>See, for example, Jack Lockhart to <italic>Salisbury Times</italic>, Telegram, December 20, 1944, Box 447, File: C.R. <italic>Salisbury Times</italic>, January 1944. The <italic>Times</italic> copy editor appealed the Office of Censorship after the local military PRO asked him to delete references in a story made by a pilot who described strafing Japanese survivors. Lockhart told the editor that the information was not covered by the <italic>Code</italic> but asked him to cooperate with the military. Without statutory censorship, however, the choice actually belonged to the editor, not the military.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn63-1077699012455999">
<label>63.</label>
<p>U.S. Office of Censorship, <italic>Code of Wartime Practices for the American Press</italic>, June 15, 1942, 5; U.S. Office of Censorship, <italic>Code of Wartime Practices for American Broadcasters</italic>, June 15, 1942, 6.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn64-1077699012455999">
<label>64.</label>
<p>Lee Ellmaker to Byron Price, September 7, 1942; N. R. Howard to Lee Ellmaker, September 8, 1942; Jack Lockhart to N. R. Howard, “Memorandum,” July 24, 1942; Mr. Mylander to Mr. Sorrells, “Memorandum,” March 21, 1942. All are in Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn65-1077699012455999">
<label>65.</label>
<p>U.S. Office of Censorship, <italic>Code of Wartime Practices for the American Press</italic>, February 1, 1943, 6; U.S. Office of Censorship, <italic>Code of Wartime Practices for American Broadcasters</italic>, February 1, 1943, 5.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn66-1077699012455999">
<label>66.</label>
<p>T. D. Higgins to Office of Censorship, January 5, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, January 1944 folder, National Archives; Jack Lockhart to T. D. Higgins, January 10, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories January 1944 folder, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn67-1077699012455999">
<label>67.</label>
<p>For a compilation of the notes and requests, see “Confidential Notes, Special Requests and Notes to Editors. (In some instances to Editors and Broadcasters),” Price Papers, Box 6, Folder 1, WHi; “Special Requests, Requests and Notes to Broadcasters,” Price Papers, Box 6, Folder 2, WHi.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn68-1077699012455999">
<label>68.</label>
<p>Jack Lockhart to Lt. Raymond J. Neumann, January 8, 1945, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, September 1944, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn69-1077699012455999">
<label>69.</label>
<p>Jack Lockhart to Lt. Raymond J. Neumann, January 8, 1945.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn70-1077699012455999">
<label>70.</label>
<p>Jack Lockhart to Lt. Raymond J. Neumann, January 8, 1945.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn71-1077699012455999">
<label>71.</label>
<p>George Mahon to Honorable Franklin D. Roosevelt, August 23, 1943; and George Mahon to Honorable Elmer Davis, August 23, 1943. Both are in Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, January 1943, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn72-1077699012455999">
<label>72.</label>
<p>“Dallas Ex-Taxidermist Sends Home Jap[anese] Teeth,” <italic>Dallas News</italic>, August 19, 1943.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn73-1077699012455999">
<label>73.</label>
<p>Major General George V. Strong to Byron Price, September 24, 1943, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, January 1943, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn74-1077699012455999">
<label>74.</label>
<p>Captain Leland P. Lovette to George Mahon, September 6, 1943, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, January 1943, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn75-1077699012455999">
<label>75.</label>
<p>Jack Lockhart to Bryon Price, September 8, 1943, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, January 1943, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn76-1077699012455999">
<label>76.</label>
<p>Jack Lockhart to George Mahon, September 6, 1943, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, January 1943, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn77-1077699012455999">
<label>77.</label>
<p>Colonel Gilbert C. Jacobus to Byron Price, November 1, 1943, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, October 1943, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn78-1077699012455999">
<label>78.</label>
<p>International News Service, Washington, January 27, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, January 1944, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn79-1077699012455999">
<label>79.</label>
<p>Byron Price, “Note to Editors and Broadcasters,” January 29, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, February 1944, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn80-1077699012455999">
<label>80.</label>
<p>Elmer Davis referred to a directive from President Roosevelt to the Secretaries of War and Navy, dated September 9, 1943, to prevent the publication or circulation of stories related to Japanese atrocities told by escaped prisoners until he authorized them, for fear the stories of Japanese atrocities might complicate repatriation efforts. Elmer Davis to Admiral William D. Leahy, December 24, 1943, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, October 1943, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn81-1077699012455999">
<label>81.</label>
<p>W. H. Mylander to Jack Lockhart, “Memorandum,” January 31, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, January 1944, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn82-1077699012455999">
<label>82.</label>
<p>Jack Lockhart, “Memorandum,” February 11, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, February 1944, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn83-1077699012455999">
<label>83.</label>
<p>Mil Petty to Jack Lockhart, “Memorandum,” February 21, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, February 1944, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn84-1077699012455999">
<label>84.</label>
<p>Major General Surles did not detail in his letter how civilian censors were to manage this plan. Major General A. D. Surles to Byron Price, February 24, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, February 1944, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn85-1077699012455999">
<label>85.</label>
<p>Jack Lockhart to Mr. Price, “Memorandum,” February 25, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, February 1944, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn86-1077699012455999">
<label>86.</label>
<p>Byron Price to Major General A. D. Surles, February 25, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, February 1944, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn87-1077699012455999">
<label>87.</label>
<p>Byron Price, “Memoir,” Box, 4 Folder 10, p. 217.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn88-1077699012455999">
<label>88.</label>
<p>The records say nothing more about the incident.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn89-1077699012455999">
<label>89.</label>
<p>Lt. Ray Neumann to Jack Lockhart, January 5, 1945, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, September 1944, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn90-1077699012455999">
<label>90.</label>
<p>Jack Lockhart to Lt. Raymond J. Neumann, January 8, 1945.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn91-1077699012455999">
<label>91.</label>
<p>Edwin W. Craig to Byron Price, May 1, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, February 1944 folder, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn92-1077699012455999">
<label>92.</label>
<p>Byron Price to Edwin W. Craig, May 3, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, February 1944 folder, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn93-1077699012455999">
<label>93.</label>
<p>John E. Fetzer to Byron Price, May 3, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, February 1944 folder, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn94-1077699012455999">
<label>94.</label>
<p>Jack Lockhart to J. E. Irving, Jr., March 14, 1945, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, September 1944 folder, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn95-1077699012455999">
<label>95.</label>
<p>Jack Lockhart to Allan C. Bartlett, November 29, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, September 1944 folder, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn96-1077699012455999">
<label>96.</label>
<p>Allan C. Bartlett to Jack Lockhart, January 1, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, September 1944 folder, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn97-1077699012455999">
<label>97.</label>
<p>Phil Adler to Jack Lockhart, “Memorandum,” July 22, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, February 1944 folder, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn98-1077699012455999">
<label>98.</label>
<p>T. W. Parker to Jack Lockhart, November 24, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, September 1944 folder, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn99-1077699012455999">
<label>99.</label>
<p>Jack Lockhart to the Editor, December 18, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, September 1944 folder, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn100-1077699012455999">
<label>100.</label>
<p>Douglas G. Wright to Jack Lockhart, December 22, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, September 1944 folder, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn101-1077699012455999">
<label>101.</label>
<p>Jack Lockhart to Harvey J. Becker, April 20, 1945, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, September 1944, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn102-1077699012455999">
<label>102.</label>
<p>Harvey J. Becker to Jack Lockhart, May 4, 1945, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, September 1944, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn103-1077699012455999">
<label>103.</label>
<p>Jim Warner to Jack Lockhart, “Memorandum,” July 31, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, February 1944, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn104-1077699012455999">
<label>104.</label>
<p>INS, London, August 6, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, February 1944, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn105-1077699012455999">
<label>105.</label>
<p>Associated Press, August 9, 1944, Record Group 216 File 012 D/8 Atrocity Stories, February 1944, National Archives.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn106-1077699012455999">
<label>106.</label>
<p>Clough, “Operations of the Press Division of the Office of Censorship”; Price, “Nation’s Press Has Complied with the Censorship Code”; Price, “Memoir,” Box 5, Folder 4, pp. 482-83; Koop, <italic>Weapon of Silence</italic>; McDaniel, “War on Words.”</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn107-1077699012455999">
<label>107.</label>
<p>Byron Price, “Governmental Censorship in War-Time.”</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn108-1077699012455999">
<label>108.</label>
<p>For a discussion of the press reaction to the My Lai massacre, see Kendrick Oliver, <italic>The My Lai Massacre in American History and Memory</italic> (Manchester, UK: Manchester University Press, 2006), 29–52.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="other" id="fn109-1077699012455999">
<label>109.</label>
<p>Blasi, “Pathological Perspective and the First Amendment.”</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
</notes>
</back>
</article>