<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SIR</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsir</journal-id>
<journal-title>Studies in Religion/Sciences Religieuses</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0008-4298</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">2042-0587</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0008429812452084q</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0008429812452084q</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Reviews Of Books / Comptes Rendus</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Reviews Of Books / Comptes Rendus: Exegesis in the Making: Postcolonialism and New Testament Studies Anna Runesson Leiden: Brill, 2011. xx + 254 pp.</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Timmer</surname>
<given-names>Daniel C.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0008429812452084q"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-0008429812452084q">Reformed Theological Seminary Jackson, Mississippi</aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>41</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<fpage>514</fpage>
<lpage>516</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Runesson</surname>
<given-names>Anna</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <publisher-loc>Leiden</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Brill</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>. xx + <page-count count="254"/> pp.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) / Le(s) auteur(s), 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">The Canadian Corporation for Studies in Religion</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>Over the last two decades, the number of publications bringing postcolonialism into contact with biblical studies has grown rapidly. This is interesting to biblical scholars for many reasons, but perhaps most of all due to postcolonialism’s critique of the historical-critical method and its own value as a complement or alternative. The majority of the present volume, written by a self-described “‘hybrid’ in the Swedish ‘diaspora’ in postcolonial Canada and Jerusalem,” analyzes the theoretical basis of postcolonial studies and its relation to the historical-critical paradigm (pp. 1–132). Five postcolonial readings of New Testament texts selected by Runesson and authored by Musa W. Dube, Khiok-Khng Yeo, Gregory D. Wiebe, George M. Soares-Prabhu, and George Zachariah round out the volume (pp. 141–234). Runesson briefly introduces these already-published pieces but allows them to illustrate on their own the issues raised in the book’s analytical section.</p>
<p>Runesson’s goal is to understand postcolonialism at the dawn of the twenty-first century “within the postcoloniality of our time via a discussion of the theoretical location of all exegesis” (8). In chapter three (pp. 17–50) she explores the “theoretical location of postcolonial studies,” sketching the postmodern roots of postcolonial studies in Foucault’s definition of the episteme as “the web in which knowledge is possible.” Accordingly, any field of knowledge must be seen as linked to “an indefinite field of relations,” as Foucault put it (35). Turning to method, Runesson suggests that a method’s “soul” exists in the “body” of “an episteme-embedded discourse” (36–37). This means that the use of postcolonial theory (originating in one discourse) in biblical studies, a field until recently dominated by historical criticism (originating in another), creates significant tensions.</p>
<p>Postcolonial theory suggests that the text is “part of a larger context, which includes the present reader and her or his perspectives, situations, limitations, and, most significantly, the episteme in which the scholar lives and writes” (44). This has consequences for interpretative objectivity, of course, and Runesson explores them in chapter four (“Deconstructing Western Biblical Studies”). She begins with a critique of the historical-critical discourse (not simply the method) in order to expose its episteme. Runesson locates the genesis of historical criticism in the Enlightenment, when “positivism was deconstructing previous paradigms” and “[h]istorical truth became, in the study of religion, the truth” (56). Most postcolonial interpreters are significantly influenced by postmodernism and so see the historical-critical approach as modern. They consequently critique its positivism, objectivism, nature, and intention. On the first two points, postcolonialism concentrates its critique on the historical-critical “claim to universality. The universalistic claim is, arguably, closely related to colonial structures” (63). Postcolonial scholars also argue that the nature and intention of the biblical text are ill-suited to the historical-critical method: as Runesson summarizes Teng Kok Lim Johnson, “when engaging in historical criticism there is a risk of atomisation of the text, which might lead to results that will miss the intention of the text as a religious text” (65). More specifically, George M. Soares-Prabhu has urged that the “divine message” of a religious text “is impossible to get at through historical critical analyses, since historical criticism is lacking the parameter of ‘faith’” (65).</p>
<p>A specifically postcolonial critique of historical-critical discourse adds the elements of orientalism, hegemony, and relevance (67–82). Orientalism involves the West’s construction of the (oriental) other on terms that serve the West’s own interests (per Edward Said), and is therefore bound up with its hegemony: “Hegemony is at work in the promotion of the view that the epistemology and the methods developed in the West are globally indispensable, indeed fundamental to any scholarly endeavor worldwide. Western hegemony prevents non-Western scholars from developing their own interpretative agendas; without worldwide recognition and respect, participation in the global academic dialogue is, in effect, made impossible” (72). No consensus as to the relevance of historical-critical methods exists among postcolonial scholars, but many agree that the reader/interpreter is the key to bringing historical-critical discourse, appropriately modified in light of the indigenous episteme, into a fruitful role in that new setting (79–81). Chapter five demonstrates that this may take place “within the historical critical paradigm” or “beyond western historical critical discourses,” though it seems to this reviewer that both the methodological foundations and the current practice of postcolonialism favor its independence from the historical-critical paradigm. Although Runesson is careful to maintain an objective tone throughout her book, she seems to lean in the same direction, as when she concludes that there is a “liberating element, which is fundamental to postcolonial exegesis in its opposition to the hegemony of (Western) historical criticism” (129; see also 49).</p>
<p>It is interesting that Runesson, who has spent considerable time in postcolonial interpretation, offers a fairly different reading of the relationship between postcolonial and historical-critical interpretation than those who have spent the majority of their time in the other sphere. As examples of the latter, note John Collins’ call for the continuation of the historical-critical paradigm, albeit enriched by new “voices from the margin” (<italic>The Bible after Babel: Historical Criticism in a Postmodern Age</italic> [Grand Rapids, MI: Eerdmans, 2005]), and John Barton’s similar claim that “critical reading of the Bible. represents insights that, once encountered, cannot be suppressed” (<italic>The Nature of Biblical Criticism</italic> [Louisville, KY: Westminster John Knox, 2007], 189). Only time will tell which of these contesting visions of interpretation will win the favor of the global audience.</p>
<p>In the meantime, Runesson has very helpfully analyzed the complex perspective of postcolonial studies, and successfully brings that field into dialogue with the historical-critical paradigm that was for so long regnant in biblical studies. More importantly, by exposing the significant epistemological distance that currently separates these two approaches, it will surely advance discussion of this and related issues, and so play a role in answering the very question it raises.</p>
</body>
</article>