<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JMM</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjmm</journal-id>
<journal-title>Men and Masculinities</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">1097-184X</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1552-6828</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1097184X12461018</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1097184X12461018</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Affirmative Reaction: New Formations of White Masculinity</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grzanka</surname>
<given-names>Patrick Ryan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-1097184X12461018"/>
</contrib>
<aff id="aff1-1097184X12461018"><italic>Arizona State University, Tempe, AZ, USA</italic></aff>
</contrib-group>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>12</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>556</fpage>
<lpage>560</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Carroll</surname>
<given-names>Hamilton</given-names>
</name>
</person-group> <source>Affirmative Reaction: New Formations of White Masculinity</source> <publisher-loc>Durham, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Duke University Press</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year>. <page-count count="232"/> pp. <price>$22.95</price> (paperback), <price>$79.95</price> (cloth). <isbn>ISBN: 978-0-8223-4948-8</isbn></product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>The concept of “invisibility” has long been a productive analytic tool with which scholars across the disciplines have theorized the place of whiteness, masculinity, middle-class status, heterosexuality, and other hegemonic forms of identity in American society and culture. The power of these dominant identities, the story goes, lies in their invisibility or unmarkedness; the unquestioned position of universality allows these subjectivities to retain an assumed and uninterrogated normative social location from which to accumulate social power, dictate the organization of society, and to place all “Other” peoples in a similarly unquestioned but inverse position of difference, inferiority, and subordination. This is how we understand, at least from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-1097184X12461018">Gramsci (1971</xref>) on, how hegemony works.</p>
<p>The primary theoretical contribution of Hamilton Carroll’s new book on white American masculinity in neoliberalism is his insistence that whiteness is less invisible than it is mutable, strategic, and “labile.” Antiracist scholars of color, feminists, and queer theorists (not mutually exclusive groups, of course) may not be surprised by this argument. Though the rhetoric and logic of “invisibility” certainly has sociological import, it also tends to obfuscate the dynamics of hegemonic social relations. Perceiving whiteness as “invisible,” for example, is typically indicative of group membership within the racial category of “white.” Accordingly, having white privilege enables one to actively <italic>ignore</italic> the consequences of racism on history, social systems, interpersonal dynamics, and so on. This willful ignorance of the power of whiteness—or of white, heterosexual masculinity, in particular—is not so easily afforded to those outside the allegedly unmarked norm. But Carroll is not merely resuscitating longstanding critiques of this discourse of white, heteromasculine invisibility. Indeed, Robyn <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-1097184X12461018">Wiegman (1999</xref>), Mike <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-1097184X12461018">Hill (2004</xref>), and Eduardo <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-1097184X12461018">Bonilla-Silva (2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-1097184X12461018">Bonilla-Silva and Embrick 2007</xref>), among many others, have already sufficiently troubled this concept: whiteness may be invisible sometimes to some people, but certainly not always already everywhere.</p>
<p>Carroll, on the other hand, pushes the discourse of critical whiteness studies <italic>and</italic> masculinity studies forward by way of an expansive, intersectional analysis of disparate-but-intertwined mediascapes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-1097184X12461018">Appadurai 1990</xref>) that offers some important conclusions about white American masculinity in our neoliberal times. At the center of the text is the assertion that white masculinity has developed some especially insidious tactics for negotiating multicultural discourse, including a cooptation of identity politics in the interest of claiming a quasi-minority status: “White masculinity has responded to calls for both redistribution and recognition by citing itself as the most needy and the most worthy recipient of what it denies it already has,” explains Carroll (p. 10). Moreover, this politics of particularity—the formation of an aggrieved and under siege white, heteromasculine subjectivity—has become <italic>the</italic> productive strategy by which white masculinity integrates new configurations of identity and affect in the interest of retaining social privilege in this uniquely neoliberal historical context. This is not, in Carroll’s terms, just a matter of how you (do not) look at white masculinity, that is from outside or within, from below or above, as universal or particular. This “sleight of hand” by way of which whiteness repackages and reconfigures itself in neoliberalism—its “lability”—is the foundational element of contemporary white masculine hegemony, and the means by which it moves through, between, and around minority and identitarian discourses of the late twentieth and early twenty-first century.</p>
<p>Carroll is appointed in an English department and his work is situated at the intersection of literature and American cultural studies. But that hardly limits the value of this book or its audience to those who do gender, race, or class studies from a literary and/or media studies perspective. To the contrary, there is much value in this work to humanists and social scientists alike, as Carroll demonstrates both astute qualitative analysis and innovative research design. With regards to the former, Carroll’s reading of recent representations of white American masculinity—from the films <italic>Gran Tourino </italic>and <italic>Syriana </italic>to the reality television (TV) series <italic>American Chopper </italic>and Marvel Comics’s commemoration of 9/11—reads like an ethnography. Carroll’s analyses of these texts are a shrewd and unpretentious thick description of discourses that may at first appear somewhat disconnected. He approaches the texts first on their own terms and then unpacks them slowly (but not boringly); he interrogates how white masculinity appears to do some “new” things with itself in these recent, widely disseminated and often-celebrated cultural products while <italic>simultaneously </italic>producing more of the same racism, sexism, xenophobia, classism, and heterosexism. In most of the case studies, which are organized into three sections with two primary texts each (representations of September 11 in TV and comic books; working-class white masculinities in TV, music, and film; and melodrama and heteropatriarchy in critically acclaimed cinema), he tackles texts that were celebrated for their so-called <italic>unique</italic> perspectives on social conflicts facing contemporary white men: the multicultural dynamics of <italic>Crash</italic>, the postindustrial city in <italic>Gran Tourino,</italic> and the threat of terrorism and a new world order in <italic>24</italic>. But with each new configuration of white masculinity, Carroll insists that whiteness merely finds ways to position itself within discourses of difference and subordination in order to reclaim its “rightful” position of superiority. With regard to <italic>Syriana,</italic> the frenetic meditation on US oil politics and counterterrorism starring George Clooney and Matt Damon, Carroll undermines discourse about the film’s complexity and ambivalence by arguing, “Rather than refusing to provide answers, as Clooney suggests, the film simply provides the wrong ones. Despite Clooney’s and [director and screenwriter] Gaghan’s claims and the opinions of the film’s reviewers, the structures of feeling of bourgeois sentimentalist and the reactionary therapeutics of family values evident in the film trump its more complex concerns with U.S. geopolitics” (p. 172). In <italic>Syriana</italic>, <italic>The Call of Duty</italic>, <italic>Million Dollar Baby </italic>and even the Eminem vehicle <italic>8 Mile</italic>, Carroll finds regressive victories of white heteromasculinity against the impending threats of women’s empowerment, immigration, the decline of the patriarchal family, and the deindustrialization of American economy and urban geographies. Rather than disinvest from white heteromasculinity, these cultural projects position it as highly at risk; once these discourses repackage white masculinity as under assault, the neoliberal logics of individualism, meritocracy, and “free enterprise” enable white masculinity to retain its power while establishing itself as a social minority group like any other in the marketplace of difference. Carroll identifies this version of White masculinity as the “exemplary neoliberal citizen” (p. 100).</p>
<p>Regarding methods and design, Carroll’s book jumps across time and space like a multisite ethnography (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-1097184X12461018">Clarke 2005</xref>), making insightful and sometimes surprising connections between cultural products by way of their affects, logic, and reception. You do not have to be familiar with his objects of analysis or have a PhD in literary criticism to follow Carroll across texts and mediums as he constructs an intricate narrative of gendered, classed racial formation. And though neoliberalism is often discussed in obtuse and (frankly) overly complicated rhetoric, Carroll adeptly highlights the most pertinent elements of neoliberalism as a sociohistorical phenomenon and clearly connects the global political economy of neoliberalism to the cultural politics of film, TV, and other mass media. In that sense, I view his work as a terrific complement to Lisa Duggan’s (2003) earlier thesis on neoliberalism and cultural politics, <italic>The Twilight of Equality?</italic> Though he does not explicitly identify or position his work as “intersectional” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-1097184X12461018">Collins 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1097184X12461018">McCall 2005</xref>), I read this book as offering an excellent example of intersectional media studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-1097184X12461018">Collins 2005</xref>), whereby Carroll illustrates the necessity of treating gender, race, sexuality, and nation as coconstitutive elements of identity, social structures, and meaning making in everyday life. There is no way, by the end of <italic>Affirmative Reaction</italic>, to understand whiteness as wholly separate or ontologically removed from hegemonic forms of masculinity, Americanness, class status, or sexuality. This is not a “new” assertion per se, but Carroll’s writing suggests a pragmatics of how to conduct careful, critical, intersectional analyses of mass-mediated texts, as opposed to more traditional forms of sociological evidence (e.g., interviews or quantitative data; see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-1097184X12461018">Dill and Kohlman 2012</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-1097184X12461018">McCall 2005</xref> for an overview).</p>
<p>Carroll is at his best when he is drawing out the substance of his multifarious analyses in order to do some theory making about contemporary white masculinity. The most powerful moments of critical insight come when he skillfully jumps from Keifer Sutherland’s Jack Bauer in <italic>24</italic> to George W. Bush’s speeches on the War on Terror to Judith Butler and back to Bauer again, underscoring the connections between ideas that are neither obvious nor simple. Carroll’s ability to make meaningful associations between otherwise seemingly disconnected cultural products is both my most enthusiastic praise for the book and my strongest criticism, though the former is much greater than the latter. Carroll opens <italic>Affirmative Reaction</italic> with a genuinely brilliant reading of Ang Lee’s <italic>Brokeback Mountain </italic>that aptly intertwines his major points and introduces the format of the book as a whole. His interpretation of that film—that Ennis and Jack’s gay love affair is foremost about whiteness, masculinity, and labor—is startling and smart. That is why, when he concludes the book by surveying an array of films that competed with <italic>Brokeback </italic>that awards season, I found myself waiting for him to compare <italic>Crash</italic> and <italic>Brokeback Mountain.</italic> <italic>Crash</italic> ultimately won the 2005 Academy Award for Best Picture in what was framed reductively in the press as the battle of socially progressive films—one about sexuality and the other about race. To me, the collision of these films in the national discourse on social politics and inequality proffers a fruitful space-time in which to consider white masculinity’s most “labile” qualities. Instead, the book ends somewhat abruptly with only a few paragraphs of meta-analysis and synthesis. I found myself wanting him to keep going; lucky for those of us who remain invested in disinvesting white heteromasculinity, I think Carroll has much more to say.</p>
</body>
<back>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="bibr1-1097184X12461018">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Appadurai</surname>
<given-names>Arjun</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1990</year>. <article-title>“Disjuncture and Difference in the Global Economy.”</article-title> <source>Theory, Culture &amp; Society</source> <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>295</fpage>–<lpage>310</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr2-1097184X12461018">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bonilla-Silva</surname>
<given-names>Eduardo</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2006</year>. <source>Racism without Racists: Color-blind Racism and the Persistence of Racial Inequality in the United States</source>. <edition>2nd ed</edition>. <publisher-loc>Lanham, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rowman &amp; Littlefield</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr3-1097184X12461018">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bonilla-Silva</surname>
<given-names>Eduardo</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Embrick</surname>
<given-names>David G.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2007</year>. <article-title>“‘Every Place Has a Ghetto. . .’: The Significance of Whites’ Social and Residential Segregation.”</article-title> <source>Symbolic Interaction</source> <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>323</fpage>–<lpage>45</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr4-1097184X12461018">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Clarke</surname>
<given-names>Adele</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2005</year>. <source>Situational Analysis: Grounded Theory after the Postmodern Turn</source>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr5-1097184X12461018">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Collins</surname>
<given-names>Patricia Hill</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2000</year>. <source>Black Feminist Thought: Knowledge, Consciousness, and the Politics of Empowerment</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr6-1097184X12461018">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Collins</surname>
<given-names>Patricia Hill</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2005</year>. <source>Black Sexual Politics</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr7-1097184X12461018">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dill</surname>
<given-names>Bonnie Thornton</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kohlman</surname>
<given-names>Marla H.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2012</year>. <article-title>“Intersectionality: A Transformative Paradigm in Feminist Theory and Social Justice.”</article-title> In <source>The Handbook of Feminist Research: Theory and Praxis</source>, <edition>2nd ed</edition>., edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Hesse-Biber</surname>
<given-names>Sharlene Nagy</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, <fpage>154</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr8-1097184X12461018">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Duggan</surname>
<given-names>Lisa</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <source>The Twilight of Equality? Neoliberalism, Cultural Politics, and the Attack on Democracy</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Beacon Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr9-1097184X12461018">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gramsci</surname>
<given-names>Antonio</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1971</year>. <source>Selections from the Prison Notebooks of Antonio Gramsci (1929-1935</source>), <comment>edited and translated by</comment> <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Hoare</surname>
<given-names>Q.</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>G. N.</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr10-1097184X12461018">
<citation citation-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hill</surname>
<given-names>Mike</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2004</year>. <source>After Whiteness: Unmaking an American Majority</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New York University Press</publisher-name>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr11-1097184X12461018">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McCall</surname>
<given-names>Leslie</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>2005</year>. <article-title>“The Complexity of Intersectionality.”</article-title> <source>Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society</source> <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>1711</fpage>–<lpage>800</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
<ref id="bibr12-1097184X12461018">
<citation citation-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wiegman</surname>
<given-names>Robyn</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>. <year>1999</year>. <article-title>“Whiteness Studies and the Paradox of Particularity.”</article-title> <source>Boundary 2</source> <issue>26</issue>:<fpage>115</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>