<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="book-review">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">VET</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spvet</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Vet Pathol</journal-id>
<journal-title>Veterinary Pathology</journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0300-9858</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1544-4221</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0300985812452581</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0300985812452581</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Book Reviews</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Book Review: Comparative Anatomy and Histology: A Mouse and Human Atlas</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sellers</surname>
<given-names>R. S.</given-names>
</name>
<degrees>DVM, PhD</degrees>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0300985812452581"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1-0300985812452581">Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Bronx, New York</aff>
<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
<month>9</month>
<year>2012</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>49</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<fpage>886</fpage>
<lpage>886</lpage>
<product>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Treuting</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dintzis</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>, eds. <source>Comparative Anatomy and Histology: A Mouse and Human Atlas</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>; <year>2012</year>. <page-count count="461"/> pp. ISBN: <isbn>978-0-12-381361-9</isbn>.</product>
<permissions>
<copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder content-type="sage">American College of Veterinary Pathologists</copyright-holder>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p>This atlas details the gross and histological differences between mice and human beings. This text is linked to expertconsult.com for convenient web access; the speed of finding text or images is relatively swift, and the quality of the images is very good. As a veterinary pathologist interacting with researchers studying human diseases, this text is a terrific resource that is long overdue. Although much of the mouse and human pathology can be obtained from other sources, this is the first time the material has been compiled into a single reference. I have often wished to have this sort of comparative information readily available both for myself and for the researcher. Although there are some issues that are typical of most first edition texts (occasional inconsistencies in format, etc), these are not significant enough to detract from the overall value of the book.</p>
<p>The text is well written and divided into 23 chapters addressing each of the organ systems as well as basic techniques and approaches to evaluating mouse models. Each chapter begins with a general introduction to the organ system and its function(s) followed by detailed descriptions of the anatomy and histology. Each anatomic region within the organ system is subdivided and discussed both at the anatomic and histologic levels with diagrams, tables, and images. Although the target audience is experienced histologists and pathologists, the text occasionally digresses into details that seem more suited to a basic histology text (although distracting, it does not detract from the overall value). The image quality in the atlas is excellent, and there are many diagrams and tables summarizing comparative anatomy and histology for a given organ system. One feature I particularly liked were the “Need-to-know” bullet points that highlighted specific differences between the mouse and human, which were located adjacent to the figures. In general, the bullet points clearly identified the species for which the points were intended. Occasionally, however, the species was not defined and had to be ascertained from the figures with which it was affiliated. Overall, this much-needed atlas is of high quality, both in its images and in its text, figures, and tables. I feel that this book is a great reference and would be an excellent addition to any mouse pathologist’s library. </p>
<p>Editor’s Note: This book review, as is standard practice with <italic>Veterinary Pathology</italic>, was not solicited nor did its content involve Dr P. Treuting, our book review editor as she is a co-editor and a contributing author to the reviewed book.</p>
<sig-block>
<sig>—C. Alden</sig>
</sig-block>
</body>
</article>